<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="c7f2d366-8ba0-4263-98e0-bdaa9336415f" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.clarrie.mackinnon" showAs="MR. CLARRIE MACKINNON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.keith.bain" showAs="MR. KEITH BAIN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.maureen.macdonald" showAs="Hon. Maureen MacDonald"/>
        <TLCPerson id="1e5b7bdc-363b-4df4-8258-edcf8f2bf7fb" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.andrew.younger" showAs="MR. ANDREW YOUNGER"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MADAM SPEAKER"/>
        <TLCRole id="clerk" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.clerk" showAs="THE CLERK"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 20 April 2012</docTitle>
      <docNumber>12-15</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2012-04-20">Friday, April 20, 2012</docDate>
      <docProponent>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docProponent>
      <legislature value="61">61st General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="4">4th Session</session>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>Order, please. We'll begin the daily routine.</p>
      </speech>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PRESENTING AND READING PETITIONS</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PRESENTING REPORTS OF COMMITTEES</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>TABLING REPORTS, REGULATIONS AND OTHER PAPERS</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>STATEMENTS BY MINISTERS</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>INTRODUCTION OF BILLS</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 34 - Entitled an Act to Repeal Out-dated Matrimonial Statutes. (Hon. Ross Landry)</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 35 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 293 of the Revised Statutes of 1989. The Motor Vehicle Act. (Mr. Andrew Younger)</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 36 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 217 of the Revised Statutes of 1989. The Income Tax Act, to Provide a Food Bank Donation Tax Credit for Farmers. (Mr. Leo Glavine)</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Ordered that these bills be read a second time on a future day.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Dartmouth East.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="307">RESOLUTION NO. 307</num>
          <speech by="#1e5b7bdc-363b-4df4-8258-edcf8f2bf7fb"><from>MR. ANDREW YOUNGER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Sunday marks the 42<sup>nd</sup> annual Earth Day, a day to recognize environmental issues, to consume less energy, and encourage the three Rs &#x2013; reduce, reuse and recycle; and</p>
<p>Whereas for the last 20 years, Joan and John Brannon of Caledonia Road in Dartmouth have personified the spirit of Earth Day during the Christmas season by decorating a tree in their front yard with over 1,000 Christmas ornaments made from recycled finds; and</p>
<p>Whereas every December, the Brannons' spectacle tree attracts many visitors and they encourage young people to develop their own sturdy ornaments from found items;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly celebrate and recognize long-term Dartmouth East residents, Joan and John Brannon, on their initiative to make the community a greener and more festive place to live.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Victoria-The Lakes.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e">
            <from>MR. KEITH BAIN</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, if I might be permitted to do some introductions before reading this resolution?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Certainly.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e"><from>MR. BAIN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, in the gallery opposite we have members of the Canadian Ski Patrol System. I would like to introduce them. I would ask that they please stand as I call out their names: Doug MacLean and his daughter, Tina Egan; Kathy Little; Ken Little; Bernard Robicheau, Scotia zone president for Ski Wentworth and Ski Martock; Judy Robertson, ski patrol; Claire Blight, ski patrol; Bill Blight; Richard Crooks, a member of the board of directors of Ski Patrol; Sue Crooks; and Bill Powell. Also, we have Brian Smith, ski patrol; Butch Stuart; Sandy Ross; and Jamie Duncan.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I would ask all members of the Legislature to make these visitors welcome. (Applause)</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>We welcome all our guests to the gallery and hope that they enjoy this morning's proceedings.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Victoria-The Lakes.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="308">RESOLUTION NO. 308</num>
          <speech by="#250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e"><from>MR. KEITH BAIN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Canadian Ski Patrol System is a non-profit charitable organization founded in 1941 by Dr. Douglas Firth and is composed of 4,496 volunteers from coast to coast to coast; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Canadian Ski Patrol System provides first-aid services at 230 Alpine and Nordic ski areas across Canada and at off-season events which include events such as marathons, mountain bike races and concerts and has provided services at the Canadian Olympic and Paralympic Games, the Canada and provincial Winter Games, Canadian and provincial championships and various World Cup races held in Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas Doug MacLean is celebrating 50 years of volunteer service with the Canadian Ski Patrol System in Nova Scotia, at both Ski Martock and Ski Wentworth;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Doug MacLean on 50 years of volunteer service with the Canadian Ski Patrol System and wish him the best in the future.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>ORDERS OF THE DAY</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT BUSINESS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#c7f2d366-8ba0-4263-98e0-bdaa9336415f">
          <from>MR. CLARRIE MACKINNON</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Government Motions.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT MOTIONS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#c7f2d366-8ba0-4263-98e0-bdaa9336415f">
          <from>MR. CLARRIE MACKINNON</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, I move that you do now leave the Chair and that the House resolve itself into a Committee of the Whole House on Supply unto Her Majesty.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The motion is carried.</p>
        </speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>9:14 a.m. The House resolved itself into a CWH on Supply with Deputy Speaker Mr. Alfie MacLeod in the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <narrative>
          <p>1:26 p.m. CWH on Supply rose and the House reconvened with Deputy Speaker Ms. Becky Kent in the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The Chairman of the Committee of the Whole House on Supply reports:</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined">
          <from>THE CLERK</from>
          <p>That the Committee of the Whole House on Supply has met, made considerable progress, and begs leave to sit again.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#c7f2d366-8ba0-4263-98e0-bdaa9336415f">
          <from>MR. CLARRIE MACKINNON</from>
          <p>Madam Speaker, that concludes the government's business for today. I move that the House do now rise, to meet again at 4:00 p.m. on Monday, April 23<sup>rd</sup>. The House hours will be from 4:00 p.m. to 10:00 p.m. After the daily routine, we will have Committee of the Whole House on Supply and Public Bills for Second Reading, Bill Nos. 5, 9, 11, 13, 17, 20, 22, 24, 30, 32, and 34.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the House do now rise to meet again on Monday, April 23<sup>rd</sup>, between the hours of 4:00 p.m. and 10:00 p.m.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Folks, I hope you all have a great weekend. We stand adjourned.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>The House rose at 1:27 p.m.</p>
        </narrative>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION UNDER RULE 32(3)</heading>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
