<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.michel.p.samson" showAs="HON. MICHEL SAMSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="c7f2d366-8ba0-4263-98e0-bdaa9336415f" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.clarrie.mackinnon" showAs="MR. CLARRIE MACKINNON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="32a29c39-915c-40e7-b749-7c09299ed1f7" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.david.allan.wilson" showAs="HON. DAVID WILSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="5da6e0aa-9066-4b5c-8d26-9222b854db7e" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.marilyn.more" showAs="HON. MARILYN MORE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8dbda583-1553-4164-a616-3008fb0fdac4" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.bill.estabrooks" showAs="HON. WILLIAM ESTABROOKS"/>
        <TLCPerson id="13283a7f-b97c-4254-a233-d0ccec196703" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.gary.ramey" showAs="MR. GARY RAMEY"/>
        <TLCPerson id="72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.chuck.porter" showAs="MR. CHUCK PORTER"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MADAM SPEAKER"/>
        <TLCRole id="clerk" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.clerk" showAs="THE CLERK"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 13 April 2012</docTitle>
      <docNumber>12-10</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2012-04-13">Friday, April 13, 2012</docDate>
      <docProponent>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docProponent>
      <legislature value="61">61st General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="4">4th Session</session>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>Order, please. We will begin the daily routine.</p>
      </speech>
      <petitions>
        <heading>PRESENTING AND READING PETITIONS</heading>
      </petitions>
      <papers>
        <heading>PRESENTING REPORTS OF COMMITTEES</heading>
      </papers>
      <papers>
        <heading>TABLING REPORTS, REGULATIONS AND OTHER PAPERS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Labour and Advanced Education.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#5da6e0aa-9066-4b5c-8d26-9222b854db7e">
          <from>HON. MARILYN MORE</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, I beg leave to table the 2011 Annual Report for the Workers' Compensation Board.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The report is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#8dbda583-1553-4164-a616-3008fb0fdac4"><from>HON. WILLIAM ESTABROOKS</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I beg leave to table the Surplus Crown Property Disposal Report, but before I do that, I want to compliment MLAs on all sides of the House for directing community groups throughout their constituencies to the Department of Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal. I'd also point out that there are some excellent buys there for second-hand furniture, second-hand air conditioners - you should use them in your office.</p>
<p>With those few comments, Mr. Speaker, I table the Surplus Crown Property Disposal Report for the period April 1, 2010, to March 31, 2011.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The report is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Lunenburg West.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#13283a7f-b97c-4254-a233-d0ccec196703">
          <from>MR. GARY RAMEY</from>
          <p>Yesterday during debate in Question Period - a fairly raucous one, I think you would agree - I made some comments which were unparliamentary. I wish to retract those comments, Mr. Speaker, and I also wish to apologize to you and to all members of this House, particularly to any member who feels that the comments that I made were directed at them. (Applause)</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Thank you.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Richmond.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be">
          <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, on behalf of our caucus I certainly commend the member for Lunenburg West. Sometimes in the heat of debate, we've all been caught - myself included, I have to add, on possibly a few occasions by yourself and your predecessors in that Chair. I certainly commend the member for Lunenburg West and look forward to continued debate.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Hants West.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7">
          <from>MR. CHUCK PORTER</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, I too would stand on behalf of the Tory caucus and commend the member for his honourable comments this morning. I appreciate that very much, and wish we have nothing but the best debate and the strongest debate in this House in the days and weeks to come.</p>
        </speech>
      </papers>
      <ministerialStatements>
        <heading>STATEMENTS BY MINISTERS</heading>
      </ministerialStatements>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Communities, Culture and Heritage.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="201">RESOLUTION NO. 201</num>
          <speech by="#32a29c39-915c-40e7-b749-7c09299ed1f7"><from>HON. DAVID WILSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas 100 years ago tomorrow, the "unsinkable" Titanic struck an iceberg in the North Atlantic, causing the death of over 1,500 passengers and crew; and</p>
<p>Whereas the City of Halifax and the Province of Nova Scotia sent cable ships to assist in the recovery efforts for those who had lost their lives, 150 of whom are buried in cemeteries in Halifax; and</p>
<p>Whereas this weekend the Titanic 100 Society will be commemorating the Titanic and Halifax's role in the tragedy through a series of public events, which I encourage Nova Scotians and visitors to participate in;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly stand in a moment of silence to commemorate the 100<sup>th</sup> Anniversary of the sinking of the Titanic and those passengers and crew members who lost their lives on the eventful night.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
          <narrative>
            <p>A moment of silence was observed.</p>
          </narrative>
        </debateSection>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>INTRODUCTION OF BILLS</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 20 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 379 of the Revised Statutes of 1989. The Public Trustee Act. (Hon. Ross Landry)</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 21 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 217 of the Revised Statutes of 1989. The Income Tax Act, to Provide a Nova Scotia Sound Recording Tax Credit. (Mr. Harold Theriault)</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Ordered that these bills be read a second time on a future day.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>ORDERS OF THE DAY</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT BUSINESS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#c7f2d366-8ba0-4263-98e0-bdaa9336415f">
          <from>MR. CLARRIE MACKINNON</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Government Motions.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT MOTIONS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#c7f2d366-8ba0-4263-98e0-bdaa9336415f">
          <from>MR. CLARRIE MACKINNON</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, I move that you do now leave the Chair and that the House resolve itself into a Committee of the Whole House on Supply.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>We will now take a short break to set up for the Committee of the Whole House on Supply unto Her Majesty.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>9:11 a.m. The House resolved itself into CWH on Supply with Deputy Speaker Mr. Alfie MacLeod in the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <narrative>
          <p>1:21 p.m. CWH on Supply rose and the House reconvened with Deputy Speaker Ms. Becky Kent in the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The Chairman of the Committee of the Whole House on Supply reports:</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined">
          <from>THE CLERK</from>
          <p>That the Committee of the Whole House on Supply has met and made considerable progress and begs leave to sit again.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#c7f2d366-8ba0-4263-98e0-bdaa9336415f">
          <from>MR. CLARRIE MACKINNON</from>
          <p>Madam Speaker, that concludes the government's business for the day. I move that the House do now rise to meet again on Monday, April 16<sup>th</sup> at 4:00 p.m., the House hours to be 4:00 p.m. to 10:00 p.m. Following the daily routine will be Public Bills for Second Reading, Bill Nos. 5, 9, 11, 13 and 17; and, of course, the Committee of the Whole House on Supply. Thank you.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the House do now rise to meet again on Monday, April 16<sup>th</sup> between the hours of 4:00 p.m. and 10:00 p.m.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>We are adjourned.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>The House rose at 1:22 p.m.</p>
        </narrative>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
