<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="5da6e0aa-9066-4b5c-8d26-9222b854db7e" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.marilyn.more" showAs="HON. MARILYN MORE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.karen.casey" showAs="HON. KAREN CASEY"/>
        <TLCPerson id="803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.frank.corbett" showAs="HON. FRANK CORBETT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.kelly.regan" showAs="MS. KELLY REGAN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.leo.glavine" showAs="MR. LEO GLAVINE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="b1bb12cd-3928-4525-bab1-d76d28109b5b" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.percy.paris" showAs="HON. PERCY PARIS"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8834559e-ddf7-4ac7-9b30-8ada0eb9a7ca" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.zach.churchill" showAs="MR. ZACH CHURCHILL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.diana.whalen" showAs="MS. DIANA WHALEN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="5e4eedce-ee17-4542-8b27-a1e87f85ec80" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.graham.steele" showAs="HON. GRAHAM STEELE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.keith.bain" showAs="MR. KEITH BAIN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.maureen.macdonald" showAs="HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="4fbcc786-c835-4a0e-bd05-40afb30e0683" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.charlie.parker" showAs="HON. CHARLIE PARKER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="2c8e1a56-2f9d-4156-a91f-77802701e3d3" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.geoff.maclellan" showAs="MR. GEOFF MACLELLAN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="799b989e-2c9d-4331-b5f3-5f78d3447b57" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.darrell.dexter" showAs="HON. DARRELL DEXTER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="1e5b7bdc-363b-4df4-8258-edcf8f2bf7fb" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.andrew.younger" showAs="MR. ANDREW YOUNGER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="05943c17-4381-46aa-8d21-dbc5ad93a99a" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.leonard.preyra" showAs="MR. LEONARD PREYRA"/>
        <TLCPerson id="72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.chuck.porter" showAs="MR. CHUCK PORTER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.jamie.baillie" showAs="Hon. Jamie Baillie"/>
        <TLCPerson id="e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.eddie.orrell" showAs="MR. EDDIE ORRELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.ramona.jennex" showAs="HON. RAMONA JENNEX"/>
        <TLCPerson id="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.michel.p.samson" showAs="HON. MICHEL SAMSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="5c3f8e78-5002-4c61-9c57-730090867f1b" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.wayne.j.gaudet" showAs="HON. WAYNE GAUDET"/>
        <TLCPerson id="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.christopher.a.dentremont" showAs="HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MR. SPEAKER"/>
        <TLCRole id="clerk" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.clerk" showAs="THE CLERK"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 7 May 2012</docTitle>
      <docNumber>12-26</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2012-05-07">Monday, May 7, 2012</docDate>
      <docProponent>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docProponent>
      <legislature value="61">61st General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="4">4th Session</session>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>Order, please. We will begin the daily routine.</p>
      </speech>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PRESENTING AND READING PETITIONS</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PRESENTING REPORTS OF COMMITTEES</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>TABLING REPORTS, REGULATIONS AND OTHER PAPERS</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>STATEMENTS BY MINISTERS</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Premier.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="860">RESOLUTION NO. 860</num>
          <speech by="#799b989e-2c9d-4331-b5f3-5f78d3447b57"><from>HON. DARRELL DEXTER</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Kji-keptin Alexander Denny dedicated his life to instilling the importance of Mi'kmaw teachings, beliefs, culture and language in his people, stressing the importance of the language and passing it on to future generations; and</p>
<p>Whereas L'nu Language Lab of the Unama'ki College of Cape Breton University, in partnership with the Mi'kmaw Kina'mnatnewey and the Nova Scotia Department of Education, supports Mi'kmaw language research and the development and delivery of Mi'kmaw language courses; and</p>
<p>Whereas Cape Breton University Unama'ki College recently named its language lab after Alex Denny to honour his leadership and his passion for the Mi'kmaw culture and language;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in congratulating Cape Breton University and the family of the late Kji-keptin on the recent naming of Kji-keptin Alex Denny Language Lab.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed?</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Labour and Advanced Education.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="861">RESOLUTION NO. 861</num>
          <speech by="#5da6e0aa-9066-4b5c-8d26-9222b854db7e"><from>HON. MARILYN MORE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas North American Occupational Safety and Health Week runs from May 6<sup>th</sup> to May 12<sup>th</sup>; and</p>
<p>Whereas this year's theme reinforces that safety is the foundation of any successful business and must be ingrained in all work practices; and</p>
<p>Whereas safety is everyone's responsibility and we must all work together to keep our workplaces free of injuries and illness;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House encourage all Nova Scotians to recognize May 6<sup>th</sup> to May 12<sup>th</sup> as North American Occupational Safety and Health Week, and emphasize that it is only through our combined efforts that we can make sure our Nova Scotia workplaces are truly safe.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Health and Wellness.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="862">RESOLUTION NO. 862</num>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas hospice palliative workers, both paid and voluntary, in Nova Scotia provide unconditional compassionate care and bring comfort and dignity to individuals approaching the end of their lives; and</p>
<p>Whereas during the week of May 6<sup>th</sup> to May 12<sup>th</sup> governments, health care workers and volunteers recognize National Hospice Palliative Care Week by raising awareness about hospice palliative care; and</p>
<p>Whereas this year's theme, "Let's Work Together!" reflects the difference that can be made in the lives of those living with a life-limiting illness when all members of the care team work together;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly recognize this week of May 6<sup>th</sup> to May 12<sup>th</sup>, as Hospice Palliative Care Week, and acknowledge the dedication of health care professionals, staff, and volunteers in the field.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="863">RESOLUTION NO. 863</num>
          <speech by="#b1bb12cd-3928-4525-bab1-d76d28109b5b"><from>HON. PERCY PARIS</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Irving Shipbuilding Inc. ranks first, and General Dynamics Canada, L-3 Communications, C-A-E, Lockeed Martin, and Bluedrop Performance Learning Inc. are among the top 18 companies of 50 ranked across Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas the province has demonstrated its commitment to this sector through its investments in Irving Shipbuilding Inc., the Aerospace and Defence Fund through jobsHere, a $1.7 million loan to Bluedrop, and past investments in L-3 Communications, Lockheed Martin, and General Dynamics; and</p>
<p>Whereas the aerospace and defence industry contributes almost $600 million in revenue annually to the province's economy;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly congratulate Irving Shipbuilding Inc., General Dynamics Canada, L-3 Communications, C-A-E, Lockheed Martin, and Bluedrop Performance Learning Inc. on being named to the top of a list that recognizes the best and brightest in Canada's growing defence sector.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>INTRODUCTION OF BILLS</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 81 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 4 of the Acts of 1994-95. The Gaming Control Act. (Hon. David Wilson)</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Ordered that this bill be read a second time on a future day.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Health and Wellness.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9">
            <from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, before I introduce my bill, I beg leave to make an introduction.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Most certainly.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9">
            <from>MS. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, in our east gallery I would like to draw the attention of the members to Mary Lee who is the executive director, or probably the CEO I would think, of Nova Scotia Association of Health Organizations. I would ask members to give her a warm welcome. I'm not sure if she's accompanied by the chairman of their board or not, but we welcome all of our guests and would ask people to extend a warm welcome. (Applause)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>We welcome all of our guests to the gallery and hope they enjoy this afternoon's proceedings.</p>
<p><b>Bill No. 82 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter III of the Acts of 1960. An Act to Incorporate Nova Scotia Association of Health Organizations. (Hon. Maureen MacDonald)</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 83 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 107 of the Acts of 1935. An Act to Incorporate the Annapolis Valley Apple Blossom Festival. (Mr. Jim Morton)</b></p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Ordered that these bills be read a second time on a future day.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Clare.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="864">RESOLUTION NO. 864</num>
          <speech by="#5c3f8e78-5002-4c61-9c57-730090867f1b"><from>HON. WAYNE GAUDET</from><p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, par la pr&#xE9;sente, j'avise que je proposerai &#xE0; une date ult&#xE9;rieure, l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendue que la communaut&#xE9; acadienne de la Nouvelle-&#xC9;cosse a subi une grande perte &#xE0; la suite du d&#xE9;c&#xE8;s de M. Gaston Chagnon, un ardent d&#xE9;fenseur des causes acadiennes de la Nouvelle-&#xC9;cosse; et</p>
<p>Attendue que Gaston Chagnon a soutenu le Courrier de la Nouvelle-&#xC9;cosse de fa&#xE7;on tangible au cours des ann&#xE9;es; et</p>
<p>Attendue que M. Chagnon a appuy&#xE9; tous les efforts de d&#xE9;veloppement de la langue francophone et la culture accadienne en Nouvelle-&#xC9;cosse;</p>
<p>Par cons&#xE9;quent qu'il soit r&#xE9;solu que tous les membres de cette assembl&#xE9;e reconnaissent la contribution remarquable de M. Gaston Chagnon et offrent leurs sinc&#xE8;res condol&#xE9;ances aux membres de sa famille.</p>
<p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, je propose l'adoption de cette r&#xE9;solution sans pr&#xE9;avis et sans d&#xE9;bats.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Nova Scotia Acadian community has lost a great supporter, Gaston Chagnon, on February 13, 2012; and</p>
<p>Whereas Gaston Chagnon was closely associated with Le Courrier de la Nouvelle-&#xC9;cosse; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Chagnon supported all efforts deployed for the development of Acadian education, culture and the French language in Nova Scotia;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize the contribution M. Gaston Chagnon has made to enhance the Acadian culture and offer our deepest sympathy to his family.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Victoria-The Lakes.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="865">RESOLUTION NO. 865</num>
          <speech by="#250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e"><from>MR. KEITH BAIN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Saturday, May 5<sup>th</sup>, family and friends gathered at the Baddeck Community Centre to celebrate 50 years in business of Gillis Construction Limited and Gillis Truckways; and</p>
<p>Whereas for over 50 years many roads in Victoria County were constructed with materials that were supplied by company owner Duncan Gillis; and</p>
<p>Whereas Duncan's contribution to his community has extended beyond his business to providing assistance and support to worthy causes within Baddeck and the surrounding community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly extend special congratulations to Duncan Gillis on 50 years in business and thank him for his tremendous contributions to his community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Natural Resources.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="866">RESOLUTION NO. 866</num>
          <speech by="#4fbcc786-c835-4a0e-bd05-40afb30e0683"><from>HON. CHARLIE PARKER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Pictou-Antigonish Regional Library has completed its eighth successful Writer-in-Residence program since its inception in 2005 with Pictou County writer Monica Graham; and</p>
<p>Whereas Monica Graham, a freelance journalist, photographer, and author, acted as mentor and instructor to writers of all types, from aspiring to experienced, by presenting sessions, workshops on writing skills and reviewing manuscripts; and</p>
<p>Whereas Monica Graham has had a successful term as the writer in the Writer in Residence Program at the Pictou-Antigonish Regional Library and has offered encouragement, guidance and support to writers in Pictou County and Antigonish County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly congratulate and thank Monica Graham for sharing her talent, her expertise and time as the 2011-12 Writer in Residence at the Pictou-Antigonish Regional Library.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Glace Bay.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="867">RESOLUTION NO. 867</num>
          <speech by="#2c8e1a56-2f9d-4156-a91f-77802701e3d3"><from>MR. GEOFF MACLELLAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the toll that child and youth mental disorders take on families and society is well-known, placing an importance on promoting mental health and early identification, diagnosis and effective treatment; and</p>
<p>Whereas it is imperative that we, as a committed and caring society, do what we know must be done to help our young people; and</p>
<p>Whereas there are innovative activities happening in our own province identifying and diagnosing and treating mental health disorders thanks to the work by Dr. Stan Kutcher, Dr. Anne Duffy, Dr. John LeBlanc, Patrick McGrath and Michael Unger;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize today, May 7<sup>th</sup>, as National Child and Youth Mental Health Day.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cape Breton North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="868">RESOLUTION NO. 868</num>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 9<sup>th</sup> Annual Gerard Morrison Memorial Montreal versus Toronto Fans Classic took place at the Sydney Mines and District Community Centre in March, named after Gerard Morrison one of the hard-core fans who started this annual event but died in 2009, a day before the game; and</p>
<p>Whereas Charlie Bowne, rink manager, provided the ice time to prove once and for all who had the most talented Northside fans - the Toronto Maple Leafs or the Montreal Canadiens; and</p>
<p>Whereas during the past nine years this has become the best attended event at the community centre with all proceeds donated to the Alex Johnson Memorial Scholarship Fund;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Northside hockey fans for this annual community spirit event.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Kings West.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="869">RESOLUTION NO. 869</num>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048"><from>MR. LEO GLAVINE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas May 7 - 13, 2012 is Mental Health Week; and</p>
<p>Whereas organized by the Canadian Mental Health Association, Mental Health Week encouraged Nova Scotians and Canadians from all walks of life to learn, converse, reflect and engage with each other on issues of mental health; and</p>
<p>Whereas this year's theme, Mental Health for All, reminds all of us that every Nova Scotian and Canadian has the right to enjoy good mental health;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this Legislature recognize May 7 - 13 as Mental Health Week and acknowledge the efforts of volunteers, professionals and all mental health organizations who are dedicated to helping our communities and province achieve better mental health for all.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Argyle.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="870">RESOLUTION NO. 870</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas today marks the beginning of the 61<sup>st</sup> Annual National Mental Health Week across Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas the recent report and recommendations of the Nova Scotia Mental Health and Addictions Strategy Advisory Committee showed 26 per cent of students in Nova Scotia are being screened for increased risk of depression and that between 10 per cent and 20 per cent of those students who wanted help did not receive it; and</p>
<p>Whereas statistics from the Mental Health Foundation of Nova Scotia show that one in every five Nova Scotians is affected by mental illness;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly compliment the ongoing work of the Mental Health Foundation and the Nova Scotia Mental Health Association and urge the Minister of Health and Wellness to complete the Nova Scotia Mental Health and Addictions Strategy.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="871">RESOLUTION NO. 871</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>MS. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on May 2, 2012, the Halifax Mainland North Volunteer Recognition Committee held their annual Community Champion Awards Dinner to recognize outstanding volunteers who consistently dedicate their time and talents to improving the lives of others; and</p>
<p>Whereas Pam Miller became a Red Cross volunteer in 1999 and during this time has taken on many roles, including that of trainer for disaster management for instructors throughout Atlantic Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas Pam Miller is the past president of the Nova Scotia Regional Council of the Canadian Red Cross and has been the Red Cross Emergency Operations Manager for several large responses in our province;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House congratulate Pam Miller for receiving a 2012 Community Champion Award for her remarkable contributions to her community and province, and wish her continued success in the future.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Hants West.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="872">RESOLUTION NO. 872</num>
          <speech by="#72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7"><from>MR. CHUCK PORTER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Andrew Seeley, son of Dave and Margie Seeley of Windsor, graduated from the RCMP Training Academy in Regina on April 30<sup>th</sup>, after beginning his initial training in November; and</p>
<p>Whereas Andrew is following in the footsteps of his father, Dave, who was a Mountie for a number of years, working in small detachments as well as with Special Security Operations, which saw his expertise called upon for seven Royal Tours across Canada, involving Queen Elizabeth II, and different Prime Ministerial visits; and</p>
<p>Whereas following a congratulatory reception, hosted by his parents, at the Windsor Curling Club Friday, Andrew's first posting will be in the sport-fishing capital of Manitoba, a small town 1,100 kilometres northwest of Winnipeg, known as Lynn Lake;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly extend good wishes to Andrew Seeley on his first RCMP posting, and wish him every success with his chosen career.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Bedford-Birch Cove.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="873">RESOLUTION NO. 873</num>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>MS. KELLY REGAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Donner Prize was established in 1998 to honour excellence and innovation in Canadian public policy thinking, writing, and research in Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas this year's $50,000 prize was awarded to <i>Democratizing the Constitution</i> by Peter Aucoin, Mark D. Jarvis, and Lori Turnbull, who argue in their book that the governing principle that the executive must be accountable to the people's elected representatives is eroding and that our Constitution and its unwritten rules no longer provide effective constraints on a Prime Minister's power; and</p>
<p>Whereas the late Dr. Aucoin was professor emeritus of political science and public administration at Dalhousie University, where Dr. Turnbull is an associate professor of political science at Dalhousie University as well;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Dalhousie's Lori Turnbull and the late Peter Aucoin and the University of Victoria's Mark Jarvis on their award and on their examination of the unchecked power of the Prime Minister.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Victoria-The Lakes.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="874">RESOLUTION NO. 874</num>
          <speech by="#250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e"><from>MR. KEITH BAIN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Municipality of the County of Victoria celebrated its 39<sup>th</sup> Annual Volunteer Recognition Night recently during Volunteer Week in Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas the South Haven Community Hall, the Iona Beautification Committee, the Neils Harbour /New Haven Development Association, Ski Cape Smokey, and the Baddeck Lions Club organizations, were recognized for their contribution and outstanding dedication to their community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteer organizations in all rural communities, such as Victoria County, are the backbone of the sport, recreation, cultural, spiritual, and social sectors;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate all board members and volunteers of the South Haven Community Hall, the Iona Beautification Committee, the Neils Harbour /New Haven Development Association, Ski Cape Smokey, and the Baddeck Lions Club, and thank them for their contribution to their communities.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Colchester North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="875">RESOLUTION NO. 875</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>HON. KAREN CASEY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Ben Holmes is a Grade 12 student at North Colchester High School in Tatamagouche, Colchester North, where he has earned Honours with Distinction each year; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ben is a dedicated team player, participating in soccer, basketball and softball, where he strives to improve his skills, doing the best for his team; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ben's determination is very evident, especially when competing at Reach for the Top, using his interest in trivia and his competitive nature to his advantage to succeed in these competitions;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate Ben Holmes for being named Student of the Month at North Colchester High School for March 2012.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cape Breton North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="876">RESOLUTION NO. 876</num>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Florence Elementary School students, as part of the Kids for Peace program, decided to make Florence a more beautiful place to live by planting daffodil and tulip bulbs on the grounds of the Canada Post Office; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Kids for Peace program for love and action cultivates a child's ability to foster peace through hands-on arts, service and environmental projects; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Grade Primary class, along with their teacher Jan Murray, are now anxiously awaiting the arrival of Spring to see their flowers pop through the soil;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ms. Murray and her students for taking such a proactive role in the beautification of their community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Yarmouth.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="877">RESOLUTION NO. 877</num>
          <speech by="#8834559e-ddf7-4ac7-9b30-8ada0eb9a7ca"><from>MR. ZACH CHURCHILL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas this week marks North American Occupational Health and Safety Week; and</p>
<p>Whereas workplace safety is paramount in protecting workers across the province and we all have a responsibility to ensure that workplaces are safe; and</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia can only prosper if the measures are taken to guarantee and promote workplace safety and injury prevention;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly work together with workers across the province to promote workplace safety and ensure safety and wellness for all Nova Scotians.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Hants West.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="878">RESOLUTION NO. 878</num>
          <speech by="#72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7"><from>MR. CHUCK PORTER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Windsor's Jake Lloy was recently named to Nova Scotia's High Performance Junior Development Golf Program; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Executive Director of Golf Nova Scotia, Dave Campbell, said 15-year-old Lloy is committed to the game and has tremendous potential; and</p>
<p>Whereas the 2012 High Performance Program will involve coaching including a clinic at Osprey Ridge Golf Club in Bridgewater, site of the 2012 Canadian Junior Men's Golf Championship, with Robert Radcliffe, one of the coaches from Canada's National Junior Team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly extend sincere wishes to Jake Lloy on being named to the 2012 Nova Scotia High Performance Junior Golf Development Program and wish him success on Nova Scotia's golf courses this summer.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Richmond.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="879">RESOLUTION NO. 879</num>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, &#xE0; une date ult&#xE9;rieure, je demanderai l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu que l'&#xE9;quipe f&#xE9;minine de volley-ball Richmond Rize Under-16 a particip&#xE9; au tournoi provincial Tier II &#xE0; Halifax durant la fin de semaine des 27 et 28 avril; et</p>
<p>Attendu que, avec seulement sept joueuses et aucune joueuse suppl&#xE9;ante sur le banc, les filles ont r&#xE9;ussi &#xE0; vaincre Sackville pour gagner la m&#xE9;daille de bronze du tournoi qui comptait dix-huit &#xE9;quipes; et</p>
<p>Attendu que sous la direction de leur entra&#xEE;neur Rhonda Gerrior, dont c'&#xE9;tait la premi&#xE8;re ann&#xE9;e, l'&#xE9;quipe &#xE9;tait form&#xE9;e de Kacie Boudreau, Samantha Martell, Kailey Landry, Megan Pierce, Grace Starkey, Simonne Savoury, Alex Burke, Kendra Sampson et Brittney Gurney, &#xE0; qui on a d&#xE9;cerne l'&#xE9;toile du tournoi pour sa performance;</p>
<p>Par cons&#xE9;quent, il est r&#xE9;solu que les membres de l'Assembl&#xE9;e l&#xE9;gislative de la Nouvelle-Ecosse se joignent &#xE0; moi pour f&#xE9;liciter l'entra&#xEE;neur Rhonda Gerrior et l'&#xE9;quipe f&#xE9;minine de volley-ball Richmond Rize Under-16 pour avoir remporter la m&#xE9;daille de bronze au tournoi provincial Tier II, et pour leur souhaiter du succ&#xE8;s dans leur prochaines comp&#xE9;titions.</p>
<p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, je demande l'adoption de cette r&#xE9;solution sans pr&#xE9;avis et sans d&#xE9;bat.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Richmond Rise Under-16 Volleyball Girls Team competed at the Tier Two Provincial Tournament in Halifax on the weekend of April 27<sup>th</sup> to 28<sup>th</sup>; and</p>
<p>Whereas with only seven players and no extra players on the bench, the girls battled back to beat Sackville and win the bronze medal game in the 18 Team Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas under the direction of first year coach Rhonda Gerrior, the team consisted of Kacie Boudreau, Samantha Martell, Kailey Landry, Megan Pierce, Grace Starkey, Simonne Savoury, Alex Burke, Kendra Sampson and Brittney Gurney, who was awarded Tournament All Star for her efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in congratulating coach Rhonda Gerrior and the Richmond Rize Under 16 Girls Volleyball Team for winning the bronze medal at the Tier Two Provincials and wish them continued success.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Colchester North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="880">RESOLUTION NO. 880</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>HON. KAREN CASEY</from><p>Mr. Speaker : I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas market needs are presenting an increasing demand for skilled workers in key sectors of our economy; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Nova Scotia Community College Truro Campus offers a five-year Automotive Service Technician course; and</p>
<p>Whereas the students have a block of six weeks of schooling each year, a total of 8,000 hours of work in the field during the course of the program and must write the test for Red Seal Certification;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate Mike Boyce of Colchester North, for receiving his Red Seal Certification in Automotive Service Technician.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Kings West.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="881">RESOLUTION NO. 881</num>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048"><from>MR. LEO GLAVINE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas May 6-12, 2012, has been dedicated as National Nursing Week in Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas this year's theme, Nursing - The Health of Our Nation, underscores the vital and essential role all nurses play in our health care system in order to improve the lives and well-being of Nova Scotians and Canadians; and</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia is most fortunate to have such a high calibre of women and men, who each and every day provide exceptional care and support to patients in our acute, long-term care, home care, and public health care sectors;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly salute our nursing workforce and extend to all nurses throughout Nova Scotia our appreciation for the exceptional care they provide each and every day.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Richmond.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="882">RESOLUTION NO. 882</num>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, &#xE0; une date ult&#xE9;rieure, je demanderai l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu que les Pieds-au-vol est une troupe de danse form&#xE9;e d'&#xE9;l&#xE8;ves de la 7e &#xE0; la 12e ann&#xE9;e de l'&#xC9;cole Beau-Port sous la direction de l'enseignante Ren&#xE9;e Samson; et</p>
<p>Attendu que, apr&#xE8;s avoir pratiqu&#xE9; de trios &#xE0; six jours par semaine, les Pieds-au-vol ont mont&#xE9; <i>Cendrillon</i> en fran&#xE7;ais et ont pr&#xE9;sent&#xE9; le spectacle &#xE0; plusieurs endroits et l'ont soumis &#xE0; Walt Disney dans le cadre du programme, &#xAB; Dance the Magic &#xBB; et</p>
<p>Attendu que les 14 et 15 avril dernier, les Pieds-au-vol, accompagn&#xE9;s d'anciens membres de la troupe aujourd'hui &#xE0; l'universit&#xE9;, ont particip&#xE9; &#xE0; la parade Disney dans la rue principale ainsi qu'au spectacle Disney Dance the Magic en Californie o&#xF9; ils ont pr&#xE9;sent&#xE9; deux danses &#xE0; claquettes de style acadien, et o&#xF9; ils ont particip&#xE9; &#xE0; plusieurs r&#xE9;p&#xE9;titions de danse ainsi qu'&#xE0; un camp de danse pr&#xE9;sent&#xE9; par les chor&#xE9;graphes de Disneyland;</p>
<p>Par cons&#xE9;quent, il est r&#xE9;solu que les membres de l'Assembl&#xE9;e l&#xE9;gislative de la Nouvelle-&#xC9;cosse se joignent &#xE0; moi pour f&#xE9;liciter l'Enseignante Ren&#xE9;e Samson et les membres de la troupe Chantal Berthier, Ren&#xE9;e N. Samson, Michelle Samson, Ren&#xE9;e George, Jannick Boudreau, Kaitlyn Boudreau, Lauren Boudreau, Janelle Boudreau, Karie Boudreau, Grace Starkey, Victoria David, Alicia David, Carly Kehoe, Tonie Pierce, Jaden David, Andr&#xE9;e Sampson, Micheline Savoury, Mychaela Sullivan, Jessica Samson, Christine Boucher, Samantha Martell, et Darby Keating pour leur remarquable performance &#xE0; Disneyland en Californie, et pour leur souhaiter du succ&#xE8;s dans les ann&#xE9;es &#xE0; venir.</p>
<p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, je demande l'adoption de cette r&#xE9;solution sans pr&#xE9;avis et sans d&#xE9;bat.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas les Pieds-au-vol is a dance troop of students from Grades 7 to 12 at &#xC9;cole Beau-Port, under direction of teacher Rene Samson; and</p>
<p>Whereas after practising three to six days a week, les Pieds-au-vol put on a performance of <i>Cinderella</i> in French, which was performed at several locations and submitted to Walt Disney under the Dance the Magic program; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 14<sup>th</sup> and April 15<sup>th</sup> les Pieds-au-vol, joined by former members who are now in university, performed in the Main Street Disney parade and performed in the Disney Dance the Magic Showcase in California, where they performed two routines of their Acadian style step dancing, while also taking part in several dance practices and a dance camp presented by the choreographers of Disneyland;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in congratulating instructor Rene Samson and les Pieds-au-vol dancers Chantal Berthier, Ren&#xE9;e N. Samson, Michelle Samson, Ren&#xE9;e George, Jannick Boudreau, Kaitlyn Boudreau, Lauren Boudreau, Janelle Boudreau, Karie Boudreau, Grace Starkey, Victoria David, Alicia David, Carly Kehoe, Tonie Pierce, Jaden David, Andr&#xE9;e Sampson, Micheline Savoury, Mychaela Sullivan, Jessica Samson, Christine Boucher, Samantha Martell, and Darby Keating for their remarkable accomplishment of dancing at Disneyland in California and wish them continued success.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Clare.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="883">RESOLUTION NO. 883</num>
          <speech by="#5c3f8e78-5002-4c61-9c57-730090867f1b"><from>HON. WAYNE GAUDET</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Canadian Welding Association held their student weld-off competition held on April 27, 2012, at the College of the North Atlantic in Port aux Basques in Newfoundland and Labrador; and</p>
<p>Whereas this event is a welding competition for welding students enrolled in one- or two-year entry level in the Atlantic Provinces; and</p>
<p>Whereas Nathan Boudreau of Clare, a first-year student at the NSCC Burridge Campus in Yarmouth, was a first-place winner in this competition;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Nathan Boudreau and wish him continued success in the future.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Bedford-Birch Cove.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="884">RESOLUTION NO. 884</num>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>MS. KELLY REGAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia-born, 19<sup>th</sup> Century war hero William Nelson Hall was the first Black man, the first Nova Scotian and the first member of the Navy to receive the Victoria Cross for extraordinary valour and devotion to duty while facing a hostile force, the highest honour in the Canadian honours system; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Hall joined the Royal Navy and had already been awarded three combat medals when he was sent to Lucknow, India, in 1857, where the Indian Mutiny was underway, and there he volunteered to serve on one of two crews ordered to break through the walls of a building where the rebel army was positioned, which he did even as every member of the crews were killed, save one other; and</p>
<p>Whereas many Nova Scotians believe it is high time that William Hall was recognized with a memorial at either the Valiants Memorial or the National War Memorial;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly urge the Government of Canada to act now to honour William Nelson Hall, VC, in our nation's capital.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Dartmouth East.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="885">RESOLUTION NO. 885</num>
          <speech by="#1e5b7bdc-363b-4df4-8258-edcf8f2bf7fb"><from>MR. ANDREW YOUNGER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Bedford Institute of Oceanography is Canada's premier centre for oceanographic research, providing advice and support on ocean issues, including safe navigation, offshore energy development, sustainable fishing, climate change, and protecting marine biodiversity and aquatic species at risk; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Bedford Institute of Oceanography has more than 600 employees, covering six federal government departments and partners with local universities, industries and community organizations; and</p>
<p>Whereas on October 24, 1962, W.E. van Steenburgh gave an address marking the official opening of Bedford Institute of Oceanography, saying, " &#x2026; I envision a period of expanding endeavour leading to a mutually integrated and beneficial research program &#x2026; which will enhance the scientific stature of each, and contribute to the solution for many complex and difficult problems to face the oceanographers of the future."</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly recognize the important contributions of the Bedford Institute of Oceanography, its staff, students, volunteers, and supporters made over the past 50 years to the knowledge, protection, and enhancement of the world's ocean environments;</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Yarmouth.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="886">RESOLUTION NO. 886</num>
          <speech by="#8834559e-ddf7-4ac7-9b30-8ada0eb9a7ca"><from>MR. ZACH CHURCHILL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas between 1976 and 1987 Elroy d'Entremont was a member of at least three provincial championship hockey teams, was on a Maritime championship team, and won a silver medal as he represented Nova Scotia at the Canada Games in Manitoba in 1979; and</p>
<p>Whereas Elroy d'Entremont was named best defenceman of five tournaments and won MVP honours at the local, regional and provincial levels; and</p>
<p>Whereas on May 5, 2012, Elroy d'Entremont was inducted into the Yarmouth Town and County Sports Heritage Association's Hall of Fame;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Elroy d'Entremont on being inducted into the Yarmouth Town and County Sports Heritage Association's Hall of Fame and recognize his athletic achievements and contributions to sports in Yarmouth.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Glace Bay.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="887">RESOLUTION NO. 887</num>
          <speech by="#2c8e1a56-2f9d-4156-a91f-77802701e3d3"><from>MR. GEOFF MACLELLAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Under 15 Tier One Nova Scotia Volleyball Championship was held at the Canada Games Complex in Halifax on April 26<sup>th</sup> to April 28<sup>th</sup>, featuring 10 teams from across the province; and</p>
<p>Whereas the number one seed Cape Breton Attackers defeated the Armview Storm of Halifax in the championship 25-21, 22-25, and finally 15-12 to capture the provincial title; and</p>
<p>Whereas Shauna Burke of Louisbourg was named championship MVP while Haley Hunt of Howie Centre and Glace Bay's own Emily MacDonald were named as tournament all-stars;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating the players and coaches of the Nova Scotia champion Cape Breton Attackers, and wish them success in the future.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="888">RESOLUTION NO. 888</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>MS. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Clayton Park community and staff at Keshen Goodman Public Library were pleased to welcome Heather MacKenzie as the new manager in December 2011; and</p>
<p>Whereas Heather has been a champion for literacy and has promoted youth education throughout her 30-year career with the Halifax public libraries; and</p>
<p>Whereas Heather has been part of the innovative IWK Read to Me Program and is currently president of the Atlantic Book Award Society;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Heather MacKenzie on her appointment as manager of the Keshen Goodman Public Library and wish her continued success in the future.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Halifax Citadel-Sable Island on an introduction.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#05943c17-4381-46aa-8d21-dbc5ad93a99a">
            <from>MR. LEONARD PREYRA</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, in the east gallery today are two, not familiar faces in this House but certainly familiar on the outside. Alison Clarke is one of the youngest and first members to join my campaign when I was being nominated in 2005, she's at the University of Guelph. Jordan Raycroft is a singer-songwriter who is travelling across the country. He has been singing at a number of coffee houses. In fact, I've had the great pleasure of being at a private concert by him this weekend and I'm delighted to welcome them to this House and I thank them for their great service to the community. I would ask them to rise and receive the warm applause of this House. (Applause)</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>ORDERS OF THE DAY</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT BUSINESS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, I move that you do now leave the Chair and the House resolve itself into a Committee of the Whole House on Bills.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The motion is carried.</p>
        </speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>4:50 p.m. The House resolved itself into a CWH on Bills with Deputy Speaker Ms. Becky Kent in the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <narrative>
          <p>4:59 p.m. CWH on Bills rose and the House reconvened. Mr. Speaker, Hon. Gordon Gosse, resumed the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The Chairman of the Committee of the Whole House on Bills reports:</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined"><from>THE CLERK</from><p>That the Committee of the Whole House on Bills has met and considered the following bills:</p>
<p><b>Bill No. 5 - Municipal Government Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 13 - Education Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 34 - Matrimonial Statutes Repeal Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 37 - Interjurisdictional Support Orders Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 39 - Maintenance and Custody Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 41 - Grandparents' Rights Affirmation Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 59 - Fish Harvesters Registration and Certification Board Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 61 - Fisheries and Coastal Resources Act.</b></p>
<p>and the chairman has been instructed to recommend these bills to the favourable consideration of the House, each without amendment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Ordered that these bills be read a third time on a future day.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, with the consent of the House, could we move to third reading of the bills that have just returned from Committee of the Whole House on Bills?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Public Bills for Third Reading.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PUBLIC BILLS FOR THIRD READING</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 5.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 5 - Municipal Government Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I move third reading of Bill No. 5.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for third reading of Bill No. 5. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill do pass. Ordered that the title be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bill be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 13.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 13 - Education Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I move third reading of Bill No. 13.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for third reading of Bill No. 13. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill do pass. Ordered that the title be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bill be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 34.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 34 - Matrimonial Statutes Repeal Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I move third reading of Bill No. 34.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for third reading of Bill No. 34. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill do pass. Ordered that the title be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bill be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 37.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 37 - Interjurisdictional Support Orders Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I move third reading of Bill No. 37.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for third reading of Bill No. 37. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill do pass. Ordered that the title be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bill be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 39.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 39 - Maintenance and Custody Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I move third reading of Bill No. 39.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for third reading of Bill No. 39. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill do pass. Ordered that the title be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bill be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 41.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 41 - Grandparents' Rights Affirmation Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Victoria-The Lakes.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e"><from>MR. KEITH BAIN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I'm pleased to stand in my place to speak for a few moments on Bill No. 41. We've said numerous times that the bill that the government has put forward is meaningless in the fact that all it does is insert the word "grandparents" and they were already included in the word "others" that was there.</p>
<p>I think grandparents have been done an injustice by bringing the bill forward in the way the government has proceeded. Grandparents, in most cases, are not looking for custody of their grandchild, but want to be able to at least see their grandchildren. In some cases that's not happening, through no fault of the child or no fault of the grandparent. We did table a bill that would give grandparents that right through proper systems, but I guess it's important - when I think about what took place here last week when we had grandparents and great-grandparents protesting in from the Legislature, how serious they are.</p>
<p>Speaking personally, I have a granddaughter who will be two in August and I can't imagine what it would be like if my right to see my granddaughter was taken away from me.</p>
<p>I think it's important that we look, as we go forward, to making it easier, unless there is any reasonable doubt, that these grandparents who are so passionate about what they are doing would have the right to see their grandchild.</p>
<p>And with that, Mr. Speaker, I'll take my seat.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for third reading of Bill No. 41. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered at this bill do pass. Ordered that the title be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bill be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 59.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 59 - Fish Harvesters Registration and Certification Board Act.</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 61 - Fisheries and Coastal Resources Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motions are carried.</p>
<p>Ordered at these bills do pass. Ordered that the titles be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bills be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, with unanimous consent of the House, I wonder if we could do the order of business, Private and Local Bills for Second Reading.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PRIVATE AND LOCAL BILLS FOR SECOND READING</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 83, the Annapolis Valley Apple Blossom Festival Incorporation Act.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 83 - Annapolis Valley Apple Blossom Festival Incorporation Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for second reading of Bill No. 83. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered at this bill be referred to the Committee on Private and Local Bills.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PUBLIC BILLS FOR SECOND READING</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 79.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 79 - Education Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Minister of Education.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a"><from>HON. RAMONA JENNEX</from><p>Thank you very much, Mr. Speaker. I move that Bill No. 79 be read a second time.</p>
<p>I am pleased to rise in my place to speak to this bill, an amendment to the Education Act. This bill is designed to align the Education Act with changes that were agreed to in the Teachers' Provincial Agreement. This amendment will ensure there is consistency and clarity between the Act and the TPA. When provisions of the TPA are adjusted as a result of negotiations, it is sometimes necessary to amend the Education Act well to mirror the changes to ensure there is consistency. That is the case with Bill No. 79.</p>
<p>Under the proposed changes, school boards in the province will have the option of extending a probationary contract for a third year, from two, if a teacher did not accrue a minimum of 145 days of service in any probationary year. Although the Ministerial Education Act Regulations define the school year as consisting of 195 days, the 145-day figure represents 75 per cent of the school year, which should provide a board with sufficient time to evaluate a teacher's performance during a probationary year, if required. Extending a probationary contract for a third year is simply providing school boards an option if it is required.</p>
<p>The other amendment deals with replacing assistant superintendent with the word director to update the terminology now being used and will align the Education Act with the definition of senior staff contained in the Ministerial Education Act Regulations. Again, Mr. Speaker, this is about providing constancy and clarity. These changes were agreed to during the last round of bargaining and signed by parties on November 10<sup>th</sup> of the last year.</p>
<p>The amendments are the result of two partners working together through the collective bargaining process and finding common ground to ensure there is no gray area with these issues. Bill No. 79 is about the province living up to its commitment made to the Nova Scotia Teachers Union to ensure there is consistency between the Education Act and the Teachers' Provincial Agreement, Thank you Mr. Speaker.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Richmond.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Thank you, Mr. Speaker, on behalf of the Official Opposition we're pleased to see this bill coming forward that better reflects the agreements that have been put in place with Nova Scotia Teachers Union.</p>
<p>I would be remiss if I did not say that we continue to be very troubled by the strained relationship that has developed between this minister, this government, with the hard-working teachers throughout this province. Just a week ago or so we did have representatives from Nova Scotia Teachers Union here to express their concern with this government's continued cuts to education which now total over $65 million, which is clearly having a negative impact on the classroom. In fact, today I spoke with a parent in my riding, who was quite concerned over the fact this school year her daughter, who has autism, was not granted a teacher assistant and the difficulties that she has encountered. Her fear now, with her daughter graduating from Grade 8 and moving on to high school, is whether or not she will have a teacher's aide to help her with that very challenging transition.</p>
<p>So these cuts are having an impact and I would be remiss if I didn't remind the minister of her comments during the day when the Teachers Union was here and her response to one of the questions was in essence, the Nova Scotia Teachers Union is looking out for their members while her government is looking out for students. Madam Speaker, a more unfortunate statement I could not think of when it comes to teachers in our province, to suggest that their union is simply looking at its membership and has absolutely no interest in our students, clearly is an extremely unfortunate statement. I received correspondence from a number of teachers who were simply outraged at the comments that were made, certainly knowing the minister's own history with the union movement as a teacher and active with the union to hear those types of comments.</p>
<p>I would suggest to you, Mr. Speaker, that more work needs to be done - more importantly, more respect needs to be shown to the men of women who each day we entrust our children to, to be cared for and to be educated in the best possible way. That is certainly no way for a Minister of Education to treat them, and it certainly is no way for this government to treat them. I certainly hope that we are going to see a change in that relationship in the very near future, which I believe is essential for the best interest of our public education system here in this province. Merci.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for second reading of Bill No. 79. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill be referred to the Committee on Law Amendments.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 78.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 78 &#x2013;Justice Administration (2012) Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Deputy Premier.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I move second reading of Bill No. 78, the Justice Administration (2012) Act.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Richmond.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, on behalf of the Minister of Justice, I would be more than happy to explain this bill in a bit more detail. The Justice Administration Act is a yearly, sometimes bi-yearly, occurrence here in the Province of Nova Scotia where government brings in a number of administrative-type changes.</p>
<p>While I've certainly been very vocal in my concerns over the years that government has tried to include some fairly controversial elements in this Justice Administration Act, this one may not fall under that title, but it certainly has a few elements to it, which I believe are of concern to us and should be of concern to Nova Scotians. In essence this bill is looking to make changes to some of the boards that we administer here in the Province of Nova Scotia. Some of the ones that will be affected are: Arts Nova Scotia, the Creative Nova Scotia Leadership Council, the Nova Scotia Liquor Corporation Board and the Film Classification Board.</p>
<p>There is, as well, a change to the House of Assembly Management Commission, which you'll be aware that I tabled legislation in essence to do the exact same thing that's included in this bill. When the House of Assembly Management Commission was created, in many ways it copied the Newfoundland and Labrador legislation and one of the peculiar items that was in there said that if you were a member of the House of Assembly Management Commission you couldn't sit as a member of the Public Accounts Committee.</p>
<p>Where the link is between the two, I'm not quite sure, but it created a bit of a bizarre situation in the fact that right now we had two members of the Management Commission who also wanted to be participants on the Public Accounts Committee, yet the Act itself did not allow that to happen. This was something that, I think, was just included in the legislation without thought of the implications. This certainly creates a major problem, especially when you have smaller caucuses - which often happens in Opposition - the idea of barring members from being able to sit on two committees is not something, I believe, that applies to any other committees of the House. This is something that was added in, which I don't think anyone would argue is a necessity. This change will now allow members who sit on the House of Assembly Management Commission to also sit as members of the Public Accounts Committee as well.</p>
<p>One of the concerns that we have with Bill No. 78, because it's a Justice Administration bill, the minister that we'd like to hear from regarding our concern is the Minister of Finance who, if I'm not mistaken, would be the Minister responsible for the Nova Scotia Liquor Corporation Board. At a time when government is cutting - whether it be education, health care, the Rural Impact Mitigation fund in the Department of Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal and a number of other programs - the government is bringing in a bill to put two new members on the board of the Nova Scotia Liquor Corporation.</p>
<p>When you look at the fact the Province of Nova Scotia, I believe you could say we're a $9 billion corporation in the revenues that we bring in, along with federal transfers, this would not be a major budgetary item. But in a time of restraint, why the government would want to increase the membership of the Nova Scotia Liquor Corporation Board, I believe is a question Nova Scotians should be asking themselves.</p>
<p>This board pays a fee to its members of $1,000 a month, so for two extra members, that's $24,000 a year. If I'm not mistaken, that may pay for the salary of a teacher assistant, or it may help pay the salary of a library assistant. Instead, we're going to put two more Nova Scotians on the Nova Scotia Liquor Corporation Board. Because this is coming from the Minister of Justice through the Justice Administration (2012) Bill, the Minister of Finance is not required to stand in the House and justify that decision.</p>
<p>If I'm not mistaken, I believe the Nova Scotia Liquor Corporation has been bringing in record profits to the Treasury of the Province of Nova Scotia. It's not a situation where it's a Crown Corporation which is not performing as we would hope. I believe the media reports were that it was to encourage a bit more diversity of backgrounds on the board. That's a laudable goal but at a time of fiscal restraint that the government is preaching, is this really the right time to be increasing the size of a board that pays probably some of the highest fees of any of the boards, agencies or commissions that we have here in the Province of Nova Scotia?</p>
<p>So, I know I'm very curious to see how the Minister of Finance would justify growing the Liquor Corporation Board, at a time of restraint spending $24,000 of taxpayers' money for members of the Liquor Corporation Board, while the Minister of Education is cutting teachers' assistants and cutting library technicians and other supports in our education system. The Minister of Health and Wellness is required to ask health authorities to cut back on their funding. This certainly sends a mixed message, to say the least, from this government.</p>
<p>So, as I said, while he's not required to do so, I would hope that the Minister of Finance who's responsible for this board would take the opportunity on second reading to explain to the House, and explain to Nova Scotians, how and why he feels this is an appropriate time to be growing the composition of the Nova Scotia Liquor Corporation. Mr. Speaker, with those comments, I certainly look forward to hearing from the Minister of Finance so that we can better understand why this is necessary at this point in time. Merci.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Minister of Finance.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#5e4eedce-ee17-4542-8b27-a1e87f85ec80"><from>HON. GRAHAM STEELE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I wasn't planning to speak today but I was listening to the wise words of the member opposite and I thought I would take a brief opportunity to address the question. It's a good question, of course - why would we be proposing to expand the board of the Liquor Corporation?</p>
<p>The answer I suppose, Mr. Speaker, is simple. It is, I would point out, fully laid out in the news release that accompanied this bill. It's being done at the request of the board. The chair of the board is prepared to speak to anyone in the House, or outside the House, who has a question about this. It is simply a matter of good governance practices that the chair of the board has found the board to be too small to be properly functional in a modern board governance environment and, in particular, the seven members of the board are not enough to have a fully functioning committee system.</p>
<p>Modern governance practice means you have to have, for example, a fully functioning audit committee, a human resources committee and so on and so on. It can't just be the same people doing all the committee work. So at the request of the chair of the board, we accept that modern governance practices would suggest that the board can function better with nine members rather than seven. I do want to stress this is coming forward at the request of the board. That is the rationale that they have offered, which the government accepts, and that's the reason for the expansion of the board.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for second reading of Bill No. 78. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill be referred to the Committee on Law Amendments.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, that concludes the government's business for today. I move that the House do now rise to meet from the hours of 12:00 noon until 8:00 p.m. tomorrow.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the House now rise to meet again tomorrow at 12:00 noon.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
          <narrative>
            <p>The House rose at 5:24 p.m.</p>
          </narrative>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION UNDER RULE 32(3)</heading>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
