<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="d6c0c78d-dcf3-456a-915c-a20ecb33050f" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.john.macdonell" showAs="HON. JOHN MACDONELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.karen.casey" showAs="MS. CASEY"/>
        <TLCPerson id="fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.stephen.mcneil" showAs="HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.frank.corbett" showAs="HON. FRANK CORBETT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.kelly.regan" showAs="MS. KELLY REGAN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="b1bb12cd-3928-4525-bab1-d76d28109b5b" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.percy.paris" showAs="MR. PARIS"/>
        <TLCPerson id="e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.eddie.orrell" showAs="MR. EDDIE ORRELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.keith.bain" showAs="MR. KEITH BAIN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.diana.whalen" showAs="MS. DIANA WHALEN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="de2082f3-cf3a-4955-8a4e-4f1bf0ac1301" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.mat.whynott" showAs="MR. MAT WHYNOTT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="2c8e1a56-2f9d-4156-a91f-77802701e3d3" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.geoff.maclellan" showAs="MR. GEOFF MACLELLAN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="1e5b7bdc-363b-4df4-8258-edcf8f2bf7fb" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.andrew.younger" showAs="MR. ANDREW YOUNGER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.allan.gerard.macmaster" showAs="MR. ALLAN MACMASTER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="4f242ac5-fc82-41a3-8089-419e69284e5e" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.maurice.g.smith" showAs="HON. MAURICE SMITH"/>
        <TLCPerson id="3b49aa8d-3e78-4679-b8f7-f3161f11d3a3" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.sterling.belliveau" showAs="HON. STERLING BELLIVEAU"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8834559e-ddf7-4ac7-9b30-8ada0eb9a7ca" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.zach.churchill" showAs="MR. ZACH CHURCHILL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="e23caf06-dcf3-42a5-8a00-f4435df40350" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.alfie.macleod" showAs="MR. ALFIE MACLEOD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="05943c17-4381-46aa-8d21-dbc5ad93a99a" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.leonard.preyra" showAs="HON. LEONARD PREYRA"/>
        <TLCPerson id="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.christopher.a.dentremont" showAs="Hon. Christopher d'Entremont"/>
        <TLCRole id="clerk" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.clerk" showAs="THE CLERK"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MR. SPEAKER"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 15 April 2013</docTitle>
      <docNumber>13-13</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2013-04-15">Monday, April 15, 2013</docDate>
      <docProponent>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docProponent>
      <legislature value="61">61st General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="5">5th Session</session>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>Order, please. We'll begin the daily routine.</p>
      </speech>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PRESENTING AND READING PETITIONS</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PRESENTING REPORTS OF COMMITTEES</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>TABLING REPORTS, REGULATIONS AND OTHER PAPERS</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>STATEMENTS BY MINISTERS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#b1bb12cd-3928-4525-bab1-d76d28109b5b"><from>HON. PERCY PARIS</from><p>Mr. Speaker, earlier this afternoon the province announced support, through a loan guarantee, for Lewis Mouldings and Wood Specialties in Weymouth. We are fortunate that several representatives of this long-standing family-owned business are in the gallery this afternoon. Jamie Lewis is the general manager and his sister, Laurie Wheatley, manages human resources and fibre fuel sales. Their father, Stewart Lewis, founded the company.</p>
<p>I would, with the permission of the House, Mr. Speaker, make a brief introduction.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>Most certainly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#b1bb12cd-3928-4525-bab1-d76d28109b5b">
          <from>MR. PARIS</from>
          <p>I would ask that the members of the House give a very warm and sincere welcome to the following individuals: Jamie Lewis, general manager; and Laurie Wheatley, manager, human resources and fibre fuel sales for Lewis Mouldings. I would ask them to stand, please. (Applause)</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>We welcome all our guests to the gallery and hope they enjoy this afternoon's proceedings.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#b1bb12cd-3928-4525-bab1-d76d28109b5b"><from>HON. PERCY PARIS</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I am pleased to rise today to talk about how this government is helping businesses of all sizes create and maintain good jobs and grow our economy. One of those companies is Lewis Mouldings and Wood Specialties in southwestern Nova Scotia. They employ 75 people in Weymouth, where they manufacture white pine mouldings, baseboards, and other millwork. They also produce fibre fuel, a briquette made from wood waste that is used as an alternative to firewood.</p>
<p>Earlier this afternoon I announced that the province is supporting Lewis Mouldings with a loan guarantee so it can continue to modernize, hire, and expand into new markets. The loan guarantee will help ensure families can stay in Weymouth, continue to earn a good living, and keep supporting the many other businesses in the community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, Lewis Mouldings is an important contributor to Nova Scotia's forestry industry, an industry that is boldly reinventing. Nova Scotia's plan for the future of our forestry includes leading in innovation and partnerships, as we've done with Renova Scotia Bioenergy centre at the former Bowater mill site.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, forestry jobs and opportunities are just as much part of our future as they are of our past. Lewis Mouldings is no stranger to innovation; they develop new and creative ways to add value to Nova Scotia's forestry sector. Tomorrow, business, industry, academia, and youth leaders from around the world will come together at Nova Scotia's first Innovation Summit. They will be discussing how we can develop a better approach to encourage and support innovation in Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, we can always look for new and better ways of doing things, Lewis Mouldings certainly is. Nova Scotia's forestry sector is poised to deliver even greater benefit by exploring new opportunities with more innovative products. Now more than ever Nova Scotia must embrace innovation and support growth to help our businesses like Lewis Mouldings to succeed. Thank you.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Glace Bay.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#2c8e1a56-2f9d-4156-a91f-77802701e3d3"><from>MR. GEOFF MACLELLAN</from><p>I would also like to thank the minister for his advance copy of his statement today. Small and medium enterprises are the backbone of our economy and it is always important to celebrate the achievements and the growth of businesses that call Nova Scotia home. As a province we are encouraged to see success in the private sector as it signals that the hard work, sacrifice, and risk is paying off for local entrepreneurs. We are fully supportive of Lewis Mouldings of Weymouth and we know that they will continue to innovate, grow, and inspire other stakeholders in the forestry sector. The guaranteeing of loans is an important tool government has to provide support to the private sector and share in that risk while recovering tax dollars when respective companies experience increasingly healthy balance sheets.</p>
<p>From a departmental perspective we must always ensure that officials have done their homework and we have a reasonably good chance of having loans repaid to the provincial coffers. However, Mr. Speaker, making a statement on a loan guarantee is hardly reassuring when it comes to our government's ability to create jobs and grow the economy. Economic growth doesn't require ministerial statements; it will be apparent in the form of GDP growth, unemployment rate decline, an expanded labour force, and the slowing of out-migration. You won't have to tell Nova Scotians their economy is growing; they will feel it in their communities and see it through their ability to pay the bills. Again, we offer congratulations and best of luck to Lewis Mouldings. Thank you.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Cape Breton North.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I'd also like to thank the minister for a copy of his remarks in advance and the member for Glace Bay for his comments. I'd like to thank Mr. Jamie Lewis for being here today. Lewis Mouldings and Wood Specialties in southwest Nova Scotia is a great small business that employs 75 people in Weymouth and the surrounding areas. Our Leader has had the opportunity to tour Lewis Mouldings and meet with the people who work there. They care deeply about maintaining good jobs and protecting the way of life in rural Nova Scotia. Lewis Mouldings is a great example of a third-generation business with deep roots in the community and a leader in the eastern white pine value-added industry, but Lewis Mouldings is just one of the many businesses that have been hit hard by the NDP's mismanagement of the economy.</p>
<p>Over the last four years under this NDP Government the South Shore economy has been hit hard. The discontinuation of the Yarmouth ferry is just one blow to this region. People in businesses in the South Shore face some of the highest taxes in Canada and the highest power rates. This has led to 2,500 fewer people employed in the region, 4,500 fewer full-time jobs, and there are 3,100 fewer people in the labour force in that region. In the last year alone there are 1,100 fewer full-time jobs. The region has an unemployment rate of 13.2 per cent, one of the highest unemployment rates in the province. As small-business families are looking for much-needed breaks from taxes and skyrocketing costs of necessities like power and food, government needs to lower taxes, stop wasteful spending, and allow all business to compete and create jobs. Thank you, Mr. Speaker.</p></speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Deputy Premier.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="307">RESOLUTION NO. 307</num>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23"><from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, on behalf of the Premier, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas April 17<sup>th</sup> marks one year since the tragic death of community leader and activist Raymond Taavel; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Taavel is remembered as someone who devoted his entire life to fighting discrimination, violence, and intolerance aimed at people because of their sexual orientation or gender identity; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Taavel's death will be marked by a quiet community remembrance where friends, family, and supporters may come together to look forward to a better, more open and inclusive Nova Scotia;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House unanimously agree that on April 17, 2013, the rainbow Pride flag will fly at half-mast on the grounds of Province House to join others in affirming the spirit of community solidarity that Raymond Taavel exemplified.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Agriculture.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="308">RESOLUTION NO. 308</num>
          <speech by="#d6c0c78d-dcf3-456a-915c-a20ecb33050f"><from>HON. JOHN MACDONELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Loblaws is a major retail grocer in many towns and cities throughout the Maritimes, operating banner stores such as Atlantic Superstore, No Frills, and SaveEasy; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 11<sup>th</sup> more than 50 food growers and producers from Nova Scotia, New Brunswick, and Prince Edward Island attended Loblaws' annual Atlantic producers meeting in Moncton; and</p>
<p>Whereas den Haan's Garden World of Brickton, Annapolis County, captured Loblaw's Vendor Development Award for 2012;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jodi and Luke den Haan on receiving Loblaw's Vendor Development Award, and recognize all of the greenhouses and farms around our province that supply Nova Scotians with fresh, local products, helping to make agriculture a thriving sector of our economy.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Fisheries and Aquaculture.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="309">RESOLUTION NO. 309</num>
          <speech by="#3b49aa8d-3e78-4679-b8f7-f3161f11d3a3"><from>HON. STERLING BELLIVEAU</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Boston Marathon is the world's largest, oldest annual marathon, and ranks as one of the world's most prestigious road-racing events; and</p>
<p>Whereas qualifying for the Boston Marathon is a difficult and competitive task which requires hard work, commitment, and training; and</p>
<p>Whereas Frank Reinhardt, a dedicated public servant for the Departments of Agriculture, and Fisheries and Aquaculture, has qualified for the 2013 race and will participate in the Boston Marathon on April 15, 2013;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate Frank Reinhardt on qualifying for the Boston Marathon and wish him the best of luck for the race.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Communities, Culture and Heritage.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="310">RESOLUTION NO. 310</num>
          <speech by="#05943c17-4381-46aa-8d21-dbc5ad93a99a"><from>HON. LEONARD PREYRA</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotians celebrated Adult Learners' Week from April 6<sup>th</sup> to April 14<sup>th</sup>; and</p>
<p>Whereas adult learners in the province participated in an essay-writing contest to help raise awareness of the tremendous value of lifelong learning and preparing them for opportunities today and tomorrow; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ariel Harper Nave, Rukhsora Sangova, Nancy MacDougall, and Ryan Maisonneuve were winners of the contest for their outstanding work and personal commitment to lifelong learning;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly join me in congratulating these winners and all those who submitted essays, marking Adult Learners' Week, and recognizing the significant impact of lifelong learning on individuals and their communities.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>INTRODUCTION OF BILLS</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 41 - Entitled an Act to Protect Children from Those Who Might Harm Them. (Hon. Jamie Baillie)</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 42 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 41 of the Acts of 2011. The Pension Benefits Act. (Hon. Frank Corbett)</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 43 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 197 of the Acts of 1901, An Act to Incorporate the Trustees of the Onslow Cemetery Company. (Hon. Karen Casey)</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Ordered that these bills be read a second time on a future day.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="311">RESOLUTION NO. 311</num>
          <speech by="#fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5"><from>HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the week of April 21<sup>st</sup> marks the beginning of National Volunteer Week, a week set aside to honour individuals who donate their precious spare time to help others in support of causes in which they strongly believe; and</p>
<p>Whereas earlier today more than 70 volunteers from across the province were honoured at the 39<sup>th</sup> Annual Provincial Volunteer Awards; and</p>
<p>Whereas this unheralded group of men and women of all ages and from all backgrounds - young Nova Scotians, seniors, workers, and those who are retired - help to make our communities and province stronger each and every day;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House acknowledge April 21<sup>st</sup> to April 27<sup>th</sup> as National Volunteer Week and extend our appreciation to the countless ordinary volunteers in Nova Scotia who give so freely of themselves to accomplish extraordinary things.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Victoria-The Lakes.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="312">RESOLUTION NO. 312</num>
          <speech by="#250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e"><from>MR. KEITH BAIN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Monday, April 15<sup>th</sup>, marks a very special day with the reopening of Talbot House in Frenchvale; and</p>
<p>Whereas for over 50 years Talbot House has been guiding the addiction recovery and rehabilitation of men from across Nova Scotia and Atlantic Canada through self-discovery and growth in a life-giving environment of faith, hope, and courage; and</p>
<p>Whereas hundreds of people showed their support for Talbot House as they attended an open house on Sunday, April 14<sup>th</sup>, to learn more about it and to celebrate the reopening;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the board and staff of Talbot House and its executive director, Father Paul Abbass, on the reopening of Talbot House, and wish them every success in the future.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="313">RESOLUTION NO. 313</num>
          <speech by="#4f242ac5-fc82-41a3-8089-419e69284e5e"><from>HON. MAURICE SMITH</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Jim Mulcahy is a retired Antigonish English and drama teacher and is the creative force behind the Park Bench Players, an amateur theatre troupe whose performance about the stigma associated with mental illness has garnered national accolades; and</p>
<p>Whereas Jim Mulcahy, himself a cancer patient, has dedicated his time to improving the experiences of those living with cancer, both as a volunteer at the Oncology Unit at St. Martha's Regional Hospital and as a member of Cancer Care Nova Scotia's Advisory Group to the Patient Engagement Project; and</p>
<p>Whereas earlier today Jim Mulcahy was recognized at the 39<sup>th</sup> Provincial Volunteer Awards ceremony for his extraordinary community and volunteer work;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House thank Mr. Mulcahy for his tireless commitment to improving the lives of others and making our community a better place.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Colchester North.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22">
            <from>HON. KAREN CASEY</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, with your permission, I would like to do an introduction.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Most certainly.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>MS. CASEY</from><p>We have in the gallery opposite this evening, three of the trustees from the Onslow Cemetery. I would ask them to stand as they are introduced and then there will be a resolution with respect. First of all, Marie McCully Collier, who is chair of the Onslow Cemetery Trustees; with her is Eleanor Norrie, no stranger to this House, a Liberal MLA for Truro-Bible Hill from 1993 to 1998; and Bonnie Waddell, who is the anniversary committee chair, part of the committee that is planning for the 250<sup>th</sup> Anniversary of the Onslow Cemetery.</p>
<p>I'd like to welcome you to the House and I'm glad that you're here for the introduction of the bill and for the reading of the resolution. (Applause)</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>We welcome all our guests to the gallery and especially former members.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Colchester North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="314">RESOLUTION NO. 314</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>HON. KAREN CASEY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Onslow Cemetery "on the east side of the island in the upper marsh" had its humble beginnings as a burying ground in 1763, making it one of the oldest in Nova Scotia; and</p>
<p>Whereas it was in 1853 that this Legislative Assembly passed an Act to establish the appointment of trustees to oversee the operation of the burial ground; and</p>
<p>Whereas it was again in this Assembly in 1901 that an Act was passed to Incorporate the Trustees of the Onslow Cemetery Company, giving them the power to make bylaws, rules, and regulations for the management and care of the burial ground;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly acknowledge and thank current and former trustees of the Onslow Cemetery Company for their stewardship over the past 250 years, and for preserving and protecting this special part of history in Colchester North and, indeed, the Province of Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cape Breton North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="315">RESOLUTION NO. 315</num>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas each year communities across Canada mark National Volunteer Week to thank and honour the people who generously give their time and talents to help others; and</p>
<p>Whereas dedicated volunteers are the backbone of Nova Scotia's tight-knit communities; and</p>
<p>Whereas Brittany Marsh of the Cape Breton Regional Municipality was recognized at the 39<sup>th</sup> Annual Provincial Volunteer Awards ceremony for the many contributions she has made to her community and her province;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly thank Brittany Marsh for all the work she does for others and congratulate her for receiving a Provincial Volunteer Award.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5">
            <from>HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, may I do an introduction before I read the resolution?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Most certainly.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5">
            <from>MR. MCNEIL</from>
            <p>I'd like to draw the attention of the House to the west gallery to where we have Mr. Dan Hennessey from Bakers Settlement, as well as Mark Furey, who is the Liberal candidate in Lunenburg West, whenever the election is going to be called. I want the House to give them a warm welcome. (Applause)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Again, we welcome all our guests to the gallery and hope they enjoy this afternoon's proceedings.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="316">RESOLUTION NO. 316</num>
          <speech by="#fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5"><from>HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas at the age of 49 Dan Hennessey was diagnosed with prostate cancer, a journey where early treatment and diagnosis, coupled with a strong support system in that of his family, community, and health care team, helped him to beat the disease; and</p>
<p>Whereas during treatment Dan took pen in hand and wrote about his thoughts and feelings, which eventually evolved into a book called <i>With the Snap of a Glove</i>, a book which shares with the world the vulnerable human side of prostate cancer; and</p>
<p>Whereas last year Dan continued his passionate journey of advocacy by creating a video which encourages discussion between teens and their fathers to get tested as a means to not only raise awareness but hopefully save a life;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly extend our deepest appreciation to Dan Hennessey for sharing his journey with us and with the world and wish him many years of health, happiness and inspiration.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Inverness.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="317">RESOLUTION NO. 317</num>
          <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff"><from>MR. ALLAN MACMASTER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas each year communities across Canada mark National Volunteer Week to thank and honour the people who generously give their time and talents to help others; and</p>
<p>Whereas dedicated volunteers are the backbone of Nova Scotia's tight-knit communities; and</p>
<p>Whereas Reverend Andrew MacDonald, of the Municipality of the County of Inverness, was recognized at the 39<sup>th</sup> Annual Provincial Volunteer Awards Ceremony today for the many contributions he has made to his community and his province;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly thank Reverend Andrew MacDonald for all the work he does for others and congratulate him for receiving a Provincial Volunteer Award.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Bedford-Birch Cove.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728">
            <from>MS. KELLY REGAN</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I beg leave to make an introduction.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Most certainly.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728">
            <from>MS. REGAN</from>
            <p>I'd like to draw the members' attention to the west gallery where we have been joined by some members, coaches and managers of the championship C.P. Allen Cheetahs boys hockey team. Guys, would you please rise and accept the warm welcome of the House. (Applause)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>We welcome all of our guests to the gallery and hope they enjoy this afternoon's proceedings.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728">
            <from>MS. REGAN</from>
            <p>I understand our Speaker was at that championship game in Sydney.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>I was.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Bedford-Birch Cove.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="318">RESOLUTION NO. 318</num>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>MS. KELLY REGAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Charles P. Allen High School Cheetahs boys hockey team claimed the Provincial Division 1 Boys championship on March 24, 2013 in Sydney; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Cheetahs showed their heart and determination by battling back from a 2-0 deficit to number one ranked Citadel High School Phoenix after the first period, and went on to score five unanswered goals; and</p>
<p>Whereas the team consists of players Michael Baxter, Liam Cavanagh, Mark Collins, Brett Estabrooks, Andrew Foster, Greg Gallagher, Connor Hartigan, Nathan Jardine, Nolan Leeco, Graeme MacKinley, Nicholas Marshall, Mathew Mayer, Jeff Miles, Connor Morrison, Connor O'Brien, Brogan Pachal, Noah Popwell, Brandon Pottie, Bruce Tomie and Leighton Yeo;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the C.P. Allen Cheetahs boys hockey team and their coaches Jack Abraham, Chris Baxter, Gary Herbert and Billy Comer and managers Paul Baxter and Rob MacKinley and school liaisons Ryan Thornton, Shawn Young and Andrew Woods, volunteer trainer Dave Quigley, the parent volunteers plus all their supporters on their Nova Scotia School Athletic Federation Provincial Boys Division 1 hockey title.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Victoria-The Lakes.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="319">RESOLUTION NO. 319</num>
          <speech by="#250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e"><from>MR. KEITH BAIN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, on behalf of the Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas more than a century has passed since the tragic sinking of the <i>RMS Titanic</i>; and</p>
<p>Whereas yesterday marked the anniversary of the day the ship that was once named unsinkable collided with an iceberg and sank to the ocean floor; and</p>
<p>Whereas more than 1,500 lives were lost that tragic night, many of which have been laid to rest in Halifax cemeteries;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly remember the lives lost on the RMS Titanic and commend those who have worked to preserve this part of our history.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Dartmouth East.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="320">RESOLUTION NO. 320</num>
          <speech by="#1e5b7bdc-363b-4df4-8258-edcf8f2bf7fb"><from>MR. ANDREW YOUNGER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Minister of Defence, the Honourable Peter MacKay, announced this year's initial list of Canadian Armed Forces promotions on February 6, 2013; and</p>
<p>Whereas Commodore John Newton is a graduate of Dalhousie University, with 30 years of distinguished naval service aboard the Iroquois, the Preserver, the Montreal, the patrol ship HMCS Anticosti, and frigate HMCS Fredericton; and</p>
<p>Whereas Commodore John F. Newton was promoted to Rear Admiral and Commander Maritime Forces Atlantic/Joint Task Force Atlantic, taking over command later this summer;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly congratulate John Newton on his promotion to Rear Admiral and commit to working with him to continue the important and beneficial relationship the Royal Canadian Navy has with Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cape Breton West.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="321">RESOLUTION NO. 321</num>
          <speech by="#e23caf06-dcf3-42a5-8a00-f4435df40350"><from>MR. ALFIE MACLEOD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Morgan Shepard from Louisbourg graduated on March 17<sup>th</sup> from basic military training; and</p>
<p>Whereas Morgan is the son of Glenn and Eleanor Shepard; and</p>
<p>Whereas Morgan's graduation was held at Victoria Park Garrison in Sydney and he will be continuing his training this summer;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Morgan Shepard and wish him the very best as he continues his military career.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cape Breton North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="322">RESOLUTION NO. 322</num>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas each year communities across Canada mark National Volunteer Week to thank and honour the people who generously give their time and talents to help others; and</p>
<p>Whereas dedicated volunteers are the backbone of Nova Scotia's tight-knit communities; and</p>
<p>Whereas Blair Boone, of the Cape Breton Regional Municipality, was recognized at the 39<sup>th</sup> Annual Provincial Volunteer Awards ceremony for the many contributions he has made to his community and his province;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly thank Blair Boone for all the work he does for others and congratulate him for receiving a Provincial Volunteer Award.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Yarmouth.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="323">RESOLUTION NO. 323</num>
          <speech by="#8834559e-ddf7-4ac7-9b30-8ada0eb9a7ca"><from>MR. ZACH CHURCHILL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 36<sup>th</sup> Annual SEDMHA hockey tournament was held in Halifax-Dartmouth from April 4<sup>th</sup> to April 7<sup>th</sup>; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Mass Consulting Yarmouth Mariners Midget A girls team, consisting of Kirsten d'Entremont, Riley MacDonald, Morgan Theriault, Sierra Scott-Dugout, Tori Comeau, Chelsea MacPherson, Anique Dugas, Janique d'Entremont, Tania Saulnier, Caylee d'Entremont, Melissa Atkinson, Josanne Deveau, Allison MacDougall, and Maria Gaudet, under the guidance of coaches Norman Gaudet, Daniel Gaudet, and Steven Gaudet, took part in this tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Mass Consulting Yarmouth Mariners Midget A girls won the championship game with an exciting 2-1 overtime victory over New Brunswick District 5;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Mass Consulting Yarmouth Mariners Midget A girls on their championship win at the 36<sup>th</sup> Annual SEDMHA hockey tournament, and wish them continued future success.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Victoria-The Lakes.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="324">RESOLUTION NO. 324</num>
          <speech by="#250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e"><from>MR. KEITH BAIN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Murdell and Larry MacNeil of Iona have received the Victoria County Volunteer of the Year Award and were today recognized by the province for their volunteer efforts; and</p>
<p>Whereas Larry is a long-standing volunteer firefighter for Iona Volunteer Fire Department, as well as volunteering for fundraising and events at the Nova Scotia Highland Village and various other projects in the community; and</p>
<p>Whereas Murdell also volunteers at the Highland Village, the Iona Legion Bingo, and the Central Cape Breton Community Ventures Group, to name a few, and both Murdell and Larry have played an instrumental role in the Rankin School of the Narrows Recreation Field Project;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Larry and Murdell MacNeil on receiving the Victoria County Volunteer of the Year Award, and thank them for their outstanding contribution to their community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Inverness.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="325">RESOLUTION NO. 325</num>
          <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff"><from>MR. ALLAN MACMASTER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas each year communities across Canada mark National Volunteer Week to thank and honour the people who generously give their time and talents to help others; and</p>
<p>Whereas dedicated volunteers are the backbone of Nova Scotia's tight-knit communities; and</p>
<p>Whereas Alyson Maclver, of the Town of Port Hawkesbury, was recognized at the 39<sup>th</sup> Annual Provincial Volunteer Awards ceremony for the many contributions she has made to her community and her province;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly thank Alyson Maclver for all the work she does for others, and congratulate her for receiving the Provincial Volunteer Award.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT BUSINESS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Government Motions.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT MOTIONS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, I move that you do now leave the Chair and the House resolve itself into a Committee of the Whole House on Supply unto Her Majesty.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Cape Breton North.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>It's an honour for me to speak on the Supply motion today. Mr. Speaker, we know the review of estimates is important in our democracy. It's about opening the books of government up for scrutiny amongst all the people in Nova Scotia, and all of us here and all potential leaders have to understand the importance of transparency. All are tested on that understanding by the decisions they make - but it's not clear here everybody does understand that.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, last week we heard the honourable member for Clayton Park, a member for whom I have the greatest respect, in her remarks it was clear that she likes throwing stones, but she threw them through gaping holes in the Liberal leadership's glass house. She throws through the breakage left behind by the Liberal past, which they stubbornly choose to live in. Sometimes it's the stone not thrown that's the most telling. When the honourable member was imploring this House accept a bill which was about transparency she declined to defend her leadership's own record and, admiring her character as I do, I believe that's because she would not have made the same poor judgments herself. It's so important that all members recognize the central role of transparency in estimates and in making good decisions.</p>
<p>Being a baseball player, Mr. Speaker, I caught one of those stones the other day and had a close look at it. I just want to assure the honourable member that in this caucus we're very proud to have a Leader who is blessed with great ability, and people sought his advice and they wanted him to serve, which remains true today. I want to assure her that we're very proud that we have a Leader whose reputation and skills in accounting, business and finance and, most importantly, helping people means he was in great demand before entering public life.</p>
<p>He brings skills to the table; he was called upon to serve for many years. Just as the member has been chosen to represent her constituents for a number of years, receiving her pay and being reimbursed for expenses, as is proper, but who is counting? Mr. Speaker, we are happy to have such a talented Leader because we know that not everybody is that fortunate and I want to remind her that people are now looking for someone who has the ability to turn things around - and people will take a closer look going into this next election.</p>
<p>In changing gears, Mr. Speaker, being from Cape Breton we've been hit hard by the negative policies of the NDP. We have the highest power rates in the country, the highest taxes in the country, job-killing regulations, and a Premier who doesn't know how to set the conditions for the private sector to create jobs, so he frivolously throws money at the problem.</p>
<p>In Cape Breton, Mr. Speaker, as you're well aware, the infrastructure is falling behind. Wastewater systems need to be replaced, and we need to see revitalization of recreation and tourism facilities in this area. Cape Breton is important to the economy of the province. We are the number one island destination in Canada - and in North America, actually - and number three in the world.</p>
<p>The mayor and council of the CBRM have taken many initiatives in his short time as mayor. We feel the Premier is dragging his feet - maybe waiting until the election is over to deal with this issue. We know that Cape Breton has never been a priority for this government. Cape Breton has an unemployment rate of 18.6 per cent, and to us, 18.6 per cent is unacceptable. It's the highest unemployment in a decade. It is partnerships, and removal of barriers that will open up the market to allow Cape Breton to stand on its own two feet. Cutting taxes to make paycheques to go much further, reducing wasteful government spending on duplicate services, and forming efficiencies allow the public sector to flourish.</p>
<p>Cape Breton has a leader for its biggest municipality, and many of the smaller municipalities as well. But if we continue to do what has been done in the past, how can we expect anything different in the future?</p>
<p>The infrastructure funding information from the federal government was released March 27<sup>th</sup>. Taking initiative and getting a plan out early was the goal of the mayor and council of CBRM; the plan was out, and the mayor didn't wait for anything, immediately setting meetings with federal and provincial officials to get his plan in action.</p>
<p>We don't feel we've gotten anywhere with this government. Some of the communities are suffering as high as 35 to 40 per cent unemployment. Where I come from in North Sydney, there's over 30 per cent unemployment. Having this infrastructure plan in place would go a long way in putting people in the Northside and people in Cape Breton back to work.</p>
<p>We in Cape Breton want to be economically stable. We want to be an economic state, not a welfare state, but with failing infrastructure, our number one island destination in North America and number three in the world may take a hit. We heard last year or the year before about our Signature Resorts in Cape Breton and Digby, that if we didn't put money into them - they were starting to fail - we would lose that feeling that those resorts were superior.</p>
<p>With an unemployment rate of 18.6 per cent on the Island, we have to make sure we can get Cape Bretoners back to work. There are some projects on the horizon, but we're also trying to make sure that these projects come to fruition. Without the infrastructure in place - the roads, sewer, wastewater treatment - some of these projects may not come to be. The plan is a little different than what has been done in the past. In the past there was one-third, one-third, and one-third - from the municipality, the province, and the federal government.</p>
<p>What the mayor and council on Cape Breton Island have proposed is to do a 25, a 25, and a 50 per cent from the feds. We feel that's an easier goal to attain, especially for a municipality that has been hit hard by unemployment and out-migration. The population in Cape Breton has decreased by 4,400 in the last four years, and those are people who we could have put to work. If this plan comes to fruition, as it should, we may get some people back to work in these areas of construction and tourism, and the new plan and the plan for infrastructure and the plan for business and development in the area may come true.</p>
<p>The municipality has put their $75 million on the table. The province has been asked to put up $75 million and the feds $150 million. This is $75 million over a five-year period, which doesn't sound like a lot of money at the time. For a municipality that's struggling like we are to be able to put the money up, we as MLAs in Cape Breton figure that if the province will put their share up, the feds will put theirs up too.</p>
<p>As I said, Mr. Speaker, our communities are suffering. We have good people living in Cape Breton. I know I represent the good people of the Northside, soon to be Northside-Westmount, and these people want to work. They want to stay at home and they want to contribute to society but, if they have to leave the area, they can't coach kids' hockey teams, they can't volunteer in a community and they can't raise money for cancer. There are a lot of things they can't do. So if we could get this financial commitment from the province and the federal government, we could hopefully keep these people around and allow them to be productive members of society.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I know that people in my area would love to stay home and be with their family and friends because having to go away to work is tough on a family situation. With either a mother or a father who is away, children suffer, families suffer and communities and neighbourhoods suffer.</p>
<p>In this budget that we've seen from this NDP Government, there's nothing in there for Cape Breton Island, nothing to help our economy, nothing to help the economy grow. So, Mr. Speaker, we're relying on the plan that the CBRM Council and mayor put up to try to stabilize that and bring some people back home. We're hoping that through communication, which has been opened up between the province and the municipality - some people say it's a communication that hasn't been there in years - we're hoping that communication will lead to some productive talks and some money being put into our fair island so that we can maintain our dignity, put people back to work, maintain the number one island destination that we have in North America, and continue to have people come to our fair land and spend money there.</p>
<p>We know that if people come they'll come back. We have number-one golf courses in the country. We have scenery that is second to none. Mr. Speaker, I will say that we have people who are probably some of the friendliest in the world. We can't help it if the honourable members - not members from the other side - don't live in this fair island. It's their choice but they should choose differently, at least come down and visit, and they would see exactly what we see. They would see exactly that the people here appreciate what we have: the natural beauty, the lay of the land, the hard-working individuals. (Interruption) As I'm hearing, we even took the toll off the causeway to make it easier for people to get in.</p>
<p>If you came, I'm sure you would come back again because we do have a beautiful area. No matter what side of the island you go down, the scenery along the water, along the lakes inland, is absolutely beautiful. When you stop along the way at some of the little caf&#xE9;s and craft shops, they are struggling because the tourism is down, struggling because the taxes are high and the power rates are high and the cost if they were to export some of their goods is high.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I'd like to conclude by inviting every member of this House to visit Cape Breton at least once over the summer and see its beauty, spend some money there, visit the shops and areas, eat at some of our fine eateries. I guarantee that you'll come back. When you drive on our roads, you'll realize what we drive on every day and the money that that capital plan would put into that infrastructure would be great. I invite everybody to come down to Lousibourg this summer to celebrate the 300<sup>th</sup> Anniversary of Louisbourg.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I just hope that in the months to come, with negotiations with the province and the federal government, that we can attain that infrastructure money, put people back to work and maintain our island in the beauty that it is. Thank you very much.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>MS. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I'm pleased to have, I think, 15 minutes going into Supply to say a few words. As the previous member has done, he had a few political statements to make and then he got to speak warmly about his home constituency and Cape Breton Island.</p>
<p>I think we all have a great deal of respect for members around this Chamber, in terms of their commitment to their areas and the people they represent. Mr. Speaker, that goes for the Leaders of our Parties as well, that they also give of their time and work hard to represent their people as well.</p>
<p>The member for Cape Breton North has a few things to say about his Leader and just before I begin to talk about Blue Mountain-Birch Cove Lakes, which is in my area, I think it is important to reiterate that while speaking about wanting to control wasteful spending in the province, it's important to know what people stand for. The Leader of the Third Party has stated, while he stands for cutting wasteful spending, at the same time he has taken significant stipends and travel costs, from Prime Minister Harper, that total over $300,000 - and that's federal tax dollars.</p>
<p>The Leader of the Third Party earned $25,000 alone for attending 25 board meetings and charged, as well, $9,000 in travel costs. This relates to openness and transparency. This sort of information is available on the public record. So, all we're saying is that, while fully employed, he did not volunteer his time. When he was asked by the Prime Minister to help out, he received significant compensation and stipends for doing so. So that's all I'm saying. Volunteer Week is coming up. We know there are thousands of people who give every day in this province to help their province, to improve their country, but these were very lucrative contracts and arrangements.</p>
<p>Now, Mr. Speaker, I was anxious today to address an issue in my riding and that is the Blue Mountain-Birch Cove Lakes, which is a wilderness area that was actually established under the years of the Progressive Conservative Government. In 2003 when I was elected as a Liberal member for Clayton Park, it was a big issue for me to create a wilderness area, or a protected area. I wasn't sure what the designation should be but I wanted to protect the lands that are in the area of Clayton Park bordered by the Highway No. 102, as you come into the city; Bayers Lake Industrial, which has become more of a business park on one side, Hammonds Plains on the other, and Timberlea on the far side.</p>
<p>The member who represents Timberlea Prospect knows, as well, that he had given his support to the idea of protecting some of that land. In the area of Clayton Park, in particular, we had seen an explosion of development and there were a lot of people asking when that was going to slow down or if we were saving any of the lands for the future because the lands in the area where I live, the area of Clayton Park West, was all woods previously. It was a place where people enjoyed the outdoors, where people even had cabins, if you go back about 50 or 60 years and now, of course, it's a major subdivision. People wanted to know when we were going to stop that frantic pace and save a little bit of land for future generations.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I raised that here and brought - in fact it was my second Private Member's Bill that I brought to the House - an Act to make the Blue Mountain- Birch Cove Lakes area a protected wilderness. That was a program - that protected wilderness program actually began under the Liberal Government in the 1990s. It is something we are very proud of. The first 31 sites that were designated were done so under the Liberal Government of the day and not one more site had been identified - and it was 2003, 2004 - not one more site had been put on the table by the Progressive Conservative Government. So it was something that was very important to me and I raised it, brought here as a Private Member's Bill, and not only did we stop there but we continued to bring it forward in terms of talking about it in the community and getting the community engaged in the importance of doing something.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, what came of that were several classes, I think there were about 90 Grade 7 students who took a walk into the Blue Mountain-Birch Cove Lakes area, from their school, Park West School. You can actually walk up to the Bayers Lake Business Park and behind Kent Building Supplies, which I'm sure many of the members have been into, you can walk straight into the woods behind that and be in the most beautiful wilderness you can imagine in just 10 or 15 minutes. It takes you to the shores of a lake called Susie's Lake.</p>
<p>The students went up with a biologist and talked about the features of the land and, when they finished, it was a wonderful exercise for the students because they got to look at it from a science point of view, from the natural point of view, and then when they went back to school they wrote letters to the Premier and the Premier actually - Premier Hamm at the time - received letters from the entire group that had gone through, 90 students writing their own letters about why they thought it was important to protect that area.</p>
<p>Because it's so close to a really high density large population, it's a real gem because within the urban core of Halifax, the existence of Blue Mountain-Birch Cove Lakes means that we have almost 3,500 acres preserved that you can reach with a bus ride from downtown Halifax. It actually has created the largest urban wilderness park in Canada and that's something I think we should all be very proud of because most of the previous properties - I'd say all of the previous wilderness areas - had been in remote areas. You know, we were protecting special ecosystems, but they were far from where the population base was. And in protecting this Blue Mountain-Birch Cove Lakes, it allowed us to preserve a very important part of our natural lands, close to where a lot of people live. I see the Minister of Environment is also very, very interested in and, I believe, supportive of this special area in HRM.</p>
<p>And as I say, I give a lot of the credit for it finally moving forward and going through the process of public consultation and the various steps of being evaluated for a wilderness area, and it really was because the public themselves signed petitions, and went up and visited, and we actually conducted quite a few walks into the area, and for that I can thank groups like the Halifax North West Trails Association, who actually knew their way around and could lead people in, because, Mr. Speaker, I'd lived in the area almost 20 years and had not gone back there, because if you looked at the woods behind Kent Building Supplies you wouldn't know where to go - it doesn't have a clearly defined path, there's no signage, no trail-blazing, so you need somebody to show you the way in and out.</p>
<p>There were so many of us living in Clayton Park West, and Clayton Park, and Wedgewood Park, who didn't know exactly how to get back there or how to safely go in and out. So the trails people led a lot of special trips back, and really, a group of us met regularly to try to put this on the political agenda. Mr. Speaker, the Canadian Parks and Wilderness is involved now, very much, because of Chris Miller, who is a young man who is one of their directors, I think their executive director for at least the Atlantic area, and he is actually the biologist who took the students into that walk on that fateful day, when they wrote to Premier Hamm as well. And Chris Miller was very involved, as I say, Bob and Wendy MacDonald, who founded the Trails Association, were very involved, and the Ecology Action Centre was involved as well. Raymond Plourde, who, as everyone knows, has been the voice for wilderness preservation in Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>So it was a very important effort to save those lands. Mr. Speaker, there were 4,000 acres actually in the original request, that's Crown land, that we wanted to preserve, but in fact we weren't able to preserve it all due to some plans for a highway and a few other uncertainties in the future, which I may not believe it's a necessary highway, but at any rate it dictated the boundary. So we have something to celebrate in Clayton Park and in the surrounding communities that are on the other sides of this wilderness area - and that is that we are home to the largest urban wilderness park in Canada, and that that land has now been preserved for eternity, really, for the future. The government will not have logging on that land, there won't be mining, there won't be anything that would destroy the natural beauty of that area.</p>
<p>My concern today, Mr. Speaker, is how do we get more people that can enjoy the land, because we are now quite a few years after its designation, and I should say that 2007, the government finally announced that they would actually look at it as a candidate, and just prior to the election of 2009, in April 2009, on the eve of Earth Day, the government of the day had an official designation ceremony and actually unveiled the fact that it was going to be preserved, and it was successful as a candidate for this. That was very good news that tied in beautifully to Earth Day that year - and I'm sure it was important for the election that followed.</p>
<p>But, Mr. Speaker, since 2009 to today, we've had four years pass, and there is not one sign anywhere on the entire perimeter of that large area that says that this is a park or a wilderness area. Again, in that ensuing four years, there has been no trail head built, no special parking area designated, no place that says come in and enjoy this park. So it's still only the few people who know their way in and out, or who decide to go in on a tour or a trail or a hike with the trails people, or sometimes with Canoe Nova Scotia they do go in and they canoe in that area - you can do a one-day loop through the lakes in that Blue Mountain-Birch Cove area and actually, you know, it's a wonderful day with a few portages and you can go around and come back to the same spot, all within an urban area, which is fantastic.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, HRM and the Province of Nova Scotia have a job to do, and that is to open this up and to provide access to the people of Nova Scotia, so that we can actually have more people getting in and enjoying it, for health, for the benefits that accrue to young people and families - they can swim there, they can skate in the winter, there's certainly wonderful hiking.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, we need access points, and the time has come for that to become a priority for HRM and for the province. I'm hoping that will be high on the agenda as we go forward into the next year, because HRM has a big responsibility to play here. I hope I'll be able to speak about this again at an upcoming time. Thank you.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Hammonds Plains-Upper Sackville.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#de2082f3-cf3a-4955-8a4e-4f1bf0ac1301"><from>MR. MAT WHYNOTT</from><p>Thank you very much, Mr. Speaker. I'm glad to again rise in my place and talk a little bit about some of the things that are going on in Nova Scotia in various communities across our lovely province and to join in the debate that is going on here today.</p>
<p>One of the interesting parts - I know the Liberals, the member for Halifax Clayton Park was talking about the consulting fees, or whatever you want to call them, from the Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party. The interesting part was the fact that the new Liberal Leader, federally, had invoiced to various community groups across the province, $10,000 to $25,000 per session to different community groups. It's kind of interesting that the Liberals bring that piece up.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I do want to - I spoke last week, going into CWH on Supply, around a few things that are issues for Nova Scotians, in particular around the notion of our energy security - our energy security that will ensure we have a local, reliable, stable, tax-free energy system here in this province. I want Nova Scotians to know where the Liberal Party really stands on energy in this province.</p>
<p>I do want to begin by pointing out an article written on February 16, 2012, by the member for Kings West, and it quotes, "It is my conviction we should be looking at importing cheap Quebec electricity rather than expensive power from Newfoundland." I'd like to table that, Mr. Speaker, which I find interesting because that's exactly what the Liberal Party says. They say sometimes in places, oh, no, we don't believe that; we don't believe that we want to just import power from Hydro-Qu&#xE9;bec; we want to see different sources of energy to our province.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, that's exactly what the Liberal Party is - they want to hitch our wagon, so to speak, solely to Hydro-Qu&#xE9;bec. In fact, that's what - and I've tabled this many times, but I'll table it again, on the Liberal caucus Web site it actually says, "Provide cheaper, cleaner energy by importing power from Hydro-Qu&#xE9;bec." But they don't mention anything here about Muskrat Falls. They don't mention anything here about the Maritime Link, that that's what they would do if they ever had their way: hitch our wagon to the notion of solely using power from Hydro-Qu&#xE9;bec. I think that's what Nova Scotians need to start asking, when they say one thing here in the Chamber and then they'll go out in public and say one other thing.</p>
<p>What we know is that we're the Party with a plan. We have a plan forward for energy. I know we'll probably be getting to some estimates from the department here shortly, talking about Nova Scotia's plan for renewable energy.</p>
<p>This is what, as a young Nova Scotian, as someone who is a new father - we need to be asking that very important question, because we know what happened in Newfoundland and Labrador back in the 1970s, when Joey Smallwood and the Liberal Government there hitched their wagon to Hydro-Qu&#xE9;bec. I want Nova Scotians to start asking that question. I would encourage anybody who is watching at home to really start to ask the question, because one of the things that I know in this Chamber - I've only had the opportunity to be elected for almost four years now, and I have been around the Chamber as a former Page and as a former caucus staffer - is that when we were in Opposition, we actually proposed things that worked for Nova Scotians and that's not what the Liberal Party in Nova Scotia is doing. They just oppose but what we did was propose.</p>
<p>We haven't heard that from the Liberal Party in this Chamber, the debate that takes place in this Chamber, about the Liberal Party. They don't say anything in here. They just go out into the communities and kind of make things up as they go. I think that is really what the difference is here, between us and the Liberal Party.</p>
<p>One of the things I wanted to bring to the attention of the public and to members of this Chamber is the notion that Liberals are good fiscal managers, the notion of that. What we know from our history books is that is not the case. I was in the Chamber here last week - and I know I mentioned this already but I'll mention it again, and I think we need to continue to mention this - the last time a Liberal Government ever balanced the books in this province was 1976. I wasn't even born then. I wasn't even thought of yet.</p>
<p>I know the Liberal Party will say, you can't talk about history and you can't talk about what happened - well, you can, because the decisions of that time, the decisions between 1976 and 2009 were to continue to bring on deficits and debt in this province. Why do we see the debt that we have? Why do we see that? It's because of the decisions of the Liberal Party to delay payments, to do things that weren't necessarily above-board, and so that is what is interesting.</p>
<p>I know that the Liberal Party says some things about how they would - especially in the 2009 provincial campaign, they talked about what their platform was and their platform actually was costed out - and I know I mentioned this last week and I'll mention it again because I think Nova Scotians need to know that - what they mentioned was that their platform would cost $527 million and the title of that was, "LIBERAL PLATFORM; So, whose dog ate page 34?" There was no mention of what their costing plan was, but this was done by different people, different organizations, talking about their plan and it was $527 million with no plan to pay for it. Typical Liberal: just promise the world and hope for the best.</p>
<p>Maybe we can do things. I remember being a young lad, following politics, and I remember what they used to call the Red Book - this is federally - the Red Book had (Interruption) Yes, let's just kind of promise everything to everyone. One of the things Canadians will never forget is what the Liberal Party of Canada did - the whole question around daycare in this country. The Liberals promised it, year after year, campaign after campaign, and talked about bringing forward a universal daycare for Canadians. How long did that take? How long did that take in order for them to come forward? Over 10 years for them to actually say, since we're going down we might as well bring something forward and hope for the best. Again, typical Liberal: promise everything to everybody and their dog.</p>
<p>One of the things that I did notice from the Liberals, when they were in government, was this whole question of foresight and having a vision for our province. The only thing that they ever saw was to put a tax on every single bottle of booze in this province, every single bottle of booze so that it would go into their own coffers, so that they could fund things like election campaigns, election ads.</p>
<p>I attended the Liberal AGM as an observer. As most Parties in this Chamber, we kind of share the ability for each caucus to represent their caucus at an AGM, as an observer. We decided that we would go and one of the things that I do know is, again, the Liberal Party can't even balance their own books in their own Party and they want to run our province. That is what I know and that's what is on paper for the Liberal Party of Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>That is just an example of fiscal responsibility and fiscal restraint under the Liberal Party. You know, one of the things that I do know is the most recent evidence of that of the Liberal Party of Nova Scotia was when they were in government in the 1990s, Mr. Speaker. Remember what they did? They rolled back collective bargaining rights. They rolled back wages. They closed 1,500 hospital beds. They created the HST, one of the first jurisdictions in the country to have HST. They put home energy as one of those things, one of those things that they did. They invented the user fee and this is the sort of thing that Nova Scotians need to know.</p>
<p>We need to know that this is what the Liberal Party stands for and if they ever had their way, they would do it again. They would do it again. They would bring forward P3 schools again and I would ask the question to the Liberal Party, would they do it with hospitals? I bet you they would, although they don't say anything about it. You know, classic Liberals: they just kind of go with the flow and hope for the best. Stay low and maybe, as they say, they have this kind of sense of governing, that it's their turn to govern. Well, Mr. Speaker, one of the things that I know, and one of the things that I've learned from my Premier, is that it is the people who decide that, not the Liberal Party of Nova Scotia who decide that.</p>
<p>I know my time is running thin here, but one of the things that I do want to mention, finally - and it's just going back to the question of our energy security - what I'm very proud of is our government moving forward with efficiency programs in this province. One thing I know, Mr. Speaker, is that the Liberal Party of Nova Scotia would get rid of Efficiency Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>For the first time in our history efficiency programs actually show up in our overall percentage of how we use our energy. It talks about, in a percentage, how much coal we use, how much wind we use, how much hydro we use, how much tidal we may use - I know it's a small amount, but some tidal that we do use. For the first time efficiency programs actually show up in that overall pie chart and the Liberal Leader actually - as an article from the Cape Breton Post on March 23, 2013 says, "As for power rates &#x2026;" the Liberal Leader said, "&#x2026; a Liberal government would eliminate the efficiency program &#x2026;"</p>
<p>The other interesting point that Nova Scotians need to really know is where the Liberal Party stands on fiscal responsibility, on Hydro-Qu&#xE9;bec, what they would say about ER closures and the CECs, what they would do with that, because I think the Liberal Leader will get rid of CECs. We know one thing they won't get rid of is the Liberal trust fund because they've been using that for many, many years.</p>
<p>One thing we know, Mr. Speaker, is that they will abandon rural Nova Scotia. They would abandon rural Nova Scotia when it comes to important industries in our province. We also know the Liberals would put the HST back on home electricity and ensuring that Nova Scotians, at some point in their life - if the Liberals ever had their way, they would certainly put the HST back on home electricity. Thank you for your time.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The motion is carried.</p>
        </speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>5:20 p.m. The House resolved itself into a CWH on Supply with Deputy Speaker Ms. Becky Kent in the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <narrative>
          <p>9:31 p.m. CWH on Supply rose and the House reconvened with Deputy Speaker Ms. Becky Kent in the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The Chairman of the Committee of the Whole House on Supply reports:</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined">
          <from>THE CLERK</from>
          <p>That the committee has met, has made some considerable progress, and begs leave to sit again.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23"><from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from><p>Madam Speaker, we made considerable progress ourselves today. I think that is going to conclude the government's business for today.</p>
<p>I move that the House do now rise, to meet tomorrow from the hour of 12:00 noon to 8:00 p.m. After the daily routine and Question Period, we will go into CWH on Supply and, if time permits, we may do some second reading of Bill Nos. 36, 37 and 42. I move that the House do now rise.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the House do now rise to meet again on Tuesday, April 16<sup>th</sup>, between the hours of 12:00 noon and 8:00 p.m.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>We stand adjourned.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>The House rose at 9:31 p.m.</p>
        </narrative>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION UNDER RULE 32(3)</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="326">RESOLUTION NO. 326</num>
          <speech by="#1e5b7bdc-363b-4df4-8258-edcf8f2bf7fb"><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas 2012-13 is Symphony Nova Scotia's 30<sup>th</sup> season, delighting 50,000 listeners each year with classical, baroque, pop, rock and folk music; and</p>
<p>Whereas Erika Beatty joined Symphony Nova Scotia in August 2007 as chief executive officer, after working with five different orchestras including Mississauga, Niagara, Winnipeg and Symphony New Brunswick; and</p>
<p>Whereas last year Ms. Beatty was the recipient of the coveted John Hobday Award in Arts Management created by the Canadian Council for the Arts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly express their sincere gratitude for Erika's eight years of dedicated service to Nova Scotia's symphony orchestra and wish her every success in her future endeavours.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="327">RESOLUTION NO. 327</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas each year communities across Canada mark National Volunteer Week to thank and honour the people who generously give their time and talents to help others; and</p>
<p>Whereas dedicated volunteers are the backbone of Nova Scotia's tight-knit communities; and</p>
<p>Whereas Della Smith, of the Town of Clark's Harbour, was recognized at the 39<sup>th</sup> Annual Provincial Volunteer Awards ceremony for the many contributions she has made to her community and her province;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly thank Della Smith for all the work she does for others and congratulate her for receiving a Provincial Volunteer Award.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="328">RESOLUTION NO. 328</num>
          <speech by="#de2082f3-cf3a-4955-8a4e-4f1bf0ac1301"><from>Mr. Mat Whynott</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the NSISP International Leadership Camp provides students with the opportunity to gain experience in international aid work, develop leadership skills, and expand their world view; and</p>
<p>Whereas Samantha Dixon, a Grade 12 student at Millwood High School, travelled with a group of fellow Nova Scotian student leaders - Hannah Tobin, Carlena Eye, Lloyd McVeigh-MacCormack, Marja Himmelman, Vanessa Stephens, Caroline Sylvester, Alyson Duff, Daniel Kim, Sarah Millman, Bailey Mosher, Allison MacAskill, Hunter MacDougall, Juliana Ali, Mason Maxwell, Ashley Haley-Sweeney, Charlee Fry, Alexandra Pulchny, Christine Ingham, Katie Snow, and Eric DeWolf - to Campeche, Mexico, in March 2013, with the assistance the Nova Scotia International Student Program, to help out at a local orphanage; and</p>
<p>Whereas over the weeks leading up to the trip, the team fundraised extensively and rounded up supplies for the orphanage like books, toiletries, and toys to bring to the children;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly extend their thanks to Sam Dixon and the team of Nova Scotian student leaders for their initiative to take part in an international aid trip to Campeche, Mexico, and to all of the aid and relief workers who give up much of their time to help others.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="329">RESOLUTION NO. 329</num>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>Ms. Kelly Regan</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Smiledog is a new business which provides the option of a live receptionist for callers who are try to contact any one of a number of businesses in Canada, rather than simply leave a message with a disembodied voice mail system; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Smiledog receptionist ensures the caller will always be able to speak directly to a live person who is fully familiar with the specifics of each organization for which she is answering phones; and</p>
<p>Whereas Smiledog was started by Jeff Doyle to put the human touch back into customer service, thereby helping small companies boost their image and big companies maintain a high profile with their customers;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jeff Doyle for recognizing a preference by many customers for human interaction as opposed to technology and providing them with that option.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="330">RESOLUTION NO. 330</num>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>Ms. Kelly Regan</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas CAN-Med Healthcare, a Bedford division of IMP Group, has secured a sales and marketing contract, exclusive in Canada, for a biohazard waste management system; and</p>
<p>Whereas CAN-Med Healthcare has signed a contract with Bertin Technologies of France to sell the Sterilwave 440 waste management system, which grinds biohazard hospital waste, such as used needles, syringes, and tubing, to a fine pulp and microwaves it to a temperature hot enough to make it safe for disposal in the landfill; and</p>
<p>Whereas this system can be installed directly in hospitals across Canada, thereby saving the time and cost of transporting the waste elsewhere for alternative disposal methods;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate CAN-Med Healthcare, the exclusive Canadian distributors of an invention which solves a serious waste disposal problem.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="331">RESOLUTION NO. 331</num>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>Ms. Kelly Regan</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Chris and Kara Burrows of Hammonds Plains launched a home renovation matchmaking Web site called RenovationAuction.com which invites homeowners to post their renovation project on-line and collect bids from local contractors, and after choosing a contractor will hold the homeowner's deposit in trust until the homeowner gives approval for its release; and</p>
<p>Whereas RenovationAuction.com assists contractors as well, by allowing them to bid on multiple projects and adjust their quote based on the competition; and</p>
<p>Whereas this Web site allows homeowners to better ensure the reliability of their contractors, and allows contractors to more efficiently bid on multiple contracts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Chris and Kara Burrows for creating a Web site that makes contracting a smoother process for all parties.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="332">RESOLUTION NO. 332</num>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>Ms. Kelly Regan</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas entrepreneur Mark Brezovan noticed that in the Halifax area there was no coffee shop offering fresh bagels, baked on the spot; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Brezovan created Izzy's Bagel Company in Bedford, a cafe serving fresh bagels every day, in 16 flavours, with no preservatives or additives, offering bagel aficionados a treat they cannot get anywhere else and taking on the competition from recognized brand names and excellent independent coffee shops throughout the Halifax region; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Brezovan plans to expand Izzy's caf&#xE9;s throughout Halifax and Dartmouth;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Mark Brezovan for his entrepreneurial spirit, and wish him success in his aim of bringing a better bagel to Bedford and beyond.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
