<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.jamie.baillie" showAs="HON. JAMIE BAILLIE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.christopher.a.dentremont" showAs="HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.michel.p.samson" showAs="Hon. Michel Samson"/>
        <TLCPerson id="3b49aa8d-3e78-4679-b8f7-f3161f11d3a3" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.sterling.belliveau" showAs="HON. STERLING BELLIVEAU"/>
        <TLCPerson id="e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.eddie.orrell" showAs="MR. EDDIE ORRELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="5e4eedce-ee17-4542-8b27-a1e87f85ec80" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.graham.steele" showAs="HON. GRAHAM STEELE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.karen.casey" showAs="Karen Casey"/>
        <TLCPerson id="c7f2d366-8ba0-4263-98e0-bdaa9336415f" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.clarrie.mackinnon" showAs="MR. CLARRIE MACKINNON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="c479d7de-83a6-47c7-a045-07816407bdb3" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.lenore.zann" showAs="MS. LENORE ZANN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="5c3f8e78-5002-4c61-9c57-730090867f1b" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.wayne.j.gaudet" showAs="HON. WAYNE GAUDET"/>
        <TLCPerson id="a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.kelly.regan" showAs="MS. KELLY REGAN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="5da6e0aa-9066-4b5c-8d26-9222b854db7e" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.marilyn.more" showAs="HON. MARILYN MORE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="e23caf06-dcf3-42a5-8a00-f4435df40350" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.alfie.macleod" showAs="MR. ALFIE MACLEOD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.maureen.macdonald" showAs="HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="c64a6bcf-fabd-4b08-bd04-ecd0fc310c2e" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.howard.epstein" showAs="MR. HOWARD EPSTEIN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.diana.whalen" showAs="MS. DIANA WHALEN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="ce90163b-7a3b-4884-b7d9-b5ca06af4cc3" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.gary.burrill" showAs="Mr. Gary Burrill"/>
        <TLCPerson id="72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.chuck.porter" showAs="MR. CHUCK PORTER"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MR. SPEAKER"/>
        <TLCRole id="#member" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.#member" showAs="AN HON. MEMBER"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 26 April 2013</docTitle>
      <docNumber>13-22</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2013-04-26">Friday, April 26, 2013</docDate>
      <docProponent>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docProponent>
      <legislature value="61">61st General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="5">5th Session</session>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>Order, please. We'll begin the daily routine.</p>
      </speech>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PRESENTING AND READING PETITIONS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Colchester North.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>HON. KAREN CASEY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I rise today to table a petition, the operative clause being:</p>
<blockquote>"The following users and residents of the 256 Highway are asking the government to provide additional funding to complete the approved capital project on Route 256 so that the entire length of the Route be completed in the 2013 Construction Season &#x2026;"</blockquote>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I have affixed my name to that petition.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The petition is tabled.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PRESENTING REPORTS OF COMMITTEES</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>TABLING REPORTS, REGULATIONS AND OTHER PAPERS</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>STATEMENTS BY MINISTERS</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Fisheries and Aquaculture.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="844">RESOLUTION NO. 844</num>
          <speech by="#3b49aa8d-3e78-4679-b8f7-f3161f11d3a3"><from>HON. STERLING BELLIVEAU</from><p>Mr. Speaker, on behalf of the Minister of Health and Wellness, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas National Medical Laboratory Week will be celebrated April 22<sup>nd</sup> to April 26<sup>th</sup>; and</p>
<p>Whereas medical laboratory technology is the fastest-growing health care profession in Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas medical laboratory technologists conduct laboratory tests, which physicians and clinicians depend on to accurately diagnose and treat illness and to monitor patient health; and</p>
<p>Whereas medical laboratory staff consist of medical laboratory technologists, medical laboratory assistants, and medical clerical staff, who work as a team to provide information about health in a timely manner;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House recognize the efforts and the professionalism of the medical laboratory technologists, assistants, and support staff who strive to maintain the health and well-being of Nova Scotians and all Canadians.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>INTRODUCTION OF BILLS</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 62 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 33 of the Acts of 2004. The Protection for Persons in Care Act. (Hon. Denise Peterson-Rafuse)</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 63 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 160 of the Revised Statutes of 1989. The Maintenance and Custody Act. (Hon. Karen Casey)</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 64 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 9 of the Acts of 2012. The Maritime Link Act, to Permit the Nova Scotia Utility and Review Board to Extend Time. (Hon. Jamie Baillie)</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 65 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 9 of the Acts of 2012. The Maritime Link Act. (Hon. Jamie Baillie)</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Ordered that these bills be read a second time on a future day.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Halifax Fairview on an introduction.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#5e4eedce-ee17-4542-8b27-a1e87f85ec80"><from>HON. GRAHAM STEELE</from><p>Thank you. I'd like to draw the attention of the members of the House to the east gallery where members will see Mr. Arno Lehwald, who is a long-time constituent of mine, a very fine gentleman who also happens to be the father of one of our Pages, Keith Lehwald. Arno is immensely proud of Keith, as he should be. Keith was the top student in his year at Halifax West High School, but that's in the past and I heard this morning that Keith may be the top student in his year at Dalhousie Law School.</p>
<p>I would like to ask all members to find lots for Keith to do this morning so his father can see him in action, and I'd like all members to give Mr. Arno Lehwald a warm welcome to the House today. (Applause)</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>We welcome all guests to the gallery this morning and hope they enjoy this morning's proceedings.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Bedford-Birch Cove.</p></speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="845">RESOLUTION NO. 845</num>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>MS. KELLY REGAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Bedford Volunteer Recognition reception annually recognizes the extensive efforts of the many volunteers who make Bedford a wonderful place in which to live; and</p>
<p>Whereas Carolyn Crowell is a compassionate social justice advocate who works tirelessly at Bedford United Church to advance progressive causes; and</p>
<p>Whereas Carolyn has held many leadership positions throughout the church, including chairperson of the Pastoral Care Team for 11 years, chair of the Inclusivity Team, co-leader of the Adult Study Group, and co-coordinator of the church elders, of which she is one, and she also advocated for Bedford United Church to become an affirming congregation and has volunteered with the Fort Sackville Foundation for many years as their secretary;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Carolyn Crowell on her many years of service to Bedford United Church and the Fort Sackville Foundation and thank her for making Bedford a more compassionate, progressive community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed.</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="846">RESOLUTION NO. 846</num>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Sunday Nova Scotia will join in the Day of Mourning to remember those who died, were injured, or became ill at work; and</p>
<p>Whereas in 2012 more than 26,000 Nova Scotians were injured at work, and tragically, 32 Nova Scotians died; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Day of Mourning is an opportunity for employees and employers to honour the lives lost on the job and to renew their commitment to improve health and safety in the workplace;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House mark the Day of Mourning by remembering those who have died, and encourage all Nova Scotian employers and workers to use safe practices in the workplace.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Bedford-Birch Cove.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="847">RESOLUTION NO. 847</num>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>MS. KELLY REGAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Bedford Volunteer Recognition Reception annually recognizes the extensive efforts of the many volunteers who make Bedford a wonderful place in which to live; and</p>
<p>Whereas Edmund Conway has been a devoted Bedford volunteer firefighter for 43 years and is described as the kind of man you can always count on, whether it is something that needs to be cleaned or repaired, a sick fireman visited, or any job that needs to be done; and</p>
<p>Whereas Edmund has also volunteered with many other organizations like the Bedford Days Parade, the Christmas Santa Parade, the Prostate Cancer and Muscular Dystrophy associations, Bedford Baptist Church, and the Sackville Winter Carnival;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved the members of this House of Assembly thank Edmund Conway for helping to keep Bedford safe and for contributing so mightily to the life of our community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cape Breton North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="848">RESOLUTION NO. 848</num>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Cape Breton Golden K and Eastlink TV have recognized the importance of the North Sydney Youth Inclusion Program with a significant donation of $10,000; and</p>
<p>Whereas the program works with troubled kids, helping them with schoolwork, behaviour issues, and community consciousness, in addition to getting the kids involved in physical activities, sporting events, and emotional support; and</p>
<p>Whereas these kids are the kids who need help, and a 67 per cent drop in the crime rate for this age group is proof that the help is working and needs to continue;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly thank the organizers of this program and the many people and organizations that support it and the young lives that it will change.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Clare.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="849">RESOLUTION NO. 849</num>
          <speech by="#5c3f8e78-5002-4c61-9c57-730090867f1b"><from>HON. WAYNE GAUDET</from><p>Monsieur le Pr&#xE9;sident, par le pr&#xE9;sente, j'avise que je proposerai &#xE0; une date ult&#xE9;rieure, l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu que la Caisse populaire de Clare joue un r&#xF4;le de premier plan dans le Relais pour la vie, une activit&#xE9; de pr&#xE9;l&#xE8;vement de fonds pour lutter contre la maladie du cancer; et</p>
<p>Attendu que le gouvernement canadien reconnait des regroupements de b&#xE9;n&#xE9;vole qui contribuent de fa&#xE7;on exceptionnelle au bien-&#xEA;tre des familles et des communaut&#xE9;s; et</p>
<p>Attendu que la Caisse populaire de Clare a m&#xE9;rit&#xE9; une reconnaissance sp&#xE9;ciale pour son b&#xE9;n&#xE9;volat pour la r&#xE9;gion Atlantique du Canada;</p>
<p>Qu'il soit r&#xE9;solu que cette assembl&#xE9;e f&#xE9;licite la Caisse populaire pour avoir re&#xE7;u cette marque de distinction du gouvernement canadien pour la r&#xE9;gion Atlantique.</p>
<p>Monsieur le Pr&#xE9;sident, je propose l'adoption de cette r&#xE9;solution sans pr&#xE9;avis set sans d&#xE9;bats.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas la Caisse populaire de Clare plays a key role in the annual Rely for Life in Clare; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Canadian Government gives awards to businesses that are making exceptional contributions to the wellbeing of families and communities across our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas la Caisse populaire de Clare was recognized as a business leader in the Atlantic region for it exceptional contribution for its volunteer work;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this assembly congratulates la Caisse populaire de Clare for winning this award for the Atlantic region.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Argyle</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="850">RESOLUTION NO. 850</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, &#xE0; une date ult&#xE9;rieure, je demanderai l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu que chaque ann&#xE9;e, au mois de septembre le Resource Recovery Fund Board lance un concours pour les &#xE9;coles de grade P-12; et</p>
<p>Attendu que ce programme encourage les &#xE9;l&#xE8;ves &#xE0; jouer un r&#xF4;le actif dans leur communaut&#xE9; &#xE0; promouvoir la r&#xE9;duction des d&#xE9;chets par le recyclage et le compostage; et</p>
<p>Attendu que le gagnant de P-1 &#xE9;tait professeur Danielle Thibault de l'&#xC9;cole Pubnico-Ouest; le finaliste de grade 2-3 &#xE9;tait Autumn Atkinson de l'&#xC9;cole Plymouth, et le gagnant de grade 7-9 &#xE9;tait Marc LeBlanc, de l'&#xC9;cole secondaire de Par-En-Bas;</p>
<p>Par cons&#xE9;quent, qu'il soit r&#xE9;solu que tous les membres de cette Assembl&#xE9;e f&#xE9;licitent Danielle Thibault, Autumn Atkinson, et Marc LeBlanc pout leur participation dans ce programme et les remercient pour leur r&#xF4;le en aidant &#xE0; faire la Nouvelle-&#xC9;cosse un leader dans la r&#xE9;duction des d&#xE9;chets.</p>
<p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, je demande l'adoption de cette r&#xE9;solution sans pr&#xE9;avis et sans d&#xE9;bat.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas every year in the month of September the Resource Recovery Fund Board launched a contest for P to 12 schools; and</p>
<p>Whereas this program encourages students to take an active role in their communities by promoting waste reduction by recycling composting; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Primary to Grade 1 winner was teacher Danielle Thibault of &#xC9;cole Pubinco-Ouest, Grades 2 to 3 runner-up was Autumn Atkinson from Plymouth School, and the Grades 7 to 9 winner was Marc LeBlanc, from &#xC9;cole Secondaire de Par-en-Bas;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Danielle Thibault, Autumn Atkinson, and Marc LeBlanc for their participation in this program and thank them for their role in helping make Nova Scotia a leader in waste reduction.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="851">RESOLUTION NO. 851</num>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas 95 years ago today marks the passage of the Nova Scotia Franchise Act which gave women the right to vote for the first time; and</p>
<p>Whereas the passage of that legislation came as the result of the courageous advocacy of Edith Archibald and understanding that the right to vote is a fundamental element in our democracy;</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia was the first province in Atlantic Canada to accept that a fully enfranchised population of men and women is a necessity so that our democracy functions properly;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House recognize this anniversary as an important milestone in Nova Scotia's history, and that men and women continue to fully participate in our democracy not only as voters but also as candidates and citizens.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="852">RESOLUTION NO. 852</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>MS. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas each year Halifax Regional Municipality recognizes extraordinary contributions of individuals and groups who volunteer their time to make our communities better; and</p>
<p>Whereas Alex Davis has been a patient and family adviser volunteering on multiple councils including the IWK Youth Advisory Council, IWK Family Leadership Council, IWK Emergency Department Family Advisory Council, along with speaking at several conferences helping to empower youth to share their stories in the health care system and educate staff on how to work with youth, parents, and families; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 17, 2013, Alex received an HRM Volunteer Award for all his efforts to make a difference in his community and province;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the Legislature congratulate Alex Davis on receiving this award, and thank him for his timeless efforts in making health care more youth-friendly.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cape Breton North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="853">RESOLUTION NO. 853</num>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Christmas season doesn't really get rolling on the Northside until the annual North City Firemen's Christmas Parade takes place; and</p>
<p>Whereas thousands of residents turn out to watch the lighted floats wind their way through the streets of North Sydney; and</p>
<p>Whereas Chief Lloyd McIntosh and his department are responsible for a multitude of smiling children and adults being filled with Christmas cheer;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly thank Chief McIntosh and the North Sydney Fire Department for their Christmas gift to the Northside.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="854">RESOLUTION NO. 854</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>MS. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community and give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas on May 8, 2013, the Halifax Mainland North Volunteer Recognition Committee will be holding their milestone 10<sup>th</sup> Annual Community Champion Awards Dinner to recognize outstanding volunteers who consistently dedicate their time and talents to improving the lives of others; and</p>
<p>Whereas Stewart Whalen of Clayton Park West has been nominated for this award by Prostate Cancer Canada in recognition of his commitment to help raise funds through events such as the Stick It To Prostate Cancer Ball Hockey Tournament and the Annual Father's Day Walk/Run, as well as his volunteer work for the VON, Camp Hill Veterans Hospital, and Abbie Lane;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House congratulate Stewart Whalen on receiving a 2013 Community Champion Award, thank him for his dedication to helping others in his community and province, and wish him every success in the future.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Argyle.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="855">RESOLUTION NO. 855</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas tomorrow is Daffodil Day, a special day which is part of the Canadian Cancer Society's annual Daffodil Month; and</p>
<p>Whereas on this special day we show our support for those living with cancer and remember those we have lost; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Cancer Society urges people across the country to renew their commitment to fight back against cancer and someday find a cure for this disease;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly acknowledge tomorrow is Daffodil Day and show our support for those living with cancer, and raise awareness about prevention and good health.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>ORDERS OF THE DAY</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT BUSINESS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#c7f2d366-8ba0-4263-98e0-bdaa9336415f">
          <from>MR. CLARRIE MACKINNON</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Public Bills for Second Reading.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PUBLIC BILLS FOR SECOND READING</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#c7f2d366-8ba0-4263-98e0-bdaa9336415f">
          <from>MR. CLARRIE MACKINNON</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 61.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 61 - Cyber-safety Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Minister responsible for the Advisory Council on the Status of Women Act.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#5da6e0aa-9066-4b5c-8d26-9222b854db7e">
            <from>HON. MARILYN MORE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I wonder if I might be permitted a brief introduction?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Most certainly.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#5da6e0aa-9066-4b5c-8d26-9222b854db7e">
            <from>MS. MORE</from>
            <p>Thank you. In the east gallery today we have Stephanie MacInnis-Langley, who is the executive director of the Advisory Council on the Status of Women, and Jeannie Flynn who works at the council office as well. I would ask them to stand and receive the appreciation of the House for all their work on these issues. (Applause)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>We welcome all our guests to the gallery and hope they enjoy this morning's proceedings.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister responsible for the Advisory Council on the Status of Women Act.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#5da6e0aa-9066-4b5c-8d26-9222b854db7e"><from>HON. MARILYN MORE</from><p>Thank you, Mr. Speaker. We're all aware that a very tragic incident in our province has touched a chord with every Nova Scotian. Over the last number of years, a number of these incidents have happened, and there's always been a certain level of response and trying to improve the situation. But this last one, I would have to say, created an anger and frustration and a general collective will that we need to be a better province in terms of how we look after one another. Nova Scotians want us to work together to prevent situations like this from happening in the future.</p>
<p>I know that every member of this House shares that view. We may be politicians, we may be leaders in our communities, but we're parents and grandparents first, and we can just imagine some of the pain and suffering that families go through when a child is bullied or cyberbullied or loses their life in this province. I certainly want to start off by expressing the sympathy of all members of this House to the Parsons family for the very unfortunate death of their daughter Rehtaeh.</p>
<p>So the province is not going to defend - we will not defend - the status quo. Like every other level of government, like every other organization, like every individual in this province, we are committed to making the changes that are needed. We understand that there's a leadership role that government needs to provide. We are going to work to ensure that Nova Scotians who need help know where to get it, and that over the years we improve the level of supports we have for families in crisis in this province.</p>
<p>I want to pay credit to Professor Wayne MacKay, who was the chair of the Task Force on Bullying and Cyberbullying; the members of the task force; and the tremendous group of people who worked behind the scenes to provide a lot of the research information, to set up the meetings, and to help prepare the report. That report is foundational in terms of what we're doing here in the Province of Nova Scotia, but has a lot of good information that I know will be shared and has been shared across jurisdictions of Canada.</p>
<p>Yesterday I introduced an Act to Address and Prevent Cyberbullying. It will help prevent cyberbullying and give out a clear message to all Nova Scotians that on-line cyberbullying will not be tolerated, and that people who perform that function will have to be accountable for their actions on-line. The legislation will allow victims and families to seek a court order protection. The court will order someone to stop talking to or about another person on-line, and it leads up to protection orders where a judge could order the computer, the smartphone, or the tablet to be confiscated if there's no co-operation, and if the earlier interventions are not heeded.</p>
<p>We also introduced, through making cyberbullying a tort, the ability of victims to sue for damages. It was a clear message to parents that they are accountable for the on-line behaviour of their young people. So if there was an underage bully, and it was taken to that point in terms of the intervention, and taken to court in a civil case, the parents would then be held liable for the actions unless they could prove that they had performed reasonable supervision of their children on-line.</p>
<p>The part of the legislation that attracted a lot of attention from people, because it's unique in Canada, is setting up a new CyberSCAN unit by the Fall of this year. It will probably take four to six months to put it into operation, and everyone's committed to have it up and operating as quickly as possible. There will be a director and five investigators. They will take complaints from anyone in the province; it could be students, family, parents, or adults.</p>
<p>This investigative unit will actually work on cyberbullying against a person of any age, not just young people in the province. It will help victims and families and it will also have the ability to file protection orders. If, after investigation, it goes to the higher end of maliciousness and lack of co-operation, the unit will then be in a position to hand the case over to the police.</p>
<p>The legislation also amended the Education Act. The amendments clarified that principals and school boards will co-operate with the province and its agencies on these issues. It also clarified that principals do have the ability to look into incidents that happen out of school hours and off the school grounds, when it affects the learning culture, the learning environment of students in their school. That was clarification that the principals and school boards were looking for.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I move that Bill No. 61 be now read a second time.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Colchester North.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>HON. KAREN CASEY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I'm pleased to rise today and speak to Bill No. 61, an Act to Address and Prevent Cyberbullying. I will repeat in my opening comments the commitment that was made in response to the ministerial statement, the commitment that was made by the Leader of the Official Opposition and by the entire Liberal caucus to support and work with the minister as she has assumed a huge responsibility. The minister has taken a file from Education and Early Childhood Development, she has taken a file from Justice, and she has been given the responsibility to oversee the workings of both of those.</p>
<p>I do sincerely - I've done it privately but I want to do it publicly - thank the minister for assuming that responsibility and again reiterate our commitment to work with her on that project or on that assignment. (Applause)</p>
<p>I would also like to say to all members of the House and to all Nova Scotians that it is truly tragic and unfortunate that these kinds of bills have to come forward, as a result of someone else's tragedy and at somebody else's expense. I guess it's an indication that, perhaps, we are more reactive than proactive but we all do extend our sympathies to all families, not just one family but to all families, who have experienced a tragedy as a result of bullying or cyberbullying.</p>
<p>We recognize that there are many things that come into play, and bringing Education and Early Childhood Development and Justice together to look at a solution is trying to cover all of those aspects that do impact on our young people's lives. Those of us who have been involved in working with young people all of our careers, in whatever profession we have chosen, recognize that the introduction of social media and the lack of controls in social media have translated, obviously, into easy, quick communication, but they've also provided a wonderful opportunity for those who wish to be malicious and cruel and evil. They are able to do that with the protection of their own privacy but not protecting and respecting the privacy of others.</p>
<p>We seem to have a generation, Mr. Speaker, who has some difficulty determining what is personal and what is private, and fail to understand that once something is posted or once something is written, it may be personal but once it's typed and once you press send, it's not personal anymore and it becomes very public. Then our young people get caught in this web, which they can't escape because they are not prepared for what will come back at them or how far those images or those comments will travel.</p>
<p>Unknowingly, in many cases, our young kids do post things and there are predators out there - they are not all young people - but there are predators out there that look for opportunities and get some thrill, I guess, about doing and harming others. It is important that the education component and the justice component come together here.</p>
<p>As I said yesterday at the announcement at Halifax West, there appear to be a lot of things in this bill that can address some of the issues that we have but what I added to that was the real proof of this, the real effectiveness of this, will be when those words are put into action. It is unfortunate that we have had opportunities in this Legislature to put words into action on this particular topic, on several occasions. I know the minster has referred to the MacKay task force - and we have mentioned that many times - and I think the language that's now being used is that it is a foundation document.</p>
<p>Well, Mr. Speaker, there was a lot of information in that document but there were some 85 recommendations and some of those recommendations were recommendations that could translate immediately into action, wouldn't cost government any money, and there were some that were long-term because we do have to address the culture of cyberbullying. We do have to look at where we are in our society with respect for ourselves and for others. But there were some recommendations that easily could have translated into action over a year ago, 14, 15 months ago, and that's the opportunity that we in this Legislature missed and that's where we in this Legislature failed young girls and families, because we didn't step up to the plate and take a recommendation and put it into action.</p>
<p>For example, Mr. Speaker - I've spoken about this before - there were two bills that were introduced in response to the task force recommendations, and we have heard from the people who have been asked to implement some of those things that they didn't feel were making any difference in the job that they were asked to do. These people were, in particular, people in our public schools. We also know from those recommendations that when the bills that were introduced by the Minister of Education and Early Childhood Development came before the Law Amendments Committee, some of those recommendations that could have translated into some immediate action were not in the bill, and the opportunity for both Opposition Parties was to submit amendments to the Law Amendments Committee, which did address some of the serious omissions in those bills.</p>
<p>Both Parties went before the Law Amendments Committee and presented those. Also at the Law Amendments Committee, members will recall that we had some members who had been on the task force and we had people from the community who had experienced a tragedy in their family because of bullying and cyberbullying.</p>
<p>I fail to understand, Mr. Speaker, how members in this Legislature who say they care about kids and who say they want to do the best they can, could have said no. Those who presented at Law Amendments Committee could not understand, and they expressed it; in fact, one of those members who presented, one of the mothers who presented, has said most recently: I feel like I've been slapped in the face.</p>
<p>If we, as members of this Legislature, cannot look those people in the eye and say that we have done, and that we are doing, everything we can possibly do to protect our young people, then we should be ashamed. When we have people in our communities who come before us - and they're not asking us for money, they're not asking us to implement something that is going to cost and become a budget line for someone, they are simply asking for a member of this Legislature to begin to speak to their counterparts in Ottawa about changes to the Criminal Code, which is exactly what Recommendation 44 from Wayne MacKay's report said would not cost a cent, but the Law Amendments Committee, which we know is dominated by NDP members, refused to accept that amendment.</p>
<p>All it would have taken 14 or 15 months ago is to do what has now been done because of severe public pressure and because, to use the Premier's words, "this has garnered international attention." Well, I'm sorry, if we have to wait until something garners international attention before we step up to the plate and do something to protect our kids (Applause) Those discussions in Ottawa could have started 15 months ago, Mr. Speaker. (Interruptions)</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Order, please. Order. The honourable member for Colchester North has the floor.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>MS. CASEY</from><p>Thank you, Mr. Speaker. We had an opportunity 15 months ago for the Minister of Justice to fly up to Ottawa and start those conversations, but 15 months have passed and nothing happened. Now, because we are garnering international attention, we're taking some steps. (Interruptions)</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, some of the people who have so much to say have never been in a position to do anything, and when you are in that position you do the best you can. When you get a recommendation from your own task force which says to contact the people in Ottawa and start talking, that doesn't take much money - it doesn't take any money, but it does take somebody who cares. It does take somebody who cares and I believe that all members in this Legislature care and if they could put partisan politics aside, sometimes there would be some action.</p>
<p>We also know, Mr. Speaker, on the task force there were members who had expertise in their own field. One of the recommendations that came out of that task force was to have the ability for service providers to discontinue the cellphone account if it had been found that there had been inappropriate use of that account. The people who are on the task force from the communications side and from service providers knew that could happen and it came as a recommendation, it came as Recommendation 42, I believe. Again, that would not have cost one red cent but there could have been something in the bills that were introduced in April and I think again in October and in the amendments that came after both of those bills that spoke to that.</p>
<p>But those bills were silent on that. Now, 14, 15 months later we see that being addressed and we welcome that. Our issue is why did we allow that time to pass? Why did we allow our young people to be caught up in this social net for the last 14, 15 months and have no place where they could reach out? I know that the minister has extended an invitation for Leaders of the other Parties to meet with her and I know that our Leader has done that. I encourage that and I thank the minister for providing that opportunity because it is an issue for all of us.</p>
<p>If the voices of the Opposition can be heard through their Leaders to the minister then I believe that can strengthen the legislation and I am pleased to know that at least one of those meetings has been held.</p>
<p>We have challenges in our schools. We have a lot of the problems of society playing themselves out in our schools and teachers are challenged with how they can best respond to that. Years ago when I was in the classroom, I used to say if you could teach for five hours - and I've heard other educators say this - if you could go in, teach for five hours, what a great day it would be and how much kids would learn.</p>
<p>But teachers are tasked with dealing with a lot of other issues and trying to get their class and their students in a state of readiness before they can start to teach. In the last couple of years, that state of readiness has been much more difficult to achieve because they are dealing with things that have happened outside the school. Yet the school is the place where they come together and the school is the place where we are trying to respond to those concerns that they have.</p>
<p>We have to remember that students are in the classroom five or six hours a day, but the other 18 or 19 hours, teachers have no control over what they're doing. Principals have no control over what they're doing. Parents and the community play a huge part in bringing about the cultural change that we need so our young people can be safe. If there is a role for teachers and for principals, then we take that seriously and trying to deal with what happens in those other 19 hours, when kids come into school for their five hours, is a huge responsibility.</p>
<p>Anything in any legislation that can give direction to principals is appreciated but you cannot give direction unless you give support. If principals are being asked to follow up on things that happen in the community, playing themselves out in the classroom, in the school so that it interferes with learning - absolutely. But if they're going to be given that responsibility, they have to be given the support that goes with it.</p>
<p>I know there was a mention made yesterday at the briefing about school boards will now be able to work with other agencies. School boards have been working with agencies, all kinds of agencies, for a long, long time. I'm not sure what the intent of that statement was but it certainly sounded to me like it's doing exactly what is happening now and what we have recognized is that we have to do things differently than we are doing them now.</p>
<p>We have technology that we did not even have two years ago and every young person that you see walking down the street from ages 5 to 25 has some sort of technology in their hand. It is their way of communicating, it is a part of their life, and it's well beyond the understanding of many of their parents. If teachers are trying to deal with something in five hours, let's not forget that there is another huge part of their day and their night where their supervision is not from a teacher, and it's not from a principal. It's from the community and it's from their parents.</p>
<p>Together, those people who care about kids - and that's parents, and community, and teachers - can come together and try to understand and try to change the culture. The minister has talked about culture, and I couldn't agree with her more. The culture that exists there now is something that we did not experience, that we did not know, and that some do not understand. Changing that culture alongside - and that's the long-term, I know in the task force report, as I said earlier, some of those recommendations were long-term - because they did speak about changing the culture, and some of them are short-term.</p>
<p>What I want to see happen, and what I believe every MLA in this House wants to see happen, is that the language in this particular bill translates into action that will help those kids in our communities who are looking for help, or who don't know that they need help, or who are afraid to come forward and say they do. If this does not translate into action, then we have not gained anything from the tragedies that we've had in this province. (Applause)</p>
<p>We know that there are a fair number of recommendations or articles in this particular bill, clauses in this bill that speak to the justice and the implementation of this bill. There will be an investigative team that is hired and tasked with going out and providing that support, doing that investigation. We know that it brings an opportunity for people, through civil court, to bring those who they believe are bullying and cyberbullying to court. We know that getting a court order in this province is not easy, and I would hope that this process will be facilitated so that if somebody does stand up, and if somebody does report, and if somebody does want a court order, they don't have to wait years and years and years for that court order. During that wait time we've seen what's happening, and we cannot afford to wait.</p>
<p>We have, as we said, many recommendations in that task force report. It pulled in a lot of Nova Scotians who wanted to make a difference. Some of them, Mr. Speaker, are waiting for that to happen. They get encouraged and then they get discouraged, because they want a change. So they are looking at this bill, they are looking at the minister who now has the lead on this, and they are having some hope that this will translate into some action.</p>
<p>Members of this Liberal caucus have spoken out about the need. We've spoken out about the opportunities that have been missed. We support the minister. We support Bill No. 61, we want it to translate into action, and we'll be watching, because none of us can afford to lose any more time. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, this has been a very sad time in our province in Nova Scotia in the last few weeks, in particular, as all Nova Scotians have followed the tragic circumstances around the death of Rehtaeh Parsons. It's a sad time in all communities of the province. It's a reminder that when one family suffers as tragically as the Parsons family has suffered, all of us in the Nova Scotia family suffer as well.</p>
<p>It is one of the great sadnesses of the province that these things happen but it is also one of our strengths that we draw on in tough times, that we do feel that same sense of family when any one Nova Scotia family goes through such a big tragedy.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I can tell you that same effect happens in community after community, time after time. Last year in my own constituency of Cumberland South, in the Town of Parrsboro, the Brown family suffered the same tragedy that too many families have been suffering, when their 17-year-old daughter, Courtney Brown, having been bullied on both the school grounds and town property, and then in her own home through cyberbullying, came to the same sad conclusion as Rehtaeh and too many others. When young people - bullied as they are, harassed as they are, assaulted as they are, sexually and physically - finally come to that awful point where they feel there is nowhere else to turn and then we see what happens.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, the most important first thing we should all say, over and over, to young people: there is always one more place to turn, there is always somewhere to go for help. There are your parents, there is your teacher and your principal; there are important mental health services, important sexual health services and important counselling services that are always there.</p>
<p>If we resolve nothing else beyond this bill, let us resolve in this House that we will always make sure that the resources are available so that not another young woman, not another young Nova Scotian, boy or girl, can come to the point where they feel there's no place else to turn. There is always another place to turn and we will make sure that there is always another place to turn, for them.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, that is one of the lessons of the tragedy of Rehtaeh Parsons, it's one of the lessons of the tragedy of Courtney Brown, one a young woman in the Halifax-Dartmouth area, another, a young woman in a rural part of our province, that no matter where you live, city or country, urban or rural, no matter what your circumstances, you have to know that there is always somewhere else to turn. There is always going to be a program for you or a person, an adult, a counsellor, to be there for you. Let us make that determination right now and we can take another step forward on this journey that we're all on together here, in the Province of Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I shared with the House before, in the wake of the tragic events of the last few weeks, that in my own house, where I have two teenage daughters, we had the conversation, the difficult one around our own dinner table over several nights about cyberbullying, about identifying it, about protecting yourself, about turning to your mum or dad, or your teacher, or wherever you need to turn, about where to call, about the hotlines that are available, so that they know for themselves and also for their friends.</p>
<p>We've seen some pretty brave stories over the last little while, of young people in our schools who weren't on the receiving end of bullying or cyberbullying but they knew someone who was because they saw it on the school ground or they saw it on Facebook and they stepped up in defence of their fellow student.</p>
<p>This is one of those examples, Mr. Speaker, that in the face of tragedy and evil that we see human goodness also step forward, as is happening in our schools. I want to applaud the students, the young people of Nova Scotia, who are now stepping up not just on their own behalf but on behalf of their friends and their fellow students.</p>
<p>There was a case just yesterday at Halifax West High School of two young students who went to the principal when they saw on Facebook that a fellow student was being cyberbullied and now that they're aware, or more aware, of the services that are available and where people can turn to get help, they stepped up on behalf of their fellow student. That is goodness in the face of evil and it is right. Young Nova Scotians are stepping up and we should applaud them for that.</p>
<p>We've had that conversation at our dinner table in our house, Mr. Speaker, and I'm sure that many members here, with their own kids or grandkids, have done the same and I actually believe that that conversation is happening at the kitchen tables and the dining- room tables of thousands of households around Nova Scotia, as it should, so that kids know that their parents are there, as a start, or their guardians are there or their aunts and uncles are there - their families are there.</p>
<p>After all, the number-one duty of a parent is to protect their children. So, too, Mr. Speaker, the number-one duty of a government is also to provide protection to the citizens of the province, starting with our youngest and most vulnerable. And that's why I rise today to speak to this bill, Bill No. 61, because it is time for the provincial laws around bullying and cyberbullying to be brought into the 21<sup>st</sup> Century, to be modernized, so that we can take strong action that sends a message to bullies and cyberbullies, and provides more information to victims about where to turn.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, this is not the first time that these ideas about how to modernize our laws have come before this House. Members of both Opposition Parties have been bringing forward their own bills and their own plans on bullying and cyberbullying for well over a year. I will say I'm pleased that the government has come around and has now brought forward a strong bill that takes up some of those ideas and because, obviously, there is a majority on the government side, we now have a chance in this House to do the right thing - and that is to enact strong laws and get them on the books as soon as possible.</p>
<p>We'll certainly do our bit to make that happen because that's what we should do in this case; that's what Nova Scotians expect us to do. So the bill's provisions, like defining cyberbullying in law, making it an offence or making it a tort, as the government proposes, spelling out that people who are guilty of cyberbullying will be sued, that they'll face awards of damages, substantial financial penalties if guilty, we've been asking for that for over a year - and now, finally, we see that that's going to move forward.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, when the guilty party is a young person, as it often is in these cases, parents may well find themselves liable for the damages inflicted by a cyberbully. That's also something that we've been calling for for over a year and, of course, I'm glad to see that that's now going forward.</p>
<p>It truly does take a whole family to protect victims of cyberbullying - not just the victim's family, but there is a duty on behalf of the family of the bully as well. So we're finally going to reflect that in law, and that's a good thing.</p>
<p>For those who are found to be cyberbullying or where a law enforcement official has reasonable grounds to believe there is cyberbullying, the bill proposes that their identity become known from their Internet service provider and they be visited by a law enforcement official. The minister describes this as an attempt to take away the keyboard courage of a cyberbully. Mr. Speaker, that is a good step, but sometimes you actually have to take away the keyboard, you actually have to confiscate the laptop or the smart cellphone, or whatever device is being used as a weapon against young people on-line.</p>
<p>Now the bill does contemplate that and I'm glad because, again, that's something we've been asking for for the last year, to give our law enforcement officials the power to confiscate electronic devices when they're used as weapons against our young people - so I'm glad that's going to come into effect, and I encourage that along as fast as possible.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, for a year we have been asking the government to give our law enforcement officials, our principals, our teachers, our mental health workers, and others, the tools to intervene early when they know of cases of cyberbullying or bullying, or they see it, or reasonably suspect it, and now we are going to go in that direction. I'm glad that's happening.</p>
<p>Just like it takes a family to protect the victims and to stop the bullies, it really does take a whole community to keep our kids safe. Whether you are a police officer, or a teacher, or a principal, or an adult in our community, it is important that people recognize their own responsibilities to keep our kids and communities safe, both on the streets, on the school grounds and on-line.</p>
<p>I'm glad that we're getting somewhere, that real action is now coming, but there's more to do. I do want to point out there is more to do. No one should declare a victory at this point - not us in Opposition who have been pushing for it for a year, nor should the government declare a victory because we now have this bill. It is not about them or us, all this should be about is our young people and keeping them safe. Only when they are safe should we all declare victory that we have taken a positive action that made our province safer on-line and on the streets, for our young people. All of this is about them and them alone.</p>
<p>They need a comprehensive plan. Nova Scotians know that our province made the news, both nationally and internationally, for very sad reasons, over the past few weeks. Let us resolve now that the next time our province makes the news, nationally or beyond, it's because we've truly become a leader in the protection of our young people in the 21<sup>st</sup> Century. That work is not done with this bill. That work is not done.</p>
<p>For example, the Wayne MacKay task force, the anti-bullying task force, which spent a year consulting with all the experts and young people and all those involved in protecting them on how we can bring our laws on bullying and cyberbullying into the 21<sup>st</sup> Century, that task force does map out a comprehensive plan. Many of its elements are incorporated into this bill and in the government's action plan, but not all. There is more to do.</p>
<p>For example, the MacKay task force calls for bringing the number of guidance councillors in our schools up to an appropriate level relative to the number of students. There are standards around how many guidance councillors we should have per student and we are short of that. In addition to this bill, I want the government to actually provide the funding to our schools to have enough guidance councillors to meet that standard - another way of telling our young people: you always have somewhere to turn when you are on the receiving end of a bully or a cyberbully.</p>
<p>More than that, although this bill does provide our school principals with the tools they need to act, it says that they may take action when they see or know of potential bullying or cyberbullying. That is a step forward but it's not enough. In Clause 26 of the bill it says principals may take action when they see it. But the MacKay task force, Recommendation 33, compels officials like our principals, when they know of a case of cyberbullying or bullying, to take action. That is a responsibility that all adults should have and I believe the bill should have said, you know this is going on in your school, you have reason to believe, then you must act. That's what the MacKay task force reported, that's not what the bill says.</p>
<p>If that is somewhere else, I would like to see that because that, to me, is an important change. The MacKay task force, in Recommendation 31, talks about expanding the jurisdiction of principals beyond the school grounds, and that is an important step forward and I acknowledge that it's there. But we also have to make clear that it also extends beyond school hours - that is what the MacKay task force reported, and the bill has not gone all that way - that that duty to act is not restricted to school hours alone because in the 21<sup>st</sup> Century, in the modern world, bullying doesn't stop when the school bell rings at the end of the day.</p>
<p>We all know when we were growing up you could get away from it by getting off the school grounds and getting home and you'd be safe. You are not safe today at 3:10 p.m., or whatever time your school closes when the bell rings, you're not because of the on-line world, which is an important part of young people's lives. So why not extend that duty to include after-school hours, Mr. Speaker, as Dr. MacKay recommended?</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, the bill does create a tort in law around cyberbullying, and spells out liability that the cyberbully, or his or her parents, is incurring - and that's good, and so we should. But matched with that we should make sure that parents and students have all the tools they need to understand the responsibility that we are now imposing on them - rightly imposing on them - when they are on-line, that if they act illegally on-line, as the bill will create an illegality, and they are liable for those actions we need to also make sure that they have the information and the tools to know how to act responsibly on-line.</p>
<p>That brings up the whole modern concept of the digital citizen and we have this wonderful new tool - not so new anymore - the wonderful tool of mass modern communication on the Internet, social media like Facebook, and so on. We are learning its power, both its great power to send information around to all people, but we're also learning of its great danger and its great evil - and I do want to speak a little bit about that in a moment but I understand there is an introduction, and I'm happy to yield.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Thank you, member. The honourable Minister of Finance on a short introduction.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>I will make it very short. Mr. Speaker.</p>
<p>We have a lot of very important guests here today, who will be introduced in a moment, but I would like to introduce one member of the visiting party who is a young man who lives in my constituency, and his dad is well known to members of the government side, for sure. I would ask Dash Hebb if he would stand and receive the warm welcome of the House. (Applause)</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Halifax Chebucto on a longer introduction.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#c64a6bcf-fabd-4b08-bd04-ecd0fc310c2e"><from>MR. HOWARD EPSTEIN</from><p>The young man, Dashiell Hebb, is part of a larger group who come to us from St. Catherine's School. They are a Grade 3 group; there are 34 students. St. Catherine's School is a French immersion school located in my constituency.</p>
<p>The group is accompanied today by their teacher, Jacky O'Leary, who in fact is a former Page from the House, and with various parents. With them: Rob Zinck, Carolyn Lowe, Brian MacIntyre, Lisa Jacobs, Kristi Wenaus, Gail DeAdder, Gina Jones, and Fiona Martin - all attending upon a group of 34 students, whose first names I will call. We have present with us: Noah, Bridget, Ella, Dashiell whom we have already heard of, Ondreia, Sophie, Surya, Frida, Rachael, Carmen, Andrew, Chase, Eli, Lori, Wiljo, Sasha, Keely, Spencer, Ethan, Sarina, Tamara, Talia, Willem, Branwen, Katie, Madison, Claire, Rebecca, Amy, James, Robbie, Phoenyx, Geordie, and Caleb. I welcome them all to the House, and I would invite members to show them your welcome. (Applause)</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>We welcome all our guests to the gallery this morning and hope they enjoy this morning's proceedings.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>MR. BAILLIE</from><p>Thank you, Mr. Speaker, and I too want to extend our welcome to the visitors in the gallery. Perhaps there's an aspiring politician or two up there in that class, and maybe someday they'll be down here.</p>
<p>I was just speaking about the need to ensure that, with this modern tool of social media, with all the good it can do in getting information around to people and all the power it has that can also be extremely hurtful, we include in our school curriculum - we include for all Nova Scotians - information and teachings about what it means to be a citizen in the 21<sup>st</sup> Century, including the rights, responsibilities, duties, and liabilities that we incur when we exercise our citizenship on-line.</p>
<p>I hope we get to that point quickly, because the MacKay Task Force actually did recommend - in Recommendation 64 and again in Recommendation 65 - that it's time, given all that has happened, to include in the school curriculum the ability to teach digital citizenship so that Nova Scotia can truly be a leader in bringing our province and our citizens, young and old, into the 21<sup>st</sup> Century. It is the duty of all citizens to use the resources that our great province has provided to them, to use the resources that through their own work, through their own efforts, they have amassed for themselves, for good and safety, for the benefit of their families and their communities and not to do harm. Now we know that there is a whole new way that harm can be done - tragic harm - through social media on-line.</p>
<p>Just to drive that point home, all of us in this House at some point or other were newly-elected members. I speak from my own experience, but I'm sure it is true for all of us that as a newly-elected member, we remember that first time that we read a newspaper report on-line or some commentary on-line and then looked to see all the anonymous comments attached to it, particularly if it's a story that we ourselves are part of, as happens to members in this House from time to time, and how stung we felt the first time we read an anonymous posting about one of us, how stung we felt that someone who we don't even know - or we don't even know if we know - is saying hurtful, nasty things about us, as people. That has happened to all of us, I'm sure.</p>
<p>We are, in politics, expected to be ready to understand that and to accept it and to move on, but it's still hard when it happens. I believe there are people who never get over it, who obsess on it, as adults, as a 40-something or 50-something or 60-something-year-old person - with all the life experiences we already had before we came to this place, how hurtful it is.</p>
<p>Imagine that exact same situation, except that you are a 15-year-old girl or a 14-year-old boy, and this is happening to you, someone who doesn't have the benefit of all of those years of growing up to know how to deal with that, and how hurtful it is, how sadly hurtful it is, whether it's anonymous or from a classmate.</p>
<p>We cannot leave our young people in that vulnerable position. We've seen where that can lead. We know that feeling of there's nowhere else to turn. For that reason it is so important that we turn this situation around, and fast.</p>
<p>I said a moment ago, Madam Speaker, that Nova Scotia made news for all the wrong reasons, nationally and internationally, in the last few weeks, as around the world people watched the Rehtaeh Parsons story unfold. Well, let's just resolve that someday soon, because of the work of all Parties, because of our resolve here to modernize our own laws and protect our young people, with this bill and others, other steps that still need to be done, Nova Scotia will again make the news - but because we are a leader in protecting our young people. We're not there yet. This bill is a step along the way. We're not there yet, but that is really what we all need to do if we're going to accomplish something positive here in this session and the future. So with those few words, Madam Speaker, I will take my place. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>MS. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Thank you so much, Madam Speaker. I think it's very important to get up and say a few words on Bill No. 61, which is known as the Cyber-safety Act. I think for the public who watch this at home, it's important to outline a little bit about what's in the bill.</p>
<p>The bill is pretty extensive; it's quite a long piece of legislation, 20 pages of clauses and various penalties, and outlining some action that will be taken to try and combat cyberbullying in our province. I would hope, as well, to set a standard for other provinces to follow. I think that is important, that we have finally begun to put some teeth into the legislation that has been brought here. As the member for Colchester North mentioned, there have been two pieces of legislation brought here in the last couple of years in relation to other cases of cyberbullying and other issues that had certainly garnered provincial attention, if not national and international attention.</p>
<p>I think the travesty here today is that it has taken such a lot of profound public input, and a petition that, the last time I looked, was at about 300,000 - it's probably many more names on that petition now - the one that asked and called for action on behalf of Rehtaeh Parsons. It takes that kind of public outcry, not only among Nova Scotians but a much broader area, to get us back to what's important here and to put some teeth into the legislation, that the government has had an opportunity to do. I wanted to mention in context, Madam Speaker, that we are, here in the Legislature, often highly partisan, and I know it has been mentioned. The member for Halifax Fairview mentioned it the other day, that we've become even more partisan in the last number of months, and perhaps years.</p>
<p>The fact is, it is pretty ridiculous to suggest that the Liberals in the 1990s should have done something about this, or even that in the Progressive Conservative time, four years ago, we would have done something about this. Texting has become very, very widely used now. I think four years ago, I wasn't sending any texts; I don't believe children and others were sending texts. It was very new. Facebook is 2005. I think maybe the most highly advanced members of the Legislature were doing it because they lived in the United States at the time and they were more adept.</p>
<p>But literally, this is very new to parents. I know a lot of parents don't text at all themselves, and a lot of them aren't using half of the facilities that their phones offer. They're not aware of what their children are doing, what the capacity is to do. I just think, to put it in context, this is a problem that has exploded in the last three, four, or five years. It really has. The extent of it, and the negativity, the nastiness of what can be said on-line, has just exploded.</p>
<p>We know how quickly the Internet has changed even in the last few years. Tools that were being widely used a few years ago, like MSN and so on, they're pass&#xE9;. There are other ways to communicate - there's Twitter, there's instantaneous communication. I just want to make that point, that it has been vastly changing, quickly changing, and it's very difficult for parents, and obviously for lawmakers, to keep up. People in positions of authority have not been keeping up. We in the Legislature have not kept pace.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, when I saw this coming today for discussion - and I'm very aware, as are all members, of the context in which we felt the concern of the public - many of the members here in the House were at the vigil that was held for Rehtaeh Parsons at Victoria Park on Spring Garden Road, and I know there was another one held in Cole Harbour. I was reminded of only a few months ago, when I attended the vigil in the Grand Parade, which was for the young girl who lost her life in British Columbia, Amanda Todd. I participated and said a few words at that gathering. Wayne MacKay was at that gathering. Again, it's such a similar circumstance, not exactly the same but similar, where a young girl feels tormented to the point where she just felt she couldn't go on.</p>
<p>We said at that time - this is what bothers me so much - the speakers were saying at that time, we have to take action; we can't let this happen to another girl. Not only do we know of those, and there are a few other cases we could name right off the top of our heads, but we know there are many countless others that it happened to, perhaps their lives have been lost, perhaps they are suffering in silence, their families are reeling from the effects of what is not just bullying. I have to say they are criminal acts, serious criminal acts, criminal acts that even under our laws today, even without the passage of this bill, should be acted upon, should be treated as criminal acts. Sexual assault, or call it what it is, it is rape, rape is against the law.</p>
<p>If a young person, a minor, has been raped and if those photographs are shared, that is child pornography, if you ask me, and there are laws against child pornography. I think a lot of us are reeling with the idea that we can't understand why those laws that we trust and that are in place haven't been acted on and aren't being acted on - not just in one case, but I think in many cases. We live in a province where sexual assault is under-reported, we know that, and yet at the same time we have the highest rate of sexual assault in the country. Even though we know it's under-reported, that a lot of women will not come forward and don't want to go through the agony, really, of the court system and trying to get anything done, any justice accomplished.</p>
<p>At the same time - so I have said we're under-reported, we still have the highest rates of reported sexual assault and we have the lowest conviction rates. Add that together, if you were a woman who was sexually assaulted, and you're already suffering emotionally and physically and mentally, would you want to put yourself into a court system that routinely is not finding criminal fault or the people are getting away with it? I just don't think the justice system has sent a strong enough signal that we've taken these concerns seriously enough. I really feel that the laws we have, have been on the record, they should be good for much more than they're being used for and I think some of that is cultural and attitudinal and we need to do more about that as well.</p>
<p>Cyberbullying, bullying in general, is a really big problem and certainly cyberbullying played a part in this criminal case that we're talking about but we shouldn't confuse outright, clearly criminal acts with bullying. The very word "bullying" might underestimate or somehow downplay the seriousness of what we're talking about. We're talking about activities that do and can ruin lives and people feel helpless, that's what struck me from listening to parents.</p>
<p>We've heard parents here at the Committee on Law Amendments. We've heard them on the news more recently saying how helpless you feel and I can only imagine where you would turn or what you would do in that circumstance. It must be extremely difficult for parents and they feel that the systems have failed their children, and the social agencies and the supports are not there.</p>
<p>I'm really glad - I do want to begin by saying again, as the member for Colchester North said, we're really glad to see one minister charged with dealing with this file and this case and doing something meaningful, not just lip service, not just small Band-Aids as we saw in a couple of the other bills that have come through that didn't fully respond to the 85 recommendations that came here from the report by Wayne MacKay. That report - and I know the minister has called it foundational - I believe it was prescriptive. It had 85 recommendations that were as clear as saying ask your Justice Minister to go to Ottawa. That's clear.</p>
<p>Start the discussion. Get the laws changed. Get on with this. We have to lobby Ottawa, obviously. Some of this is in the Criminal Code, federal laws, but if the provinces don't tell Ottawa that this is needed, then it's not going to be on their agenda. That was one of the recommendations, start that discussion now. We could have begun that discussion months ago if that had in fact been seen as a blueprint or an outline for all the things that needed to be done. Instead it was seen as something that could be maybe chipped away at over a long time or maybe not urgent enough.</p>
<p>Again, it was mentioned - twice at Law Amendments Committee we have had parents and others asking for changes and stronger changes in the two pretty light bills that we had earlier, relating to cyberbullying and the amendments that were put on the table. I don't really care if they were Progressive Conservative amendments or Liberal amendments - they were Liberal amendments - but they were turned down at that committee for partisan reasons.</p>
<p>Members of the public would probably know that because we have a majority government, our committees are also a majority of members from the governing side, from the NDP side of the House, and fewer members from the Opposition side of the House. Therefore, any suggestions that are brought by Opposition members can be very easily voted down at a committee of nine members, where we are outnumbered.</p>
<p>I think there has been a shift away from looking for good ideas and trying to accommodate good ideas, which we did see in a minority government situation. Now I agree that my first six years in the Legislature was a minority situation - it wasn't a majority - so the Progressive Conservatives during their years, from 2003 at least to 2009, were willing to consider and accommodate some Opposition requests. There certainly were NDP requests that were accepted during that time. There was more dialogue on bills that came through. As an Opposition member, I was able to make suggestions on a number of bills where I was very - I felt that I could be part of the process. I felt that, as an Opposition member, we were being listened to; at least there was a little bit of consideration.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, you were also a member of Opposition during that time and I know other members who were elected at the same time as I was - including the minister who is now responsible for this file - will know what I'm saying is true and that with a majority government you can wield utter control. The government can tell the Opposition to pound sand and, therefore, no wonder we get a little bit frustrated.</p>
<p>We put good ideas in front of the Law Amendments Committee, we try to make positive and constructive change. Our amendments are not done to obstruct government. They're not brought forward to somehow make life difficult for government. They're brought forward because we're also listening to people who we represent. We know that people come to us with good ideas and we're trying to also be an avenue to bring those ideas to the floor of the Legislature to be accepted into our legislation, as we go forward. That's what the Law Amendments Committee is for.</p>
<p>I think it's wonderful that Nova Scotia has a Law Amendments Committee. I think we're the only province that has it - maybe the Clerk will let me know - but I think we're certainly one of the very few that has a law amendments process where people have an opportunity to say something about legislation, that members of the public, as well, have an opportunity to say something about legislation as it is moving through the Legislature and being considered.</p>
<p>We need to listen to the public because as an MLA, I can tell all members of the House, the best ideas I've had I think have come from members of the public when they've had an issue themselves and they've faced some problem and they've come to me and said, why don't we just have a law that does this, or why don't we amend that rule so that it would address this circumstance? Very often, because they've faced that issue, they have insight and wisdom about it. I may never have even looked at that particular issue, had it not been for their advice.</p>
<p>Therefore, I would suggest that the members of the government would have been well served 15 months ago, had they listened, had the members who were sitting around that table said, let's have a break and discuss this with our caucus. These amendments make sense, let's put them in play. It's not just the Opposition asking - sometimes it is parents. There definitely was a parent from Truro who spoke to Law Amendments Committee who had already suffered the same loss that we're here today responding to, the same loss of a child, basically the same circumstance.</p>
<p>We need to be sensitive and open-minded. That's why I'm disappointed and I'm sure other members feel the same way - I'm sure the minister feels the same way - how dreadful it is that it takes such a tragedy, and a tragedy that we could not overlook, we couldn't turn away from, it's so big and the attention on it is so strong. We've said it before, again I say when we spoke at the vigil for Amanda Todd, we said this should never happen again. (Interruption) I have an electronic device here that's making noise so it's going away because I don't know how to deal with that at this moment. Thank you.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, there were a number of good recommendations in the MacKay Report - we know 85 recommendations, and quite a few of the ones with teeth are now in this bill. I wanted to just make the point about some of the points that are in here now - obviously the ability to go to Ottawa and to start the discussion with other Justice Ministers around the country and with the federal Justice Minister. That has now been kick-started, and literally kick-started.</p>
<p>It's unfortunate that it has to be in this circumstance, because now it does look like damage control rather than the kind of positive thing we could have done when it wasn't in the face of a disaster. Fifteen months ago we could have said we'd taken steps, and if something like this had happened, all of us could have said the bills were good, we brought in good legislation, and now it would be a question of, how do we enforce it?</p>
<p>Again, I go back to some of the criminal laws that we have today, and I wonder why they're not properly enforced and why women and children and youth are not protected from so many of these attacks that they're suffering. I understand the technology is new, and that's what I said - we haven't had this kind of technology. It certainly didn't exist in the 1990s.</p>
<p>I don't think it does any good to lay blame to earlier governments in this case. We have to respond now that we know the enormity of the problem, and now we know how pervasive technology is, and it will always be now in the lives of young people. We have to now set those parameters, set rules, and set penalties, and this does do that now.</p>
<p>I understand that the Minister of Justice has announced an investigative team that is going to go into place in the next four to six months, and that investigative unit will work around the province and respond to any complaints that come in on cyberbullying. It says that in the most extreme cases they will have the power to take away an electronic device from somebody who is abusing it and using it for harm to others.</p>
<p>I think it's very good to know that the power will be there for people to sue another person who cyberbullies them, who uses electronic means to harm them, and that if that person happens to be underage and they're sued, their parents will be held responsible. I think that's important, too, because I know how difficult it is to make people responsible, but they are responsible for their children and the activities of their children. We have other laws in different cases that do that, but I think it's important that parents know that they are going to be held accountable as well. We need to make that loud and clear and make sure that people know that this is required.</p>
<p>Again, the recommendation - I think it was No. 42 - that would give Internet providers the power to basically pull the plug on somebody who is abusing their Internet service, using it for hate and using it for criminal activities like cyberbullying and harming others, that if that inappropriate and illegal activity is going on, they can pull the plug and take away that account. That could have been done when Dr. MacKay's report was tabled here more than a year ago, but we're glad to see that it's going to be in place now.</p>
<p>Again, I think the recommendations that have real teeth have now finally found their way into a piece of legislation here. I don't know why the government monkeyed around with it in the previous two bills that were really soft-shoe, soft-peddling, no more than lip service to the problem that was before us. I think that is a travesty, and I think that the government most likely regrets it today, that there wasn't more action on the part of the ministers who had control at the time.</p>
<p>One positive move right now is that we have one minister who can take responsibility and move this file forward on behalf of several ministries, because there's too much division, I guess, in terms of who has control, if it's Justice and Education and Early Childhood Development and people being territorial about their individual levels or spans of control. I don't know if the ministers were being territorial and not wanting to share that file with each other, but so many of the issues we deal with cross over. It's Health and Wellness, Justice, and Education and Early Childhood Development together.</p>
<p>These things are common, that they're going to cross boundaries. We have the Status of Women, which is affecting a number of different departments. This is definitely a women's issue today, although there are boys who are bullied as well, but I think that like so many things you might - I don't have the figures, but I know that individually, the case that has propelled us here has been an issue of a girl. I think that the cases we've mentioned where it has ended in tragedy, they've all been girls that we know of, and who have been in the press here in Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>We need to protect all our young people, Madam Speaker, because we know there are cases around homophobia, around anybody who is different, around people who are new to our country, whose languages aren't as good - there's just a lot of meanness in the world. Often when you are in high school or even younger, anybody who is a little bit different gets targeted or anybody who is a little bit vulnerable or has made any mistakes at all, they get targeted.</p>
<p>I spoke earlier about drinking, under Health and Wellness estimates, and the worry around our drinking culture. There is an element of that as well, a health element in this. I know the minister was at the high school in my riding, last evening or yesterday, in Halifax West and it's a school of 1,500 students. I know that like every other school in this province, drinking is an issue there, so are drugs, but drinking is an issue and I think we need to have better education to protect young people from the physical, mental and vulnerability issues that come around drinking. Oftentimes it's somebody young who isn't aware and hasn't anyone to look after them, in that case.</p>
<p>I think many of us may have been there ourselves in our youth and I say that there are a lot of things where I often think, there but for the grace of God, go I. There are so many times when you think that could have happened to me or to my own children, or to somebody I love. I think we need to be really conscious about that.</p>
<p>I mentioned the drinking because I think there is a health issue here and I'm talking about how this transcends one department. I see the minister is acknowledging that and that's good because that may be an element of what you have to weave in to the answers that we're looking for. I know it's not in this bill alone because this is about technology and this is about how it's being abused.</p>
<p>The member for Cumberland South did say there are a lot of good kids out there and I know, in the media reports yesterday from Halifax West, there were some wonderful young people who were interviewed and spoke and they have just a fantastic school spirit. I think there are over 100 students involved in student government at Halifax West. They have a volunteer committee, a community-involvement committee, a world-involvement committee. They're raising money for Gambia, doing food and clothing drives for Halifax and they just did a big Head for the Cure event where they raised $17,000 to help the Terry Fox Foundation. They have been doing that for 10 years and over that time they've raised about $70,000 at that school. When I went to the rally for that, you could just see all of the young people who were so involved.</p>
<p>We mustn't forget there are some great things going on and that a lot of the young people are really socially aware and concerned about each other. But we need to raise that level for all of them as much as we can and we really do need not only the education and the soft side of it - the appealing to them and teaching them - but we need some enforcement tools because if we know it's happening, and happening in a prevalent way, we have to have the enforcement tools and somebody who can investigate it and treat it seriously. It is not unlike what the prosecution service did some years ago in getting some prosecutors who were specialists in sexual assault.</p>
<p>We didn't have that and we wanted some that would know, exactly, the rules and the precedents and the ability that the Crown had to act on sexual assault. I know in our Prosecution Service here, we had at least one - I think more than one - specialist to deal with those cases. I think we need to get that level of expertise among our law enforcement officers, through this investigative team, and further right through to the prosecution service to the courts.</p>
<p>There's too much of a boys-will-be-boys attitude around a lot of the bullying and cyberbullying. I've heard it on a number of the interviews where young people have been interviewed, the last couple of days on CBC, saying that when they went to their school, they were told, oh, well, that's life, boys will be boys, take it in stride. The woman I'm speaking about was from New Brunswick, it was a Fredericton High School incident, and she'll be a speaker, apparently, here in May at a conference in Halifax. She is now in university but she said that was the attitude, just a few short years ago, boys will be boys, just live with it, and she had to go back to school and sit in the same classroom with boys who were sexually harassing her and bullying her and putting things out on-line and so on. That can't be accepted and when see this happening we have to be - here in this Legislature we have to be strong and stand up and make rules that are going to protect people.</p>
<p>As I said, Madam Speaker, my intent is to try not to be blaming, but we know that we've had 15 months since the recommendations came in from Dr. MacKay, and now that this bill is before us my appeal would be let us move quickly on these recommendations. Let's pass this bill, let's listen to the public in Law Amendments, but see that any good suggestions that come forward are listened to this time, whether it's from the public and through the public, perhaps through the Opposition as amendments - let's listen.</p>
<p>I don't know what amendments we may want because I don't know what we'll hear from the public, but if there are good suggestions I would appeal to the government not to reject them purely because they think the Opposition get a win. This is not about us getting a win, or the government a win - there is no win in this. We're in a situation where the public are concerned, people are hurting, young people have lost their lives and others are suffering, and will never have the same life as a result of some of the activities that they've suffered.</p>
<p>We need to look at this in what is the true sense of our work here, and that is to make life better for Nova Scotians and to work to make a safe and secure place for our young people to grow up. Now that includes not just our physical surroundings but the cyber world in which people are also active and living, and social life is now taking place - that may be very unfamiliar to those of us who grew up 50 years ago but it is now the reality. Social life, a lot of it, is purely digital and so we need to protect people in that realm as well.</p>
<p>I am glad to see these changes before us; I do feel that they are late in the fact that the prescription was there 15 months ago and that Dr. MacKay had been pretty clear about what was needed in many ways with 85 recommendations. But the government certainly has our support in seeing action today, and I think you've given it to one the most capable ministers on the government side to handle such a sensitive and difficult issue and I therefore will be looking forward to Law Amendments and to see this bill become enacted. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Truro-Bible Hill.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#c479d7de-83a6-47c7-a045-07816407bdb3"><from>MS. LENORE ZANN</from><p>Madam Speaker, in one way it gives me pleasure to rise today, as always, to speak in this House but it does not give me pleasure that it has to be about a bill that unfortunately we need in this society today - the Cyber-safety Act, or an Act to Address and Prevent Cyberbullying.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I've been listening this morning to many things that have been said in the House about this very urgent and important initiative and, to tell the truth, it saddens me that in some ways we're all dancing around the issue which is basically about abuse and about the dangers of people trying to have power over others, which seems to be so prevalent in this society today.</p>
<p>Kids learn from adults, Madam Speaker, and I think that until the time comes when children see from our grown-up actions that bullying and abuse in all its many forms is not an acceptable form of communication in our society, nothing is going to change. I think children see it from a very early age on, from the television shows that they watch to the videos that they play where they see people killing and hurting each other, and the movies and television shows that they watch; in fact by the time a child is about eight years old they've already seen 5,000 killings of various sorts. To me this is not acceptable, this is not something that I would like to see our children taught. And when we are surprised at children's action in the schoolyard or with each other, I really have to shake my head and say, well where do you think they learned it?</p>
<p>When you read the newspapers and you see people bullying each other in the newspapers, or you even watch reality TV and see people screaming and yelling each other and calling each other names - this does not send a good message to children. Here in this House, oftentimes - we've been talking lately about the toxic atmosphere, it's true, it is toxic, and I think jabbing at each other and using anecdotes of different people in communities and saying that these people are against whatever our government is doing when, in fact, we're trying to do something to make a change in society here, is not helpful.</p>
<p>I understand that critics have a role to play, but I do believe that we all have to work together on these very, very important issues in order to change the behaviour that the bill is actually talking to. For instance, earlier today when the member for Colchester North was discussing some of the issues in Truro-Bible Hill with our CISS, it's called - the Cyber Internet Safety Society - the fact is we've been working on that project for four years now. I've personally been working on it in the community. The whole community has put a lot of effort into this group and into this project.</p>
<p>The Nova Scotia Community College students, the digital animation students, worked hours, weeks, months on this project for free. Jonathan Torrens, a wonderful professional actor from Nova Scotia, and I as well, as a professional actor, we waived our professional fees to perform in the video, which - as the member from across the way mentioned - has now been seen by 25,000 students across the province. What we do as actors in that video is speak directly to the students, teaching them about the dangers of bullying on-line and teaching them Internet safety issues.</p>
<p>Now, Madam Speaker, those kinds of things are invaluable and we put our time and energy into this because we believe in it, and we believe that it's going to do good with these young students, with these elementary school students. I was really pleased to be able to contribute my work for this great initiative.</p>
<p>They've also received several grants from the Department of Justice, Lighthouses Grants. I was very happy to help them work on their grant application, and was pleased that they were able to receive. They also actually received just yesterday, Madam Speaker - it was announced that our local Truro credit union has now come up and the Truro Community Credit Union has just awarded $2,500 to two local anti-bullying initiatives, the Kids Helpline and CISS - the Cyber Internet Safety Society.</p>
<p>The Cyber Internet Safety Society has been supported in large part by the Town of Truro, and now by the Truro Police Board, so this initiative is not over yet. It's nice to see it growing and growing in the amount of people who are aware of it and the children who are aware of it. I just wanted to bring that information to the House floor today as well.</p>
<p>Also, I'm really pleased that our Department of Education and Early Childhood Development and our Department of Justice have really come up shining on this issue, at a time when really no other government has even addressed the issue. In fact, I've been told that the last Progressive Conservative government, the Minister of Education - who is now the member for Colchester North in the Liberal Party - was actually approached by one of our NDP members, the member for Halifax Atlantic. She was approached about the problem of bullying, but nothing was done about it, so I don't really understand why she is now speaking today and scornfully addressing us in this House over here and the Minister of Education and Early Childhood Development here for actually doing something. To me, that doesn't really make sense, Madam Speaker, so perhaps that's something she might want to talk about next time.</p>
<p>Also, there is no federal component for education, because of course education is covered by the provinces. So when somebody says, well, what have you done with the federal government, that actually is covered by the Department of Justice. In fact, our Minister of Justice just came back from Ottawa, where he had meetings about this very issue.</p>
<p>We've also heard that the Minister of Education and Early Childhood Development has had many meetings with the various ministers from around the country about this issue. She is, in fact, the chair of the CMEC, and bullying is very, very much on their agenda and is one of their number one priorities, which she spoke with them about as recently as last week. There are many phone calls going back and forth, Madam Speaker, and when they meet in person that is on the agenda.</p>
<p>We've already seen several changes in the Department of Education and Early Childhood Development with schools right across Nova Scotia. Every staff member, every bus driver, everybody, every E.A., every teacher, and all the principals now have to report all incidents of bullying, and the department has developed an actual software, Madam Speaker, that is already being used in order to report every incident so that at the end of the year, we'll be able to get a report about the bullying behaviour. All staff members have also been trained on how to report and what to report so that everybody is on the same page.</p>
<p>I think, Madam Speaker, this speaks volumes to what this government is doing. It's interesting to note that CTV has certainly noticed what we're doing, because in fact, last night it was quoted both by Lisa LaFlamme, and another reporter that, "Nova Scotia walked the walk today, they not only talked about the issue of Cyber-Bullying they've done something about it." I think that says a lot.</p>
<p>So, Madam Speaker, I have one last thing I'd like to mention about this issue before I sit down and that is that in Truro-Bible Hill, we did have a candlelight vigil for Amanda Todd, who was another innocent victim of bullying from British Columbia. And the reason that we had that candlelight vigil in Truro is because her aunt, Leana Todd, is a very good friend of mine, lives in Truro now, and she asked me to participate in that candlelight vigil, which she held in honour of her niece. Hundreds of people came, we spoke, we cried, we sang. My 12-year-old nephew, Aiden Zann-Roland, wrote a song called Ghost Before My Time with his aunt, with me, last summer at the cottage, and we performed that with his nine-year-old brother on drums. He played bass, I sang, I wrote the lyrics, he wrote the music, and his little sister, who is eight years old, and all her little girlfriends, got up dressed in pink with anti-bullying slogans saying, tell the haters that we don't hate, say no to haters, and they danced and sang and got the crowd jiving with them.</p>
<p>I'll tell you, Madam Speaker, there wasn't a dry eye in the park. With that, I want to say, let's say no to bullying; let's say no to bullying each other in this House, and adults, please, say no to bullying, and walk the walk instead of just talking the talk. Support the bill. Thank you very much.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Bedford-Birch Cove.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>MS. KELLY REGAN</from><p>Thank you, Madam Speaker. I do want to point out to the members opposite, that the Liberals will be supporting this bill. Any steps that make young people safer are positive. We are, however, disappointed that it took the government so long to act. And while we will be supporting this bill, it's taken far too long to see these changes come forward. We don't understand why the government didn't act on these recommendations when they came forward 14 months ago. In fact, the NDP voted down our amendments that would have given the then-cyberbullying bill some teeth. They took the conscious decision - they didn't just fail to act, they actually voted down amendments that would have strengthened that bill. That wasn't a sin of omission; that was a sin of commission. They decided to do that. And you have to ask yourself, how was that making life better or safer for Nova Scotian families?</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, too many young people have died. A week ago, actually just as I left this parking lot, I got a phone call from a mom - we had been going back and forth on e-mail, and I had given her my cell number - and I had a phone call from a mother whose daughter has been bullied at school. And that tells you that the bullying law that we had in place either is not effective or is not being applied. What has so disappointed this young woman who is being bullied is that the very people that she trusted to ensure her safety, to make sure she wasn't being bullied have let her down. I talked to her disappointed mum and she said we feel bullied again by a system that just hung us out to dry and didn't do anything.</p>
<p>At Law Amendments Committee we heard from the parents of bullied children. We heard from a mother who had lost her child due to bullying, and her comment - and I will reiterate it because my colleague, the member for Colchester North mentioned that after the NDP members in Law Amendments Committee voted down those amendments, she said I feel like I've been slapped in the face. And that's the way a lot of bullied kids and their families feel right now - they feel like they've been let down.</p>
<p>Don't get me wrong, they're happy to see this stuff coming forward, these bills, they're really pleased, as are we, but let's not forget we're in this position today because, as legislators, the important work that we're entrusted to do did not get done well enough.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="##member" status="undefined">
            <from>AN HON. MEMBER</from>
            <p>Come on.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728">
            <from>MS. REGAN</from>
            <p>I understand that the members opposite may not like that, but the fact of the matter is those members on the opposite side of the House voted down provisions that would have strengthened the anti-bullying law, that could have stopped this.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="##member" status="undefined">
            <from>AN HON. MEMBER</from>
            <p>That's a shame.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>MS. REGAN</from><p>It is a shame.</p>
<p>Professor Wayne MacKay's report recommended talking to the federal government. It was a suggestion that would have cost nothing, the price of a stamp, and yet we did not see a letter go to the government until this month. All that time past and it wasn't a priority &#x2026;</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="##member" status="undefined">
            <from>AN HON. MEMBER</from>
            <p>How long ago?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>MS. REGAN</from><p>Fourteen months - all that time, nothing was done. The government members could have allowed amendments that would have removed access to a Web site, they chose not to. Nova Scotians know that the NDP dropped the ball on this - and not because they just failed to act, they willfully decided not to take those amendments. They did these things even in the face of expert advice. You didn't have to listen to us, fine, but you could have listened to the experts who appeared before that committee who wrote the report. You had an option, you decided not to do it - that was the NDP's choice. They only decided to act when, as the Premier put it, we were embarrassed on an international stage.</p>
<p>This week in The ChronicleHerald, in the Editor's Note, was a piece entitled "Teach respect, I implore you as a rape survivor." I want to commend Doreen Coady for coming forward and publishing her report in the newspaper. She makes a couple of points that I thought were really key. She says: "As a youth, I was raped, I was drunk, and I was a virgin. I can speak for many friends who experienced their first sexual encounter the same way. The same problem existed over 20 years ago and is clearly still very prevalent." Then she goes to say later in the article: "There is no question in my mind that given today's prevalence of social media, and the increased comfort with sharing the details and visuals, I would have met the same fate as Rehtaeh when I was raped."</p>
<p>I would point out to the members opposite that Facebook was invented, or came into being, in 2005; Twitter was even later, and this has been an evolving issue. What has been an issue of communications one year is not the next year; it has changed. I think we all know kids who were bullied or we may have been bullied ourselves growing up. At least when you got in the door you didn't have to worry about a constant onslaught from social media. That has changed, that has evolved, and that has certainly been exacerbated over the past four years.</p>
<p>Proof of the effectiveness of this bill will be when we see action, when we see that kids actually get protected because let's face it, there are already laws against sexual assault, there are already laws against harassment, and yet that doesn't always protect our young people.</p>
<p>I do hope that at some point in this whole process that the kids who are bullied and their families are going to get an opportunity to have some input to the minister, whether it's through the task force or in some other form but I really do hope that there is some way they are going to get to say to the minister or her staff, what happened to them, how it felt, because I'm not sure we really understand the depth or breadth of it and what it does to a kid when their school year is ruined or their school life is ruined because someone at their school has decided to bully them.</p>
<p>I would hope that at some point we're going to take some of those advertising dollars that I spoke about yesterday and educate young people, and not-so-young people, about what constitutes consent. I believe that the vast majority of young people do not know what constitutes consent and they think that if you get another person drunk and you have sex with them, you have consent because they said yes. But they may not be able to actually consent and people need to know this, people need to stop and think about that.</p>
<p>I have found the last few weeks excruciating. I don't know what it has been like for other members, whether they've been contacted by people in their riding who are being bullied, who have been sexually assaulted, who have been through this kind of thing. It may just be because of my critic portfolio that I had more phone calls, but I have found it excruciating to listen to these stories over and over again. The worst part is that I sit here and I know that at least some of it might have been prevented or stopped, if we had acted sooner. That's what really bothers me.</p>
<p>There are names that are now forever etched in our memories, young people who should only have had their names etched in our memories because of their achievements, not because they died so young. So Jenna Bowers, Courtney Brown, Amanda Todd, Rehtaeh Parsons, we know their names, not because they got to do the great things they planned in life, we know their names because their lives were cut short because other people decided that they wanted to bully them. They may be our neighbours' kids, they may be our relatives, but there are just too many of them.</p>
<p>If there are kids out there today who happen to be listening to us, I want to tell you what a young woman who was bullied told me the other day. She said it gets better, you're going to get out of high school and you'll find out when you go on to post-secondary education that nobody cares what you're wearing, if you wear different clothes, if your hair is blue, if you have bad acne, whatever, nobody is going to care about that. What they are going to care about is, are you smart? Do you work hard? Do you do what you say you are going to do? Do you have a talent? It's going to completely change. The people who tormented you in public school, in high school, they're not going to be there. You're going to have a great life. Hang in there, get help, and it will get better. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Hants West.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7"><from>MR. CHUCK PORTER</from><p>Madam Speaker, I'm happy to take a few minutes this morning and offer a few comments on what I think is an important step in this Legislature and an important bill that has come forward. As most would know, this is something that has been on the minds of this caucus for some time. We've put legislation forward, as have others. It has taken a while to get where we are.</p>
<p>Okay, we are here. We have put something forward. We can be critical if we want to be. We all know, looking back, the unfortunate, very serious circumstances that go on every day. I have had calls in my office regarding this issue from people who don't even live in my constituency. That is not uncommon. I think they know that we, as legislators, are raising the issue. We've been talking about it, and of course it has been in the media.</p>
<p>When we have the circumstances where we have a case that we're all aware of - I always hate raising people's names in here, and I'm not going to, but where we have people who have taken their own lives in these circumstances have gone on for some time, I can tell you - thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Cape Breton West.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#e23caf06-dcf3-42a5-8a00-f4435df40350"><from>MR. ALFIE MACLEOD</from><p>Madam Speaker, I just wanted to say that when I listened to the minister introduce this bill this morning, it was probably one of the proudest moments for me to be in this House. I know that this bill isn't perfect, but I also know that it's way ahead of where we were yesterday. (Applause)</p>
<p>One of the jobs that we have as members of the Legislature is to give people hope, and I think today the minister, with this bill, is doing that. Each of us who are here should be proud of the fact that we are taking a non-partisan stand and doing something that will make a difference for the future of our province and our children.</p>
<p>Somebody once asked me why I ever got involved in politics, and I said I had three reasons, and those were my three children. That has increased. I now have four grandchildren, and if we in this House don't look after the future for those people - not just mine, but all of our families - then I think we have failed.</p>
<p>I think what we need to do here is look at each other and say, let's move on with this. It is a beginning; it is not the end. It is a place that will allow us, as a group, to make an improvement in the quality of life and help the families, who have been mentioned here by many others today.</p>
<p>I look forward to the opportunity of this bill going forward to the Committee on Law Amendments and for it to come back here with whatever changes that seem necessary, and am ready to move forward to make a difference. It's one of those bills that I hope we don't take a whole lot of time to get to where it needs to be, and that we all do what is right for the people of Nova Scotia, as they expect us to do. Thank you. (Applause)</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Cape Breton North.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Madam Speaker, as my two previous colleagues have echoed what we try to say on this side, we've all been hearing the situations that are going on in our province and throughout the country over the last number of months. It has only been a short time here for me, but I've heard and seen the effects that bullying and cyberbullying have had on people in my community and people within our province.</p>
<p>I know we have all introduced legislation and we have tried to make changes to legislation that has already been introduced. As two previous speakers, speakers before us have said, we're proud that this is a starting point; we hope it's not the end point because we know that this legislation is good legislation but it can be improved. We, on this side of the House, as well as, hopefully, anyone else on the other side of the House, are willing to put all our differences aside to make sure that we make this legislation the best we can and to protect everybody in society but especially the most vulnerable, our children, especially in situations where we know the technology - I'm not as technologically savvy as some of the people who may be here or some of our children are and I get a lot of help from my own children in doing this.</p>
<p>I just hope that we will work together to make this the best legislation we can, and if there are amendments to be made, that the government of the day will accept those amendments and if there are amendments they want to put in that we will accept their amendments and we will push to make sure that this becomes law as quickly as possible, to protect the most vulnerable in our society. Hopefully it will be adopted by other jurisdictions in the country, to protect every child in this country who may be touched by bullying or cyberbullying and to make sure that when a kid goes to school that they get to learn what they need to learn and now how to protect themselves. We have to do that protection for them. With that I will take my seat as well.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>If I recognize the minister it will be to close the debate.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister responsible for the Advisory Council on the Status of Women Act.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#5da6e0aa-9066-4b5c-8d26-9222b854db7e"><from>HON. MARILYN MORE</from><p>I rise to close debate on Bill No. 61 but I'd like to make a few comments first. I want to thank my honourable colleagues for their comments on this bill. I certainly appreciate how emotional the topic is because I think we all, while honouring the young people of our province, we are humans first and I think we put our children and our grandchildren's faces on this bill and we want to make it a safer place for them. (Applause)</p>
<p>This legislation will better protect youth and all Nova Scotians from cyberbullying and violence in this province and it gives out a strong, clear message to cyberbullies that they have to be accountable for their on-line actions. I want to set a little bit of context here. My caucus, my Cabinet, and the Premier of this province are fully in support of taking a broad-based approach to this, and I don't want to be seen as being defensive here, but quite frankly we have been working on a lot these issues behind the scenes for the past four years. I know, for example, two have us have been the Minister responsible for the Advisory Council on the Status of Women and have been working with our Atlantic colleagues on cyber-safe programs and have a Web site for young girls in Atlantic Canada.</p>
<p>It's an excellent Web site and the work has gone extremely well and I highly recommend it to everyone who wants to be better informed about how we can encourage and counsel our young people to better look after themselves and to know what the risks are. The point I'm trying to make is that there is a lot of work going on but I think this incident has driven us to fast-track that work and you'll be hearing more about those initiatives over the next few weeks.</p>
<p>As you recognize, this is a societal issue that has been around for generations. Violence against women has been happening for thousands of years but I think what we've seen is an awareness, a synergy, and a collective will that this time we are going to make things different. I am just so encouraged by the response from across Nova Scotia and the support within this Chamber. If there is any credit for this bill we will share it with you and all the civil servants who worked on this bill well into the night during this week. (Applause)</p>
<p>We recognize the research and effort and time you have spent on these issues as well. This bill has to be a joint effort, it really does. When it goes to the Law Amendments Committee, perhaps there are some improvements, but we have to get started. We have to send a strong signal out to Nova Scotians that the Legislature of Nova Scotia is taking this seriously, and that we will do everything in our power to make this a safer Nova Scotia for all residents, especially our young.</p>
<p>I do want to reassure you that the balance of the recommendations from the Task Force on Bullying and Cyberbullying are under active consideration. They are being looked at in terms of implementing them. So it's like major initiatives everywhere: you do your short-term, your medium-term, and your long-term implementation, and that's exactly what is happening here.</p>
<p>I am so pleased to be working more closely with Wayne MacKay, but I have to assure you that the Department of Education and Early Childhood Development and the other departments that would have been impacted by those recommendations have been actively working on them over the past 14 months, I think someone said. So we are going to fast-track that.</p>
<p>Are we doing enough? Probably not. Are there gaps? Yes, and we're going to be looking at those. This is a real opportunity for everyone in Nova Scotia, at all levels of government, across community and government, to do a better job - not to be protecting our own particular mission or turf, but to look at new ways of relating to one another, working together.</p>
<p>I have been blessed over the last two weeks to meet with groups of people. I met with youth; I met with the district health authority CEOs; I met with the superintendents. I was able to speak to a number of municipal, recreational, and volunteer leaders, and without a doubt, every single person is onside. We have to take that renewed commitment, that energy, and move it into something that is going to improve our province. The momentum is there, the will is there, and I know it's going to make a difference.</p>
<p>I just want to commit that we will continue to work in partnership with you, with our community groups, across all departments of government. Our response to this has to be a multi-faceted approach. This legislation is just one small piece - it may be significant, but it is one small piece of what we need to be doing together.</p>
<p>I just want to finish off by saying that I think what has come out of all of this is that we want a more respectful and a more caring province. I know it starts with me, it starts with us, it starts with all Nova Scotians to put more energy, time, and priority on making our communities as safe as possible. Everyone in this province, but especially our young, deserves to work, learn, live, and play safely. I know you are all onboard, and I really appreciate that. With those comments, Madam Speaker, I will close debate and thank everyone sincerely. (Applause)</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for second reading of Bill No. 61. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill be referred to the Committee on Law Amendments.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Halifax Chebucto on an introduction.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#c64a6bcf-fabd-4b08-bd04-ecd0fc310c2e">
            <from>MR. HOWARD EPSTEIN</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, thank you very much. For the second time today I am happy to welcome a class from St. Catherine's School to observe us at our work in the Legislature - another Grade 3 class, this time Madame LeBlanc's class. The students are also Grade 3 students. They are accompanied, I believe, by Kevin Zwicker, Tayla Paul, and Mr. Carvery. We have at least 16 of the students, I counted, sitting in the gallery. I would ask members to join me in welcoming these students to observe our proceedings. (Applause)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>We welcome all of our guests to today's proceedings.</p>
<p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#c7f2d366-8ba0-4263-98e0-bdaa9336415f">
            <from>MR. CLARRIE MACKINNON</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 51.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 51 - Financial Measures (2013) Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Minister of Finance.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Madam Speaker, I move that Bill No. 51, the Financial Measures (2013) Act be read a second time.</p>
<p>As we all know, this bill is the Act that makes measures, introduced in the budget that passed earlier in the week, it brings them into force, ensuring the success of our financial plan. Budget 2013 represents a significant achievement for our government and, most importantly, for all Nova Scotians. We made a commitment to balance the budget and we did it.</p>
<p>Each year since coming into office my colleague, the member for Halifax Fairview, former Minister of Finance, stood here before this House to introduce the Financial Measures Act and each time he reminded us all of the path to balance that we were on. In the fourth year of this plan, I'm pleased that I'm able to introduce, and have introduced, the Financial Measures (2013) Bill and to demonstrate that the strategic choices that have been made were strategic choices about making life more affordable, creating good jobs and growing the economy, and helping to make life better for families in all parts of our province.</p>
<p>Balancing the budget isn't solely based on finances, it's also about creating balance within our province. I know just how hard Nova Scotians work to make life better for their families and loved ones. Over the last four years our government has made changes to help make life more affordable for families, for individuals, and for seniors. We have taken the provincial portion of the HST off basic electricity and home heat, and off children's diapers, children's clothing, children's footwear, as well as feminine hygiene products.</p>
<p>We have increased the maximum HST rebate for first-time homebuyers and we have kept rebates in place for new vehicles for the physically impaired, for computers for the visually and hearing impaired and mentally and physically challenged, as well as equipment used for municipal firefighting and volunteer fire departments. Essential items are just that - essential. These rebates help make sure Nova Scotians can keep the heat on and afford to buy the things they and their families need to live.</p>
<p>This year's Financial Measures (2013) Bill therefore includes a provincial referendum, which will now be required to ask for approval from a majority of Nova Scotians before the provincial portion of the HST can be added back to these essential items. We have heard from Nova Scotians that these exemptions from the provincial portion of the HST have made a difference, they have helped people make ends meet. We think it's very important that these items stay exempted. We also strongly believe that Nova Scotians should have their say in any future action that could alter or eliminate these actions. This change gives more of a say to each and every Nova Scotian, in the everyday costs that affect their lives.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, there are other important changes in this year's Financial Measures (2013) Bill. Our government listened to Nova Scotians when they said exemptions on the provincial portion of the HST for essential items make a real difference. We also listened to the concerns of the business community. We heard small business owners when they said that lower tax rates would help them thrive and we took action. We reduced the income tax for the majority of small businesses to historic lows.</p>
<p>Changes to the FMA follow through on our commitment to reduce the rate of corporate income tax for small businesses. For the fourth year in a row, this rate will fall by 0.5 per cent to 3.0 per cent, starting in January 2014. Over four years we have lowered the small business tax by two percentage points. This has meant almost $78 million in savings for small businesses, savings that can be reinvested to compete, to grow their business and to hire new employees. This year's reduction brings the tax rate for small business to the lowest it has been in more than 20 years.</p>
<p>The FMA will also lower the small business limit threshold to $350,000 - 93 per cent of small businesses are not impacted by the threshold change and they will save $26 million in 2013-14 and more than $33 million per year when the rate reduction is fully implemented.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, the Corporation Capital Tax Act is also being updated to clarify language. The amendments will clarify items that corporations must include in taxable capital. They will also clarify that the province does not pay interest on overpayments of corporate capital tax. These housekeeping changes will make the intent clearer and bring wording in line with current accounting standards and the practices of other jurisdictions, particularly the federal jurisdiction.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, this year's FMA is also important to low-income seniors. Amendments to the Income Tax Act will give more low-income seniors tax relief. Since the 2010 tax year, many low-income seniors, receiving the Guaranteed Income Supplement, benefited from not having to pay provincial income tax. This put an average of $450 per year back into the hands of 17,000 seniors who needed it most.</p>
<p>This year we are introducing a new provincial age-amount tax credit and it will do two very important things: first, this new tax credit will increase the number of low-income seniors who do not pay any provincial tax to 25,000 from 17,000; second, 4,000 more low-income seniors will see a portion of their provincial income tax returned to them. In total, Madam Speaker, 29,000 seniors will receive income tax relief. This means a great deal when your income is fixed.</p>
<p>On April 1<sup>st</sup> a new non-profit corporation took over responsibility for pension and investment administration for all Public Service Superannuation Plans. This was the culmination of several years of work, under this government, to modernize how the province's largest public pension plan is governed. Directors representing employers, employees, and retirees now have responsibility for the plan. The plan is now in line with Canada's leading pension plans, and the plan is more secure over the long term. To ensure that retired employees are represented by a member reflecting their interests, the FMA will make changes to the Nova Scotia Pension Services Corporation Act. These amendments will put the Nova Scotia Government Retired Employees Association in the position to choose their own representative on the trustee board.</p>
<p>As we have already announced, Madam Speaker, most provincial user fees will increase to match the provincial consumer price index. No one likes when the price of something goes up. But the increase is needed to maintain the current level of services that Nova Scotians have come to depend on. This adjustment will be reflected in the respective Acts.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, finally, as you know, the tobacco tax has increased for all tobacco products: cigarettes, each gram of fine-cut tobacco, pre-proportioned tobacco sticks, and all other forms of tobacco. This change, the first in four years, will be reflected in amendments to the Revenue Act. Our government wants to help Nova Scotians stop smoking, or even better, to never start. Research shows that higher tobacco prices act as a deterrent, particularly for youth. In other words, higher taxes equal lower consumption. This increase will generate $18.1 million that the province can use to support services that matter most to Nova Scotians, including better care sooner, high-quality education for children, and opportunities to create good-paying jobs.</p>
<p>A portion of the revenue from the tobacco tax increase will be directed into our comprehensive tobacco control strategy. Our total investment in smoking cessation in 2013 will almost double to $1 million. This will benefit Nova Scotians and help relieve pressure on our health care system. So with those few words regarding the Financial Measures (2013) Bill, I have already moved second reading of Bill No. 51 and, Madam Speaker, I would move that we adjourn debate on this.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that we adjourn debate on Bill No. 51. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#c7f2d366-8ba0-4263-98e0-bdaa9336415f"><from>MR. CLARRIE MACKINNON</from><p>Madam Speaker, that concludes the government's business for the day. I move that the House do now rise, to meet again on Monday, April 29<sup>th</sup>, at 4:00 p.m., with the House hours to be from 4:00 p.m. to 10:00 p.m. Following the daily routine we will call Public Bills for Second Reading, Bill No. 51 and Bill No. 62, and we will also call, if time permits, Address in Reply to the Speech from the Throne.</p>
<p>Thank you very much, Madam Speaker.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is to adjourn.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>I hope that you all have an enjoyable weekend and that you take the time to re-energize yourself, and we'll meet again on Monday for some good parliamentary debate.</p></speech>
          <narrative>
            <p>The House rose at 11:46 a.m.</p>
          </narrative>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION UNDER RULE 32(3)</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="856">RESOLUTION NO. 856</num>
          <speech by="ce90163b-7a3b-4884-b7d9-b5ca06af4cc3"><from>Mr. Gary Burrill</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Upper Musquodoboit Consolidated School (UMCS) was founded in 1963, merging its predecessor Caribou, Chaplin, Dean Settlement, Greenwood, Henry, Hutchinson, and Pleasant Valley Schools; and</p>
<p>Whereas UMCS demonstrates exemplary levels of parent and volunteer involvement and serves as a model of the kind of school community connection that is widely recognized as integral to a quality education; and</p>
<p>Whereas the people of the Upper Musquodoboit Consolidated School district are gathering May 8, 2013, to celebrate a half century of excellence in elementary education;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the Nova Scotia House of Assembly extend its warm congratulations to the students, staff, and volunteers of Upper Musquodoboit Consolidated School on the occasion of UMCS's 50<sup>th</sup> Anniversary, and affirm the continuing contributions of Upper Musquodoboit "Small School, Big Spirit" consolidated school.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="857">RESOLUTION NO. 857</num>
          <speech by="4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>Hon. Jamie Baillie</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Frank William Nichols of North Kentville dedicated nearly 50 years of his life to the democratic process as a passionate campaigner and party organizer for the PC Party; and</p>
<p>Whereas he was honoured as Kings North PC Volunteer of the Year this past February at the AGM; and</p>
<p>Whereas Frank worked hard every day of his life and was so deserving of his successes, and he will be sadly missed;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly send condolences to the family and friends of Frank William Nichols, and honour him for his contributions to his community.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="858">RESOLUTION NO. 858</num>
          <speech by="4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>Hon. Jamie Baillie</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Joan Jones, a lifelong resident of Parrsboro, recently passed away; and</p>
<p>Whereas Joan was an energizing force, serving as town councillor, Main Street coordinator, and on a variety of boards, including the Parrsboro and District Board of Trade and Ships' Company Theatre; and</p>
<p>Whereas her storefront has remained a part of the downtown for more than 35 years, serving generations, and she worked tirelessly to keep the downtown thriving and full of opportunity;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly send condolences and best wishes to the family of Joan Jones, an exemplary Parrsboro businesswoman and a model of community spirit and dedication.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="859">RESOLUTION NO. 859</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Sherry Martell has worked with TC MEDIA for more than 10 years as a reporter for the Truro Daily News and The News, based in New Glasgow, and has served as editor of the Colchester Weekly News since May, 2011; and</p>
<p>Whereas Martell has been nominated by Newspapers Atlantic for an award at the 2013 Newspapers Atlantic Better Newspapers Competition; and</p>
<p>Whereas Martell's entry in the best feature photo category was of a breast cancer survivor who bared her mastectomy scars, as well as 53 other women from across Canada, in a book titled <i>Breast Stories; Cancer Survivors Speak Out</i>;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Sherry Martell for being nominated for this prestigious award, which is to be announced at the Newspapers Atlantic 41<sup>st</sup> Annual Conference in Halifax, and wish her success with the nomination and continued success with her career.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="860">RESOLUTION NO. 860</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas 53-year-old Wanda Parker of North River, Colchester North, has been giving blood to the Canadian Red Cross blood donor clinics since she was a teenager; and</p>
<p>Whereas Parker, who began donating because her father always did, now donates blood four times a year between the Truro and Bible Hill clinics; and</p>
<p>Whereas Parker has received special recognition certificates for her 35<sup>th</sup> and 50<sup>th</sup> donations and on Monday, March 18<sup>th</sup> she reached a special milestone when she donated blood for the 100<sup>th</sup> time;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Wanda Parker who has consistently worked to benefit others by giving the gift of life 100 times, and express our admiration and thanks for her commitment to helping others.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="861">RESOLUTION NO. 861</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Sugar Moon Farm in Earltown, Colchester North, is noted locally and provincially for its delicious pancakes; and</p>
<p>Whereas Sugar Moon approximates that they make 40,000 pancakes annually; and</p>
<p>Whereas owners Quita Gray and Scott Whitelaw have kept their recipe a guarded secret, it is now available for everyone to try, but not everyone has the special cooking skill;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Sugar Moon Farm for being listed as one of the 10 best spots for pancakes in Canada by <i>Canadian Living Magazine.</i></p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="862">RESOLUTION NO. 862</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 29<sup>th</sup> Annual Truro Sport Heritage Society Awards were presented on February 28, 2013; and</p>
<p>Whereas Roger Bastarache from Valley, Colchester North, received the very prestigious honour of being named coach of the year; and</p>
<p>Whereas Bastarache's team, the Ecole Acadienne de Truro girls volleyball team, had only 20 eligible girls to draw from, yet posted a perfect season on their way to taking regional and district titles and won gold at the Jeux de l'Acadie Atlantic finals;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly commend Roger Bastarache for his outstanding coaching skills and congratulate him for being named the Truro Sport Heritage Society Coach of the Year.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="863">RESOLUTION NO. 863</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the North Shore Recreation Centre is to receive $47,108 to be put towards a new baseball field and to assist with upgrades, the Fraser Cultural Centre is to receive $20,000 from Canada's Community Infrastructure Fund; and</p>
<p>Whereas Canada's Community Infrastructure Fund, which is designed to help improve already existing community buildings, arenas and cultural centres, operates on a cost-share basis so the community must raise 50 per cent of the needed funds; and</p>
<p>Whereas to fulfill the recipients' share requirement, the Municipality of the County of Colchester contributed $40,000 to the projects and the rest of the money was acquired through fundraising;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the North Shore Recreation Centre and the Fraser Cultural Centre in Tatamagouche, Colchester North, for receiving money from Canada's Community Infrastructure Fund and for raising the money to fulfill their portion of the joint projects.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="864">RESOLUTION NO. 864</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 29<sup>th</sup> Annual Truro Sport Heritage Society Awards were presented on February 28, 2013; and</p>
<p>Whereas Kayla Gallagher, from the Truro Lions Club throwing team, was named female athlete of the year in the 16 to 20-year-old category; and</p>
<p>Whereas Kayla, who was named Cobequid Educational Centre Female Athlete of the Year in 2012, is now attending the University of Lethbridge;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate this exceptional young athlete for the numerous awards she has received and wish her success with her future athletic and educational endeavours.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="865">RESOLUTION NO. 865</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Eileen Eaton has been a member of the Great Village Garden Club, Colchester North, for 50-plus years; and</p>
<p>Whereas Eileen has held all the executive positions of the club, assisted with their many plant sales and shows, and helped to orchestrate many of their other activities and functions; and</p>
<p>Whereas in December, 2012, Eileen was presented with the Nova Scotia Association of Garden Clubs Outstanding Member Award;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Eileen Eaton on receiving this special award and thank her for the contribution she has made to the club, to her community and to the many aspiring gardeners she has helped throughout the years.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="866">RESOLUTION NO. 866</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas 30-year-old Brad MacCallum of Upper Onslow, Colchester North, has been an umpire for the past seven seasons; and</p>
<p>Whereas in 2012 MacCallum worked at the International Softball Challenge in Montreal, the peewee provincial championship in Stewiacke, and the Under-18 Canadian championship in Montreal; and</p>
<p>Whereas in 2012 while in Montreal, MacCallum also received his Level 4 certification;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Brad MacCallum for being named Umpire of the Year for 2012 by Softball Nova Scotia's Umpires Association.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="867">RESOLUTION NO. 867</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas 13-year-old Noah Patriquin from Debert, Colchester North, had a fourth- and a third-place finish at this year's Atlantic Cup Cadet Biathlon provincials at Martock, Hants County; and</p>
<p>Whereas in only his second year in the sport, Noah earned a spot as a junior competitor at Cadet Biathlon Nationals in Valcartier, Quebec; and</p>
<p>Whereas Noah identified his weaker skill and spent extra time on his shooting, since speed and precision marksmanship are necessities for competition;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Noah Patriquin, a relative newcomer to the sport, who, in competition with athletes from all across Canada, finished in the top 10 at the Cadet Biathlon Nationals in Quebec, placing ninth in the mass start competition and eighth in the pursuit race.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="868">RESOLUTION NO. 868</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Debbie Lewis was overweight, depressed, and on a number of medications when she decided to join the TOPS (Take Off Pounds Sensibly) N.S. Portaupique Chapter, Colchester North; and</p>
<p>Whereas Lewis said the group provided support, encouragement, information on nutrition, exercise, and a healthier lifestyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas combined with group support, good eating habits, and daily exercise Lewis lost over 100 pounds and is free of pills, with one exception;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Debbie Lewis for receiving a certificate of accomplishment from Leader Rilla MacDougall of TOPS N.S. 5261, and for successfully achieving such a personal goal.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="869">RESOLUTION NO. 869</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Five Islands Bazaar was formed 20 years ago by the people from the community who wanted a venue to sell their assorted crafts; and</p>
<p>Whereas for the past two years the Bazaar has sponsored a community event where many of its members, as well as other volunteers from the community, spent two full weeks making baby quilts from cutting and sewing fabric pieces to quilting and binding the finished product; and</p>
<p>Whereas last year these talented ladies made and donated 50 quilts to the IWK Children's Hospital, and this year increased the number to 55;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the ladies of the community of Five Islands, Colchester North, who volunteer their time and effort for such a worthy cause, and express our thanks on behalf of all those children who benefit from their generous gifts.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="870">RESOLUTION NO. 870</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving other rural Nova Scotians; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills, and time, they often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas an annual banquet is held as a way to thank these dedicated volunteers, and to present special awards for years of service and for outstanding contributions;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ian Jennings, a junior member who just turned 19 and became a full member of the Debert Volunteer Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his Five Year Service Award, and commend him for his commitment to serving others.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="871">RESOLUTION NO. 871</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving other rural Nova Scotians; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills, and time, they often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas an annual banquet is held as a way to thank these dedicated volunteers, and to present special awards for years of service and for outstanding contributions;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Trevor Lockhart of the Debert Volunteer Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his Ten Year Service Award, and commend him for his commitment to serving others.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="872">RESOLUTION NO. 872</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving other rural Nova Scotians; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills, and time, they often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas an annual banquet is held as a way to thank these dedicated volunteers, and to present special awards for years of service and for outstanding contributions;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Shane Slack of the Debert Volunteer Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his Twenty-five Year Service Award, and commend him for his commitment to serving others.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="873">RESOLUTION NO. 873</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving other rural Nova Scotians; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills, and time, they often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas an annual banquet is held as a way to thank these dedicated volunteers, and to present special awards for years of service and for outstanding contributions;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Kevin Totten of the Debert Volunteer Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his Twenty-five Year Service Award, and commend him for his commitment to serving others.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="874">RESOLUTION NO. 874</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving other rural Nova Scotians; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills, and time, they often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas an annual banquet is held as a way to thank these dedicated volunteers, and to present special awards for years of service and for outstanding contributions;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Randy Barnhill of the Debert Volunteer Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his Thirty Year Service Award, and commend him for his commitment to serving others.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="875">RESOLUTION NO. 875</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving other rural Nova Scotians; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills, and time, they often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas an annual banquet is held as a way to thank these dedicated volunteers, and to present special awards for years of service and for outstanding contributions;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Brandon Slack of the Debert Volunteer Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving the Wendell Barnhill Most Improved Firefighter Award, and the award for Firefighter of the Year for 2012, and commend him for his commitment to serving others.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="876">RESOLUTION NO. 876</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving other rural Nova Scotians; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills, and time, they often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas an annual banquet is held as a way to thank these dedicated volunteers, and to present special awards for years of service and for outstanding contributions;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Don Geldart of the Debert Volunteer Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving the award for Fire Officer of the Year for 2012, and commend him for his commitment to serving others.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="877">RESOLUTION NO. 877</num>
          <speech by="5c3f8e78-5002-4c61-9c57-730090867f1b"><from>Wayne Gaudet</from><p>Monsieur le Pr&#xE9;sident, par le pr&#xE9;sente, j'avise que je proposerai &#xE0; une date ult&#xE9;rieure, l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu que l'Association Madeleine-LeBlanc est membre de la F&#xE9;d&#xE9;ration des femmes acadiennes da la Nouvelle-&#xC9;cosse; et</p>
<p>Attendu que l'Association Madeleine-LeBlanc regroupe des femmes de la r&#xE9;gion de Clare pour la promotion de la femme et du patrimoine acadien de la r&#xE9;gion; et</p>
<p>Attendu que l'Association Madeleine-LeBlanc f&#xEA;te son 30 &#x364; anniversaire;</p>
<p>Qu'il soit r&#xE9;solu que cette Assembl&#xE9;e offre ses meilleurs v&#x153;ux &#xE0; l'Association Madeleine-LeBlanc et leur souhait plein succ&#xE8;s pour les ann&#xE9;es &#xE0; venir.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="878">RESOLUTION NO. 878</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "a new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. Leshan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on January 25, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Trina and Chris Adams welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Trina and Chris on this miraculous event in their lives and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="879">RESOLUTION NO. 879</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "a new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. Leshan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on February 7, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Ren&#xE9;e Surette and John Malone welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ren&#xE9;e and John on this miraculous event in their lives and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="880">RESOLUTION NO. 880</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "a new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. Leshan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on January 11, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Raegan Tracey Belliveau welcomed her daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Raegan on this miraculous event in her life and wish her many more happy years as a parent.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="881">RESOLUTION NO. 881</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "a new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. Leshan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on February 7, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Jeanette and Joshua Thompson welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jeanette and Joshua on this miraculous event in their lives and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="882">RESOLUTION NO. 882</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "a new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. Leshan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on December 31, 2012, a very special occasion took place when Jill and Adam Aldred welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jill and Adam on this miraculous event in their lives and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="883">RESOLUTION NO. 883</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "a new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. Leshan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on February 18, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Justine and Gilles d'Entremont welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Justine and Gilles on this miraculous event in their lives and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="884">RESOLUTION NO. 884</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "a new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. Leshan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on February 14, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Melissa and Derek Amirault welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Melissa and Derek on this miraculous event in their lives and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="885">RESOLUTION NO. 885</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "a new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. Leshan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on February 19, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Paula and Mark Hatfield welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Paula and Mark on this miraculous event in their lives and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="886">RESOLUTION NO. 886</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "a new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. Leshan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 3, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Ren&#xE9;e Corporon LeBlanc and Graham Spinney welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ren&#xE9;e and Graham on this miraculous event in their lives and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="887">RESOLUTION NO. 887</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 39<sup>th</sup> National Volunteer Week runs from April 21 to 27, 2013, under the theme, Volunteers: Passion. Action. Impact.; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 26, Club Acadien in Ste. Anne du Ruisseau will host the Annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Argyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the 21 volunteers to be honoured is Hector Babin, posthumously, of Ste. Anne du Ruisseau who, throughout his life, devoted so much time and tireless effort to so many organizations in and around the community, in particular his passion for his local fire department;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly pay tribute to Hector Babin, celebrate his memory, and honour his life.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="888">RESOLUTION NO. 888</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 39<sup>th</sup> National Volunteer Week runs from April 21-27, 2013, under the theme, Volunteers: Passion. Action. Impact.; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 26, Club Acadien in Ste. Anne du Ruisseau will host the Annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Argyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the 21 volunteers to be honoured is Angela Spinney, of Pubnico, a youth volunteer representing &#xC9;cole secondaire de Par-en-Bas, for her devotion of time and tireless effort to her school and many other organizations in and around the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Angela Spinney on being honoured by the Municipality of Argyle, thank her and all volunteers for their dedication to others, and wish her continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="889">RESOLUTION NO. 889</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 39<sup>th</sup> National Volunteer Week runs from April 21 to 27, 2013, under the theme, Volunteers: Passion. Action. Impact.; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 26, Club Acadien in Ste. Anne du Ruisseau will host the Annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Argyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the 21 volunteers to be honoured is Cerena Amirault, of Middle West Pubnico, for her devotion of time and tireless effort to her school and many organizations in and around the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Cerena Amirault on being honoured by the Municipality of Argyle, thank her and all volunteers for their dedication to others, and wish her continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="890">RESOLUTION NO. 890</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 39<sup>th</sup> National Volunteer Week runs from April 21 to 27, 2013, under the theme, Volunteers: Passion. Action. Impact.; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 26, Club Acadien in Ste. Anne du Ruisseau will host the Annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Argyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the 21 volunteers to be honoured is Charles Campbell, of Surette's Island, for his devotion of time and tireless effort to so many organizations in and around the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Charles Campbell on being honoured by the Municipality of Argyle, thank him and all volunteers for their dedication to others, and wish him continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="891">RESOLUTION NO. 891</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 39<sup>th</sup> National Volunteer Week runs from April 21 to 27, 2013, under the theme, Volunteers: Passion. Action. Impact.; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 26, Club Acadien in Ste. Anne du Ruisseau will host the Annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Argyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the 21 volunteers to be honoured is David Meuse, of Comeau's Hill, for his devotion of time and tireless effort to so many organizations in and around the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate David Meuse on being honoured by the Municipality of Argyle, thank him and all volunteers for their dedication to others, and wish him continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="892">RESOLUTION NO. 892</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 39<sup>th</sup> National Volunteer Week runs from April 21 to 27, 201, under the theme, Volunteers: Passion. Action. Impact.; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 26, Club Acadien in Ste. Anne du Ruisseau will host the Annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Argyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the 21 volunteers to be honoured is Dianne Crowell, of Argyle Head, for her devotion of time and tireless effort to her school and many organizations in and around the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Dianne Crowell on being honoured by the Municipality of Argyle, thank her and all volunteers for their dedication to others, and wish her continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="893">RESOLUTION NO. 893</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 39<sup>th</sup> National Volunteer Week runs from April 21 to 27, 2013, under the theme, Volunteers: Passion. Action. Impact.; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 26, Club Acadien in Ste. Anne du Ruisseau will host the Annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Argyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the 21 volunteers to be honoured is Ella Muise, of Ste. Anne du Ruisseau, for her devotion of time and tireless effort so many organizations in and around the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ella Muise on being honoured by the Municipality of Argyle, thank her and all volunteers for their dedication to others, and wish her continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="894">RESOLUTION NO. 894</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 39<sup>th</sup> National Volunteer Week runs from April 21 to 27, 2013, under the theme, Volunteers: Passion. Action. Impact.; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 26, Club Acadien in Ste. Anne du Ruisseau will host the Annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Argyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the 21 volunteers to be honoured is Gary Dulong, of East Pubnico, for his devotion of time and tireless effort to so many organizations in and around the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Gary Dulong on being honoured by the Municipality of Argyle, thank him and all volunteers for their dedication to others, and wish him continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="895">RESOLUTION NO. 895</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 39<sup>th</sup> National Volunteer Week runs from April 21 to 27, 2013, under the theme, Volunteers: Passion. Action. Impact.; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 26, Club Acadien in Ste. Anne du Ruisseau will host the Annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Argyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the 21 volunteers to be honoured is Gwen LeBlanc, of Wedgeport, for her devotion of time and tireless effort to so many organizations in and around the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Gwen LeBlanc on being honoured by the Municipality of Argyle, thank her and all volunteers for their dedication to others, and wish her continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="896">RESOLUTION NO. 896</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 39<sup>th</sup> National Volunteer Week runs from April 21 to 27, 2013, under the theme, Volunteers: Passion. Action. Impact.; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 26, Club Acadien in Ste. Anne du Ruisseau will host the Annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Argyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the 21 volunteers to be honoured is Jennifer Gates, of Kemptville, for her devotion of time and tireless effort so many organizations in and around the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jennifer Gates on being honoured by the Municipality of Argyle, thank her and all volunteers for their dedication to others, and wish her continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="897">RESOLUTION NO. 897</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 39<sup>th</sup> National Volunteer Week runs from April 21 to 27, 2013, under the theme, Volunteers: Passion. Action. Impact.; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 26<sup>th</sup>, Club Acadien in Ste. Anne du Ruisseau will host the annual volunteer banquet for the Municipality of Argyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the 21 volunteers to be honoured is Marjorie Parker, of Kemptville, for her devotion of time and tireless effort to so many organizations in and around the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Marjorie Parker on being honoured by the Municipality of Argyle, and thank her and all volunteers for their dedication to others, and wish her continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="898">RESOLUTION NO. 898</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 39<sup>th</sup> National Volunteer Week runs from April 21 to 27, 2013, under the theme, Volunteers: Passion. Action. Impact.; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 26<sup>th</sup>, Club Acadien in Ste. Anne du Ruisseau will host the annual volunteer banquet for the Municipality of Argyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the 21 volunteers to be honoured is Nadine DeViller, of Plymouth, for her devotion of time and tireless effort to so many organizations in and around the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Nadine DeViller on being honoured by the Municipality of Argyle, and thank her and all volunteers for their dedication to others, and wish her continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="899">RESOLUTION NO. 899</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 39<sup>th</sup> National Volunteer Week runs from April 21 to 27, 2013, under the theme, Volunteers: Passion. Action. Impact.; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 26<sup>th</sup>, Club Acadien in Ste. Anne du Ruisseau will host the annual volunteer banquet for the Municipality of Argyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the 21 volunteers to be honoured is Romayne Swim, of Glenwood, for her devotion of time and tireless effort to so many organizations in and around the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Romayne Swim on being honoured by the Municipality of Argyle, and thank her and all volunteers for their dedication to others, and wish her continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="900">RESOLUTION NO. 900</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 39<sup>th</sup> National Volunteer Week runs from April 21 to 27, 2013, under the theme, Volunteers: Passion. Action. Impact.; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 26<sup>th</sup>, Club Acadien in Ste. Anne du Ruisseau will host the annual volunteer banquet for the Municipality of Argyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the 21 volunteers to be honoured is Sandra d'Entremont, of West Pubnico, for her devotion of time and tireless effort to so many organizations in and around the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Sandra d'Entremont on being honoured by the Municipality of Argyle, and thank her and all volunteers for their dedication to others, and wish her continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="901">RESOLUTION NO. 901</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 39<sup>th</sup> National Volunteer Week runs from April 21 to 27, 2013, under the theme, Volunteers: Passion. Action. Impact.; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 26<sup>th</sup>, Club Acadien in Ste. Anne du Ruisseau will host the annual volunteer banquet for the Municipality of Argyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the 21 volunteers to be honoured are husband and wife Marilyn and Stillman Muise for their devotion of time and tireless effort to so many organizations in and around the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Marilyn and Stillman Muise on being honoured by the Municipality of Argyle, and thank them and all volunteers for their dedication to others, and wish them continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="902">RESOLUTION NO. 902</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 39<sup>th</sup> National Volunteer Week runs from April 21 to 27, 2013, under the theme, Volunteers: Passion. Action. Impact.; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 26<sup>th</sup>, Club Acadien in Ste. Anne du Ruisseau will host the annual volunteer banquet for the Municipality of Argyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the 21 volunteers to be honoured is Tanya DeViller, of Wedgeport, for her devotion of time and tireless effort to so many organizations in and around the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Tanya DeViller on being honoured by the Municipality of Argyle, and thank her and all volunteers for their dedication to others, and wish her continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="903">RESOLUTION NO. 903</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 39<sup>th</sup> National Volunteer Week runs from April 21 to 27, 2013, under the theme, Volunteers: Passion. Action. Impact. and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 26<sup>th</sup>, Club Acadien in Ste. Anne du Ruisseau will host the annual volunteer banquet for the Municipality of Argyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the 21 volunteers to be honoured is Valerie Belliveau, of East Pubnico, for her devotion of time and tireless effort to so many organizations in and around the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Valerie Belliveau on being honoured by the Municipality of Argyle, and thank her and all volunteers for their dedication to others, and wish her continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="904">RESOLUTION NO. 904</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 39<sup>th</sup> National Volunteer Week runs from April 21 to 27, 2013, under the theme, Volunteers: Passion. Action. Impact.; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 26<sup>th</sup>, Club Acadien in Ste. Anne du Ruisseau will host the annual volunteer banquet for the Municipality of Argyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the 21 volunteers to be honoured is Terri Amirault of East Pubnico, a youth volunteer representing Drumlin Heights Consolidated School, for her devotion of time and tireless effort to so many organizations in and around the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Terri Amirault on being honoured by the Municipality of Argyle, and thank her and all volunteers for their dedication to others, and wish her continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="905">RESOLUTION NO. 905</num>
          <speech by="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 39<sup>th</sup> National Volunteer Week runs from April 21 to 27, 2013, under the theme, Volunteers: Passion. Action. Impact.; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 26<sup>th</sup>, Club Acadien in Ste. Anne du Ruisseau will host the annual volunteer banquet for the Municipality of Argyle; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the 21 volunteers to be honoured is Carmella Surette, of Amirault's Hill, for her devotion of time and tireless effort to so many organizations in and around the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Carmella Surette on being honoured by the Municipality of Argyle, and thank her and all volunteers for their dedication to others, and wish her continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="906">RESOLUTION NO. 906</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 9, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 150, where Maurice James Drysdale of Arichat was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Maurice Drysdale for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="907">RESOLUTION NO. 907</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 9, 2013, a ceremony was held at St. Anne's Community and Nursing Care Centre, where Lawrence Daniel Landry of Arichat was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Lawrence Landry for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="908">RESOLUTION NO. 908</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 9, 2013, a ceremony was held at St. Anne's Community and Nursing Care Centre, where Lawrence Archibald Campbell of Arichat was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Lawrence Campbell for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="909">RESOLUTION NO. 909</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 9, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 150, where Dominique Alcide Landry of Petit de Grat was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Alcide Landry for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="910">RESOLUTION NO. 910</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 9, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 150, where Andrew Madden was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Andrew Madden for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="911">RESOLUTION NO. 911</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 9, 2013, a ceremony was held at St. Anne's Community and Nursing Care Centre, where Stanley Leonard Boudreau of Arichat was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Stanley Boudreau for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="912">RESOLUTION NO. 912</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 9, 2013, a ceremony was held at St. Anne's Community and Nursing Care Centre, where Robert Douglas Nicholl of Arichat was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Robert Nicholl for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="913">RESOLUTION NO. 913</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 9, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 150, where Douglas Charles Forgeron was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Douglas Charles Forgeron for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="914">RESOLUTION NO. 914</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 9, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 150, where Charles James Landry of Arichat was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Charles Landry for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="915">RESOLUTION NO. 915</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 9, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 150, where Lorenzo Louis Boudreau of Arichat was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Lorenzo Boudreau for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="916">RESOLUTION NO. 916</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 9, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 150, where Frederick James Martel of Little Anse was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Frederick Martel for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="917">RESOLUTION NO. 917</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 9, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 150, where Francis Joseph Martel of Arichat was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Francis Martel for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="918">RESOLUTION NO. 918</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 9, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 150, where Harold Joseph Martell of Petit de Grat was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Harold Martell for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="919">RESOLUTION NO. 919</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 9, 2013, a ceremony was held at the St. Anne's Community and Nursing Care Centre, where James John Tyrrell of Arichat was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate James Tyrrell for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="920">RESOLUTION NO. 920</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 9, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 150, where Helen Kehoe of Rocky Bay was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Helen Kehoe for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank her for her dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="921">RESOLUTION NO. 921</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 9, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 150, where Elias Amedee Gaudet of Poulamon was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Elias Gaudet for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="922">RESOLUTION NO. 922</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 9, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 150, where Joseph Leonard Marchand of Arichat was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Leonard Marchand for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="923">RESOLUTION NO. 923</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where William G. MacRae of Louisdale, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate William G. MacRae for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="924">RESOLUTION NO. 924</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Arnold H. Chamberlain of West Bay, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Arnold H. Chamberlain for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="925">RESOLUTION NO. 925</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Alex Morrison of St. Peter's, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Alex Morrison for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="926">RESOLUTION NO. 926</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Arthur R. Goyetche of Sydney, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Arthur R. Goyetche for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="927">RESOLUTION NO. 927</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Arthur E. Bouchard of River Bourgeois, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Arthur E. Bouchard for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="928">RESOLUTION NO. 928</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Charles E. Kyte of St. Peter's, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Charles E. Kyte for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="929">RESOLUTION NO. 929</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Charles A. Williamson of River Bourgeois, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Charles A. Williamson for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="930">RESOLUTION NO. 930</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Clarence Richard of River Bourgeois, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Clarence Richard for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="931">RESOLUTION NO. 931</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Creighton R. Leonard of West Bay, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Creighton R. Leonard for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="932">RESOLUTION NO. 932</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Donald G. Cornell of Louisdale, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Donald G. Cornell for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="933">RESOLUTION NO. 933</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Albenie A. Boudreau of Louisdale, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Albenie A. Boudreau for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="934">RESOLUTION NO. 934</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Donald M. Henri of Louisdale, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Donald M. Henri for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="935">RESOLUTION NO. 935</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Earl C. Martell of St. Peter's, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Earl C. Martell for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="936">RESOLUTION NO. 936</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Herman J. MacDonald of St. Peter's, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Herman J. MacDonald for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="937">RESOLUTION NO. 937</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where George W. McPhee of Louisdale, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate George W. McPhee for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="938">RESOLUTION NO. 938</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Jack L. O'Brien of West Bay, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Jack L. O'Brien for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="939">RESOLUTION NO. 939</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where James E. W. Bowden of Louisdale, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate James E. W. Bowden for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="940">RESOLUTION NO. 940</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Joseph M. Landry of River Bourgeois, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Joseph M. Landry for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="941">RESOLUTION NO. 941</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where John E. Hillier of Louisdale, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate John E. Hillier for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="942">RESOLUTION NO. 942</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Donald M. Hiltz, of St. Peter's, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Donald M. Hiltz for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="943">RESOLUTION NO. 943</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Kenneth W. Pringle of West Bay, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Kenneth W. Pringle for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="944">RESOLUTION NO. 944</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Lawrence D. Whitty of St. Peter's, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Lawrence D. Whitty for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="945">RESOLUTION NO. 945</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Lawrence J. Burke of River Bourgeois, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Lawrence J. Burke for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="946">RESOLUTION NO. 946</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Paul C. Martell of River Bourgeois, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Paul C. Martell for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="947">RESOLUTION NO. 947</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Melvin Landry of Louisdale, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Melvin Landry for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="948">RESOLUTION NO. 948</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Joseph M. Sutherland of St. Peter's, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Joseph M. Sutherland for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="949">RESOLUTION NO. 949</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Sidney E. Hardiman of St. Peter's, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Sidney E. Hardiman for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="950">RESOLUTION NO. 950</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Trevor Boudreau of St. Peter's, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Trevor Boudreau for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="951">RESOLUTION NO. 951</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Sonya L. Hayter of River Bourgeois, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Sonya L. Hayer for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank her for her dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="952">RESOLUTION NO. 952</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Vincent H. DeWolfe of St. Peter's, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Vincent H. DeWolfe for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="953">RESOLUTION NO. 953</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Wesley A. Peeples of Grand Anse, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Wesley A. Peeples for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="954">RESOLUTION NO. 954</num>
          <speech by="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee is a time to honour Her Majesty's 60 years of service and dedication to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal is a way to recognize veterans for their past service to our country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on April 20, 2013, a ceremony was held at the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 in St. Peter's, where Wilfred A. Barrette of L'Ardoise, Richmond County, was awarded the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Honorary Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate Wilfred A. Barrette for receiving this exceptional medal, and thank him for his dedication to our country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
