<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.michel.p.samson" showAs="HON. MICHEL SAMSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="980981f9-4823-4d4b-8134-a47d4ecf5405" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.denise.peterson.rafuse" showAs="HON. DENISE PETERSON-RAFUSE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="2c4ef79f-acb1-4c92-8ff4-e6bfac04ddc0" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.karla.macfarlane" showAs="MS. KARLA MACFARLANE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="81ace0ab-54e7-4b6d-8d48-6d416fbcd939" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.gordie.gosse" showAs="MR. GORDON GOSSE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="32a29c39-915c-40e7-b749-7c09299ed1f7" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.david.allan.wilson" showAs="HON. DAVID WILSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.diana.whalen" showAs="HON. DIANA WHALEN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.maureen.macdonald" showAs="HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MR. SPEAKER"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 31 March 2014</docTitle>
      <docNumber>14-17</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2014-03-31">Monday, March 31, 2014</docDate>
      <docProponent>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docProponent>
      <legislature value="62">62nd General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="1">1st Session</session>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>Order, please. We'll now proceed with the daily routine.</p>
      </speech>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PRESENTING AND READING PETITIONS</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PRESENTING REPORTS OF COMMITTEES</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>TABLING REPORTS, REGULATIONS AND OTHER PAPERS</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Finance and Treasury Board.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="800">RESOLUTION NO. 800</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>HON. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall:</p>
<p>(1) read and table the message from His Honour the Lieutenant Governor transmitting the Estimates of Sums required for the service of the province for the fiscal year ending March 31, 2015, for the consideration of this House;</p>
<p>(2) table the Estimates Books;</p>
<p>(3) table the Crown Corporation business plans;</p>
<p>(4) table the Estimates and Crown Corporation business plans resolutions;</p>
<p>(5) deliver my Budget Speech; and</p>
<p>(6) move that the Estimates of Sums required for the service of the province, for the fiscal year ending March 31, 2015, being Supply to be granted to Her Majesty, and the Crown Corporation business plans be referred to the Committee of the Whole House on Supply.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, for the information of the House, the budget will be presented on April 3<sup>rd</sup>.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>[The notice is tabled.]</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Labour and Advanced Education.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>INTRODUCTION OF BILLS</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 37 - Entitled an Act to Ensure the Provision of Essential Health and Community Services. (Hon. Kelly Regan)</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 38 - Entitled an Act to Require Balanced Budgets, Limit Government Spending and Reduce the Harmonized Sales Tax to Thirteen Per Cent. (Mr. Tim Houston)</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Ordered that these bills be read a second time on a future day.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Pictou West.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="801">RESOLUTION NO. 801</num>
          <speech by="#2c4ef79f-acb1-4c92-8ff4-e6bfac04ddc0"><from>MS. KARLA MACFARLANE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Boat Harbour is an environmental disaster that should be cleaned up; and</p>
<p>Whereas a previous Liberal Government relieved mill owners of responsibility for cleaning up Boat Harbour, making the environmental problems worse; and</p>
<p>Whereas the previous Liberal Government made a deal with the mill owners to put the cleanup costs squarely on the backs of taxpayers;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly demand the Liberal Government get on with cleaning up Boat Harbour.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the New Democratic Party.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="802">RESOLUTION NO. 802</num>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas behind every successful MLA is a hard-working constituency assistant; and</p>
<p>Whereas constituency assistants are multi-tasking caseworkers, advocates, information officers, office administrators, computer geniuses, and event planners; and</p>
<p>Whereas Bill Matheson will retire today, after working for 11.5 years as the constituency assistant to the MLA for Halifax Needham;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the Nova Scotia Legislature thank Bill Matheson for his many years of service and extend best wishes for a well-deserved retirement.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Sackville-Cobequid.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="803">RESOLUTION NO. 803</num>
          <speech by="#32a29c39-915c-40e7-b749-7c09299ed1f7"><from>HON. DAVID WILSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas successive Liberal and Conservative governments have reduced the federal government's share of funding from 50 per cent to 18 per cent over the last number of decades; and</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia will receive $902 million less in health care transfers from Ottawa over the next 10 years, which could mean the closure of hospital beds, the loss of nursing positions and less joint replacement operations;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House send a clear message to the federal Conservative government to negotiate a new health accord that will see an investment in our health care system, instead of cuts that could see significant reduction in health care for Nova Scotians.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Sydney-Whitney Pier.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="804">RESOLUTION NO. 804</num>
          <speech by="#81ace0ab-54e7-4b6d-8d48-6d416fbcd939"><from>MR. GORDON GOSSE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Alison Keough recently made her mark in Cape Breton University history; and</p>
<p>Whereas Alison Keough won the Kathy Shields Award as Canadian University Sport rookie of the year, the first Cape Breton University women's basketball player to win a national award; and</p>
<p>Whereas Alison Keough was also selected to the Canadian intercollegiate sport all-rookie team, as well as being selected a second team all-star, named to the all-rookie team and rookie of the year in Atlantic University Sport;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the Nova Scotia Legislature congratulate Alison Keough on her outstanding scholastic achievement, and wish her continued success.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Chester-St. Margaret's.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="805">RESOLUTION NO. 805</num>
          <speech by="#980981f9-4823-4d4b-8134-a47d4ecf5405"><from>HON. DENISE PETERSON-RAFUSE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Gerri Allen, resident of Chester, Nova Scotia, has been a community volunteer for over 20 years; and</p>
<p>Whereas Gerri Allen has dedicated herself to the betterment of the Village of Chester and its residents through volunteering for such causes as Shoreham Village Relay for Life as well as many others; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mrs. Allen has received the Queen's Diamond Jubilee Medal for her volunteer service;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the Nova Scotia Legislature congratulate Gerri Allen for her commitment to service through volunteering and for her significant contribution to her community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>ORDERS OF THE DAY</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT BUSINESS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be">
          <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, with the consent of the House I would move the House recess for a period of one hour, until 8:15 p.m., when we will reconvene. During that time we will have an opportunity to brief the Opposition on the legislation which was tabled this evening. I would so move.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>The House will now recess until 8:15 p.m.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>7:14 p.m. The House recessed.</p>
        </narrative>
        <narrative>
          <p>8:16 p.m. The House reconvened.</p>
        </narrative>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be">
          <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, following the briefing that we are able to provide, there is opportunity now for the Opposition caucuses to discuss the legislation, but in order to provide more ample time I would ask for the consent of the House to extend the recess until 8:45 p.m., when we will resume at that point in time and provide an update.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The request by the Government House Leader is to extend the recess until 8:45 p.m.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>The House stands recessed until 8:45 p.m.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>8:17 p.m. The House recessed.</p>
        </narrative>
        <narrative>
          <p>8:45 p.m. The House reconvened.</p>
        </narrative>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Order, please.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be">
          <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, as you know, we introduced Bill No. 37 at the start of the session. I would ask for the unanimous consent of the House to have this bill added to tonight's order paper so that second reading of this bill can take place immediately this evening.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for unanimous consent. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The request has been tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, in light of the decision by the Opposition to not allow this bill to be debated this evening and in light of the emergency nature of this matter, with potential labour disruption taking place as early as tomorrow morning, I wish to advise that the government will be calling the hours for tomorrow: starting at 12:01 a.m. and the House will continue until 11:59 p.m. During that time we will start with the daily routine at 12:01 a.m., followed by Oral Questions Put By Members. Following that, we will call for Government Business, Bill No. 37, to start second reading on that piece of legislation.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I also wish to advise that the Law Amendments Committee will meet immediately following the passage of Bill No. 37 from second reading. At this point in time we have instructed Legislative Counsel to start booking presentations at the Law Amendments Committee, beginning at 8:30 a.m. tomorrow morning. We will have the Law Amendments Committee meet at that time or following the completion of second reading of Bill No. 37.</p>
<p>With that, Mr. Speaker, I would move that the House do now rise to meet tomorrow, April 1<sup>st</sup>, at 12:01 a.m.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the House rise to meet again tomorrow, Tuesday, April 1<sup>st</sup>, at 12:01 a.m., until 11:59 p.m.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>We stand adjourned until 12:01 a.m. tomorrow.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>The House rose at 8:48 p.m.</p>
        </narrative>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION UNDER RULE 32(3)</heading>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
