<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="81ace0ab-54e7-4b6d-8d48-6d416fbcd939" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.gordie.gosse" showAs="MR. GORDIE GOSSE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="aef785d7-7697-4453-8f9c-eef26e4928c3" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.keith.colwell" showAs="Hon. Keith Colwell"/>
        <TLCPerson id="71280477-3de0-4cef-90bd-e23864226ad3" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.patrick.dunn" showAs="Hon. Pat Dunn"/>
        <TLCPerson id="af446054-6fe0-422a-94d6-7cdff4623b7e" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.joanne.bernard" showAs="MS. BERNARD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.maureen.macdonald" showAs="MS. MACDONALD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="5dac0dde-7ef3-4f75-a137-834785ff1ae4" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.tim.houston" showAs="MR. HOUSTON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="34c1e608-d873-4164-95f2-86ccabbc60e9" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.terry.farrell" showAs="MR. TERRY FARRELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="c9bfa1a9-47ac-4d47-b492-7496e858718c" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.stephen.gough" showAs="MR. STEPHEN GOUGH"/>
        <TLCPerson id="0206420c-7710-4c22-9cee-dc3d70a99352" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.suzanne.lohnes.croft" showAs="MS. SUZANNE LOHNES-CROFT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.eddie.orrell" showAs="MR. EDDIE ORRELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="e23caf06-dcf3-42a5-8a00-f4435df40350" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.alfie.macleod" showAs="MR. ALFIE MACLEOD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="32a29c39-915c-40e7-b749-7c09299ed1f7" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.david.allan.wilson" showAs="HON. DAVID WILSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.diana.whalen" showAs="HON. DIANA WHALEN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.karen.casey" showAs="MS. CASEY"/>
        <TLCPerson id="6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.allan.gerard.macmaster" showAs="MR. ALLAN MACMASTER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.kelly.regan" showAs="HON. KELLY REGAN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.margaret.miller" showAs="Ms. Margaret Miller"/>
        <TLCPerson id="15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.leo.glavine" showAs="HON. LEO GLAVINE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="2c8e1a56-2f9d-4156-a91f-77802701e3d3" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.geoff.maclellan" showAs="HON. GEOFF MACLELLAN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="bc54523e-7553-4c28-b315-79d18165339b" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.john.a.lohr" showAs="MR. JOHN LOHR"/>
        <TLCPerson id="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.christopher.a.dentremont" showAs="HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="578ba1c9-5f6c-4b7b-a5cd-b915e1801c37" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.lena.m.diab" showAs="HON. LENA DIAB"/>
        <TLCPerson id="ac013fcf-fe88-4578-8a8e-9f7973ddac75" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.brendan.o.maguire" showAs="MR. BRENDAN MAGUIRE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="2c4ef79f-acb1-4c92-8ff4-e6bfac04ddc0" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.karla.macfarlane" showAs="MS. KARLA MACFARLANE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="1e5b7bdc-363b-4df4-8258-edcf8f2bf7fb" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.andrew.younger" showAs="Hon. Andrew Younger"/>
        <TLCPerson id="4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.jamie.baillie" showAs="MR. BAILLIE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="97532239-d15e-407a-8c67-706ed1bbc595" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.keith.irving" showAs="MR. KEITH IRVING"/>
        <TLCPerson id="fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.stephen.mcneil" showAs="HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.frank.corbett" showAs="HON. FRANK CORBETT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="e32945dc-539b-44e0-9a14-ec06f74edd6a" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.labi.kousoulis" showAs="HON. LABI KOUSOULIS"/>
        <TLCPerson id="bf8b9586-8d64-4f8f-b12a-88dfc38ac185" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.lloyd.hines" showAs="MR. LLOYD HINES"/>
        <TLCPerson id="980981f9-4823-4d4b-8134-a47d4ecf5405" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.denise.peterson.rafuse" showAs="HON. DENISE PETERSON-RAFUSE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.chuck.porter" showAs="Mr. Chuck Porter"/>
        <TLCPerson id="d20d446c-118f-4445-81f4-cf995b335391" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.randy.delorey" showAs="Hon. Randy Delorey"/>
        <TLCPerson id="c479d7de-83a6-47c7-a045-07816407bdb3" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.lenore.zann" showAs="MS. LENORE ZANN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="16a35513-2bff-496f-85bc-9a815574e9ba" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.bill.horne" showAs="MR. BILL HORNE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="eb42d545-c815-47c5-a60b-237f29603d3e" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.patricia.arab" showAs="MS. PATRICIA ARAB"/>
        <TLCPerson id="0f46e5e4-b06b-4b91-9e3a-5bd1cd63809d" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.larry.harrison" showAs="MR. LARRY HARRISON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="16c306ab-30c7-40a9-8c13-d2d2aafda27d" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.allan.rowe" showAs="MR. ALLAN ROWE"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MR. SPEAKER"/>
        <TLCRole id="premier" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.premier" showAs="THE PREMIER"/>
        <TLCRole id="clerk" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.clerk" showAs="THE CLERK"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 15 April 2014</docTitle>
      <docNumber>14-28</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2014-04-15">Tuesday, April 15, 2014</docDate>
      <docProponent>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docProponent>
      <legislature value="62">62nd General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="1">1st Session</session>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Order please. We will now begin the daily routine.</p>
<p>I would draw your attention to the top of your daily order papers. Make note that this will be the last day that all of the resolutions will be listed on the order paper. We're going to make a change with that so that only the new resolutions on a daily basis from the last day or two will be included on the order papers. If you want a record of it please refer to Hansard or keep the order paper from today in your desk.</p></speech>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PRESENTING AND READING PETITIONS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Inverness.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff">
          <from>MR. ALLAN MACMASTER</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, I beg leave to table a petition. It contains 1,528 signatures, including my own. This petition calls on the government, "&#x2026; to partner with our local health foundation to immediately purchase and operate a CT Scan for the Inverness Consolidated Memorial Hospital (ICMH)."</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The petition is tabled.</p>
<p>Before we move on to the order of business, Presenting Reports of Committees, I'd like to do an introduction from the Speaker's Chair. We have special guests in the Speaker's Gallery. Many of the members had occasion over last night and this morning to meet with Wendell Hannaford, director and Earl Eisenhart, Canada-U.S. Relations and Policy consultant, visiting us from the Eastern Regional Conference of the Council of State Governments.</p>
<p>Mr. Hannaford and Mr. Eisenhart are touring the Maritime Provinces over the next couple of days to discuss our relationship with the Eastern Regional Conference and we were pleased to introduce them to a number of members of this House last night and this morning. We hope to further develop our relationship and enjoy productive sessions with them this summer in Baltimore. Please extend to them a warm welcome in the Speaker's Gallery. (Applause)</p></speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PRESENTING REPORTS OF COMMITTEES</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>TABLING REPORTS, REGULATIONS AND OTHER PAPERS</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>STATEMENTS BY MINISTERS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of the Public Service Commission.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#e32945dc-539b-44e0-9a14-ec06f74edd6a"><from>HON. LABI KOUSOULIS</from><p>Mr. Speaker, today I want to share with you the government's commitment to mental health in the Public Service. Did you know that according to the Mental Health Commission of Canada, in any given year one in five working Canadians experienced mental health challenges or illness?</p>
<p>To take that a little further, data suggests there are significant direct and indirect costs associated with not providing a psychologically healthy workplace. Unhealthy workplaces can lead to distress for employees, high rates of absenteeism, lost productivity and employee turnover. This also impacts the families and communities in which they live.</p>
<p>As an employer, the government cares a great deal about creating a safe and supportive workplace for its employees and is making a significant investment to help promote and protect the psychological health and well-being of employees.</p>
<p>In 2013, the Mental Health Commission of Canada developed a voluntary psychological health and safety standard for mental health and safety. This standard is designed to create a culture of continuous improvement around mental health and ensure that we have the processes in place that are responsive to the needs of workers. The Province of Nova Scotia is the first provincial government in Canada to participate in the adoption of this national psychological health and safety standard. The pillars of the standard are: prevention of harm, promotion of health, and the resolution of concerns.</p>
<p>Today I am pleased to share with you that the province has been selected to participate in a three-year, case-study, research project with the Mental Health Commission of Canada, to examine best practices and identify areas of improvement regarding the implementation of the national standard for psychological health and safety in the workplace.</p>
<p>Over the next several months, we will be looking for ways to reduce the negative stigma around mental health and examine ways to create and promote healthy work environments within our Public Service. In addition to some of our current policies, like Respectful Workplace and Occupational Health and Safety, we know the psychological health and safety standards will help strengthen and supplement our workplace safety.</p>
<p>So what does this mean? We will utilize the psychological health and safety standard as our minimum standard. There is a cost of doing nothing. There are growing implications of doing nothing, as well as an indication that without the preventive practices, we will experience an increase in absences. The standard will make a difference. Departments will look to fostering respectful relationships among the organization, its management, its workers and worker representatives, which includes maintaining the confidentiality of sensitive information; and departments will consider organizational decision-making, implications on mental health, and benefits. We will see an increase in the amount of training that provincial employees receive about mental health and how they can become more aware.</p>
<p>As a result of adopting the standard, we should see measurable improvements in the following: employee health, overall workplace psychological safety, enhanced organizational effectiveness as a result of better overall productivity, a decrease in costs related to ill health, and an overall enhancement of the service provided to the public.</p>
<p>This is an important initiative for the province as an employer. Please join in helping to make the Nova Scotia Government a great place to work: a place where we promote good mental health and improve overall mental health in the workplace, as well as reduce the mental health stigma, workplace absences, disability claims, and lost productivity. I am very pleased that the province is participating in this important initiative, and look forward to sharing our progress with you. Thank you.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Northside-Westmount.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>I want to thank the minister for providing us with a copy of his statement earlier today. On behalf of the Progressive Conservative caucus, I am very pleased to see that Nova Scotia is becoming a leader in this area. After all, the Mental Health Foundation of Nova Scotia tells us that mental illness directly affects all Canadians at some time, through a family member, friend, or colleague.</p>
<p>By providing support to members of the Public Service who are experiencing mental health challenges, we are building a stronger province. It is in everybody's interest to create healthy, supportive workplaces in our Public Service, to decrease the negative impacts on families and on our government offices. Helping to decrease the stigma associated with mental illness will hopefully encourage all Nova Scotians to seek help if they need it.</p>
<p>As the minister pointed out, our province was the first in the country to adopt a national psychological health safety standard. That ensures that a process is in place to support workers who may be struggling with mental health issues and that as a province we prevent harm, promote health, and resolve concerns in the workplace.</p>
<p>It is encouraging that Nova Scotia has been chosen to participate in the case study research project with the Mental Health Commission of Canada. With this study we can only build on the strong foundation that already exists. Over the coming months, I know we will all watch with interest as change begins to take hold in the Public Service, and as we move toward making government a place where we promote good mental health and improve overall mental health in the workplace, and reduce mental health stigma, workplace absences, disability claims, and lost productivity. As the minister rightly says, the cost of doing nothing is simply too high. Thank you.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Cape Breton Centre.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23"><from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from><p>I want to thank the minister for supplying us with an advance copy of his statement. I share the views of both him and the previous speaker. You know, Mr. Speaker, this is an interesting topic. There is probably not one of us in this Legislature that hasn't at some time been asked to participate in a fundraiser for a community member, a family member, anybody even remotely close to us, if there is an illness, whether it's cancer or issues like that. The communities are so great to get behind and support these worthwhile causes.</p>
<p>The one cause that doesn't seem to get that kind of oomph, if you will, is mental illness. We really don't want to talk about it. We want to support it, but it's almost one of the last taboos, that mental health is not a real issue to some people. But what started here today, and with the previous government, about recognition - it goes a long way. I mean, in this province, I think it's today we have Clara Hughes cycling across the country in support of mental health awareness, and that's what it is. We've got to get this terrible disease out and shine the proper light on it, Mr. Speaker.</p>
<p>One of the best employers, I believe, to do this through is our Public Service sector. It is just by virtue - it's in the public. People will know when people aren't there, and they miss time and so on. People say, well, why is so-and-so not at work? Oh, well, it's a family issue. If it was a broken leg, we'd say a broken leg, but for some reason the mental health side of it is one we really don't want to talk about.</p>
<p>I commend the minister for this statement today. I think it's incumbent on each and every one of us in this House, whether it's in the public sector unions or public sector employees, or in the private sector, that we all be champions of the mental health well-being of all of our constituents.</p>
<p>This is a first step, a very good first step, and I want to thank the minister, I want to thank the previous speaker, and now it's onward to fight this terrible disease.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Before we move on to the next agenda item, I would be remiss if I did not read the subject for late debate this evening, which I forgot to do, as submitted by the honourable member for Sydney River-Mira-Louisbourg:</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly urge the Liberal Government to recognize the excellent services provided by Roots for Youth Society and to provide the organization with funding to ensure Pictou County youth who are homeless get the support they need.</p>
<p>This will be debated this evening at 6:00 p.m.</p></speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Finance and Treasury Board.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2">
          <from>HON. DIANA WHALEN</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, before I introduce a bill I would like your permission to do an introduction, as well, in the east gallery.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>Permission granted.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2">
          <from>MS. WHALEN</from>
          <p>If I could draw the attention of the members to the east gallery, where we're visited today by someone who has been here before, Ross Harrington, a constituent of mine and also a business owner - he owns Wine Kitz in Clayton Park West - and also Steven Haynes and Mark Haynes who own Noble Grape in the province. I ask you to stand and receive the warm welcome of the House. (Applause)</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>INTRODUCTION OF BILLS</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 52 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 260 of the Revised Statutes of 1989. The Liquor Control Act. (Hon. Diana Whalen)</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 53 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 31 of the Acts of 2004. The Police Act, Respecting the Serious Incident Response Team. (Hon. Lena Diab)</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 54 - Entitled an Act to Maintain and Preserve Voluntary Blood Donations in Nova Scotia. (Hon. David Wilson)</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Ordered that these bills be read a second time on a future day.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1130">RESOLUTION NO. 1130</num>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Dr. John Hamm will receive the highly distinguished honorary Doctor of Civil Law degree from the University of Kings College during their ceremony on May 15<sup>th</sup>; and</p>
<p>Whereas Dr. Hamm will be recognized for his service to Nova Scotia as a trusted family physician, community volunteer, recipient of the Order of Nova Scotia and, of course, our province's 25<sup>th</sup> Premier; and</p>
<p>Whereas under Dr. Hamm's leadership our province made significant improvements to health care and education, all while maintaining balanced provincial budgets;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House recognize Dr. Hamm's significant contributions to his community and province, and congratulate him for receiving this prestigious honour.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the New Democratic Party.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1131">RESOLUTION NO. 1131</num>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Evan Brown is a playwright, designer, and performer who has worked on such innovative plays as <i>Instrumental Windows</i>,<i> Litmus Road</i>, and <i>Phaedra's Bed</i>; and</p>
<p>Whereas Evan Brown serves as the artistic director of the Us vs. Them Theatre Cooperative in the north end of Halifax; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 24, 2014, Evan Brown received the Robert Merritt Mayor's Award for Emerging Theatre Artist, which recognizes the outstanding talent of an emerging theatre artist who is a resident of the Halifax Regional Municipality;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the Nova Scotia House of Assembly congratulate Evan Brown on being chosen as the 2014 winner of the Robert Merritt Mayor's Award for Emerging Theatre Artist, and express its appreciation for his contribution and commitment to Halifax and its theatre community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Community Services.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#af446054-6fe0-422a-94d6-7cdff4623b7e">
            <from>HON. JOANNE BERNARD</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I'd like to make an introduction, if I could.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Permission granted.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#af446054-6fe0-422a-94d6-7cdff4623b7e">
            <from>MS. BERNARD</from>
            <p>If you'd look to the east gallery, Krista Alford and her daughter Emily. Both are extraordinarily dedicated volunteers, both to their community and to different causes. Emily, who is nine years old, has worked on many political campaigns, including mine and various other members of the House. They are constituents of Stephen Gough and I would like the House to be able &#x2026;</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Order, please. I would just remind the honourable minister to refer to the other honourable member by his riding name.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#af446054-6fe0-422a-94d6-7cdff4623b7e">
            <from>MS. BERNARD</from>
            <p>&#x2026; the honourable member for Sackville-Beaver Bank - and I would like the warm welcome of the House, please. (Applause)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Argyle-Barrington.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1132">RESOLUTION NO. 1132</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas today marks the anniversary of the tragic sinking of the <i>RMS Titanic</i> more than a century ago; and</p>
<p>Whereas in the early hours of April 15<sup>th</sup>, the once named "unsinkable ship" collided with an iceberg and sank to the ocean floor; and</p>
<p>Whereas more than 1,500 lives were lost that tragic night, many of which were laid to rest here in Halifax cemeteries;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly remember the lives lost on the <i>RMS Titanic</i> and commend those who have worked to preserve this part of our history.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Sackville-Cobequid.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1133">RESOLUTION NO. 1133</num>
          <speech by="#32a29c39-915c-40e7-b749-7c09299ed1f7"><from>HON. DAVID WILSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Gord Dwyer who is originally from Lower Sackville, Nova Scotia, is looking forward to the start of the 2014 NHL Playoffs; and</p>
<p>Whereas Gord began his referee career many years ago as an amateur, and a highlight was the chance to referee the championship game of the World Under-17 Tournament in 2001; and</p>
<p>Whereas Gord joined the NHL Officials Association in 2003, has refereed over 497 regular season NHL games, and for the first time Gord will officiate during the first round of the 2014 NHL playoffs;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the Nova Scotia Legislature congratulate Lower Sackville's Gord Dwyer for his career as an NHL referee and for being selected to officiate during the first round of the 2014 NHL playoffs, and wish him continued success in the future.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Health and Wellness.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1134">RESOLUTION NO. 1134</num>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048"><from>HON. LEO GLAVINE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas reflexology is a professional therapy that uses the application of precise pressure to reflex areas on the feet to stimulate the body's natural healing abilities to treat symptoms of illness and injury; and</p>
<p>Whereas the week of April 13<sup>th</sup> to 19<sup>th</sup> is Reflexology Therapy Week in Nova Scotia, a time to recognize reflexologists and reflexology therapy as a healing art and science; and</p>
<p>Whereas reflexology therapy is a simple yet effective way of providing quality health care that works well with other medical therapies and is a safe way to restore order and health to the body;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize Reflexology Therapy Week in Nova Scotia and the services and benefits that reflexology therapists provide to Nova Scotians.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Sydney River-Mira-Louisbourg.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1135">RESOLUTION NO. 1135</num>
          <speech by="#e23caf06-dcf3-42a5-8a00-f4435df40350"><from>MR. ALFIE MACLEOD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the WW Louis Memorial Library in Louisbourg is celebrating its 50<sup>th</sup> Anniversary on April 22, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas the WW Louis Memorial Library is one of the mainstays in the community of Louisburg and surrounding areas; and</p>
<p>Whereas the WW Louis Memorial Library plays a very important role in the community of Louisburg as people gather regularly to exchange their many publications and is also a place to meet new people on a regular basis;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the WW Louis Memorial Library and its staff for continuing to serve their community at this vital landmark.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Sydney-Whitney Pier.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1136">RESOLUTION NO. 1136</num>
          <speech by="#81ace0ab-54e7-4b6d-8d48-6d416fbcd939"><from>MR. GORDIE GOSSE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on May 3, 2014, the 587 Whitney Pier Royal Canadian Air Cadet Squadron will hold their 60<sup>th</sup> Anniversary Alumni Dinner and Dance; and</p>
<p>Whereas approximately 300 current and former cadets and staff members are planning to attend; and</p>
<p>Whereas this reunion promises to be a most memorable event;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the Nova Scotia Legislature congratulate the 587 Whitney Pier Royal Canadian Air Cadet Squadron on their 60<sup>th</sup> Anniversary and wish them all the best in their future endeavours.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Hants East.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1137">RESOLUTION NO. 1137</num>
          <speech by="#0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de"><from>MS. MARGARET MILLER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Maxime St. Pierre and Scott Brison, Member of Parliament for Kings-Hants, welcomed their daughters Claire and Rose to the world on February 21, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas there is nothing more beautiful than the birth of a child, and double that joy with twins; and</p>
<p>Whereas the pleasures of parenthood will stay with Scott and Maxime as they watch in splendour as their daughters grow through every stage of life;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate Scott Brison and Maxime St. Pierre on the birth of their daughters Claire and Rose Brison-St. Pierre.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Inverness.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1138">RESOLUTION NO. 1138</num>
          <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff"><from>MR. ALLAN MACMASTER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas SkySquirrel Technologies is a company dedicated to the development and production of lightweight aerial search and rescue drones; and</p>
<p>Whereas SkySquirrel recently relocated their research and development operations to Inverness County; and</p>
<p>Whereas SkySquirrel is currently expanding its personnel with hopes of perfecting an increase in production of their already functional unmanned drone;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Tim Stekkinger, Richard van der Put and St&#xE9;phane Sogne for their entrepreneurial spirit and wish them well as they build the technology of the future.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Chester-St. Margaret's.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1139">RESOLUTION NO. 1139</num>
          <speech by="#980981f9-4823-4d4b-8134-a47d4ecf5405"><from>HON. DENISE PETERSON-RAFUSE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Andrea Redmond, a local artist with a studio located in Seabright, Nova Scotia, organized and curated an art show and silent auction for the students of East St. Margaret's Elementary School; and</p>
<p>Whereas the silent auction will see 50 per cent of the proceeds going directly to the school and each student will donate 50 per cent of the proceeds from their own artwork to one of the following organizations: a place of worship in the area, Animal Rescue Coalition, St. Margaret's Bay Stewardship Association, St. Margaret's Bay Skate Park Project and St. Margaret's Bay Food Bank; and</p>
<p>Whereas all of the students' artwork was showcased at Rhubarb Restaurant in Indian Harbour during the month of March;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the Nova Scotia Legislature congratulate Andrea Redmond on her contribution to the success of the show and silent auction and wish the students of East St. Margaret's Elementary School much success with the unique fundraising project.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Dartmouth South.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1140">RESOLUTION NO. 1140</num>
          <speech by="#16c306ab-30c7-40a9-8c13-d2d2aafda27d"><from>MR. ALLAN ROWE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Destination Imagination is a non-profit organization that inspires students to become global leaders and innovators by challenging competing teams to use creative process and collaborative problem-solving skills; and</p>
<p>Whereas a team of six ninth-graders at Bicentennial Junior High School, called Advanced Skyhawks, placed first in the Destination Imagination regional tournament for their successful construction of a project using materials like wood, glue, fishing wire and which needed to weigh less than 40 grams, withstand two types of tension, and which could hold as much weight as possible; and</p>
<p>Whereas Advanced Skyhawks, a team of promising engineers and carpenters, have qualified to attend the Destination Imagination Global Finals in Knoxville, Tennessee, along with 1,300 other top scoring teams;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating the Advanced Skyhawks of Bicentennial School for their regional tournament win and wish them every success as they represent all future global leaders from our region at the Global Finals in Tennessee.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Northside-Westmount.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1141">RESOLUTION NO. 1141</num>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas a North Sydney native, Trevor Lawley, is conducting potentially lifesaving research in England to treat the C. difficile infection; and</p>
<p>Whereas this valuable research could prevent unnecessary deaths each year; and</p>
<p>Whereas Trevor has a Ph.D. in microbiology and works with pathogens at the Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute in England;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in wishing Trevor's team success in their research making C. difficile a thing of the past.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Truro-Bible Hill-Millbrook-Salmon River.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1142">RESOLUTION NO. 1142</num>
          <speech by="#c479d7de-83a6-47c7-a045-07816407bdb3"><from>MS. LENORE ZANN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Robert (Bob) Gogan, a long-time Colchester County resident, has lived an outstanding and very interesting life; and</p>
<p>Whereas Bob has been an educator in the Colchester County school system since 1957, eventually finishing his career as a principal commanding respect from his students, the community and the school board; and</p>
<p>Whereas an excellent sportsman, Bob was inducted into both the Acadia University Hall of Fame and the Colchester County Sport Hall of Fame, for his passion and success in all sports including being a master equestrian;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the Nova Scotia Legislature congratulate Bob Gogan for his contribution to his community and for being inducted into both the Acadia University Hall of Fame and the Colchester County Sport Hall of Fame, and wish him all the very best in the future.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Halifax Atlantic.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1143">RESOLUTION NO. 1143</num>
          <speech by="#ac013fcf-fe88-4578-8a8e-9f7973ddac75"><from>MR. BRENDAN MAGUIRE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas National Volunteer Week is April 6-13, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas the 40<sup>th</sup> Provincial Volunteer Awards ceremony was held April 7, 2014, to honour volunteers for their tremendous contributions made to their communities and the province; and</p>
<p>Whereas Brian Dempsey of Halifax Atlantic is a recipient of the 2014 Volunteer Representative Award;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly congratulate Brian Dempsey for being chosen as this year's recipient of the Volunteer Representative Award, and thank him for his outstanding contributions to his community and province.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Kings North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1144">RESOLUTION NO. 1144</num>
          <speech by="#bc54523e-7553-4c28-b315-79d18165339b"><from>MR. JOHN LOHR</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on February 18<sup>th</sup> the Annapolis Valley Chamber of Commerce handed out the 2014 Valley's Best Awards; and</p>
<p>Whereas Collective Tattoo Studio was awarded Best Specialty/Gift Shop; and</p>
<p>Whereas Collective Tattoo Studio is well known for its artistry and talents in body art;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House congratulate the Collective Tattoo Studio for being awarded the Annapolis Valley Chamber of Commerce Valley's Best Specialty/Gift Shop for 2014.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Lunenburg.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1145">RESOLUTION NO. 1145</num>
          <speech by="#0206420c-7710-4c22-9cee-dc3d70a99352"><from>MS. SUZANNE LOHNES-CROFT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Bluenose Coastal Action Foundation (BCAF), formerly the Bluenose Atlantic Coastal Action Program (BACAP), was incorporated in December 1993 as part of the federal Green Plan to develop remedial action plans for Atlantic Canadian harbours; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Bluenose Coastal Action Foundation is a non-profit charitable organization that addresses the environmental concerns within Lunenburg County watershed, and BCAF's goal is to promote the restoration, enhancement, and conservation of our ecosystem through research, education, and action; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Bluenose Coastal Action Foundation has recently celebrated its 20<sup>th</sup> Anniversary;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Bluenose Coastal Action Foundation on making the Bluenose coast a better, more environmentally friendly place to live.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Colchester-Musquodoboit Valley.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1146">RESOLUTION NO. 1146</num>
          <speech by="#0f46e5e4-b06b-4b91-9e3a-5bd1cd63809d"><from>MR. LARRY HARRISON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas every year the Town of Truro holds an art show in order to choose a piece to be added to their permanent collection on display at the town hall; and</p>
<p>Whereas this year Diane Redden's <i>Truro Train Station (circa 1928)</i> was chosen from 66 entries on display at the Town of Truro Art Acquisition Show for 2014 at the McCarthy Gallery; and</p>
<p>Whereas Redden, a multimedia artist from Middle Stewiacke, who is known for using upcycled materials in her artwork and jewellery, created the train station piece from coloured zippers that she found at Frenchy's;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Diane Redden for having <i>Truro Train Station (circa 1928)</i> chosen by the Art Collection Committee to join the Town of Truro's permanent art collection.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Waverley-Fall River-Beaver Bank.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1147">RESOLUTION NO. 1147</num>
          <speech by="#16a35513-2bff-496f-85bc-9a815574e9ba"><from>MR. BILL HORNE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Fall River Gardening Club promotes the improvement of home and community flower and vegetable gardens, lawns, trees and landscaping in the community of Fall River, and the club is open to anyone interested in gardening; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Fall River Gardening Club currently sponsors three projects: the LWF Community Centre, Jamieson Park, and one of the gardens at the Waverley Green, and has undertaken the design and maintenance of a new garden in front of the Fall River Fire Museum; and</p>
<p>Whereas these community volunteers range from amateur gardeners to expert gardeners, and many donate their plants and labour as well as organize annual fundraisers;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly thank the Fall River Gardening Club for the ongoing improvements and beautification of the community of Fall River.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Pictou Centre.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1148">RESOLUTION NO. 1148</num>
          <speech by="#71280477-3de0-4cef-90bd-e23864226ad3"><from>HON. PAT DUNN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas New Glasgow resident Bill Dimock participated on Team Canada's hockey team in the 1949 World Championships; and</p>
<p>Whereas he was a talented young athlete who grew up in the small community of Trail, British Columbia, where we was nurtured by his father who was the coach of the Trail Smoke Eaters; and</p>
<p>Whereas in 1942, he attended the University of Alberta, where he studied chemical engineering and played hockey in the newly formed Western Intercollegiate League, after which he moved to Montreal and was chosen to play on the Canadian hockey team at the World Championships held in Stockholm, Sweden;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Bill Dimock for having been part of one of sport's most prestigious events, the World Hockey Championships, and for bringing home a silver medal in 1949.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Kings South.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1149">RESOLUTION NO. 1149</num>
          <speech by="#97532239-d15e-407a-8c67-706ed1bbc595"><from>MR. KEITH IRVING</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Chris Cuvilier has been instrumental in minor baseball and softball in the community of Hantsport as coach and fundraising chair for over a decade; and</p>
<p>Whereas Chris Cuvilier has dedicated his time and experience to raising significant funds to fight cancer and other diseases; and</p>
<p>Whereas the province has recognized Chris Cuvilier's exemplary service to his community through the recent awarding of a Provincial Volunteer Award;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly thank and congratulate Chris Cuvilier on his years of dedicated public service in the community of Hantsport.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Inverness.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1150">RESOLUTION NO. 1150</num>
          <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff"><from>MR. ALLAN MACMASTER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Andrew MacDonald has just signed a six-year, $30 million contract with the Philadelphia Flyers; and</p>
<p>Whereas this is the largest contract ever signed by a Judiquer in the NHL; and</p>
<p>Whereas Andrew led the NHL in blocked shots this season with 242, and played an average of well over 20 minutes per game;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House congratulate Andrew MacDonald on his success and wish him well as the Flyers take on the Rangers in round one of the playoffs on Thursday night.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Guysborough-Eastern Shore-Tracadie.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1151">RESOLUTION NO. 1151</num>
          <speech by="#bf8b9586-8d64-4f8f-b12a-88dfc38ac185"><from>MR. LLOYD HINES</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Canso Lions Club is a volunteer organization that has been offering many services to the people of their community for over the past 45 years; and</p>
<p>Whereas Canso Lions Club officers Doug Samson, Catherine DeRabbie, Carl Bond, Buzz Lumsden, Ray White, Paul Horne, Bill Roberts, Joe Parker, Janet Delorey, Dave MacMillian, Emily Lumsden, and Paul Horne have been involved in every aspect of the life of the Canso area and have touched the lives of so many; and</p>
<p>Whereas they have assisted with the Eastern Memorial Hospital, Canso Arena, Canso Fire Department, Canso Library, Canso Minor Hockey, Canso Academy and Fanning Education Centre, Shamrock Seniors Club, Scouts, Cadets, local museums, Canso Regatta, GOALS, and many, many others;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly express their sincere appreciation and gratitude for the Canso Lions Club officers' commitment to making their community a better place to live, and acknowledge the many lives they have improved.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>ORDERS OF THE DAY</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>ORAL QUESTIONS PUT BY MEMBERS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The time is now 2:47 p.m. Question Period will conclude at 3:47 p.m.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition.</p></speech>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>PREM. - EFFICIENCY FEE: PROMISE - BREACH ADMIT</heading>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Yesterday the Premier's efficiency fee shell game actually got an endorsement from the Ecology Action Centre. Catherine Abreu of the Ecology Action Centre said (Applause) Better wait for the quote. She actually said that it's "always better" for ratepayers to pay for conservation programs. That is, of course, the opposite of what the Premier promised Nova Scotians when he guaranteed them that their efficiency fees would be paid for out of Nova Scotia Power's profits.</p>
<p>In light of this endorsement, Mr. Speaker, I would like to ask the Premier if he will now finally admit the obvious: that he broke his promise to the people of Nova Scotia.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5">
            <from>HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I am so proud of the fact that we finally have a government that is leading energy policy in this place to the best interest of Nova Scotian ratepayers. Power rates will be going down January 1<sup>st</sup>, and the efficiency tax will come off every power bill in the province. That's $46 million in savings, and I think that what the Ecology Action Centre said was that the only way that any Nova Scotian would pay for efficiency programs was if it actually was a cheaper fuel source, which in turn would drive power rates down even further.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>MR. BAILLIE</from><p>Actually, Mr. Speaker, what Nova Scotians are continuing to look for is a government that does what it says it will do in the election, not the opposite. But Ms. Abreu had a lot to say about the government shell game. In commending the Premier for charging the efficiency fee right back onto the pocketbooks of Nova Scotians, Ms. Abreu of the Ecology Action Centre said that, "What we've seen in this bill is acknowledgment that the situation was perhaps more complicated than the [Premier's] promise suggested."</p>
<p>Now, Mr. Speaker, where have we heard that before? That's exactly what the NDP said when they broke their promise to Nova Scotians that they wouldn't raise their taxes, and now we're hearing the same reason for why this government broke their promise to Nova Scotians on their power rates.</p>
<p>So I'll ask the Premier if he will acknowledge the obvious: that he made a reckless promise to Nova Scotians, and as a result they will continue to pay the efficiency fee on their power bills?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, what I will inform the Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party is that we promised Nova Scotians that we would remove the efficiency tax off every power bill; that will happen as of January 1, 2015. On top of that, we didn't stop there. We now are going to continue to drive down fuel sources so that power rates will continue to drop. Why is the Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party afraid to allow Nova Scotians to pay less for power rates?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>MR. BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, if they were truly to going to pay less, we'd all cheer that, of course, but when a government promises to take the fee off our bill and then allows the power company to charge it right back on to our bills again in another line, that's not reducing our power rates. That's a shell game, and a complicated one at that.</p>
<p>But speaking of complicated, Mr. Speaker, the complications and the fine print just get longer and longer as the government announced that Nova Scotia Power would make, in their words, a $37 million contribution to Clean Nova Scotia over 10 years. That does not match what the power company itself said, on Friday, when they described it as a $3.4 million contribution, per year, renewable every year for up to 10 years. That is why the Affordable Energy Coalition themselves are concerned that low-income Nova Scotians will be cut off at any time, another shell game, this time on the backs of the lowest-income Nova Scotians.</p>
<p>I will ask the Premier if he can explain, in his elaborate shell game, why what his government is saying is not the same as what Nova Scotia Power is saying.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, let me be clear to the Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party. One thing that Nova Scotia Power and its president know is that this government will dictate energy in the Province of Nova Scotia and when we make a commitment to the people of this province, we will deliver on it and we expect them to deliver on their end of it.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Leader of the New Democratic Party.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>PREM. - NURSES/CAP. HEALTH: RELATIONSHIP - REPAIR REQUIREMENT</heading>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question through you is to the Premier. Nurses are the backbone of our health care system and they work extremely hard to care for their patients and they want to be treated with dignity and respect. After the Liberal Government's essential services legislation, repairing the relationships between nurses and their employer is of the utmost importance.</p>
<p>My question is, after what we heard at the Law Amendments Committee and during the protest by health care workers two weeks ago, does the Premier believe there is work to be done to repair the relationship between nurses and Capital Health?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, if there is one thing that has become clear to me after four years of that government, not only is there repair work to be done between nurses and Capital Health, there is repair to be done between every organization in the Government of Nova Scotia. It is why I'm so proud of the Minister of Health and Wellness, who very clearly said he is going around talking to health care providers, those who deliver services to the people of this province and one thing is certain, we will move from an administrative-focused health care system to one that is clearly focused on patients.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9">
            <from>MS. MACDONALD</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, we have learned recently that 100 nurses at Capital Health are being called in by their employer for what Capital Health is calling investigative meetings into their protest activities, the first step into the possibility of disciplinary action. Does the Premier believe investigative meetings and disciplinary action will help repair the relationship between nurses and Capital Health or will he ask the administration at Capital Health to respect health care workers' rights to speak out on behalf of their patients?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I don't know what the Leader of the New Democratic Party is referring to. That is something between the employer and those who work for the employer. One thing that I will tell the Leader of the New Democratic Party, quite frankly, is, as we've said all along in the debate, there have been issues raised about the staffing on floors not only in the Capital Region but across the province. The Minister of Health and Wellness has said he is going to investigate. The difference between us and the NDP is that we don't believe everything has to end up in the collective bargaining process.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9">
            <from>MS. MACDONALD</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, health care workers' morale has sunk to a new low because of the actions of that government. Yesterday in Estimates, when discussing changes to the nursing strategy, the Minister of Health and Wellness said, satisfaction in the workplace is key and that he hopes nurses will stay in the province. The threat of disciplinary action seems pretty unlikely to improve nurses' morale. My question for the Premier is, what will he do to ensure nurses in our province aren't driven to leave Nova Scotia because they don't feel respected, they feel threatened?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I can tell you what the Minister of Health and Wellness is doing. He is going around talking to nurses and talking to Nova Scotians about the issues that they face, quite frankly, which didn't show up on October 22<sup>nd</sup>, they were there long before we took power. As a matter of fact, I would daresay they were there when that member was Minister of Health and Wellness. The difference between this Party and that Party is that we're listening and we will respond.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>PREM. - POWER RATES: NSP - CHARGES</heading>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, all Nova Scotians are waiting for a real plan from this government about their power rates, not just a complicated, elaborate shell game. They are rightly worried that by changing governments, when it comes to power, really nothing has changed, that rate increases lie in their future.</p>
<p>The Premier says that the government will set power policy. Let me just quote from the president of Nova Scotia Power who said yesterday that: Nova Scotia Power is looking to defer this winter's fuel bills beyond 2015, based on a request by the Liberal Government. I will table that.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I have a pretty simple question for the Premier, why is he simply kicking rate increases down the road, instead of doing what he promised and charge it to the power company instead?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined"><from>THE PREMIER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, first of all, if there was any Party that was going to kick down the road in future increases it was the Progressive Conservative Party. Let me be clear, the quote that was attributed to the president of Nova Scotia Power is actually not a quote - it was an interpretation in the article. It was not an absolute quote.</p>
<p>Let me deliver what was in the article: Nova Scotia Power CEO Bob Hanf said, "The province expressed their concern about affordability so it's our job to make sure we achieve that objective."</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, finally a government that is delivering a message to Nova Scotia Power.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>MR. BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, it's pretty obvious that the only message that government has delivered to Nova Scotia Power is to put off a rate increase to a future day, and charge interest to the ratepayers of Nova Scotia who are still going to get that bill. That's the sad reality - after being promised that the efficiency charge would be paid for out of the profits of the power company, it turns out the biggest defender of those profits is the new Premier of Nova Scotia. That is what's wrong.</p>
<p>It turns out that in an effort to defend the pushing of future rate increases down the road, the Minister of Energy turned himself into Reveen yesterday, pulling out his crystal ball, Mr. Speaker, and said - the Minister of Energy, as Reveen: There will probably be a decline in fuel prices in 2016 and 2017.</p>
<p>Well that's comforting to know, but it's also odd since just a few months ago he said "I'm not going to sit here and predict what energy rates will be &#x2026;" in the future.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Does the member have a question?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92">
            <from>MR. BAILLIE</from>
            <p>My question to the Premier is, when will his government get serious about dealing with power rates, instead of setting policy by crystal ball?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, let me be clear, the Minister of Energy has done something that we haven't seen in a very long time. On January 15<sup>th</sup> Nova Scotia ratepayers will be paying less for energy.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>MR. BAILLIE</from><p>Well not only is the government setting its power policy based on Reveen-like abilities to predict the future, they are now borrowing the Leon's "pay later, not now" policy by deferring our costs well into the future.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, Nova Scotians deserve better, they already pay the highest power rates in the country and now they get this elaborate shell game in response from the government. They are struggling to pay their bills every month and they get a minister who looks in his crystal ball and promises that rates will go down at a future date.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, Nova Scotians already had one promise from the Liberals during the election and they broke that, so why is this promise that fuel rates are going to go down in the future any better than the first one?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined"><from>THE PREMIER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, we promised Nova Scotians that we would be removing the efficiency tax off every power bill in the Province of Nova Scotia - that will take place January 1, 2015. Not only that, the Minister of Energy didn't stop there, he continued to ensure to drive more savings for Nova Scotia ratepayers by creating an Energy Efficiency department that will continue to compete against fuel prices in the Province of Nova Scotia, which will continue to drive down prices.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, he went even further than that, he went into the pockets of shareholders of Nova Scotia Power and said it's time for you to create an energy program so that low-income Nova Scotians can afford to take advantage of efficiency programs in this province.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Inverness.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>JUSTICE: MARSHALL INQUIRY - LESSONS LEARNED</heading>
          <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff">
            <from>MR. ALLAN MACMASTER</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, my question is for the Minister of Justice. It has been 25 years since the Marshall Inquiry. That report led to Donald Marshall, Jr. being compensated for a wrongful conviction. The commissioners found that the mistreatment of minorities also extended to the Black community. The commission had recommended that when a person is wrongfully convicted, an independent judicial inquiry be held to consider a compensation claim. Does the Minister of Justice agree with the lessons learned from the Marshall Inquiry?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#578ba1c9-5f6c-4b7b-a5cd-b915e1801c37">
            <from>HON. LENA DIAB</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I very much appreciate the question. I certainly feel for anybody who has had a difficult experience in the justice system. I think the honourable member is referring to a case that has just happened in court last week, and as he very well knows, the defence has dropped the case against the province of malicious prosecution. Thank you.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff"><from>MR. MACMASTER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, the gentleman that the minister is speaking about was still wrongfully convicted. We all know of Gerald Barton, a young Black man at the time of the alleged offence. He was wrongfully convicted and labelled a sex offender. We know that doors were likely closed to him over the course of his life for jobs and other opportunities. He actually said in 2012, "I am not angry. It was a dirty trick they played on me. They threw me in jail, like I was nothing, and I don't think that's right. And they never even stopped to ask if I was guilty."</p>
<p>My question for the Minister of Justice is, will the minister act immediately to let Mr. Barton know that he isn't "nothing", that what happened to him was wrong, and that institutionalized racism in our justice system in this province is a thing of the past?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#578ba1c9-5f6c-4b7b-a5cd-b915e1801c37">
            <from>MS. DIAB</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, Nova Scotians want to feel confident that the players in the justice system are doing their job to ensure that people are treated fairly. In cases of this sort, they are sometimes more complex than what you hear in the media. As I stated before, I certainly feel for anybody that has gone through what Mr. Barton has gone through. I sympathize, I have a lot of remorse and it simply is unfair what he went through. Again, the case is still in front of the courts. Thank you.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff">
            <from>MR. MACMASTER</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, the Marshall Inquiry said that when it is determined that someone has been wrongfully convicted, a judicial inquiry will be constituted. My final question to the minister is, will the minister reaffirm what the Court of Appeal said in 2011, respect the lessons of the Marshall Inquiry and ensure that an independent judicial inquiry be convened to consider compensation for Mr. Barton?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#578ba1c9-5f6c-4b7b-a5cd-b915e1801c37">
            <from>MS. DIAB</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I will be clear, as this is his second supplementary. The decision has not yet been rendered by the court and there has not been a verdict of the nature that he is speaking about, so we will await the decision. Thank you very much.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Leader of the New Democratic Party.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>PREM. - EFFICIENCY PROGS.: COSTS - NSP INVOLVEMENT</heading>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question through you is to the Premier. During the CBC Leaders' election debate, the Premier, then Leader of the Official Opposition, said, "You cannot continue to allow the utility to continue to drive the energy process in this province &#x2026;" because, as he said, "They're trying to get the most expensive project through, because then they get a 9 per cent rate of return, which is good for their shareholders."</p>
<p>But under the new Liberal Efficiency Nova Scotia scheme, not only will Nova Scotia Power be able to charge ratepayers directly for the cost of efficiency programs, they will also be able to directly negotiate the cost of these programs beginning in 2016. My question for the Premier is, why is he now allowing the fox in the henhouse by giving Nova Scotia Power a direct say in the cost of efficiency programs?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined"><from>THE PREMIER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, no wonder Nova Scotia Power enjoyed it when the NDP were in power. It clearly shows how little they know about the energy policy with that question. Quite frankly, under their plan, every Nova Scotian paid that efficiency tax on every power bill. Regardless of your ability to pay, you were still charged that tax.</p>
<p>What we have done, Mr. Speaker, is actually create a system where the only way any Nova Scotian will pay for efficiency programs is if it actually drives savings in the fuel costs. Nova Scotia Power would prefer the old system, under the NDP, but ratepayers would prefer the one we have delivered.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>MS. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, it's not what the consumer advocate says. The Premier also used to say that revenue to run efficiency programs would come directly from Nova Scotia Power's shareholders. We now know that promise was not exactly as advertised and that customers or ratepayers, not shareholders, will be footing the bill.</p>
<p>My question is, does the Premier believe there are any differences at all to what he promised before the election and what he is delivering to Nova Scotians now? If so, perhaps he'd share them.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined"><from>THE PREMIER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, prior to the election every ratepayer had to pay the efficiency tax or, as it is affectionately known around this place, as the NDP electricity tax. Not only that, they had to pay the highest cost for fuel - every ratepayer had to pay the highest cost for fuel.</p>
<p>What we've delivered, Mr. Speaker, is we eliminated the NDP electricity tax and we have driven competition to drive fuel prices down, which means more savings.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>MS. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I'd like to table a column from The Chronicle Herald in which Claire McIlveen wrote, "As of Jan. 1, the levy is gone, but up to 75 per cent of the cost of ENS could remain, built into power bills that - you guessed it - we all pay." So it is not just MLAs on this side of the House who see a difference between what the Premier promised on energy efficiency, before the election, and what he says now, after the election.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, my question is, will the Premier now admit that the Liberal platform was not exactly as advertised and is a bit of a fraud?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, what I will tell the honourable member is that the piece of legislation that was introduced drives even further savings to ratepayers than our platform advertised. So most Nova Scotians say that not only do we deliver, we did better than we said.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Kings North.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>AGRIC. - N.S. PROV. EXHIBITION COMMN.: FORENSIC AUDIT - UPDATE</heading>
          <speech by="#bc54523e-7553-4c28-b315-79d18165339b"><from>MR. JOHN LOHR</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question is for the Minister of Agriculture. In August a Grant Thornton report stated that without outside intervention the Nova Scotia Provincial Exhibition Commission in Truro was on a collision course with bankruptcy. The Minister of Agriculture, in January, ordered a forensic audit because the commission owed the province $450,000, had not been making loan payments, and was refusing to hand over its financial data. In total, the commission is $1.1 million in debt, which includes more than $200,000 it owes to racetracks across North America.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, my question to the minister is, will the minister update this House of Assembly today on the status of this forensic audit and when it will be finished?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#aef785d7-7697-4453-8f9c-eef26e4928c3">
            <from>HON. KEITH COLWELL</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, the audit is presently underway and it should be finished, I believe, by the end of July.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#bc54523e-7553-4c28-b315-79d18165339b"><from>MR. LOHR</from><p>Mr. Speaker, it is my understanding that this audit is going to cost $100,000, and as we speak this afternoon, interest is still being added to the Exhibition Commission's original debt with the Farm Loan Board.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, my question to the minister is, when will the minister provide clarification on what the board owes, how this money is going to be paid and to whom, and the plan accepted by the province moving forward?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#aef785d7-7697-4453-8f9c-eef26e4928c3">
            <from>MR. COLWELL</from>
            <p>First of all I'd like to correct the honourable member: the audit will be paid for by the Department of Agriculture, not by the Exhibition Commission. We want to be clear that it is totally independent of that commission and we get the results straight back to the department.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#bc54523e-7553-4c28-b315-79d18165339b"><from>MR. LOHR</from><p>I'd like to thank the minister for that answer. Mr. Speaker, a new three-man board was to have been appointed by the province, but Colchester County residents and all Nova Scotia harness racing owners have yet to learn who that third person will be.</p>
<p>My question to the minister is, will the minister indicate when that third person will be appointed, and can he assure this House and the communities of Truro and Bible Hill that their Truro Raceway will operate its full program this coming season, including the annual provincial exhibition in late August?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#aef785d7-7697-4453-8f9c-eef26e4928c3">
            <from>MR. COLWELL</from>
            <p>I'm pleased to hear that the honourable member has raised this question. It's a very important question. Yes, indeed, it's going to be a full slate of activities this year, including the provincial exhibition. Horse racing started last weekend, actually. The 4-H program will continue, as will most all of the other programs, and we're very pleased that's the case. I'm very pleased that next week - I believe it is Thursday of next week - I will announce the three-person board, and we're very pleased with the people that have put their names forward. We're already moving toward making the facility long-term feasible and profitable for a change.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Cape Breton Centre.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>PREM. - EFFICIENCY N.S. CHANGES:</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>PRE/POST ELECTION - CONSISTENCY</heading>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23"><from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question is for the Premier. In an interview on CTV on September 10, 2013, I'll quote from the Premier : "You may not have agreed with everything I said [ &#x2026; ] but I was upfront with you and I told you the truth, and I told you the truth before you voted."</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, would the Premier characterize his changes to Efficiency Nova Scotia as being consistent with what he told voters before the election?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Yes.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23"><from>MR. CORBETT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, when asked about the changes to Efficiency Nova Scotia, the Premier's Energy Minister was quoted as saying, "We have come up with a slightly different way of addressing" the Liberal campaign promise.</p>
<p>So through you, Mr. Speaker, I want to ask the Premier, was cutting the Graduate Retention Rebate a "slightly different way" of addressing the Liberal campaign promise he made to young Nova Scotians?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>I'm very proud, quite frankly, Mr. Speaker. For the first time, there is a government that is actually driving investment and job creation to keep more young people here. We're going to increase the number of apprenticeship opportunities. We have research grants out for university students, and on top of that, we're doing something that that former government would refuse to do, and that is work with the private sector to create job opportunities for young Nova Scotians to stay here.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23"><from>MR. CORBETT</from><p>That's a good one, Mr. Speaker. Just a short while ago, we were working too well with the private sector. I'd like to table another little document here. It may be of some interest to people on the benches across. It's called the Liberal platform, so that the Premier, his Energy Minister, and the Cabinet Ministers - and for those that just need some bedtime reading over there would like to have a read, because it would give some sober second thought, much like their friends in the Senate.</p>
<p>It's obviously been a long time since anybody has really read this document, so I want to ask the Premier once again around this, Mr. Speaker. After taking away the rights of health care and ECS workers who collectively bargain, imposing arbitrary limits on Efficiency Nova Scotia, and bringing back that old-time tradition of Liberal patronage, will the Premier finally admit that he has come up with a "slightly different way" of addressing all the major Liberal campaign promises he made less than a year ago?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined"><from>THE PREMIER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I want to thank the honorable member for his question. I want to remind the honourable member that it was the New Democratic Party that took away the right to strike from paramedics.</p>
<p>What we've done is ensure that Nova Scotians receive health care services in their communities, the essential service pieces, while continuing to protect the right to strike for health care workers. Let me be clear: not only have we kept those promises and that platform but we're going to continue to focus on Nova Scotians and provide good government.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Pictou Centre.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>COM. SERV. - ROOTS FOR YOUTH: FUNDING - DENIAL EXPLAIN</heading>
          <speech by="#71280477-3de0-4cef-90bd-e23864226ad3"><from>HON. PAT DUNN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question, through you, is to the Minister of Community Services. Roots for Youth is an organization that provides crucial supports for young people struggling with homelessness in northern Nova Scotia. Since their official opening in 2011, they have helped hundreds of young people by giving them a safe place to stay, helping them find employment and addressing the deeper issues of homelessness, including abuse, mental illness, and crime. The government recently denied their request for funding, causing them to lay off six employees, leaving one to staff the home.</p>
<p>My question to the minister is, why did the minister deny funding to this important organization?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#af446054-6fe0-422a-94d6-7cdff4623b7e"><from>HON. JOANNE BERNARD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I thank the member opposite for the question. For the first time ever, this week I actually looked into Roots for Youth in Pictou County and I've made a commitment to tour the facility and go and see the work first-hand and what they do. There are many non-profit organizations across this province that struggle daily. Coming from the non-profit sector I know how difficult it is to run a non-profit sector, with or without government funding, and layoffs are a reality, unfortunately, for people who live there.</p>
<p>I made the commitment to go to Pictou County, look at the work first-hand, and I aim to keep that commitment. Scarce resources within the Department of Community Services, we're not accepting any new applications this year until we do an internal review of all organizations that receive discretionary and core funding from the department, but it is on my radar and I have made that commitment to the members for Pictou, opposite, to go and tour that facility.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#71280477-3de0-4cef-90bd-e23864226ad3"><from>MR. DUNN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, Roots for Youth is developing a plan to become self-sustainable in the coming years; they are not an organization looking for a permanent handout. This organization helps young people who have lost their way to stand on their own two feet again.</p>
<p>The government recently announced they would be providing SHYFT, in Yarmouth, with the necessary funding to run their program - $350,000. In fact, the government may have committed $350,000 annually, while Yarmouth County which serves many of the youth in southern Nova Scotia, Roots for Youth provides services for people in Colchester, Pictou, Antigonish, and Cape Breton.</p>
<p>My question to the minister is, why has the minister given no consideration to regional supports when denying much of northern Nova Scotia's youth with these services?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#af446054-6fe0-422a-94d6-7cdff4623b7e">
            <from>MS. BERNARD</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I had the privilege and honour to open SHYFT in January, and stood in a room that was packed with community members, non-profit members, the business community, many other levels of government officials were there, Chris was there - oops, did I say the name again, sorry &#x2026;</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Order, please. I'd like to remind the honourable minister to refer to the other honourable members by their riding name.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#af446054-6fe0-422a-94d6-7cdff4623b7e"><from>MS. BERNARD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I was very privileged to stand there that day in that packed room of community members who had worked years and years to make sure that SHYFT, which had not been supported by the previous government, that this youth organization which services the Tri-County area of southwestern Nova Scotia, an area of the province that has been hit on a number of fronts with bad economic policies over the last four years, so I was very proud to open that.</p>
<p>As a former executive director, I think it's really unfair when organizations criticize other organizations for getting funding. It is an offensive way of doing business in the non-profit sector - I never participated in it. Every non-profit organization has value, every organization has the ability to deliver services, so I have absolutely no regret and am very proud that this Party stood behind the people of Yarmouth and SHYFT and opened it. (Applause)</p></speech>
          <speech by="#71280477-3de0-4cef-90bd-e23864226ad3"><from>MR. DUNN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I think what matters in this House today is that in estimates the minister admitted that this was a campaign issue with the member for Yarmouth and that it was a political move on their part to give $350,000 to SHYFT, whereas it looks like the youth up in northern Nova Scotia are not important or maybe the volunteers are not important.</p>
<p>Once again, Mr. Speaker, Roots for Youth struggles to find a way forward, and they have to rely entirely on volunteer supports. Staff who were laid off due to lack of funding are now volunteering at the home because they believe in this cause. Each day is filled with uncertainty for the young people who rely on their supports. Basically, they are in crisis mode now.</p>
<p>My question to the minister, will the minister make it her priority to meet with Roots for Youth as soon as possible, before this important organization is forced to close their doors?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#af446054-6fe0-422a-94d6-7cdff4623b7e"><from>MS. BERNARD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I'm completely puzzled. I just listened, not less than five minutes ago, where the Premier was accused of not keeping political platform commitments, and here I did. It was in the platform. It was a commitment of this Party. It's open. There are youth in Yarmouth who are now being taken care of because it was a platform commitment and the honourable member knows that. We did not hold back on that.</p>
<p>I have made the commitment that I will go to that area, I will meet with staff and I will tour the facility.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Leader of the New Democratic Party.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>FIN. - GRAD. RETENTION REBATE:</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>ELIMINATION - STUDENTS' CONCERNS</heading>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question through you is to the Minister of Finance and Treasury Board. Last week, when we were debating the elimination of the Graduate Retention Rebate, the minister accused members of the Legislature of "mixing up the interests of students with the interests of young graduates. They are two very different things."</p>
<p>Well, Mr. Speaker, I beg to differ. There are more than 40,000 students in HRM alone who stand to be impacted by the elimination of the Graduate Retention Rebate when they graduate.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I'd like to ask the minister if she could please explain how the elimination of a program that helps graduates reduce their debt is not of interest to students?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2">
            <from>HON. DIANA WHALEN</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, in answer to the honourable member's question, I'd like to remind all members of the House again that what students need when they graduate from university is a job. And that's exactly what we're going to provide for them, through the use of our Graduate to Opportunities, through the graduate scholarships, through the other opportunities for co-ops, for internships and more experience for young people coming into the workforce.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>MS. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, if it was only so simple. If there was only one thing that people needed in life - eh, just a job. But students need more than a job. They need jobs. They need debt relief. They need to be able to have incentives to stay in the province. They need to be able to invest in starting small businesses.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, Nova Scotia has a long history of providing debt relief to students and graduates in Nova Scotia at varying levels, dating back to 1993. New information released today by the Canadian Centre for Policy Alternatives confirms that our students continue to graduate with some of the highest debt loads in the country.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, my question to the minister is this, why is she slashing support for post-secondary students to the lowest level in over a decade when we know they are struggling now more than ever financially?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2">
            <from>MS. WHALEN</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I would like to pass that question to the Minister of Labour and Advanced Education.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>HON. KELLY REGAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, as the mother of three children, I can tell you that I am very aware of what students go through as they go through their post-secondary education. I have one daughter who graduated several years ago and is unable to work because of illness. I have another daughter who is about to graduate and will go into the job market. Fortunately for her, she has one waiting for her. I have another child who is in high school. So we're very aware of the cost of education.</p>
<p>Keeping post-secondary education affordable in Nova Scotia is a priority for this government, and we will continue to meet with students on this and other issues. We'll also engage universities to help make post-secondary education more affordable in Nova Scotia, including looking at tuition fees.</p>
<p>I would note, Mr. Speaker, that the CCPA tool, the report that's out today, is somewhat misleading. It does not include the Nova Scotia university tuition bursary, which is nearly $1,300. So, actually, when it talks about where we are in terms of other provinces, it is entirely inaccurate. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>MS. MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I don't know what the minister reads to inform herself about the debt load that students in this province carry but it has been well documented in many reports that students in our province carry some of the highest debt loads in the country because they face some of the highest costs in the country for their tuition. (Interruption) I hear members on the government side saying no, that is not the case. But I would recommend that they inform themselves because the data is clear on this. We have among the highest tuition costs in the country and debt loads are among the highest in the country. That's just a fact.</p>
<p>I will ask the Minister of Finance and Treasury Board, again, because the Graduate Retention Rebate is in her department - how long will students have to wait for the minister to realize that eliminating tens of millions of dollars in support of post-secondary students was the wrong thing to do?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>HON. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I'll have to say it again, there are two very different issues here. Young people in the workforce are one issue and people in post-secondary education have different issues. That is exactly why so many student groups actually recommended eliminating the Graduate Retention Rebate, because they wanted money put into post-secondary education. They have very different views and very different needs.</p>
<p>What we do know is that economic development depends on people getting their first job. Nobody was getting the Graduate Retention Rebate unless they had a job and it paid well. They had to owe taxes in this province in order to get that rebate. We want to get more people into the workforce and that is what we will do.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Fairview-Clayton Park.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>EDUC. - EAL: CURRICULUM REVIEW - INCLUSION CONFIRM</heading>
          <speech by="#eb42d545-c815-47c5-a60b-237f29603d3e"><from>MS. PATRICIA ARAB</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question today is for the Minister of Education and Early Childhood Development. My riding of Fairview-Clayton Park has the highest number of refugees and new immigrants in Atlantic Canada. The children in these families come into our education system and immediately begin the process of becoming multi-lingual, learning English as an additional language. Having EAL learners in our system can be seen as a negative or a hurdle that must be overcome. We need to change the perspective and highlight our EAL learners, not as students to present a challenge but instead as gifted learners who will leave our education system with knowledge and proficiency in at least two different languages.</p>
<p>My question through you to the minister is, is EAL on the agenda for the upcoming curriculum review and is the department committed to putting this on the agenda as a priority?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>HON. KAREN CASEY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, to the member's question that I know is important to her in her constituency, but it is also important to all Nova Scotians. With the influx of immigrants that we have and with what we expect, in order to grow the population and the economy, we know that English as an alternate language is becoming more and more of a priority.</p>
<p>I have said in this House and I've said publicly that the review that's currently underway, the slate is clear and I would encourage the member and others, if that is an issue, that that come forward to the panel. We already put $500,000 into that but perhaps that is not enough.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Northside-Westmount.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>EECD - COBEQUID CHILDREN'S CTR: CLOSURE - DEPT. RESPONSE</heading>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question is to the Minister of Education and Early Childhood Development. Parents who started arriving at the Cobequid Children's Centre in Sackville at 6:00 a.m. yesterday found the doors locked and no trace of the owners. The Sackville daycare had been in business for 13 years. The sudden closure left about 50 children without care and their parents panicked and confused.</p>
<p>My question to the minister is, will the minster advise this House today what her department knew about the financial difficulties at the daycare and when it was first brought to the department's attention?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22">
            <from>HON. KAREN CASEY</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, to the member opposite, it is a very unfortunate situation that the parents found themselves with they arrived at the daycare; the door was locked and there had been no notice. It is in violation of what we ask all daycares to do and that is to provide a 120-day notice to both the parents and the families of the children who use those services and to the department. I will say here, and I've said in the media, that no notice was given either to the parents and families or to the department.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. ORRELL</from><p>Media reports indicate that the Department of Education and Early Childhood Development understood that financial difficulties had been worked out with the daycare. When 50 children are left without daycare and parents are provided with no advance notice, it's quite clear that difficulties had not been resolved.</p>
<p>My question to the minister is, will the minister provide clarification on what was actually taking place with the board and what led the minister and her officials to think they no longer should have any concerns about the Cobequid Children's Centre?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>MS. CASEY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I would like to correct the member - our department and our staff never give up, we always have concerns about the young children in our system.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, the centre was operated by a company that chose not to respond to us. We have continued to try to reach them by email and by voice mail, and neither one of those attempts have been accepted. We have heard nothing from the company; we have informed them by registered mail that they are in violation.</p>
<p>We have always worked with families and centres in order to provide that service, but our priority was not with the company on that day, our priority was how do we make sure that those families and those children have a space so that tomorrow, the day after it is closed, they can have a daycare to go to. That has been our priority and we've been working with other daycare centres that have come forward to tell us what spaces they have, and our priority has been, and will continue to be, to place those young children.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2">
            <from>MR. ORRELL</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, neither the operators of the daycare nor the owner of the building can be reached by telephone. There was no effort to inform the parents or the teachers over the weekend of the situation they may be facing Monday morning. Parents are now missing work and scrambling to find care for their children, so my question to the minister is, will the minister indicate how much money concerning subsidies to these families and subsidies to the daycare were being paid out and, if so, how much money in advance was paid out by the department to the daycare?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22">
            <from>MS. CASEY</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, if the member is interested in the particulars about funding for that particular daycare centre, I would be glad to provide that. I do agree with the member that it was very unfair for the operator of that business to not give the department notice and to not give the families notice and to leave everyone scrambling on an early morning when they thought the daycare would be open.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Pictou Centre.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>LAE: FED.-PROV. LBR. MARKET AGREEMENT - NEGOTIATIONS</heading>
          <speech by="#71280477-3de0-4cef-90bd-e23864226ad3"><from>HON. PAT DUNN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question through you is to the Minister of Labour and Advanced Education. The provincial and federal governments have been working towards a compromise in the labour market agreement. Vulnerable Nova Scotians are being caught in the crossfire and that is not fair.</p>
<p>My question to the minister is, will the minister work to ensure that the most vulnerable Nova Scotians are not denied services because of the federal-provincial disagreement?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728">
            <from>HON. KELLY REGAN</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I thank the member opposite for the question - that's exactly what we're doing.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#71280477-3de0-4cef-90bd-e23864226ad3"><from>MR. DUNN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, the Valley Community Learning Network arranged staff layoffs for April 1<sup>st</sup>, with a return to work date of September. The Hants Community Learning Association received notification March 19<sup>th</sup> that their funding application was to be revised and the province was not willing to consider any budgetary expenses over the base amount that they had provided the HCLA to work with. For HCLA this will mean that if they continue to maintain programs until June, they would be left with $8,000 to run programs from September to March 31, 2015.</p>
<p>My question to the minister is, will the minister commit to working with these facilities through negotiations, with an eye to maintaining important services?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728">
            <from>MS. REGAN</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, we provided two months of emergency funding to our partners to make sure they would be able to continue to operate.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#71280477-3de0-4cef-90bd-e23864226ad3"><from>MR. DUNN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, places like the Dartmouth Learning Centre have been offering tuition-free programs for adults 19 years of age and older who are functioning at a pre-high school literacy level in the areas of basic literacy, GED preparation, employment readiness, life skills, health and safety, nutrition and financial literacy. This is a vital source of education in our province for people who may have fallen through the cracks. These programs provide incredible benefit to both the student and the province.</p>
<p>My question for the minister is, will the minister commit to reducing the high anxiety created by this situation, settle this issue with the federal government and allow the education centres to continue the wonderful job they have done so for so many years?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728">
            <from>MS. REGAN</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I thank the honourable member for the question. I just want to make the honourable member aware that we have, in fact, an agreement in principle and we are now in bilateral negotiations with the federal government, so it is my hope that we will have an agreement concluded soon. Thank you.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Sydney-Whitney Pier.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>PREM. - VETERANS: SUPPORT - ADEQUACY</heading>
          <speech by="#81ace0ab-54e7-4b6d-8d48-6d416fbcd939"><from>MR. GORDIE GOSSE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question through you is to the Premier. As every member of this House knows, the closure of the Veterans Affairs office in Sydney has made life very difficult for our veterans. The NDP believes our veterans stood up for us when we needed them the most, and now it's our turn to stand up for them.</p>
<p>At the March 24<sup>th</sup> Veterans Affairs Committee meeting, the Deputy Minister of Intergovernmental Affairs told the members of this House that in the previous three months, the Premier had no discussions with the federal government about the closure of the Sydney office and only sent one letter to Minister Fantino.</p>
<p>My question for the Premier is, does he think sending a single letter to the federal minister is doing enough to support our veterans in their time of need?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined"><from>THE PREMIER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I want to thank the honourable member for the question. As I said to a question from a member of the Official Opposition last week, there have been a number of conversations that I've had with members of the federal government, dealing with not only veterans' issues - the previous question talked about the labour market agreement, we're talking about the European free trade deal to ensure that we can move forward.</p>
<p>It was certainly our hope, as we were moving toward the federal budget, that we would have seen a change, that there would have been some financing in place to allow for those offices to remain open or, quite frankly, to provide a better alternative, or another alternative that would have been satisfactory to veterans across this province. We didn't see that, so we're responding and now we're waiting for the federal government to return that response.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#81ace0ab-54e7-4b6d-8d48-6d416fbcd939"><from>MR. GOSSE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, in today's Halifax Chronicle Herald, it was reported that the total budget for the Veterans Affairs office in Sydney was just over $1 million. At the Veterans Affairs Committee meeting held in March, the Deputy Minister of Intergovernmental Affairs said the province could not create a veterans' advocate to replace the services provided by the Sydney veterans office because "&#x2026; the downloading impact and what we're feeling from the federal government is actually incredible."</p>
<p>My question for the Premier is, now that he knows the full cost of the replacement of services provided at the Veterans Affairs office in Sydney, will the Premier reconsider hiring a veterans' advocate for Nova Scotia?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined"><from>THE PREMIER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, it is my hope that the federal government will see the fact that we need them to provide us with a veterans' advocate in this province. As we clearly know, the responsibility to fund that squarely lies with the federal government.</p>
<p>As you know, Mr. Speaker, there has been a change to the way we fund health care in this country now, towards population base. For a province like ours, it's an aging demographic, chronic illnesses - it's creating a much greater burden on the provincial government to deliver on the health care commitments that we had to our citizens. As was alluded to in the previous question, the provincial government has put out two months of emergency funding to ensure that organizations across this province can continue to deliver services to the most vulnerable Nova Scotians - funding, I might add, that should be coming from the federal government. We cannot continue to backfill every time the federal government decides it's going to pull away from it.</p>
<p>I want to encourage all members of this House to continue to do the work they have been doing on behalf of veterans in their individual constituencies and on being an advocate on behalf of them. I hope that all members of this House will continue to support the government in its efforts to have the federal government fund an advocate program here in the province. (Applause)</p></speech>
          <speech by="#81ace0ab-54e7-4b6d-8d48-6d416fbcd939"><from>MR. GOSSE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, in the Spring budget, the Liberal Government revealed it will increase the combined ministers' office budgets of the Departments of Labour and Advanced Education, Finance, Environment, and Energy by approximately $750,000. When it comes to supporting veterans, this government has not allocated a single new dollar for veterans.</p>
<p>My question for the Premier is, why is this government willing to invest close to $1 million to support the day-to-day activities of four Cabinet Ministers, but not willing to provide the same support for our military veterans?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined"><from>THE PREMIER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I want to remind all members of this House that members of this Cabinet continue to find savings inside their departments. Not only did they meet the 1 per cent target of $28 million, they found $76 million. Quite frankly they've gone above and beyond. What I believe is important here is that all provincial members remain focused on the fact that it is the national government's responsibility to deliver services to Nova Scotians and continue to deliver services to veterans.</p>
<p>All members of this House should be united behind - Mr. Speaker, if the members of this House can't unite behind veterans what can we unite behind? Let's get together and make sure that Ottawa continues to drive, admit their responsibilities, and ensure they have a veterans advocate in this province.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Pictou East.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>TIR - HWY. NO. 104 (SOUTHERN RIVER-ANTIGONISH):</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>TWINNING - COMMIT</heading>
          <speech by="#5dac0dde-7ef3-4f75-a137-834785ff1ae4">
            <from>MR. TIM HOUSTON</from>
            <p>My question today is for the Minister of Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal. The stretch of Highway No. 104 between Sutherland's River and Antigonish is one that has seen many devastating accidents. Students travelling to St. F.X., tourists, residents, and even the minister, use this stretch of highway pretty regularly. In the past five years there have been more than 65 motor vehicle accidents and nine fatalities on that stretch of highway, but despite all this there is no mention of the twining of this section in the department's five-year highway improvement plan. My question today for the minister is, will the minister commit to twinning this stretch of road given how dangerous it is?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#2c8e1a56-2f9d-4156-a91f-77802701e3d3"><from>HON. GEOFF MACLELLAN</from><p>The member is certainly correct that Highway No. 104 is a stretch of highway that I use twice weekly and now many members of the House, and of course commuters across the province, access. The reality is - and, again, well taken with the points about the injuries and the collisions and, of course, the fatalities - there is no member of this House, government or otherwise, who wants to see those types of things happen on our roadways, as it is all about Nova Scotians and road safety is our priority.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, as the member knows, we are in the process of completing Phase II, which will be finished in 2016 which again, as any commuters will know, that has been a tremendous impact for the travel back and forth in that corridor and we are going to continue the discussions with the federal government. The Building Canada Fund will operate a new round very shortly. We are in discussions on those.</p>
<p>There isn't a member in this Legislature who wouldn't want to see the continuing of that Highway No. 104 project and all projects, Mr. Speaker, as the twinning of the highways provides that added level of safety. Anything we can do in terms of the upgrades is important to us, so I do truly thank the member for the question. Road safety is what we are all about and we will use the funding from the capital plan to create priorities that keep Nova Scotians safe.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#5dac0dde-7ef3-4f75-a137-834785ff1ae4">
            <from>MR. HOUSTON</from>
            <p>I know it must be difficult to prioritize which roads are done when and I guess I'm just a little curious about the metrics the department uses to prioritize the major projects like this. Not only is this stretch of road dangerous, but the toll it takes on the volunteer firefighters who respond to the scene of these accidents is pretty devastating. Barney's River Fire Chief Joe MacDonald recently wrote a letter to the department urging that they make the twinning of this section a priority. Mr. MacDonald says it scares him how many people have died or were seriously hurt on the stretch of highway through his district just in the past few years. My question today to the minister would be, what can the minister share with me that I can go back and tell Fire Chief Joe MacDonald about the twinning of this stretch?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#2c8e1a56-2f9d-4156-a91f-77802701e3d3"><from>MR. MACLELLAN</from><p>I actually did see that correspondence. Again, when you are hearing from those who put their lives on the line and spend a lot of their own personal time keeping Nova Scotians safe, you certainly take their word for it and what they say to heart. Again, it is a priority for us; we are doing the very best we can.</p>
<p>Phase I, for example, is a $75 million project and, Mr. Speaker, you can't put price tags on these types of things, but the reality is we have massive infrastructure deficits in this province. We certainly have to get creative as a government on how we complete those projects. Again, safety is first and foremost for us. Twinning is the Cadillac version of what we can do for road safety so we do as much as we can. We'll endeavour to let Nova Scotians know - certainly the Legislature, but all Nova Scotians - what projects we've endeavoured into conversations with the feds with respect to Building Canada.</p>
<p>The reality is that Nova Scotians can't do the heavy lifting on a lot of these large scaled projects so we need our partners with the federal government, and I have to say, Mr. Speaker, the Building Canada Fund has been invaluable for us, so we'll continue to use that and we'll make decisions that are prioritized for Nova Scotians in the name of road safety. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#5dac0dde-7ef3-4f75-a137-834785ff1ae4"><from>MR. HOUSTON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, certainly the safety of Nova Scotians is paramount when it comes to considering whether or not this priority becomes a priority. Beyond that, there are economic benefits that our province could realize by twinning this stretch. Trucking companies cannot use longer-combination vehicles on single-lane highways, and products could be moved more efficiently and reach more Nova Scotians if this stretch of highway were twinned.</p>
<p>My question today for the minister is, will he consider the economic benefits that may go along with twinning this stretch, and would he commit to seeing that this section is twinned during the government's current four-year mandate?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#2c8e1a56-2f9d-4156-a91f-77802701e3d3">
            <from>MR. MACLELLAN</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I'd like to talk to you about the history of road building in Nova Scotia and the importance that it carries for the province. This is an important section of Nova Scotia's highways, and we certainly want to support economic development endeavours in all their forms. Again, we want to keep people safe, so we'll do our best to do that and prioritize based on traffic numbers and counts and the things that make Nova Scotians safe. Thank you.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Cape Breton Centre.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, my question is to the Minister of Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal. Last week he compared himself to a baseball team. The people we've talked to about their tires feel like they have "A-Rod" broken in them, or something like that. Since this minister became in charge of roads, they feel more like the Dodgers, dodging the potholes from one end of the province to the other. So as our Steinbrenner-esque minister would want us to know, there are many teams supported in this House, and it's not the New York Yankees. It may be the Red Sox, but I think, more importantly, the way the conditions of the roads are, they are really the Dodgers. Thank you.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Order, please. The time allotted for the Oral Question Period has expired.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT BUSINESS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#34c1e608-d873-4164-95f2-86ccabbc60e9">
          <from>MR. TERRY FARRELL</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Government Motions.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT MOTIONS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#34c1e608-d873-4164-95f2-86ccabbc60e9">
          <from>MR. TERRY FARRELL</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, I move that you do now leave the Chair and the House resolve itself into a Committee of the Whole on Supply unto Her Majesty.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Pictou West.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#2c4ef79f-acb1-4c92-8ff4-e6bfac04ddc0"><from>MS. KARLA MACFARLANE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I stand here today to speak about an issue of great importance and of personal relevance to me and to many residents of Pictou County and beyond. I grew up in Pictou West, and for as long as I have been alive the pulp mill and Boat Harbour have been a part of my daily life. As a child it was the cloud machine. It was something to be stared at in amazement crossing the Causeway. It was the place where my friends' dads worked, as well as my own father, who was employed with Canso Chemicals for 42 years.</p>
<p>As an adult, it is the first thing I smell when I leave my house. It burns my eyes and my nose and there's a constant film on my car. It fills me with fear and dread as I wonder what on earth my kids are breathing into their lungs. I sit on my deck, look at the clouds produced by the pulp mill rolling in great waves over the harbour, and worry about the long-term effects the pulp mill in Boat Harbour has on the environment and the health of residents in the surrounding communities.</p>
<p>The resolution the Liberal Party passed at their AGM about cleaning up Boat Harbour gave hope to many residents of Pictou County. It recognized the significant and negative impacts on the environment, health, and well-being of northern Nova Scotia. It acknowledged the impact on Pictou Landing and the First Nation community, and it resolved that the government take immediate and effective steps to clean up Boat Harbour. I can't help but wonder why the government passed this resolution at the AGM but didn't bring it to the House.</p>
<p>Of greater concern, why is there nothing in the budget for Boat Harbour? Are they scared they will be held accountable? They shouldn't be, as I have stated over and over in many interviews that we are all accountable.</p>
<p>As you are all aware, I tabled Resolution No. 801 after it did not pass without waiver and debate. I sought to gauge the commitment level of the Liberal Government to immediately take effective steps to clean up Boat Harbour, as they resolved to do at their AGM. The government had an opportunity to bring their own resolutions to the House, just as they did at their AGM, and chose not to. I have every right to speak with vitriolic language, as the Minister of Environment so eloquently stated in the news, as my kids live and breathe the pulp mill every single day - we don't just read about it, we live it.</p>
<p>The people of Pictou County do not have the luxury of pouring over stories and information. I don't need to read stories; I only need to speak to my constituents. The member for Pictou East only needs to speak to his constituents and the member for Pictou Centre only needs to speak with his constituents.</p>
<p>The Minister of Environment stated that the purpose of passing resolutions at the AGM is to establish policies, "&#x2026; to give the Party direction." Yet he also stated, "&#x2026; always remembering you can't do everything for all people at all times." So which is it? It is the right thing to do. Yes, it definitely is, we all know it, so let's do it.</p>
<p>If the Minister of Environment wants to discuss the issue, we are always willing to meet and talk, but do we really need any more discussion? We all agree that it's an environmental disaster; we all agree it must be dealt with immediately - perhaps the time for discussions has ended and now it is time for action.</p>
<p>As I have repeatedly stated, all Parties have played a role in where we are with Boat Harbour. I stated it in print and I've stated it on radio, the urgency of this matter on many occasions.</p>
<p>Too many times this problem has been handed off to some future day. So my fellow members, the future has arrived and it is time to face this head-on - it's time for action. When we know better, we do better. We know better. Boat Harbour must be cleaned up; we all know this. The precipitator must be fixed; we all know this. We must look at the current environmental laws that exist in Nova Scotia and change them to come more in line with the rest of Canada. Our environmental laws must be strengthened and must be enforceable if we are to move forward. We must seize this opportunity to become the leaders of our constituents in what they want and to make change for things that are better for them.</p>
<p>Let's show the leadership that is expected of us all and correct this environmental mess of Boat Harbour. This is the reason why we were elected - to make Nova Scotia a better place to live for our generation and for the generations to come. Thank you. (Applause)</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>In the absence of more speakers - oh, we have a latecomer. The honourable member for Lunenburg.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#0206420c-7710-4c22-9cee-dc3d70a99352"><from>MS. SUZANNE LOHNES-CROFT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I suppose you all expect me to speak about roads, roads, and more roads. I will excuse the minister, and I will not be speaking on roads today. But I will be speaking about something that is dear and near to my heart. I am from the Town of Mahone Bay, known as the Town of Spires to many of you, where when you come into our town you are graced by the beauty of our three churches - they are only three of the five churches.</p>
<p>We have another spire in Mahone Bay, Mr. Speaker, and that is the tower of the old Mahone Bay school. I would like to speak today on the old Mahone Bay school, which is celebrating its 100<sup>th</sup> Anniversary this year. High up on the hill it overlooks the Town of Mahone Bay, and it is the fourth school in Mahone Bay. Originally the first school in Mahone Bay was built in 1861, down in front of the Lutheran church, along Edgewater Street. In 1870, due to an increase in population, another school was built across from St. James Anglican church, and then in the 1870s, because of more and more settlers moving in and families getting larger, a new site was found, which housed multiple classes.</p>
<p>As the town grew and prospered with boat building, there was a need for a larger school. So an academy style school was designed and through the funds raised by members of the community and, believe it or not, it cost only $16,000 to build this school which still stands today - today when we're building schools we're talking millions and millions of dollars, and this structure is still standing and it is strong.</p>
<p>Many people have graduated from that school; many notable MLAs have graduated from that school. The Honourable Bruce Cochrane was a graduate of that school; we have two former Home and School presidents from that school who were MLAs - Lila O'Connor, a Liberal MLA in 1993, and Pam Birdsall, who was the previous member for the Lunenburg constituency - she was a Home and School president who has served here in this House. I've been the treasurer of the Mahone Bay Home and School, and not a Home and School president until the doors closed and we moved on to Bayview.</p>
<p>We have had two Rhodes Scholars who have graduated from that school and we have recognized sports teams that have won provincial tournaments. We've had incredible people who have gone on to do great and wonderful things.</p>
<p>In 2000, the school closed its doors as an education facility, and it was empty for about two years until a group of citizens took over the school. Instead of demolishing the structure, they revitalized this building, and it is now called the Mahone Bay Centre, which houses many community events. It has really become the heart of Mahone Bay. It facilitates a large gathering of seniors. We have an incredible seniors project, which does lunches; it organizes SCANS, which is the university for seniors in Nova Scotia; a conversation series. We have the Alternate School from the South Shore Regional School Board housed there. We have all sorts of dance classes. We have a faith community that uses the facility, and many, many community groups near and far.</p>
<p>We are really a role model for some of these vacant buildings that have been established in the area. We've made it a success. But it's only been a success through the volunteers that have come on the board of directors, have volunteered their time, their talents. We are fortunate in Mahone Bay because we have a large number of retired persons who take their knowledge from their previous careers, bring it forward and have helped to find the financial means to keep going. They network with other people. We've received wonderful grants, we've received great fundraising opportunities and these people have given their hearts and souls to everything from raising funds to painting walls and scraping floors.</p>
<p>This year, the board of directors is pleased to be celebrating the 100<sup>th</sup> Anniversary of the Mahone Bay school and they will be celebrating many times. They've already begun with an information and potluck session. There will be an exhibit of old memorabilia and history of the Mahone Bay school. There will be a gala ball for people who are connected now and those who were connected previously to the Mahone Bay school.</p>
<p>The highlight, I think, of the whole year's events will be the reunion weekend, which is planned for July 4<sup>th</sup>, 5<sup>th</sup> and 6<sup>th</sup>, where graduates and volunteers, former staff, parents - anyone who has any connection to the old Mahone Bay school as it was as an education facility, or those who are connected to it now through its role as a community centre. We will host many events during that weekend, and we expect up to 2,000 people to attend some of these events. We are really looking forward to it.</p>
<p>I would like to take this opportunity to wish the Mahone Bay Centre board of directors and their committee all the best in the celebration and in recognizing that you don't have to start with something new to have something good. You can take something that's been well established and just have a vision and keep it going, and that's what the people of Mahone Bay have done with this wonderful structure. Thank you.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Order, please.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>3:59 p.m. The House resolved itself into a CW on Supply with Deputy Speaker Ms. Margaret Miller in the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <narrative>
          <p>5:57 p.m. CW on Supply rose and the House reconvened with Deputy Speaker Margaret Miller in the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The Chairman of the Committee of the Whole on Supply reports:</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined">
          <from>THE CLERK</from>
          <p>That the committee has met, has made some progress, and begs leave to sit again.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>We have reached the moment of interruption. The topic for tonight's late debate was submitted by the honourable member for Sydney River-Mira-Louisbourg and is:</p>
<p>"Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly urge the Liberal Government to recognize the excellent services provided by Roots for Youth Society and to provide the organization with funding to ensure Pictou County youth who are homeless get the support and services they need."</p></speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>ADJOURNMENT</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>MOTION UNDER RULE 5(5)</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Pictou Centre.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>ROOTS FOR YOUTH SOC.: FUNDING - PROVIDE</heading>
          <speech by="#71280477-3de0-4cef-90bd-e23864226ad3"><from>HON. PAT DUNN</from><p>Madam Speaker, Roots for Youth provides crucial supports for young people struggling with homelessness in northern Nova Scotia. Since their official opening in 2011, they have helped hundreds of young people by giving them a safe place to stay and providing the necessary support services. In March 2014 alone, they have assisted well into the hundreds of young people with a variety of issues.</p>
<p>Roots for Youth understands the need to address the deeper issues around homelessness including abuse, criminal behaviour, violence and drug addiction. Some of the programs they offer, Madam Speaker, include: Girl Talk, How I Roll, suicide prevention, self-esteem, life skill development and pride and future goals.</p>
<p>Roots for Youth has been such a success that local area high schools like North Nova Education Centre and the Northumberland Regional High School have asked for their programs along with requests from organizations in Halifax to adopt some of their programs.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, their impact is far-reaching and effective. These results speak for themselves and the government should recognize that. Government departments have relied on the services provided by Roots for Youth since its opening. The Department of Community Services, the Department of Justice and the local health authority have all required support from this wonderful organization. This has been done with very little financial assistance from the government. The minister knows that Roots for Youth provides incredibly vital services to help youth get back on their feet. The organization is trying to do the same as they work toward becoming self-sustainable.</p>
<p>Many issues that were mentioned before - abuse, broken family units, drugs, potential for ending up in the justice system - are all things that we are worried about if this particular facility has to close. After being involved with youth over the past 40 years as a school teacher, as a hockey coach and also as an MLA, I feel strongly that a facility like this in northern Nova Scotia is essential. I guess it's the old saying: pay now or pay later.</p>
<p>This facility, although only open a short time, since 2011, has been incredibly successful with regard to the number of youth that it has helped. One thing that did happen in our community during the past three years is the fact that it really wasn't known the number of homeless youth that did exist in the Counties of Pictou, Antigonish and Guysborough. After this facility opened its doors and we had the staff to look after it, we finally realized the numbers were a lot higher than we had anticipated.</p>
<p>In closing, I hope the government will take a strong look at this facility and provide the necessary funds, like they did for a ship in Yarmouth, to keep this facility open and look after the youth in northern Nova Scotia. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Sackville-Beaver Bank.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#c9bfa1a9-47ac-4d47-b492-7496e858718c"><from>MR. STEPHEN GOUGH</from><p>Madam Speaker, I would like to thank the member for Sydney River-Mira-Louisbourg for presenting this resolution for late debate.</p>
<p>Homelessness, particularly with regard to how it affects our youth, is always concerning and should be placed in the forefront of our minds. It's always tragic when we see youth who are unable to find shelter. We know some of the root causes for homelessness are family breakdowns, violence, mental illness and a limited availability of affordable housing. We know the issue of homelessness knows no boundaries. Last year a report entitled Halifax Report Card on Homelessness in HRM cited that the number of homeless people in this region increased by 8 per cent.</p>
<p>Housing is a basic human right, and our government is working with stakeholders from the Affordable Housing Association, Shelter Nova Scotia and other organizations to ensure we are addressing the areas of greatest need. Housing Nova Scotia will continue to invest approximately $450,000 in the Housing Support Worker program to help transition homeless individuals or individuals at risk of homelessness into stable, long-term housing options. Last year, the Housing Support Worker program helped 590 individuals transition to more permanent housing options. Investments are also being made this year in SHYFT in Tri-County, which offers outreach support to homeless and at-risk youth in Digby, Shelburne and Yarmouth Counties. The investment in SHYFT amounts to $350,000 in annual funding.</p>
<p>As alluded to before, our government is committed to working with organizations to address this problem. The Minister of Community Services recently stated in an opinion editorial that it's this government's role to ensure we give the best possible service with the resources we have available. That is why the minister's department is working on a new process to ensure the tax dollars of Nova Scotians are being spent in the most effective way possible, and account for how our tax dollars are being used.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, at this time I would like to conclude my remarks by saying we should always do as much as we can to help the most vulnerable in Nova Scotia, and our government will continue to work with stakeholders to address this issue. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Chester-St. Margaret's.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#980981f9-4823-4d4b-8134-a47d4ecf5405"><from>HON. DENISE PETERSON-RAFUSE</from><p>I also want to speak on homelessness and youth homelessness, and I want to remind the member opposite that it was the NDP Government that created the homelessness outreach program, which in the first 18 months here in Halifax saw approximately 280 individuals getting homes, and now I understand it's well over 500. That is a program that is showing great success, and I'm proud that as the Minister of Community Services I could bring that to the people of Nova Scotia. (Applause)</p>
<p>I want to also give some background information on the situation with youth homelessness, and I'll start with a little bit of a story about SHYFT in Yarmouth. I do understand, in terms of the board of directors and the community in the Yarmouth area, how important it was to go forward to tackle the issues of homelessness. However, it is important to know that as the previous Minister of Community Services I worked very closely with staff and the community and the board of directors in terms of the direction that they were to take, or should take, in creating a 24/7 homeless residence for youth in the Yarmouth area.</p>
<p>What often happens, Madam Speaker, that people do not realize, is the federal government comes forward with these nice big cheques that are only to be used for capital purchases. Then what happens is, when a program is established in a community, they find their place of residence - say, for example, SHYFT - and then they quickly find that they do not have the ability to sustain that operation and the operational cost.</p>
<p>Therefore, if the federal government is offering these dollars, which people are very happy to receive, there has to be a strategy to continue the sustainability. They start something and then they run pretty quickly, and that is with any federal program. Therefore, when we worked with the SHYFT organization, it was only several years ago that they came to us with this idea, and the staff at Community Services - the same staff that our minister today is working with - advised the minister of the day, which was myself, and also other staff people, that this was not a good route to take in terms of offering a 24/7. It was the overnight aspect of SHYFT that they did not feel was going to be sustainable.</p>
<p>The other piece of advice that was given was, please do not purchase the big Victorian home that you want to offer this service from. It was an older home, and the cost to maintain that is just something that they would not be able to sustain in a smaller rural community.</p>
<p>The whole idea at that time was to work on a completely different model, very similar to the model that we established here in Halifax as an outreach model that provided wraparound services for our youth. There is also another organization in Yarmouth called Split Rock, and they do a great amount of work in terms of youth at risk and youth homelessness. The whole suggestion and plan was that SHYFT would work with the community resources that already existed, become collaborative in its approach. I met with the board of directors, and they agreed to this. It was only about two weeks later that we saw in the media that they decided they didn't want to go that route and they wanted to be able to offer the 24/7.</p>
<p>The other important factor was that not only was this not what we had advised but that they did come to the Department of Community Services several times for operational dollars and we did give them those dollars - it was in the hundreds of thousands of dollars - to keep them going because we did not want any youth to be homeless.</p>
<p>We made several recommendations to them such as utilizing the expertise at the local community college with a social services program and a nursing program to bring staff in to do the overnight, if that was their desire. But in terms of offering a 24/7 service, it would set a precedent for the rest of the province. Our direction was to be more of a holistic approach and getting at the core of the issue with youth homelessness.</p>
<p>I do know that the people will say, well you support Phoenix House here in Halifax, which is a 24/7. The difference with that is that they are well established and they have a huge capacity to raise funds within the HRM area, so it's a striking difference. That doesn't work in rural Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>Now we have a situation where the new Liberal Government came in and provided $350,000 to SHYFT, which, I've been told by the minister, will be on an annual basis. At the same time it was what we feared in terms of - you have other communities throughout Nova Scotia that have similar issues with youth homelessness and right away we're talking about the program in the Pictou area, Roots for Youth Society, who actually have been in existence way longer than SHYFT, who has never come to government for support and now when they need it, they may not get it.</p>
<p>The minister said she would meet with them sometime in May but that could very well be too late for those youth because of the fact that the executive director and some volunteers are now trying to keep this program going for those youth. It is very unfortunate that youth have been drawn into patronage and political support because the minister in Budget Estimates actually said to me several times that it was a political decision but one that she supports.</p>
<p>Now I am not going to take one bit away from all the work that has been done by SHYFT, the wonderful staff, the great board of directors they have, but sometimes when we're in these leadership roles we have to be strong in the sense that if we know it is not a fair direction or the direction that those youth need, we need to stand tall and say no, I'm sorry, we need to work this out.</p>
<p>The Department of Community Services and its staff had alternative means for housing for the few youth who were staying over the 24/7. I think there were roughly three or four at a time, if that - that probably was the highest number. Now in the province we have a situation where the door has been open to the rest of those who need support for youth, in particular the Pictou Roots for Youth Society.</p>
<p>I would stress that it's very important and necessary for the minister and for the government to provide financial support so their doors can be open tomorrow, with the staff complement they need. How can you make a political decision on the backs of youth in Yarmouth? (Interruption) Access 808 is another youth program. We could go through a long list of rural communities that need financial support with youth homelessness and youth at risk. We must follow a model that is consistent across the province.</p>
<p>It's very sad that a political decision was based - and the money, $350,000 on an annual basis - and it all came down to politics. What a shame. Does that mean that those youth in Pictou are being punished because of the fact that the people of Nova Scotia, in that county, chose to go with a different political Party?</p>
<p>We've seen so many of these things happen in less than six or seven months of this government - patronage, patronage, patronage. This time it has happened on the backs of youth in this province by providing political funding. Thank you very much, Madam Speaker.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>HON. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Madam Speaker, on a point of order. I wasn't sure the member was finished, but I think she was saying things that were frankly wrong and unparliamentary really to even suggest that one person (Interruption) it's not mine, do you want me to move over one? Sorry. Thank you. As you know it's estimates time and my desk has been used by someone else - and the former Speaker might know that.</p>
<p>As I say, I really think that it is important to correct the record and to ask you to rule on whether or not that was parliamentary to even consider that there's some sort of punitive measures going on in any county in any area of this province. That's absolutely false. The Minister of Community Services answered the question today about this program, and she's certainly going to visit and she said so, and there's absolutely nothing that's political about this decision and I think that should be retracted. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Leader of the New Democratic Party.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9">
            <from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I'm rising on the supposed point of order to essentially say that in my view that was not a point of order. We have a disagreement between members about a set of facts. With respect to what was unparliamentary, that also, I think, is not substantiated by what generally would be seen as being not parliamentary.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>I would have to agree on that point. I believe it is just a dispute between the two parties and a disagreement in terminology.</p>
<p>The time for the late debate has expired.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
          <narrative>
            <p>6:17 p.m. The House resolved itself into a CW on Supply with Deputy Speaker Ms. Margaret Miller in the Chair.</p>
          </narrative>
          <narrative>
            <p>8:31 p.m. CW on Supply rose and the House reconvened with Deputy Speaker Ms. Margaret Miller in the Chair.</p>
          </narrative>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The Chairman of the Committee of the Whole on Supply reports:</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined">
            <from>THE CLERK</from>
            <p>That the committee has met and made some progress and begs leave to sit again.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>It is agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#34c1e608-d873-4164-95f2-86ccabbc60e9">
            <from>MR. TERRY FARRELL</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I call on the member for Sydney River-Mira-Louisburg to call Opposition business for tomorrow.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Acting Deputy House Leader of the Official Opposition. (Applause)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#e23caf06-dcf3-42a5-8a00-f4435df40350"><from>MR. ALFIE MACLEOD</from><p>That's only because they know now when I finish we're going home.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, tomorrow, after we do the daily routine and Orders of the Day, Oral Questions Put By Members to Ministers, we will follow that with Bill No. 8, the Nova Scotia Jobs Fund Transfer Act, and Bill No. 46.</p>
<p>I'll now turn it back to the Deputy Government House Leader to call the hours for tomorrow.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#34c1e608-d873-4164-95f2-86ccabbc60e9"><from>MR. TERRY FARRELL</from><p>Madam Speaker, I move that the hours for tomorrow be from 2:00 p.m. to 6:00 p.m.</p>
<p>I move that the House do now rise and meet again tomorrow from 2:00 p.m. to 6:00 p.m.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the House rise to meet again tomorrow between the hours of 2:00 p.m. and 6:00 p.m.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>We stand adjourned until 2:00 p.m. tomorrow.</p></speech>
          <narrative>
            <p>The House rose at 8:32 p.m.</p>
          </narrative>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION UNDER RULE 32(3)</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1152">RESOLUTION NO. 1152</num>
          <speech by="af446054-6fe0-422a-94d6-7cdff4623b7e"><from>Hon. Joanne Bernard</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Destination Imagination is an educational program that gives students the chance to learn and experience the creative process from imagination to innovation; and</p>
<p>Whereas for the first time, a team from Crichton Park Elementary calling themselves the Lollipop Bandits, made up of three Grade 6 students and four Grade 5 students, competed and won in the Fine Arts category in the regional challenge; and</p>
<p>Whereas the team used the Mona Lisa as a springboard for an entirely new art piece and have been the first Halifax Regional School Board team invited to participate in the global competition in Knoxville, Tennessee;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating the seven members of the Lollipop Bandits of Crichton Park Elementary School and wish them every success on their trip to Knoxville in May 2014.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1153">RESOLUTION NO. 1153</num>
          <speech by="aef785d7-7697-4453-8f9c-eef26e4928c3"><from>Hon. Keith Colwell</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Cinera States was raised in Ontario but now lives with her grandmother in North Preston; and</p>
<p>Whereas Cinera graduated with her Bachelor of Science degree with a double major in biology and psychology from Dalhousie University in 2012 and has been accepted in Dalhousie Medical School and intends to remain in Nova Scotia after graduation to practise paediatric medicine; and</p>
<p>Whereas for five years, Cinera has mentored young students in an after-school program that aims to increase the number of African Nova Scotians pursuing post-secondary education in the fields of science, technology and engineering;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House recognize and congratulate Cinera States for her many accomplishments and for the good work she has done in mentoring youth in her community.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1154">RESOLUTION NO. 1154</num>
          <speech by="aef785d7-7697-4453-8f9c-eef26e4928c3"><from>Hon. Keith Colwell</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Brenda Galbraith was born and raised in Sudbury, Ontario, and joined the Canada Armed Forces at the age of 18 years and, after completing her training, was posted to Ottawa, where she met and married her husband and together they raised their son; and</p>
<p>Whereas Brenda Galbraith volunteered throughout her career, and was a member of the Critical Incident Response Team and worked with Dr. Butt following the Swiss Air Disaster with the Dental Forensic Team, to which 90 of the identifications were attributed; and</p>
<p>Whereas Brenda was responsible for designing a kids' first aid course, aptly named <i>I Can Help</i>, and which is still used to this very day, and for this Brenda received the Order of St. John, the second-highest honour a military person can receive;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House recognize the significant contributions that Brenda has made to her province and to her country as she now enjoys a well-deserved early retirement in Lake Echo, Nova Scotia.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1155">RESOLUTION NO. 1155</num>
          <speech by="4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>Hon. Jamie Baillie</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas one year ago today, we were devastated when what should have been a joyous occasion turned to tragedy at the Boston Marathon; and</p>
<p>Whereas today we remember those who lost their lives to senseless violence and show our lasting gratitude to those volunteers and bystanders who, at the darkest time, showed the world that human kindness endures; and</p>
<p>Whereas we will never forget what happened on this day, and while we honour those families impacted, we believe that the Boston Marathon is still a symbol of hope and determination;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly remember those whose lives were lost one year ago today, and the bravery shown by the volunteers and citizens who intervened to help those in need.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1156">RESOLUTION NO. 1156</num>
          <speech by="bc54523e-7553-4c28-b315-79d18165339b"><from>Mr. John Lohr</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Kentville Wildcats Division Three Bantam Girls basketball team recently captured a bronze medal in provincial championship play; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Wildcats, in an exceptionally close game, edged the Kennetcook Cannons 42-41 to claim the bronze medal in a championship tournament which featured six other teams; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Wildcats were led to their provincial championship by Head Coach Russ Payne;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly applaud the efforts of Russ Payne and his Bantam Division Three Kentville Wildcats on a memorable season and for being the third-best team in the province in their age category.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1157">RESOLUTION NO. 1157</num>
          <speech by="5dac0dde-7ef3-4f75-a137-834785ff1ae4"><from>Mr. Tim Houston</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Donald Sobey has recently been named to the Order of Canada for his contributions as a philanthropist and entrepreneur, notably for founding one of Canada's leading awards for young artists; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Order of Canada is one of the country's highest civilian honours to recognize outstanding achievement, dedication to the community and service to the nation; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Governor General of Canada has acknowledged all of those characteristics and more in Mr. Sobey;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Mr. Sobey on this well-deserved appointment and thank him for his many contributions to Nova Scotia.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1158">RESOLUTION NO. 1158</num>
          <speech by="5dac0dde-7ef3-4f75-a137-834785ff1ae4"><from>Mr. Tim Houston</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the school year is winding down, and Nova Scotia Community College graduates will soon be entering the workforce; and</p>
<p>Whereas the students of the leadership class at the Stellarton Campus know that having the appropriate wardrobe is essential for work terms and employment; and</p>
<p>Whereas these women invited students and staff to donate professional attire and accessories to be sold for $1 and $3 to ensure the graduates could put their best foot forward as they begin their new careers;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate these women who had the vision to make the transition from school to the workplace as seamless as possible for the graduates.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1159">RESOLUTION NO. 1159</num>
          <speech by="2c4ef79f-acb1-4c92-8ff4-e6bfac04ddc0"><from>Ms. Karla MacFarlane</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Stones Superior Homes Limited, located on the Westville Road, Pictou County, has been awarded the 2013 Pictou County Chamber of Commerce Large Business of the Year Recognition Award; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Stone family has worked hard to diversity their company, including RV sales and service, and as a dealer for Prestige Homes; and</p>
<p>Whereas Stones Superior Homes Limited has experienced significant growth over the past three years, employing 40 persons, positively impacting the Pictou County economy;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Stones Superior Homes Limited and the Stone family on receiving this award and wish them continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1160">RESOLUTION NO. 1160</num>
          <speech by="fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5"><from>Hon. Stephen McNeil</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Brenda Thompson of the Women's Place Resource Centre, Annapolis Royal, has recently been named vice-president of Canada Without Poverty, a national group dedicated to eradicating poverty; and</p>
<p>Whereas Brenda's commitment to addressing issues such as homelessness and food insecurity, combined with her energy and enthusiasm, made her a shoe-in for the job; and</p>
<p>Whereas she is proud of the work that this group is doing to raise awareness around homelessness, the plight of First Nations communities and poverty eradication in Canada;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Brenda Thompson on her recent appointment and wish her success in her future endeavours.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1161">RESOLUTION NO. 1161</num>
          <speech by="d20d446c-118f-4445-81f4-cf995b335391"><from>Hon. Randy Delorey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the CACL Antigonish Workshop is celebrating 40 years of providing vocational programming for people with disabilities; and</p>
<p>Whereas the workshop has more than 70 clients who lend a hand in the bakery, wood shop, print shop or any of the other contracts being done, and each participant has a program tailored to his or her needs; and</p>
<p>Whereas the CACL also has a community employment component, meaning clients are hired at local business and organizations and therefore working in the broader community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the CACL Antigonish Workshop on 40 years of offering service to its clients and the community of Antigonish.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1162">RESOLUTION NO. 1162</num>
          <speech by="2c4ef79f-acb1-4c92-8ff4-e6bfac04ddc0"><from>Ms. Karla MacFarlane</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas 19-year-old Hailey Scotland, of River John, won national awards at the 4-H Royal in Toronto; and</p>
<p>Whereas Hailey competed and won in showmanship and conformation in the Junior Heifer and Overall Shorthorn categories; and</p>
<p>Whereas this was the first time anyone from Nova Scotia has ever won an overall breed category;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Hailey Scotland on her hard work and dedication that ultimately resulted in the winning of these two national awards, and wish her all the best in her future endeavours.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1163">RESOLUTION NO. 1163</num>
          <speech by="0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de"><from>Ms. Margaret Miller</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Averill Scott Barkhouse, of West Core, passed away January 9, 2014, at Windsor, Nova Scotia; and</p>
<p>Whereas despite becoming a paraplegic at the age of 20, Averill began painting and developing his latent artistic talents, which the community was able to enjoy for over 20 years; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Barkhouse was renowned mouth painter, capturing the beauty of everyday life - especially that of rural Nova Scotia;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly express their condolences to the Barkhouse family.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1164">RESOLUTION NO. 1164</num>
          <speech by="71280477-3de0-4cef-90bd-e23864226ad3"><from>Hon. Pat Dunn</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Nova Scotia Community College, Pictou Campus, is celebrating its 50<sup>th</sup> Anniversary; and</p>
<p>Whereas in 50 years as an educational institution, the NSCC has helped to develop and hone the skills of thousands of students who have gone on to make changes and improvements in their fields of expertise; and</p>
<p>Whereas NSCC has maintained their exemplary level of instruction and operation through the decades of change;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Principal Dave Freckelton and his staff of instructors, administration and maintenance for their continued professionalism and dedication to the students past, present and, most importantly, the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1165">RESOLUTION NO. 1165</num>
          <speech by="72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7"><from>Mr. Chuck Porter</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Newport and District Rink Commission is managed by a strong group of volunteers who are presently involved with ensuring major renovations to the facility are completed; and</p>
<p>Whereas besides the major renovations scheduled or already completed, the management group is always looking at innovative ways to enhance visits to the facility and were the recent recipients of a $3,000 gift certificate from Canadian Tire by ensuring a helmet policy is mandatory, in turn wanting to create healthier families and prevent injuries; and</p>
<p>Whereas just recently the commission members became part of the provincial program known as the playing strong, eating healthy menu program that was launched in late February and now includes veggie chili, hummus, pretzels, baked potatoes, and a variety of other healthy foods including apple slices and yogurt;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize the tremendous work being done by the staff of the Newport and District Rink Commission and executive members in President Garnet Davison, Vice-President Darrin Verge, Secretary/Treasurer Phyllis Blanchard, and Directors Barry Bruce-Payne, Andrew Blanchard, Bruce Fletcher, Wayne Lunn, Lawrence Tupper, Mel Caldwell, Lloyd Anthony, Robert and Darrell Wainman, and Michael Mackenzie, while wishing them every continued success.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1166">RESOLUTION NO. 1166</num>
          <speech by="e23caf06-dcf3-42a5-8a00-f4435df40350"><from>Mr. Alfie MacLeod</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Adam Mugridge of Marion Bridge, project development manager for Natural Oceans Products, was the winner of the InNOVAcorp Ocean Technology Sector Award at the I-3 Technology Competition; and</p>
<p>Whereas this prize includes a $25,000 cash award and was earned by the company by creating a new way to extract the nutritious elements of seaweed in a natural way; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Mugridge has said the award makes the hard work they've put into the project worthwhile;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Adam Mugridge and Natural Oceans Products, which is a subsidiary of Louisbourg Seafoods, on winning this award.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1167">RESOLUTION NO. 1167</num>
          <speech by="1e5b7bdc-363b-4df4-8258-edcf8f2bf7fb"><from>Hon. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Bernie Gunning, a resident of the Dartmouth East riding and long-time member of the Nova Scotia Liberal Party and Liberal Party of Canada, has been an important local Party volunteer; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Dartmouth East Liberal Association is a group of members, supporters, and volunteers who share a Liberal vision of a prosperous, socially just, united, and environmentally health community and country; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 29, 2014, the Dartmouth-Cole Harbour Federal Liberal Association presented Bernie Gunning with a Volunteer Appreciation Award;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in thanking Bernie Gunning for his tireless hours of support and dedication to the Dartmouth East Liberal Association and wish him every success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1168">RESOLUTION NO. 1168</num>
          <speech by="1e5b7bdc-363b-4df4-8258-edcf8f2bf7fb"><from>Hon. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Gary Johnson, a resident of the Dartmouth East riding and coach at City of Lakes Boxing Club, has coached, mentored, and provided leadership to hundreds of at-risk youth; and</p>
<p>Whereas City of Lakes Boxing Club has produced a world amateur champion, two Olympic athletes, a junior Olympic champion, 20 National Canadian title holders, and a number one World Heavy Weight professional boxer; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Dartmouth Community Health Board honoured Gary Johnson with an award for his 35 years of volunteer work within the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in thanking Gary Johnson for his tireless hours of volunteer support and dedication to youth in boxing, and wish him every success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1169">RESOLUTION NO. 1169</num>
          <speech by="e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>Mr. Eddie Orrell</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas seven students from the Munro Academy in Sydney Mines have left to spend seven days at the Cayo Deaf Institute in Belize to participate in activities such as class work, farming, chores, meal preparation, cleanup, yard work, and church services; and</p>
<p>Whereas the students have been studying Spanish and learning sign language in preparation for the trip; and</p>
<p>Whereas they held fundraisers to purchase computers for the school, where they will be setting up a computer network for the students;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate these students for their Christian generosity, outreach, and compassion.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1170">RESOLUTION NO. 1170</num>
          <speech by="0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de"><from>Ms. Margaret Miller</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Municipality of East Hants recognized the contributions and commitments of volunteers during their Annual Volunteer Recognition Awards on April 25, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas Alice Gould of Walton was recognized for her volunteer efforts and dedication to the Walton and Area Development Association; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers such as Ms. Gould are the backbone of our communities, providing countless hours of devoted service;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly recognize Alice Gould's contributions and thank her for her tireless volunteer efforts.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1171">RESOLUTION NO. 1171</num>
          <speech by="0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de"><from>Ms. Margaret Miller</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Municipality of East Hants recognized the contributions and commitments of volunteers during their Annual Volunteer Recognition Awards on April 25, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas Al Watson Gould of Elmsdale was recognized for his volunteer efforts and dedication to Upper Nine Mile River; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers such as Mr. Gould are the backbone of our communities, providing countless hours of devoted service;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly recognize Al Watson Gould's contributions and thank him for his tireless volunteer efforts.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1172">RESOLUTION NO. 1172</num>
          <speech by="0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de"><from>Ms. Margaret Miller</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Municipality of East Hants recognized the contributions and commitments of volunteers during their Annual Volunteer Recognition Awards on April 25, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas Chester van der Kooi was recognized for his volunteer efforts and dedication to the Upper Nine Mile River Community Hall Association; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers such as Mr. van der Kooi are the backbone of our communities, providing countless hours of devoted service;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly recognize Chester van der Kooi's contributions and thank him for his tireless volunteer efforts.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1173">RESOLUTION NO. 1173</num>
          <speech by="0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de"><from>Ms. Margaret Miller</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Municipality of East Hants recognized the contributions and commitments of volunteers during their Annual Volunteer Recognition Awards on April 25, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas Avis Pick of Greenfield was recognized for his volunteer efforts and dedication to the Rawdon Hills Community Health Board; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers such as Mr. Pick are the backbone of our communities, providing countless hours of devoted service;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly recognize Avis Pick's contributions and thank him for his tireless volunteer efforts.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1174">RESOLUTION NO. 1174</num>
          <speech by="0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de"><from>Ms. Margaret Miller</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Municipality of East Hants recognized the contributions and commitments of volunteers during their Annual Volunteer Recognition Awards on April 25, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas Cecile Lloy of Lantz was recognized for her volunteer efforts and dedication to Maple Ridge Elementary School; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers such as Ms. Lloy are the backbone of our communities, providing countless hours of devoted service;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly recognize Cecile Lloy's contributions and thank her for her tireless volunteer efforts.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1175">RESOLUTION NO. 1175</num>
          <speech by="0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de"><from>Ms. Margaret Miller</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Municipality of East Hants recognized the contributions and commitments of volunteers during their Annual Volunteer Recognition Awards on April 25, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas Corinne Williams of Kennetcook was recognized for her volunteer efforts and dedication to the Hants North Community Food Bank; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers such as Ms. Williams are the backbone of our communities, providing countless hours of devoted service;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly recognize Corinne Williams' contributions and thank her for her tireless volunteer efforts.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1176">RESOLUTION NO. 1176</num>
          <speech by="0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de"><from>Ms. Margaret Miller</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Municipality of East Hants recognized the contributions and commitments of volunteers during their Annual Volunteer Recognition Awards on April 25, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas David Lewis of Enfield was recognized for his volunteer efforts and dedication to the East Hants Community Rider; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers such as Mr. David Lewis are the backbone of our communities, providing countless hours of devoted service;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly recognize Mr. Lewis' contributions and thank him for his tireless volunteer efforts.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1177">RESOLUTION NO. 1177</num>
          <speech by="0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de"><from>Ms. Margaret Miller</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Municipality of East Hants recognized the contributions and commitments of volunteers during their Annual Volunteer Recognition Awards on April 25, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas Denise Crowe of Maitland was recognized for her volunteer efforts and dedication to the Cobequid 4-H Club; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers such as Ms. Crowe are the backbone of our communities, providing countless hours of devoted service;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly recognize Denise Crowe's contributions and thank her for her tireless volunteer efforts.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1178">RESOLUTION NO. 1178</num>
          <speech by="0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de"><from>Ms. Margaret Miller</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Municipality of East Hants recognized the contributions and commitments of volunteers during their Annual Volunteer Recognition Awards on April 25, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas the management and staff of Enfield Home Hardware were recognized for their volunteer efforts and dedication to the Caring and Sharing Angel Tree Food Bank; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers are the backbone of our communities, providing countless hours of devoted service;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly recognize contributions of Enfield Home Hardware and thank them for their tireless volunteer efforts.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1179">RESOLUTION NO. 1179</num>
          <speech by="0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de"><from>Ms. Margaret Miller</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Municipality of East Hants recognized the contributions and commitments of volunteers during their Annual Volunteer Recognition Awards on April 25, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas Gerry Walsh was recognized for her volunteer efforts and dedication to the 1<sup>st</sup> Enfield Scouts; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers such as Ms. Walsh are the backbone of our communities, providing countless hours of devoted service;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize Gerry Walsh's contributions and thank her for her tireless volunteer efforts.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1180">RESOLUTION NO. 1180</num>
          <speech by="0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de"><from>Ms. Margaret Miller</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Municipality of East Hants recognized the contributions and commitments of volunteers during their Annual Volunteer Recognition Awards on April 25, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas Janet Savary of Elmsdale was recognized for her volunteer efforts and dedication to the East Hants Family Resource Centre; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers such as Ms. Savary are the backbone of our communities, providing countless hours of devoted service;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize Janet Savary's contributions and thank her for her tireless volunteer efforts.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1181">RESOLUTION NO. 1181</num>
          <speech by="0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de"><from>Ms. Margaret Miller</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Municipality of East Hants recognized the contributions and commitments of volunteers during their Annual Volunteer Recognition Awards on April 25, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas John McMullen of Milford was recognized for his volunteer efforts and dedication to the Milford and District Lions Club; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers such as Mr. McMullen are the backbone of our communities, providing countless hours of devoted service;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize Mr. McMullen's contributions and thank him for his tireless volunteer efforts.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1182">RESOLUTION NO. 1182</num>
          <speech by="0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de"><from>Ms. Margaret Miller</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Municipality of East Hants recognized the contributions and commitments of volunteers during their Annual Volunteer Recognition Awards on April 25, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas Kirsten Belanger of Upper Rawdon was recognized for her volunteer efforts and dedication to the Rawdon District Home and School Association; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers such as Ms. Belanger are the backbone of our communities, providing countless hours of devoted service;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize Kirsten Belanger's contributions and thank her for her tireless volunteer efforts.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1183">RESOLUTION NO. 1183</num>
          <speech by="0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de"><from>Ms. Margaret Miller</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Municipality of East Hants recognized the contributions and commitments of volunteers during their Annual Volunteer Recognition Awards on April 25, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas Leona Ross of Gore was recognized for her volunteer efforts and dedication to the Upper Nine Mile River Homemakers' Women's Institute; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers such as Ms. Ross are the backbone of our communities, providing countless hours of devoted service;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize Leona Ross' contributions and thank her for her tireless volunteer efforts.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1184">RESOLUTION NO. 1184</num>
          <speech by="0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de"><from>Ms. Margaret Miller</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Municipality of East Hants recognized the contributions and commitments of volunteers during their Annual Volunteer Recognition Awards on April 25, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas Marilyn Babineau-Doucette of Shubenacadie was recognized for her volunteer efforts and dedication to the 1<sup>st</sup> Enfield Scouts; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers such as Ms. Babineau-Doucette are the backbone of our communities, providing countless hours of devoted service;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize Marilyn Babineau-Doucette's contributions and thank her for her tireless volunteer efforts.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1185">RESOLUTION NO. 1185</num>
          <speech by="0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de"><from>Ms. Margaret Miller</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Municipality of East Hants recognized the contributions and commitments of volunteers during their Annual Volunteer Recognition Awards on April 25, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas Tom Hunter of Enfield was recognized for his volunteer efforts and dedication to Elmsdale Lumber; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers such as Mr. Hunter are the backbone of our communities, providing countless hours of devoted service;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize Tom Hunter's contributions and thank him for his tireless volunteer efforts.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1186">RESOLUTION NO. 1186</num>
          <speech by="0b7af00d-43e4-452a-84f1-4e982155e7de"><from>Ms. Margaret Miller</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Municipality of East Hants recognized the contributions and commitments of volunteers during their Annual Volunteer Recognition Awards on April 25, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas Trudy Hiltz of Mount Uniacke was recognized for her volunteer efforts and dedication to the Girl Guides of Canada - Carter District; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers such as Ms. Hiltz are the backbone of our communities, providing countless hours of devoted service;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize Trudy Hiltz's contributions and thank her for her tireless volunteer efforts.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
