<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.michel.p.samson" showAs="HON. MICHEL SAMSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.jamie.baillie" showAs="Hon. Jamie Baillie"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.maureen.macdonald" showAs="HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="bc54523e-7553-4c28-b315-79d18165339b" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.john.a.lohr" showAs="Mr. John Lohr"/>
        <TLCPerson id="34c1e608-d873-4164-95f2-86ccabbc60e9" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.terry.farrell" showAs="MR. TERRY FARRELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="5dac0dde-7ef3-4f75-a137-834785ff1ae4" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.tim.houston" showAs="Mr. Tim Houston"/>
        <TLCPerson id="e32945dc-539b-44e0-9a14-ec06f74edd6a" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.labi.kousoulis" showAs="HON. LABI KOUSOULIS"/>
        <TLCPerson id="2c4ef79f-acb1-4c92-8ff4-e6bfac04ddc0" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.karla.macfarlane" showAs="Ms. Karla MacFarlane"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MR. SPEAKER"/>
        <TLCRole id="clerk" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.clerk" showAs="THE CLERK"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 11 April 2014</docTitle>
      <docNumber>14-26</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2014-04-11">Friday, April 11, 2014</docDate>
      <docProponent>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docProponent>
      <legislature value="62">62nd General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="1">1st Session</session>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Order, please. Just prior to us starting the daily routine, as Speaker I do want to acknowledge the passing of former Sergeant-at-Arms Noel Knockwood, who passed away yesterday. Noel was our first Aboriginal Sergeant-at-Arms here at the House, serving the Legislature from 2000 to 2005.</p>
<p>Of course he was a well-known Mi'kmaq spiritual leader, a veteran of the Korean War, and a great, great Nova Scotian. I actually had the pleasure of meeting Noel several times as his grandchildren lived in my community of Lake Echo and he did attend our church where his grandchildren were. It was a very moving experience just in the two or three times that I did meet him and had occasion to spend a few minutes with him. I felt much calmer after spending a few minutes with Mr. Noel Knockwood.</p>
<p>So I would ask that all members of the House please rise and observe a moment of silence in honour of former Sergeant-at-Arms Noel Knockwood.</p></speech>
      <narrative>
        <p>A moment of silence was observed.</p>
      </narrative>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>We will begin the daily routine.</p>
      </speech>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PRESENTING AND READING PETITIONS</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PRESENTING REPORTS OF COMMITTEES</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>TABLING REPORTS, REGULATIONS AND OTHER PAPERS</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>STATEMENTS BY MINISTERS</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>INTRODUCTION OF BILLS</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 49 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 293 of the Revised Statutes of 1989. The Motor Vehicle Act. (Hon. Geoff MacLellan)</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 50 - Entitled an Act to Amend and Consolidate the Acts Relating to St. Francis Xavier University. (Mr. Lloyd Hines)</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Ordered that these bills be read a second time on a future day.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of the Public Service Commission.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#e32945dc-539b-44e0-9a14-ec06f74edd6a">
          <from>HON. LABI KOUSOULIS</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, on an introduction. I'd like to take everyone's attention to the east gallery. We have with us Fergus Dearden, who is a new graduate of Saint Mary's University and has just authored a book called <i>The Coffee Shop Meditations</i>. A round of applause for our new author. (Applause)</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of the Public Service Commission.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1049">RESOLUTION NO. 1049</num>
          <speech by="#e32945dc-539b-44e0-9a14-ec06f74edd6a"><from>HON. LABI KOUSOULIS</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Fergus Dearden is a 2011 graduate of Saint Mary's University who battled tremendous adversity, authored <i>The Coffee Shop Meditations</i>, and founded the One Man on a Mission campaign to raise money for the Canadian Mental Health Association; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Dearden overcame a serious mood disorder, homelessness, and a gambling addiction to obtain two bachelor degrees and become a published author, and it is his goal to inspire others and give hope where they feel there is none; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Dearden is an inspirational example of the great potential of our graduates and those coping with mental illness;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize Fergus Dearden's exceptional achievements, dedication in the face of adversity, and outstanding contributions to our community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1050">RESOLUTION NO. 1050</num>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, on behalf of the Minister of Labour and Advanced Education, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the province has both adjudicative and non-adjudicative agencies, boards, and commissions in place to help government operate and serve the people of Nova Scotia; and</p>
<p>Whereas these agencies, boards, and commissions are made up of engaged citizens who volunteer their time and expertise; and</p>
<p>Whereas today marks the beginning of the Spring campaign asking Nova Scotians to apply for an agency, board, or commission;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House encourage people in their communities to volunteer to serve on one of Nova Scotia's 165 agencies, boards, and commissions.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the New Democratic Party.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1051">RESOLUTION NO. 1051</num>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Noel Knockwood's strength of character was evident from an early age as he overcame the struggles of the residential school system and fought in the trenches of the Korean War; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Knockwood used his own life lessons as tools to teach and mentor others - including members of the Legislature, as the first Mi'kmaq Sergeant-at-Arms, who many of us here were fortunate enough to meet; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Knockwood, a compassionate spiritual leader and elder, passed away yesterday at the age of 81;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this Legislature send our deepest condolences to Mr. Knockwood's family and community, and join them as they celebrate his life and many accomplishments.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>ORDERS OF THE DAY</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT BUSINESS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be">
          <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Government Motions.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT MOTIONS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be">
          <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, I move that you do now leave the Chair and the House resolve itself into a Committee of the Whole House on Supply unto Her Majesty.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion carried.</p>
<p>The House will now recess for one minute while we get set up for Supply.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>9:20 a.m. The House resolved itself into a CWH on Supply with Deputy Speaker Ms. Margaret Miller in the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <narrative>
          <p>1:44 p.m. CWH on Supply rose and the House reconvened with Deputy Speaker Ms. Margaret Miller in the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The Chairman of the Committee of the Whole House on Supply reports:</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined">
          <from>THE CLERK</from>
          <p>That the Committee of the Whole on Supply has met and made progress and begs leave to sit again.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#34c1e608-d873-4164-95f2-86ccabbc60e9"><from>MR. TERRY FARRELL</from><p>Madam Speaker, I move that the hours for Monday, April 14<sup>th</sup>, be 4:00 p.m. to 10:00 p.m. The order of business will be Government Business, Committee of the Whole House on Supply unto Her Majesty. If time permits we will call second reading of Bill Nos. 35, 40, 43, 44, and 45.</p>
<p>I move that the House do now rise to meet again from 4:00 p.m. to 10:00 p.m. on Monday, April 14<sup>th</sup>.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the House rise to meet again on April 14<sup>th</sup> between the hours of 4:00 p.m. and 10:00 p.m.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>We stand adjourned until Monday at 4:00 p.m. Please enjoy your weekend, everyone.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>The House rose at 1:45 p.m.</p>
        </narrative>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION UNDER RULE 32(3)</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1052">RESOLUTION NO. 1052</num>
          <speech by="#5dac0dde-7ef3-4f75-a137-834785ff1ae4"><from>Mr. Tim Houston</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the East Pictou Silver Blades held their annual ice show and awards banquet on March 4<sup>th</sup> at the Ivor MacDonald Memorial Arena in Thorburn, cheered on by a large crowd; and</p>
<p>Whereas there was great cause for celebration as all JumpStart, figure skaters and program assistants received certificates; and</p>
<p>Whereas special awards were presented to CanSkate Champions Quinn Lynch and Gabrielle Young; the Connie Frazee Memorial Award to Kaitlin Kelly; the Derrick Brightman Memorial Trophy to Sydney Swain; and the CanSkater of the Year was Adelle Thomsen;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate these deserving young skaters and wish them many more successful seasons on the ice.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1053">RESOLUTION NO. 1053</num>
          <speech by="#5dac0dde-7ef3-4f75-a137-834785ff1ae4"><from>Mr. Tim Houston</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Brenda Murphy's Grade Primary students at Dr. W.A. MacLeod Elementary School wore pink to celebrate Pink Shirt Day and to raise awareness about bullying and its effects; and</p>
<p>Whereas by starting at an early age, these students will be advocates for anti-bullying throughout their school life; and</p>
<p>Whereas they will be examples and role models of the message they learned in a short video entitled <i>How to be Kind to Each Other</i>;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate these students on their stand against bullying and thank them for embracing the anti-bullying message.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1054">RESOLUTION NO. 1054</num>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>Hon. Jamie Baillie</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Noel Knockwood, the first Aboriginal Sergeant-at-Arms, has passed away at the age of 81; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Knockwood was a survivor of the Shubenacadie Residential School, an author and a Korean War veteran, who generously told his story to high school and university students; and</p>
<p>Whereas Noel Knockwood was a keptin of the Mi'kmaq Grand Council and had served as the council's spiritual leader since 1974, was the recipient of a National Aboriginal Achievement Award for culture, heritage and spirituality, and will be remembered for ceremonially lifting the curse from the A. Murray MacKay Bridge at its opening;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly give thanks for the remarkable life of Noel Knockwood and send our most sincere condolences to his family, friends and loved ones.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1055">RESOLUTION NO. 1055</num>
          <speech by="#bc54523e-7553-4c28-b315-79d18165339b"><from>Mr. John Lohr</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Port Williams Hawks Bantam Girls Division IV basketball team captured a silver medal in provincial championship play this past weekend; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Hawks competed in the tournament with seven other teams before finally losing in the championship game; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Port Williams team has a dedicated group of enthusiastic layers in Kaitlyn and Errol Zwicker; Meghan, Margaret, and Heather MacLean; Caty Sweet; Addie Rand Smith; Lucy Wilkie; Emily Larkin; Michaela Rafuse; Brittany Dell; and Georgia Bauer;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the 2014 Port Williams Hawks Bantam Girls basketball team on capturing a silver medal at Basketball Provincials.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1056">RESOLUTION NO. 1056</num>
          <speech by="#bc54523e-7553-4c28-b315-79d18165339b"><from>Mr. John Lohr</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas each year Wealth Professional Magazine recognizes the Top 50 Financial Advisors in Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas the purpose of the list is to give recognition to Canada's most hard-working and successful advisors, whose dedication to the profession often gets overlooked; and</p>
<p>Whereas David Ritcey, a wealth advisor with ScotiaMcLeod in Kentville, was 45<sup>th</sup> on the Top 50 list for 2014;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate David Ritcey on being named to Wealth Professional Magazine's Top 50 List and wish him continued success in his career.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1057">RESOLUTION NO. 1057</num>
          <speech by="#2c4ef79f-acb1-4c92-8ff4-e6bfac04ddc0"><from>Ms. Karla MacFarlane</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Tyler MacLean, age 7, of Durham Road, Pictou County, has begun a campaign to collect enough pop tabs to purchase a wheelchair for an 18-month-old toddler diagnosed with a rare disease; and</p>
<p>Whereas Tyler has displayed a combination of humanitarianism and call to action in order to help someone in need, even asking Santa to bring him some pop tabs for Christmas; and</p>
<p>Whereas Tyler is a student at Scotsburn Elementary and has rallied his peers as well as people of all ages to take up the cause and donate;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly thank Tyler for his hard work and congratulate him for making a positive impact in the life of another child and on his community.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
