<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="5dac0dde-7ef3-4f75-a137-834785ff1ae4" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.tim.houston" showAs="Mr. Tim Houston"/>
        <TLCPerson id="16c306ab-30c7-40a9-8c13-d2d2aafda27d" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.allan.rowe" showAs="MR. ALLAN ROWE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.eddie.orrell" showAs="Mr. Eddie Orrell"/>
        <TLCPerson id="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.michel.p.samson" showAs="HON. MICHEL SAMSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.karen.casey" showAs="Hon. Karen Casey"/>
        <TLCPerson id="0c003e1d-f0de-4ef6-85c6-604c99fbd41f" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.gordon.l.wilson" showAs="MR. GORDON WILSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.diana.whalen" showAs="HON. DIANA WHALEN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="2c4ef79f-acb1-4c92-8ff4-e6bfac04ddc0" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.karla.macfarlane" showAs="Ms. Karla MacFarlane"/>
        <TLCPerson id="578ba1c9-5f6c-4b7b-a5cd-b915e1801c37" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.lena.m.diab" showAs="Hon. Lena Diab"/>
        <TLCPerson id="97532239-d15e-407a-8c67-706ed1bbc595" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.keith.irving" showAs="MR. KEITH IRVING"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MADAM SPEAKER"/>
        <TLCRole id="clerk" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.clerk" showAs="THE CLERK"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 25 April 2014</docTitle>
      <docNumber>14-34</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2014-04-25">Friday, April 25, 2014</docDate>
      <docProponent>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docProponent>
      <legislature value="62">62nd General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="1">1st Session</session>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
        <p>Order, please. We will now proceed with the daily routine.</p>
      </speech>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PRESENTING AND READING PETITIONS</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PRESENTING REPORTS OF COMMITTEES</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>TABLING REPORTS, REGULATIONS AND OTHER PAPERS</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>STATEMENTS BY MINISTERS</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>INTRODUCTION OF BILLS</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 69 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 5 of the Acts of 2010. The House of Assembly Management Commission Act. (Hon. Labi Kousoulis)</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Ordered that this bill be read a second time on a future day.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Kings South.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1373">RESOLUTION NO. 1373</num>
          <speech by="#97532239-d15e-407a-8c67-706ed1bbc595"><from>MR. KEITH IRVING</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Ms. Abbey Duinker is a native of Cambridge, Kings County, and a point forward with the University of Acadia basketball team in Wolfville; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ms. Duinker played her most successful season in 2013-14, leading both offensively and defensively; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ms. Duinker has been awarded the inaugural Acadia President's Award for exceptional leadership skills in athletics, academics, and community building;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly congratulate Abbey on her achievements and wish her continued success in her sport.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Dartmouth South.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1374">RESOLUTION NO. 1374</num>
          <speech by="#16c306ab-30c7-40a9-8c13-d2d2aafda27d"><from>MR. ALLAN ROWE</from><p>Madam Speaker, on behalf of the honourable member for Hants East, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas small businesses are the foundation of Nova Scotia; and</p>
<p>Whereas Main Town Pizza of Enfield, Nova Scotia, serves up delicious pizzas, subs, donairs, and seafood to residents, after having made the strategic decision to move and establish a business in Enfield; and</p>
<p>Whereas Main Town Pizza is celebrating its 5<sup>th</sup> Anniversary of operations;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate the team at Main Town Pizza for reaching this landmark and thank them for their investment in Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Clare-Digby.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1375">RESOLUTION NO. 1375</num>
          <speech by="#0c003e1d-f0de-4ef6-85c6-604c99fbd41f"><from>MR. GORDON WILSON</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Education Week is an opportunity to recognize teachers and education partners' commitments for their outstanding work and dedication to public education; and</p>
<p>Whereas this year's theme is Active Citizenship: Get Involved, Take Action, Be the Difference; and</p>
<p>Whereas Jennie O'Brien, Digby Regional High School, is the recipient of an Education Week Award for 2014;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jennie O'Brien and acknowledge her contribution to the public education system of Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>ORDERS OF THE DAY</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT BUSINESS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be">
          <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
          <p>Madam Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Government Motions.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT MOTIONS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be">
          <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
          <p>Madam Speaker, I move that you do now leave the Chair and the House resolve itself into a Committee of the Whole on Supply unto Her Majesty.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>We will take a moment's recess to convene Committee of the Whole on Supply.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>9:15 a.m. The House resolved itself into CW on Supply with Deputy Speaker Ms. Margaret Miller in the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <narrative>
          <p>1:31 p.m. CW on Supply rose and the House reconvened. Mr. Speaker, Hon. Kevin Murphy, resumed the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The Chairman of the Committee of the Whole on Supply reports:</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined">
          <from>THE CLERK</from>
          <p>That the Committee of the Whole on Supply has met and come to agreement on 50 estimate resolutions including votes on business plans and on capital. The Chair has been instructed to recommend these estimates to the favourable consideration of the House, each without amendment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the House concur on the report of the Committee of the Whole on Supply. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be">
          <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Introduction of Bills.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>INTRODUCTION OF BILLS</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 70 - Entitled an Act to Provide for Defraying Certain Charges and Expenses of the Public Service of the Province. (Hon. Diana Whalen)</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Minister of Finance and Treasury Board.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2">
            <from>HON. DIANA WHALEN</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, the bill is printed and I believe the Pages have already distributed a copy to each member.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Ordered that this bill be read a second time on a future day.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PUBLIC BILLS FOR SECOND READING</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Finance and Treasury Board.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2">
          <from>HON. DIANA WHALEN</from>
          <p>I move second reading of Bill No. 70, the Appropriations Act, 2014.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for second reading of Bill No. 70. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PUBLIC BILLS FOR THIRD READING</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Finance and Treasury Board.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2">
          <from>HON. DIANA WHALEN</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, I move third reading of Bill No. 70, the Appropriations Act, 2014.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for third reading of Bill No. 70.</p>
<p>There has been a request for a recorded vote. We'll now ring the bells for 10 minutes.</p>
<p>The House will resume in 10 minutes or until such time as the Whips are satisfied.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>The Division bells were rung.</p>
        </narrative>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>Are the Whips satisfied?</p>
        </speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>The Clerk calls the roll.</p>
        </narrative>
        <recordedTime time="2014-04-25T01:43:00-03:00">
          <p>1:43 p.m.</p>
        </recordedTime>
        <other>
<p>Mr. Colwell Mr. MacMaster</p>
<p>Mr. Churchill Mr. Porter</p>
<p>Ms. Bernard Mr. Dunn</p>
<p>Ms. Regan Mr. Baillie</p>
<p>Mr. Samson Mr. d'Entremont</p>
<p>Mr. McNeil Ms. MacDonald</p>
<p>Ms. Whalen Mr. David Wilson</p>
<p>Mr. Glavine Ms. Zann</p>
<p>Ms. Casey Ms. Peterson-Rafuse</p>
<p>Mr. MacLellan Mr. Belliveau</p>
<p>Ms. Diab Ms. MacFarlane</p>
<p>Mr. Younger Mr. Houston</p>
<p>Mr. Horne Mr. MacLeod</p>
<p>Mr. Hines Mr. Harrison</p>
<p>Mr. Stroink Mr. Lohr</p>
<p>Ms. Arab</p>
<p>Mr. Delorey</p>
<p>Mr. Ince</p>
<p>Mr. Kousoulis</p>
<p>Mr. Furey</p>
<p>Mr. Farrell</p>
<p>Mr. Gordon Wilson</p>
<p>Mr. Rankin</p>
<p>Ms. Miller</p>
<p>Mr. Rowe</p>
<p>Mr. Maguire</p>
<p>Ms. Eyking</p>
<p>Ms. Lohnes-Croft</p>
<p>Ms. Treen&#xFFFD;</p>
<p>Mr. Jessome</p>
<p>Mr. Irving</p></other>
        <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined">
          <from>THE CLERK</from>
          <p>For, 31. Against, 15.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is carried. (Applause)</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill do pass. Ordered that the title be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bill be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, before giving the business for Monday, all members of this House would recognize the hard work that our staff do in the administration of this building, especially our Pages. But as we all know, at times we have to say goodbye to our Pages as they move on to other careers and other employment. Today is the last day for Page Helen Hanbidge.</p>
<p>On behalf of all members of the House, we want to thank Helen for her dedicated service to all the members, to you, Mr. Speaker, and to all your staff, and we want to wish her the greatest success into the future. Thank you, Helen. (Standing Ovation)</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, that concludes the government's business for today. We will meet again on Monday, April 28<sup>th</sup>, from the hours of 4:00 p.m. until 10:00 p.m. At that time we will be doing second reading of Bill Nos. 69 and 67. As well, we will be doing third reading of Bill Nos. 32, 33, 34, 41, 44, 49, 52, 53, 55, 57, and 58. We will also be doing in Committee of the Whole House on Bills, Bill Nos. 35, 43, 45, and 51. If time permits, we will be looking at Private and Local Bills for Second Reading and Third Reading.</p>
<p>With that, I move that the House do now rise to meet again between the hours of 4:00 p.m. and 10:00 p.m. on Monday, April 28<sup>th</sup>.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the House rise to meet again on Monday, April 28<sup>th</sup>, between the hours of 4:00 p.m. and 10:00 p.m.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>We now stand adjourned until 4:00 p.m. on Monday, April 28<sup>th</sup>.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>The House rose at 1:49 p.m.</p>
        </narrative>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION UNDER RULE 32(3)</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1376">RESOLUTION NO. 1376</num>
          <speech by="578ba1c9-5f6c-4b7b-a5cd-b915e1801c37"><from>Hon. Lena Diab</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on April 12<sup>th</sup> I had the honour of attending the Annual General Meeting for the German Canadian Association of Nova Scotia, a volunteer, non-profit organization; and</p>
<p>Whereas the association elected the following individuals to its board of directors: Hannes Weiland, Christine Hoehne, Stefan Eisebraun, Joerg Kanehl, Andr&#xE9; Trzebiatowski, Steffen K&#xFFFD;ubler, Julia Poertner, Jessica Wyss, Katie Woller, Jessica Kressebuch, and Ron Kronstein, and also on the board are Honorary German Consul Anthony Chapman, Q.C. and Honorary Swiss Consul Ren&#xE9; Botzenhardt; and</p>
<p>Whereas the association and the board will continue to support their mandate of cultivating the customs, language, and social activities of Germany, Switzerland, and Austria in a unified manner on behalf of the citizens of Nova Scotia;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House recognize their hard work and commitment and congratulate each and every one of them for their valuable contribution to the multiculturalism of Nova Scotia.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1377">RESOLUTION NO. 1377</num>
          <speech by="578ba1c9-5f6c-4b7b-a5cd-b915e1801c37"><from>Hon. Lena Diab</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on March 6, 2014, the Department of Justice paid special recognition to 72 staff for their 25, 30, and 35 years of commitment to the Government of Nova Scotia during a Long Service Award luncheon; and</p>
<p>Whereas these civil servants serve Nova Scotia every day on the front lines, answering calls, responding to emails, working with our citizens, and delivering Nova Scotians the services they need; and</p>
<p>Whereas their work is not always easy but it is essential, and it helps Nova Scotians feel safe and supported in their communities;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House recognize their hard work and commitment and congratulate each and every one of them for their wonderful achievement.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1378">RESOLUTION NO. 1378</num>
          <speech by="2c4ef79f-acb1-4c92-8ff4-e6bfac04ddc0"><from>Ms. Karla MacFarlane</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Pictou branch of the Bank of Nova Scotia celebrated its 175<sup>th</sup> Anniversary in February 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Bank of Nova Scotia originated in Halifax in 1831 and came under charter in 1832, and the Pictou branch was once located on Water Street and moved to its current location on the corner of Coleraine and Front Streets in 1887, when it took over the Bank of Pictou; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Bank of Nova Scotia has immense historical significance to the Town of Pictou, with the basement vault still bearing the name the Bank of Pictou;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize and congratulate the Pictou branch of the Bank of Nova Scotia, as well as all past and present staff and managers, as it celebrates its 175 years in the Town of Pictou.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1379">RESOLUTION NO. 1379</num>
          <speech by="2c4ef79f-acb1-4c92-8ff4-e6bfac04ddc0"><from>Ms. Karla MacFarlane</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Indigo Caf&#xE9;, owned and operated by Ms. Deidre McLean and located on Water Street in the Town of Pictou, won the 2013 Pictou County Chamber of Commerce New Business of the Year Recognition Award; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Indigo Caf&#xE9; is a 26-seat boutique coffee shop offering homemade food and specializing in an all-day breakfast; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ms. McLean established her business just over a year ago and has a regular clientele who enjoys her coffee and warm greeting when they frequent her shop;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ms. Deidre McLean of the Indigo Caf&#xE9; on her award and wish her much success in her future endeavours.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1380">RESOLUTION NO. 1380</num>
          <speech by="5dac0dde-7ef3-4f75-a137-834785ff1ae4"><from>Mr. Tim Houston</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Cathy Leeming and the Friends By the Sea Artists Association are hosting an annual fundraiser to support the New Glasgow Public Library; and</p>
<p>Whereas the funds raised go toward library collection development; and</p>
<p>Whereas Cathy also donates a wonderful piece as a door prize, a true incentive that ensures a large turnout;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly thank Cathy Leeming and her fellow artists for their generosity and their continued support of the library.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1381">RESOLUTION NO. 1381</num>
          <speech by="e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>Mr. Eddie Orrell</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for nearly 35 years it has been a tradition for the veterans at the Harbourview Hospital to receive winter throws from the Cape Breton Veterans Hospital Comfort Fund; and</p>
<p>Whereas this fund is a project of the Royal Canadian Legions and Army Navy Air Force Clubs that deliver gifts to 260 veterans in the Cape Breton area every Christmas; and</p>
<p>Whereas the generosity of the Legions and Army Navy Air Force Clubs brings a smile to veterans who are institutionalized or are at home every Christmas;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly salute local Legions and Army Navy Air Force clubs for their act of kindness for our deserving veterans.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1382">RESOLUTION NO. 1382</num>
          <speech by="e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>Mr. Eddie Orrell</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Kiwanis Ceilidh Golden K have had a very busy December, with donations and community volunteer efforts; and</p>
<p>Whereas donations have been made to local food banks, the Association of Safer Communities, the Salvation Army, and the Bras d'Or Combined Christmas Cheer Fund; and</p>
<p>Whereas the club volunteered with the Salvation Army Kettles, Meals on Wheels, Lights for Health, Builders Clubs, and chauffeuring officials in the World Under-17 Hockey Championship, and also found time to sell fruitcakes;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate this service club for their exemplary service to the Northside community.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1383">RESOLUTION NO. 1383</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's volunteer fire brigades are made up of individuals who show their dedication to serving others by contributing hard work, skills, and time, often risking their lives, taking on the role of first responders, and dealing with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas training, fundraising, recruitment, and public relations are only a few of the additional responsibilities of members of a fire brigade; and</p>
<p>Whereas since the members of volunteer fire brigades seldom receive the accolades they deserve, an annual banquet is usually held to thank all their members and to present special awards;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Fire Chief Nigel Leggett for receiving a 30-year service pin at the annual banquet of the Valley Kemptown Fire Brigade in Colchester North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1384">RESOLUTION NO. 1384</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's volunteer fire brigades are made up of individuals who show their dedication to serving others by contributing hard work, skills, and time, often risking their lives, taking on the role of first responders, and dealing with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas training, fundraising, recruitment, and public relations are only a few of the additional responsibilities of members of a fire brigade; and</p>
<p>Whereas since the members of volunteer fire brigades seldom receive the accolades they deserve, an annual banquet is usually held to thank all their members and to present special awards;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Merlyn Smith for receiving a 20-year service pin at the annual banquet of the Valley Kemptown Fire Brigade in Colchester North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1385">RESOLUTION NO. 1385</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's volunteer fire brigades are made up of individuals who show their dedication to serving others by contributing hard work, skills, and time, often risking their lives, taking on the role of first responders, and dealing with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas training, fundraising, recruitment, and public relations are only a few of the additional responsibilities of members of a fire brigade; and</p>
<p>Whereas since the members of volunteer fire brigades seldom receive the accolades they deserve, an annual banquet is usually held to thank all their members and to present special awards;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jason McRae for receiving a 5-year service pin at the annual banquet of the Valley Kemptown Fire Brigade in Colchester North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1386">RESOLUTION NO. 1386</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's volunteer fire brigades are made up of individuals who show their dedication to serving others by contributing hard work, skills, and time, often risking their lives, taking on the role of first responders, and dealing with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas training, fundraising, recruitment, and public relations are only a few of the additional responsibilities of members of a fire brigade; and</p>
<p>Whereas since the members of volunteer fire brigades seldom receive the accolades they deserve, an annual banquet is usually held to thank all their members and to present special awards;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Alex Teed for receiving the Officer of the Year Award at the annual banquet of the Valley Kemptown Fire Brigade in Colchester North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="1387">RESOLUTION NO. 1387</num>
          <speech by="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's volunteer fire brigades are made up of individuals who show their dedication to serving others by contributing hard work, skills, and time, often risking their lives, taking on the role of first responders, and dealing with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas training, fundraising, recruitment, and public relations are only a few of the additional responsibilities of members of a fire brigade; and</p>
<p>Whereas since the members of volunteer fire brigades seldom receive the accolades they deserve, an annual banquet is usually held to thank all their members and to present special awards;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Graham Jacobs for receiving a 10-year service pin at the annual banquet of the Valley Kemptown Fire Brigade in Colchester North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
