<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="d36a0432-7994-4030-ab00-b21fc858e7d2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.ross.landry" showAs="MR. LANDRY"/>
        <TLCPerson id="6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.allan.gerard.macmaster" showAs="MR. ALLAN MACMASTER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.frank.corbett" showAs="HON. FRANK CORBETT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="5da6e0aa-9066-4b5c-8d26-9222b854db7e" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.marilyn.more" showAs="HON. MARILYN MORE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.christopher.a.dentremont" showAs="MR. D'ENTREMONT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.diana.whalen" showAs="MS. DIANA WHALEN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.michel.p.samson" showAs="MR. SAMSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="aefec392-99d6-4923-8d87-227e50d567e8" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.pam.birdsall" showAs="Ms. Pam Birdsall"/>
        <TLCPerson id="e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.eddie.orrell" showAs="MR. EDDIE ORRELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8834559e-ddf7-4ac7-9b30-8ada0eb9a7ca" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.zach.churchill" showAs="MR. ZACH CHURCHILL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="169d581a-9c34-47f3-9660-9ccb38d06bf4" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.harold.theriault" showAs="Mr. Harold Theriault"/>
        <TLCPerson id="4fbcc786-c835-4a0e-bd05-40afb30e0683" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.charlie.parker" showAs="HON. CHARLIE PARKER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="b723d7ff-ed62-4b67-ae5f-83b903707923" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.vicki.conrad" showAs="Ms. Vicki Conrad"/>
        <TLCPerson id="20520cce-c7eb-4da6-bc5e-8e9f24f3db6b" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.jim.boudreau" showAs="Mr. Jim Boudreau"/>
        <TLCPerson id="b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.ramona.jennex" showAs="Hon. Ramona Jennex"/>
        <TLCPerson id="980981f9-4823-4d4b-8134-a47d4ecf5405" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.denise.peterson.rafuse" showAs="HON. DENISE PETERSON-RAFUSE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.kelly.regan" showAs="Ms. Kelly Regan"/>
        <TLCPerson id="5e4eedce-ee17-4542-8b27-a1e87f85ec80" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.graham.steele" showAs="MR. STEELE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.stephen.mcneil" showAs="MR. MCNEIL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="b1bb12cd-3928-4525-bab1-d76d28109b5b" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.percy.paris" showAs="MR. PARIS"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.maureen.macdonald" showAs="HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.keith.bain" showAs="MR. KEITH BAIN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="a5e0e841-506b-4c0b-a88e-c09691bd745b" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.manning.macdonald" showAs="HON. MANNING MACDONALD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.jamie.baillie" showAs="MR. BAILLIE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="1e5b7bdc-363b-4df4-8258-edcf8f2bf7fb" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.andrew.younger" showAs="MR. ANDREW YOUNGER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.karen.casey" showAs="MS. CASEY"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8dbda583-1553-4164-a616-3008fb0fdac4" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.bill.estabrooks" showAs="HON. WILLIAM ESTABROOKS"/>
        <TLCPerson id="799b989e-2c9d-4331-b5f3-5f78d3447b57" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.darrell.dexter" showAs="HON. DARRELL DEXTER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="d6c0c78d-dcf3-456a-915c-a20ecb33050f" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.john.macdonell" showAs="MR. MACDONELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.leo.glavine" showAs="MR. GLAVINE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="aef785d7-7697-4453-8f9c-eef26e4928c3" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.keith.colwell" showAs="HON. KEITH COLWELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="4993eadf-848c-4786-8f94-855a5b2bc709" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.trevor.zinck" showAs="MR. TREVOR ZINCK"/>
        <TLCPerson id="de2082f3-cf3a-4955-8a4e-4f1bf0ac1301" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.mat.whynott" showAs="MR. MAT WHYNOTT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="5c3f8e78-5002-4c61-9c57-730090867f1b" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.wayne.j.gaudet" showAs="HON. WAYNE GAUDET"/>
        <TLCPerson id="22119b83-0505-4c62-95ff-e8c0e378764c" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.jim.morton" showAs="MR. JIM MORTON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="32a29c39-915c-40e7-b749-7c09299ed1f7" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.david.allan.wilson" showAs="Hon. David Wilson"/>
        <TLCPerson id="13283a7f-b97c-4254-a233-d0ccec196703" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.gary.ramey" showAs="MR. GARY RAMEY"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MADAM SPEAKER"/>
        <TLCRole id="premier" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.premier" showAs="THE PREMIER"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 13 December 2011</docTitle>
      <docNumber>11-65</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2011-12-13">Tuesday, December 13, 2011</docDate>
      <docProponent>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docProponent>
      <legislature value="61">61st General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="3">3rd Session</session>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
        <p>We will now commence with the daily routine.</p>
      </speech>
      <petitions>
        <heading>PRESENTING AND READING PETITIONS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Natural Resources.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#4fbcc786-c835-4a0e-bd05-40afb30e0683">
          <from>HON. CHARLIE PARKER</from>
          <p>Madam Speaker, I beg leave to table a petition entitled a Petition to Ban Hydraulic Fracturing in Nova Scotia, signed by 312 individuals. I, too, have affixed my signature.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The petition is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>MS. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Madam Speaker, I beg leave today to table a petition. The operative clause of this petition says:</p>
<blockquote>"We, the undersigned, are concerned citizens who urge the Nova Scotia legislature to act now to amend the Liquor Control Act to exempt beer and wine making kits from the definition of liquor contained in the Act. Furthermore we urge that retailers be permitted to commence Ferment on Premise as is done in other Provinces."</blockquote>
<p>Madam Speaker, there are 602 signatures on this petition and I have affixed my name. Thank you very much.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The petition is tabled.</p>
        </speech>
      </petitions>
      <papers>
        <heading>PRESENTING REPORTS OF COMMITTEES</heading>
      </papers>
      <papers>
        <heading>TABLING REPORTS, REGULATIONS AND OTHER PAPERS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of the Public Service Commission.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Madam Speaker, I'd like to table a report on diversity, <i>Moving Toward Equity: Employment Equity and Diversity in the Nova Scotia Public Service, 2010-2011</i>.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The report is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Labour and Advanced Education.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#5da6e0aa-9066-4b5c-8d26-9222b854db7e">
          <from>HON. MARILYN MORE</from>
          <p>Madam Speaker, I'd like to table the <i>Report on The Nova Scotia College of Art and Design: Time to Act</i>, prepared by Howard Windsor. Thank you.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The report is tabled.</p>
        </speech>
      </papers>
      <ministerialStatements>
        <heading>STATEMENTS BY MINISTERS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Community Services.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#980981f9-4823-4d4b-8134-a47d4ecf5405"><from>HON. DENISE PETERSON-RAFUSE</from><p>Madam Speaker, I'd like to take this opportunity to update you and the members of the House of Assembly on new programming now available for persons with disabilities. This is good news that will help make life better for Nova Scotians with disabilities; good news that clearly shows our commitment to improve services for persons with disabilities and their families.</p>
<p>In April this government announced $500,000 that would allow more Nova Scotians with disabilities to access day programs across the province. Day programs give people with disabilities the opportunity to be productive members of their communities and to be engaged in a variety of fulfilling activities. They help persons with disabilities build confidence and realize their individual potential.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I'm happy to say that the investment announced in April is becoming a reality. Nine day programs have been identified to provide programming for about 30 Nova Scotians with disabilities who have high support needs. This investment marks the first time funding has been provided specifically for individuals with high, complex needs and the first time this kind of programming is available to so many who need it.</p>
<p>This government is making positive change for Nova Scotians with disabilities and their families. Across Nova Scotia a variety of day programs provide supportive employment, skill training, and vocational programming. They are wonderful programs that make a real difference in people's lives.</p>
<p>The funding is being rolled out to these programs as we speak and we couldn't be happier about it. Day programs not only provide persons with disabilities opportunities for meaningful work and activity, they help the families of those who attend. It means parents and other caregivers are able to work and support their families knowing their loved one is well cared for and engaged in appropriate activities for their particular development.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, that's exactly what this government is working so hard for - to make life better for families in Nova Scotia. This investment is one of a series of improvements this government has made to expand and improve services for Nova Scotians with disabilities. Since 2009 we have increased investments in services for persons with disabilities by nearly $20 million.</p>
<p>Today's news is yet another example of this government keeping its commitment to make life better for Nova Scotian families. Thank you, Madam Speaker.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Victoria-The Lakes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e"><from>MR. KEITH BAIN</from><p>Madam Speaker, although it's very short notice, I'd like to thank the minister for providing us with a copy of her statement ahead of time.</p>
<p>It's good to hear from this minister that the day program has had positive feedback, and Nova Scotians are accessing the program and benefiting from it. Far too often, we see the misplaced priorities of this NDP Government. They'd rather spend funds on ad campaigns and fancy consultants than make investments in health, education, and programs for Nova Scotia's most vulnerable citizens. It was just this summer, after all, that the minister eliminated funding for some uninsured medical services for the disabled. For some, that meant deteriorating health and eventually a higher cost to government when they end up in hospitals.</p>
<p>I'm pleased to hear that disabled Nova Scotians and their families are feeling positive about this program. We'll be checking in with our constituents to make sure, however, that they feel the funding is being allocated in the appropriate way. Thank you, Madam Speaker.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>MS. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Madam Speaker, I'm pleased to say just a few words about the minister's statement today around new day programs for people with special needs and disabilities.</p>
<p>We are very happy to see that there is an expansion of those services, but there are certainly other things to be said around the behaviour of this government in recent months concerning people with disabilities.</p>
<p>Funding for day programs for people with disabilities is a very welcome initiative and will mean a lot, not only to the people with disabilities but, as the minister said, to their caregivers and families. We know that it's very hard for them to carry on and have work and be certain that their family members are well cared for. Having access to day programs where people are given support to fully participate in their community is essential.</p>
<p>Vocational training can be a real benefit to people's lives as we have seen through the successes of the Dartmouth Adult Service Centre in particular. The Liberal caucus was pleased to see that DASC finally got funding from the government, months after securing funding and support from the federal and municipal governments. It was also very convenient that this funding for DASC was announced minutes before they appeared before an all-Party Community Services Committee. I believe that DASC was coming before the committee to ask for funding from the government to support that expansion.</p>
<p>In fact, their PowerPoint presentation had not included the funding from the province because the announcement was so sudden. It would seem that funding announcements received minutes before presentation would preclude such edits. We're very happy that DASC got the support it needed from the provincial government - the very support Liberal members were calling for for the past few months, months before the announcement actually was made.</p>
<p>The Liberal caucus supports initiatives that will make life better for people with disabilities; we also support initiatives that will alleviate pain and suffering for people with disabilities and illness. This is why we stood in the House to protect exceptional special needs provisions for people on unemployment support and income assistance. For many disabled people, accessing special needs not found on the MSI formulary is their only option to gain freedom from suffering.</p>
<p>I would hope that the minister will reconsider her position on providing exceptional needs to disabled people to relieve pain and suffering. Investing $500 million for day programs for people with disabilities - not $500 million, I think we haven't the amount right there - but it certainly does help to invest for people in the day programs. It's essential that people can access programming in their own communities.</p>
<p>I would hope that in offering these services the government has taken into account the particular needs of rural Nova Scotians and Nova Scotians who live in areas where accessible transit is not readily available. I hope the government has also taken into account the specific needs of parents with disabilities who may require child care to access these programs. The Liberal caucus supports day programs for people with disabilities and looks forward to further initiatives to best support disabled people in Nova Scotia.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>At this point I would like to make sure I read the late debate topic:</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the Minister of Health and Wellness justify the chaos being caused by changes made to vendor lists for the Home Oxygen Program.</p>
<p>It was submitted by the honourable member for Glace Bay.</p></speech>
      </ministerialStatements>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Health and Wellness.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3007">RESOLUTION NO. 3007</num>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Legacy of Life is Nova Scotia's provincial organ and tissue donation program, and its purpose is to ensure all Nova Scotians know about organ and tissue donation and choose to donate; and</p>
<p>Whereas organ and tissue donation saves and improves lives - an organ donation from one person can save the lives of up to eight people, while a single tissue donor can improve the lives of up to 40 people; and</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia leads the country in the number of registered organ and tissue donors, with over 50 per cent of residents signed up to donate;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in commending the work of the Legacy of Life program and encourage all Nova Scotians to register as organ and tissue donors.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3008">RESOLUTION NO. 3008</num>
          <speech by="#b1bb12cd-3928-4525-bab1-d76d28109b5b"><from>HON. PERCY PARIS</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the world-class Glen Arbour Golf Course has been announced as the host for the TELUS World Skins Game in July 2012 - one of the most prestigious golf events, with a history of attracting some of the biggest names in professional golf, including Jack Nicklaus, Fred Couples, and Mike Weir; and</p>
<p>Whereas this event has recognized Nova Scotia's major event-hosting expertise by selecting our province for its 20<sup>th</sup> Anniversary celebration with golf enthusiasts from across Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas the event will attract more than 10,000 attendees and bring international exposure for Nova Scotia;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Glen Arbour Golf Course and the team at Trade Centre Limited on their success in attracting this major event to Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>INTRODUCTION OF BILLS</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 136 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 282 of the Revised Statutes of 1989. The Members' Retiring Allowances Act, and to Amend Chapter 1 (1992 Supplement) of the Revised Statutes of 1989. The House of Assembly Act. (Hon. Frank Corbett.)</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>Ordered that this bill be read a second time on a future day.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#8dbda583-1553-4164-a616-3008fb0fdac4"><from>HON. WILLIAM ESTABROOKS</from><p>To my earlier comments, I must read this into the record and have it tabled, if you would, Madam Speaker.</p>
<p>In accordance with the Constitution Act, 1867, I hereby recommend an Act to Amend Chapter 282 of the Revised Statutes of 1989, the Members' Retiring Allowances Act, to the House of Assembly.</p>
<p>I respectfully submit this on behalf of the Deputy Premier.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The message has been tabled.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3009">RESOLUTION NO. 3009</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>MS. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Halifax West High School has opened its annual Model Parliament on December 8, 2011, with the member for Halifax Clayton Park acting as Governor General and reading the Speech from the Throne for more than 50 parliamentarians present; and</p>
<p>Whereas this year the school-wide elections resulted in a majority Liberal Government, with the Anarchist Party holding the Official Opposition, and the Green Party and new Multicultural Party also holding seats; and</p>
<p>Whereas the two days of debate for the students provided ample challenge to the Speaker of the Model Parliament, Keith Lehwald, who is a former student at Halifax West and a current Page in the Nova Scotia Legislature;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House congratulate Halifax West on their Model Parliament and particularly recognize the efforts of Department Head Sandra Starratt and volunteers Keith Lehwald and Ryan Brownell, who filled the roles of Speaker and Legislative Clerk, who all together made the parliament possible.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3010">RESOLUTION NO. 3010</num>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Gary Greeley of North End Halifax exemplifies the best of credit union values and co-operative principles; and</p>
<p>Whereas Gary Greeley has worked in the credit union system for 39 years, including 34 years as General Manager of the Halifax Civic Credit Union on Lady Hammond Road in Halifax; and</p>
<p>Whereas Gary Greeley will be retiring this week after a distinguished career of service to his community and the credit union movement;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House thank Gary Greeley for his tremendous career and wish him all the best in the future.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Health and Wellness.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3011">RESOLUTION NO. 3011</num>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Madam Speaker, on behalf of the Premier, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nick Lachance, a 29-year-old Cole Harbour native now studying at Wilfrid Laurier University in Waterloo, Ontario, decided to pursue his passion for history and writing by co-authoring a cutting-edge book on Canadian military history; and</p>
<p>Whereas the book, entitled <i>Canadian Battlefields 1915-1918: A Visitor's Guide</i>, uses Google Earth topographical maps to chart soldiers' movements during the First World War, helping to bring those historic battles to life for the reader; and</p>
<p>Whereas royalties from the book go to the Laurier Centre for Military Strategic and Disarmament Studies, where Mr. Lachance first met his two co-authors;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this Legislature congratulate Nick Lachance and his colleagues on creating this innovative tool that not only honours World War I veterans but also helps people learn more about the experience of war and understanding the mentality of a soldier.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Kings West.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3012">RESOLUTION NO. 3012</num>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048"><from>MR. LEO GLAVINE</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Bill Scott, a teacher of science and health at Somerset and District Elementary School outside of Berwick in Kings County, took two months to ride his bike across Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas Bill Scott is now 60 years young, has lost more than 50 pounds while biking since 2003, and continues to keep track of the miles logged in his trek across this country; and</p>
<p>Whereas Bill Scott has not only improved his health but travelled through flood damage in Manitoba and smoke from forest fires in northern Ontario, sometimes logging 180 kilometres a day;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly recognize and congratulate Bill Scott for his amazing bicycle journey across Canada.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Victoria-The Lakes.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3013">RESOLUTION NO. 3013</num>
          <speech by="#250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e"><from>MR. KEITH BAIN</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Baddeck Lions Club received their charter as a club in June 1951 and this year is celebrating their 60<sup>th</sup> year as an active community organization; and</p>
<p>Whereas projects that boost community spirit demonstrated by the Baddeck Lions Club include offering a free ferry service to Kidston Island and ensuring lifeguards are available free of charge on Kidston Island beach; and</p>
<p>Whereas Baddeck Lions Club also hosts such things as an annual Christmas party at the Alderwood Rest Home for Seniors;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize the tremendous spirit of volunteerism put forth by the Baddeck Lions Club and thank them for their commitment to the people of Baddeck and surrounding area.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Education.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3014">RESOLUTION NO. 3014</num>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a"><from>HON. RAMONA JENNEX</from><p>Madam, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on December 23, 2010, Mr. Ricky Coldwell helped in the rescue of Alton and Sheila Allen on Melanson Mountain Road; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Coldwell crawled into the back seat of the Allens' car while it rested in a tree over an 80-foot drop, and helped Mrs. Sheila Allen out of the car; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Coldwell risked his life to safe another through his courageous action;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly recognize the importance of this act of heroism by Mr. Ricky Coldwell and recognize his example of selfless compassion for his neighbour.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Clare.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3015">RESOLUTION NO. 3015</num>
          <speech by="#5c3f8e78-5002-4c61-9c57-730090867f1b"><from>HON. WAYNE GAUDET</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Cloudburst won the Michael Weir Award for Best Original Screenplay at the 31<sup>st</sup> Atlantic Film Festival in Halifax, in September 2011; and</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia actor Ryan Doucette, from Clare, is acting with Olympia Dukakis and Brenda Fricker in the best Canadian film at the Edmonton International Film Festival on October 1<sup>st</sup>; and</p>
<p>Whereas Cloudburst also won the Cinefest Sudbury International Film Festival Audience Choice Award in September;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Brian Doucette for his acting role in Cloudburst, an award-winning film.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cape Breton North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3016">RESOLUTION NO. 3016</num>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Ruth Sichky has lived through two world wars, the Great Depression and raised a family of six, all the while keeping her sense of humour; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ruth turned 105 and enjoys her extended family of 31 grandchildren; 71 great-grandchildren; 57 great-great-grandchildren; and three great-great-great- grandchildren; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ruth enjoyed baking until she was in her 90s and continued camping with her family until she was 95, her sense of humour is the key to her long life;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Ruth on her 105<sup>th</sup> birthday and remembering that a sense of a humour is the key to a long life.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Queens.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3017">RESOLUTION NO. 3017</num>
          <speech by="#b723d7ff-ed62-4b67-ae5f-83b903707923"><from>MS. VICKI CONRAD</from><p>Madam Speaker, on behalf of the member for Cole Harbour-Eastern Passage, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the introduction of the first CH-124 Sea King helicopter to serve the Canadian Armed Forces took place in August 1963, and has since proven itself to be one of the busiest and most operational deployed aircraft in the Forces; and</p>
<p>Whereas August 31, 2013 will mark the official 50<sup>th</sup> Anniversary of the Sea King's service to Canadians and nations around the world; and</p>
<p>Whereas Colonel (Ret'd) John M. Cody and a team of passionate Nova Scotians have formed the Sea King 50<sup>th</sup> Anniversary Association celebrating its Golden Jubilee, and are working hard to plan a series of events in Nova Scotia to celebrate this rich history and milestone;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly commend Colonel (Ret'd) John M. Cody, chairman of Sea King 50<sup>th</sup> Anniversary Association, and members of his team for spearheading the year-long program of events to mark the occasion of the 50<sup>th</sup> Anniversary of the CF helicopter, the Sea King, and celebrate the tremendous service that this aircraft and its crew and support personnel have provided for our country.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Richmond.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3018">RESOLUTION NO. 3018</num>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas George Robertson of St. Peter's, owner of the MacBouch Restaurant and Lounge, was a minor baseball and hockey coach as well as a standout pitcher with the Richmond Amateur Baseball Association, playing for the River Bourgeois Schooners; and</p>
<p>Whereas George Robertson is known for his generosity in supporting local athletes, sports teams, and many worthwhile causes, including hosting many fundraisers at the MacBouch; and</p>
<p>Whereas when the St. Peter's Lions Club embarked on their ambitious goal to build a new recreation centre which includes a ball field, soccer field, playground, outdoor fitness centre, and a walking track, they unanimously decided to name the complex in honour of George Robertson;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly thank George Robertson for his many years of generosity and community leadership, and recognize him for having the new St. Peters Lions Club Recreation Centre named in his honour.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Argyle</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3019">RESOLUTION NO. 3019</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas today is Acadien Remembrance Day, a day set aside to commemorate the heavy loss of life that resulted from the deportation of nearly 12,000 Acadiens from the Atlantic Provinces; and</p>
<p>Whereas on December 13, 1758, the vessel the <i>Duke William</i>, carrying nearly 2,000 Acadiens from Ile-Saint Jean, sank in the North Atlantic taking over 360 lives; and</p>
<p>Whereas people all over the Maritimes mark the event of Le Grand D&#xE9;rangement by wearing a black star to show their respect for the lives lost, and the preservation of our Acadien heritage;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly reflect upon the tragedy that befell the Acadiens over two and a half centuries ago, and recognize Acadien Remembrance Day as an important piece of our history.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Lunenburg West.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#13283a7f-b97c-4254-a233-d0ccec196703">
            <from>MR. GARY RAMEY</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I'd like to call the attention of the House to the east gallery. With us today is Mr. David Pottie; he's a constituent of mine. Dave used to be the former superintendent of the Lunenburg County District School Board and he was also president of the Lunenburg County Retired Teachers Association at one point. A good guy, an all-round good fellow, and I am very pleased to have him here today. I'd like the House to give him a good round of applause in the usual manner. (Applause)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>I welcome all of our visitors to the gallery today and we hope you enjoy today's proceedings.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Preston.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3020">RESOLUTION NO. 3020</num>
          <speech by="#aef785d7-7697-4453-8f9c-eef26e4928c3"><from>HON. KEITH COLWELL</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Leona Boutilier celebrated her 100<sup>th</sup> birthday on Saturday, December 10, 2011, with a large gathering of family and friends; and</p>
<p>Whereas Leona Boutilier is a lifelong resident of Spry Bay, Nova Scotia, where she and her husband raised four children - three boys and one girl; and</p>
<p>Whereas Leona Boutilier is known for her love of playing cards and her generous hospitality, always welcoming local children and friends into her home regardless of the time of day, and she always had room for one more;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House congratulate Leona Boutilier on her 100<sup>th</sup> birthday and thank her for the many contributions she has made to her community on behalf of the many children she has helped over the years.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Victoria-The Lakes.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3021">RESOLUTION NO. 3021</num>
          <speech by="#250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e"><from>MR. KEITH BAIN</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas 84 runners participated in the 6<sup>th</sup> Annual Englishtown Mussel Festival five-kilometre road race in late June; and</p>
<p>Whereas since the race was established, there has been an increase in the number of people who participate each year; and</p>
<p>Whereas this year the youngest runner was 9-year-old Juliana Vickers and the oldest was Colin Waye;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Juliana and Colin and the organizers of the 6<sup>th</sup> Annual Englishtown Mussel Festival.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Richmond.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3022">RESOLUTION NO. 3022</num>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on September 11, 2011, residents of St. Peter's and area gathered to attend the opening of the newly-built George Robertson Recreation Complex; and</p>
<p>Whereas the recreation centre, built next to the West Richmond Education Centre and Richmond Villa, includes a soccer field, a baseball field, an outdoor fitness centre, a walking track, and a playground; and</p>
<p>Whereas the new recreation centre, an initiative of the St. Peter's Lions Club, would not have been possible without the contribution made by the Government of Canada to Enterprise Cape Breton Corporation, as well as funding provided by the Province of Nova Scotia, the Municipality of Richmond, the Strait Regional School Board, and the St. Peter's Lions Club;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly congratulate all the funding partners, but especially the St. Peter's and Area Lions Club, for helping make this project a reality for the community of St. Peter's.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cape Breton North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3023">RESOLUTION NO. 3023</num>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Habitat for Humanity Canada just recently launched its National Leadership Council, a group of influential Canadians brought together by their belief that safe, decent, and affordable housing is the key to building a stronger community and a stronger Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas Annette Verschuren, former president of Home Depot Canada and a North Sydney native, was appointed to the prestigious National Leadership Council; and</p>
<p>Whereas this group will work to make housing a priority issue by acting as Habitat for Humanity ambassadors locally and globally and pledging to devote their personal time, expertise, and influence to raising awareness and understanding of this issue affecting more than four million Canadians;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in supporting Annette for her dedication and interest in trying to resolve the housing crisis with a program that is not a handout, but rather a hand up.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Bedford-Birch Cove.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3024">RESOLUTION NO. 3024</num>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>MS. KELLY REGAN</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Katherine Diana Aske, a Grade 11 student at C.P. Allen High School in Bedford, has achieved a commendable performance in the courses in which she was enrolled; and</p>
<p>Whereas Katherine has demonstrated qualities of leadership and service at her school and in her community; and</p>
<p>Whereas Katherine has been awarded a Lieutenant Governor's Education Medal for 2010-11;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Katherine Diana Aske on her accomplishments and on her award, and wish her every success in the future.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Argyle.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3025">RESOLUTION NO. 3025</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas field work has confirmed that ticks collected from in and around Yarmouth County carry the bacteria that can cause Lyme disease; and</p>
<p>Whereas neither the Minister of Natural Resources nor the Minister of Health and Wellness contacted the local MLAs before sending the release out to media that could have caused undue hysteria in our constituencies; and</p>
<p>Whereas this government has not outlined how they will educate the people of Yarmouth County about how to recognize the symptoms of Lyme disease or reduce their risk of coming in contact with ticks;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly call on the NDP to properly consult the people of Yarmouth County about ways to protect themselves against Lyme disease in order to minimize the hysteria that can be caused by the lack of proper communication.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Colchester North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3026">RESOLUTION NO. 3026</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>HON. KAREN CASEY</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Excellence in Teaching Awards are sponsored by the Chignecto-Central Regional School Board and the Nova Scotia Teachers Union; and</p>
<p>Whereas these awards are presented annually to recognize outstanding teachers and to celebrate teaching excellence within the board; and</p>
<p>Whereas Eric Allen of Tatamagouche Elementary School in Colchester North was the winner of the 2011 Excellence in Teaching Award;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Eric Allen for winning this prestigious award and thank him for his exceptional efforts to provide a learning environment that ensures the very best in education for his students.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Yarmouth.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3027">RESOLUTION NO. 3027</num>
          <speech by="#8834559e-ddf7-4ac7-9b30-8ada0eb9a7ca"><from>MR. ZACH CHURCHILL</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Yarmouth's Howard Nickerson has written a compilation of stories about growing up in Yarmouth during the 1940s and 1950s; and</p>
<p>Whereas his memoir, titled <i>Sawdust Trail Memories - once more around the kitchen table</i>, is described as a love story and a tribute from a son to his parents and siblings, above all it's a story about what is important in life and the little things money can't buy; and</p>
<p>Whereas Howard Nickerson's book, <i>Sawdust Trail Memories - once more around the kitchen table</i>, was recently published and brings to light numerous touching and meaningful stories of our community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Yarmouth's Howard Nickerson on the publication of his book and thank him for sharing with us such wonderful and valuable memories of growing up in Yarmouth.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Kings West.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3028">RESOLUTION NO. 3028</num>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048"><from>MR. LEO GLAVINE</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Tyler Ryerson of Aylesford was chosen as 2011's Snowmobiler Association of Nova Scotia Youth of the Year; and</p>
<p>Whereas Tyler has great passion and ambition for the sport of snowmobiling; and</p>
<p>Whereas Tyler's dedication to the sport extends to four-wheeling, dirt-biking, and swimming, and works hard in all areas;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House congratulate Tyler Ryerson on his dedication to snowmobiling in the province.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3029">RESOLUTION NO. 3029</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>MS. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Sarah Wenning was a key person involved in the building of the Keshen Goodman Library in Clayton Park, where she has been the manager since its opening in 2001; and</p>
<p>Whereas Sarah Wenning is retiring after 34 years of library service, during which she has been praised by all and seen as a mentor by many staff; and</p>
<p>Whereas during her career Sarah has worked at the Capital District Library and the Halifax Public Libraries;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Sarah Wenning on a long and successful career in library service and thank her for her contribution to the Halifax Clayton Park community.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Preston.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3030">RESOLUTION NO. 3030</num>
          <speech by="#aef785d7-7697-4453-8f9c-eef26e4928c3"><from>HON. KEITH COLWELL</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Norma Downey has been a resident of North Preston all her life and it is here that she brought up her eight children and two grandchildren; and</p>
<p>Whereas she was one of the founding committee members who helped establish the North Preston Day Care Centre in 1970 which holds a licence to care for 55 children, working there as a teacher and later becoming the director and remained employed there for a total of 39 years before retiring in December 2010; and</p>
<p>Whereas she is a member of St. Thomas United Baptist Church, a member of the Community Gospel Choir, a member of the Missionary Society, and a member of the I.O.D.E.;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Norma Downey on her retirement and recognize the significant contributions that Norma has made to her community of North Preston and to all of Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Yarmouth.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3031">RESOLUTION NO. 3031</num>
          <speech by="#8834559e-ddf7-4ac7-9b30-8ada0eb9a7ca"><from>MR. ZACH CHURCHILL</from><p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Yarmouth Area Community Fund established in 2008 is administered by co-chairs Mary and Peter Eldridge, who helped grow the fund and gather financial and community resources to support the fund's activities; and</p>
<p>Whereas co-chairs of the fund Mary and Peter Eldridge also actively engage with fellow committee members to determine where help is most needed; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mary and Peter Eldridge also distribute income from the fund to local charities and non-profit organizations and assist initiatives that benefit our community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly recognize Mary and Peter Eldridge for the meaningful work they do as co-chairs of the Yarmouth Area Community Fund and thank them for their tireless dedication to our community.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Clare.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3032">RESOLUTION NO. 3032</num>
          <speech by="#5c3f8e78-5002-4c61-9c57-730090867f1b"><from>HON. WAYNE GAUDET</from><p>Madame la Pr&#xE9;sidente, par la pr&#xE9;sente, j'avise que je proposerai &#xE0; une date ult&#xE9;rieure, l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu qu'il existe des liens acadiens &#xE9;troits entre la Nouvelle-&#xC9;cosse et la Louisiane; et</p>
<p>Attendu que Madame Rachelle Dugas a contribu&#xE9; de fa&#xE7;on remarquable au d&#xE9;veloppement de la jeunesse acadienne tant en Louisiane qu'en Nouvelle-&#xC9;cosse; et</p>
<p>Attendu que la m&#xE9;daille Camille-Antoine Richard est donn&#xE9;e &#xE0; ceux et celles qui contribuent de fa&#xE7;on sp&#xE9;ciale &#xE0; l'avancement de la jeunesse acadienne;</p>
<p>Qu'il soit r&#xE9;solu que les membres de cette assembl&#xE9;e se joignent &#xE0; moi pour f&#xE9;liciter Mme Rachelle Dugas et l'encourager &#xE0; continuer le beau travail.</p>
<p>Madame la Pr&#xE9;sidente, je propose l'adoption de cette r&#xE9;solution sans pr&#xE9;avis et sans d&#xE9;bats.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas there is a close Acadian connection between Louisiana and Nova Scotia; and</p>
<p>Whereas Madame Rachelle Dugas has made a remarkable contribution to Acadian awareness among the youth in Nova Scotia and in Louisiana; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Camille-Antoine Richard medal is given to those who contribute in a special way to the advancement of the Acadian youth;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Madame Dugas on receiving the prestigious Camille-Antoine Richard award.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>ORDERS OF THE DAY</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <questions>
        <heading>ORAL QUESTIONS PUT BY MEMBERS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>Question Period will begin at 2:49 p.m. and end at 3:49 p.m.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition.</p></speech>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>PREM.: BOWATER - EMPLOYMENT GUARANTEES</heading>
          <speech by="#fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5">
            <from>HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL</from>
            <p>My question is for the Premier. Madam Speaker, the Premier has signed a deal with Bowater worth up to $90 million and Nova Scotians are still left with some unanswered questions. As I'm sure you're well aware, more people in the Bowater area were laid off as of late last week, yet there are no guarantees in this deal which will keep the remaining employees at the mill employed, not at the end of the five years or during the life of the agreement at any point. What guarantees did the Premier get from Resolute that there would be no further layoffs coming for the people of Bowater when he signed this deal?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#799b989e-2c9d-4331-b5f3-5f78d3447b57">
            <from>HON. DARRELL DEXTER</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I just point out that part of the agreement was that in addition to the very difficult decisions that were made by the workers in the plant themselves, there was an understanding that they would not be disproportionately affected by having more of their workers laid off than were taken up in management. In the cuts that you saw last week it was on the management side of the mill's administration. The commitment from the mill is to operate the two paper machines over the course of that time. The manner in which that operation takes place, who will be in the plant, what those numbers look like, are part of the collective agreement that is signed with the union.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5">
            <from>MR. MCNEIL</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, when Nova Scotians look at this deal they will find nowhere are there guarantees that employees will be kept on. Employees have no job security - not today, not next week, not next year. Furthermore there is nothing in this agreement to stop Resolute from packing up and leaving at any time. My question to the Premier is, will the Premier point out where in this agreement that there are guarantees of job security for the remaining employees at Bowater?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, what I would point out to the Leader of the Official Opposition is that there is a great deal more job security today for those people of that mill than if the mill were closed.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5">
            <from>MR. MCNEIL</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, that is cold comfort to those employees who have had to make the very tough decision to vote against laying off some of their neighbours. All we're asking is a simple question, what assurance did the Premier get from Resolute that the remaining employees at Bowater would not be faced with the same decision and be forced to be laid off, what job security do they have under your agreement?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>I'm sure this is just obstinance and I'm sure it's late in the session so they don't really want to hear the answer, but the negotiation of the job levels are done with the union through their collective agreement. The jobs that are in place through the union contract are the ones that will allow them to safely operate the two paper machines at the facility.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>PREM. - SPENDING SPREE: SERV. PROVISION - EFFECTS</heading>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Madam Speaker, my question is to the Premier. Last week the Minister of Finance kicked off a $610 million spending spree, a spree that will be paid for largely with borrowed money. This is a bit of a surprise given that just before the last election the then Leader of the NDP, the now Premier said, "That dramatically affects the ability of future governments to be able to provide services &#x2026; it will affect everything from health care to the ability to reduce taxes."</p>
<p>I will table that for the benefit of the Premier. Given the Premier felt that way before the last election my question to him now is, will he agree that his spending spree this time will also decrease the province's ability to provide services and make life a little harder for Nova Scotians in the future?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, the simple fact of the matter is, unless the Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party is suggesting that we shouldn't be replacing bridges, or that we shouldn't be paving roads, or that we shouldn't build infrastructure, it is necessary to have a capital plan each and every year. This is a good plan; it is set out for everyone to see, which I know is a novelty for the Progressive Conservatives.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92">
            <from>MR. BAILLIE</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, what's a novelty for Nova Scotians is a Leader that says one thing before the election and keeps to the same tune after the election, that's what a novelty is and that is the point here today. The fact of the matter is the capital plans in this province over the last decade have averaged around $300 million, but he's just launched an amount twice that as a spending spree this year. This is the same Premier that said before the election in that same article, "This is not a race to see who can spend the most money." My question to the Premier is, will he stop the race to spend the most money and assure Nova Scotians that he is serious about reducing debt and not adding to it every year?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, that's a fair challenge, so I'll meet his challenge. Name one project in a Progressive Conservative riding that you would have me cancel. (Interruptions)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>MR. BAILLIE</from><p>Yes, well, Madam Speaker, that is an old trick and the Premier knows it. No one knows an old trick better than our Premier, apparently. Here's another novelty. In the NDP's election platform they made a commitment to Nova Scotians, and that is that the NDP is committed to ensuring that Nova Scotians live within their means - certainly a novelty now if we've ever seen one. This is another example of an NDP broken promise. This one just happens to be a very expensive one, paid for with more debt.</p>
<p>So my question to the Premier is, will he admit today that the promises that he made to Nova Scotians back in 2009 were in fact meaningless and that the $610 million spending spree that he's now engaged in is just another example of an expensive promise made with borrowed money?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined"><from>THE PREMIER</from><p>Well, Madam Speaker, I'm sure the former chief of staff for the former Tory Government understands that the way the capital plan works is that each year what actually gets added is the amortized cost of the plan to the government. He knows that. I don't think he was referring to me as an old trick, he was referring to past Progressive Conservative Governments and the things that they used to do.</p>
<p>We instead like to very plainly set out the infrastructure plan and the capital plan for the people of the province so they can transparently understand what it is that the government of the province is doing.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Colchester North.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>PREM.: PUBLIC EDUC. FUNDING - PROTECT</heading>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>HON. KAREN CASEY</from><p>Madam Speaker, my question through you is to the Premier. Nova Scotia's education partners - representing the province's teachers, parents, Acadian parents, school administrators, and elected board officials - spoke out today to warn that further funding cuts to education will negatively impact students in the classroom. These are the same partners who spoke out in the Fall of 2010 with their concerns about the impact of budget cuts to public education. The government at that time ignored those and continued on with their cuts. In fact, on April 11<sup>th</sup>, the Minister of Education stood in the House and said that she trusted the impact would not be felt in the classroom.</p>
<p>Well, we're hearing now that it certainly is; the realities of the cuts are being felt. So my question to the Premier is, since the minister is not listening or responding to teachers, parents, and administrators about the real impact of cuts, can Nova Scotians count on the Premier to protect public education funding in this province?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, the truth of the matter is that per-student funding in this province has gone from $5,800 per student in 2001 to $10,370 in 2011 - a huge increase in the per-student funding in this province.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>MS. CASEY</from><p>Madam Speaker, there has been lots of talk about education funding, and what this government fails to recognize is the complexity in the classroom and the increased costs to deliver those programs.</p>
<p>Representatives from the home and school association said in the conference today that they, as parents, are extremely concerned about funding. Home and school associations raise funds to support school activities for their children, and when the provincial association was asking individual home and school associations how much money they raised for their schools, the local associations were reluctant to share that information. In some cases they refused to share it. We were told this morning that the reason they refused is for fear that if the government had those numbers, there would be additional cuts to those particular school boards.</p>
<p>The minister has been telling some education partners and the school board members informally that there will be cuts in the next budget. So my question to the Premier is, will there be additional cuts to the funding for public education in this coming budget?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>I want to point out, and I know the Education Critic for the Progressive Conservatives - oh, I'm sorry, I mean the Education Critic for the Tories - no, for the Liberals - already knows this. The simple fact of the matter is that we have 30,000 less students than we had 10 years ago.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>MS. CASEY</from><p>Madam Speaker, this morning the Nova Scotia Federation of Home and School Associations gave an example of how this government's gouging of public education has affected them in the classroom. Before last year's funding cuts, home and school associations would raise money for extracurricular events, for playground equipment and other additional services for their children. This, by the way, is the accumulated surplus fund that the minister at one point suggested school boards could use, failing to recognize it is fundraising money. It's not accessible to the school boards to use.</p>
<p>Now these associations are continually forced to raise money for essential classroom supplies like batteries for calculators, markers for white boards and bulbs for projectors. Madam Speaker, will the Premier show the leadership that's needed around the Cabinet Table, the leadership to identify public education as a priority and to fund it adequately to support programs for students in our province?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, there are 300 more teachers in the school system today than there were 10 years ago when there were 30,000 less students. The question is, how much more money do the members think need to go into the system?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Bedford-Birch Cove.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>WOMEN, STATUS OF: DOMESTIC VIOLENCE POLL - COST</heading>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728">
            <from>MS. KELLY REGAN</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, women's organizations in this province are under-resourced and underfunded. While service providers should be focusing their energies on serving their clientele, they have to spend a lot of their time and energy worrying about levels of funding from year to year. On top of this, the cost of service delivery is climbing with the high price of power, fuel and increased taxes. Women's service providers, the very service providers who are forced to stretch every dollar to the maximum to meet their clients' needs, those service providers are asking us exactly how much money was spent on a recent domestic violence poll?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#5da6e0aa-9066-4b5c-8d26-9222b854db7e">
            <from>HON. MARILYN MORE</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I don't have that information but certainly I can check it out and make it available to the honourable member.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728">
            <from>MS. REGAN</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, my question is, will the minister commit to tabling the amount of money spent on a public opinion poll and the printing costs of the poll results?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#5da6e0aa-9066-4b5c-8d26-9222b854db7e">
            <from>MS. MORE</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I do have to check with my staff and just understand better the details of that request. I don't feel I'm in a position to commit to tabling it with any specific time period but I will check into it. Thank you.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728">
            <from>MS. REGAN</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, since this government can commit to funding an annual poll to tell us what we already know, will this government commit to multi-year funding for these community-based organizations that serve women?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#5da6e0aa-9066-4b5c-8d26-9222b854db7e"><from>MS. MORE</from><p>Madam Speaker, as I outlined in my response at the press conference yesterday for the Women's Action Alliance for Change, we've taken a multi-pronged approach in this province. We're helping to build the capacity of our voluntary sector. Certainly this government made a one-time trust fund available to the voluntary sector of $800,000 and many of the women's organizations made applications and some of them received funding through that.</p>
<p>In addition we've increased our budget to support the capacity-building through retaining and training volunteers. Other funding programs across other departments have provided additional funding for women's organizations. We understand the challenges that they face providing critical programs and services in our communities and we are trying to assist and support them in every way possible. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>PREM. - MOBILE PAVER: LOCAL INDUSTRY - COMPETITION</heading>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Madam Speaker, my question is to the Premier. Yesterday the government chose to express its displeasure at an important private industry in our province by purchasing a $3.7 million mobile paver. I will point out that that cost doesn't even include the accompanying equipment that's needed to make it truly mobile and truly work, and as we all know from the media, it was bought in Florida.</p>
<p>My question to the Premier is, why bully a competitive, homegrown Nova Scotia industry by &#x2026;</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Order. The use of the term "bully" is unparliamentary. I'd ask that you retract it and rephrase your question, please.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92">
            <from>MR. BAILLIE</from>
            <p>I didn't realize that, and I apologize.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>I recognize the honourable Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party on his retraction.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>MR. BAILLIE</from><p>Thank you, Madam Speaker. I didn't realize that and I do retract that word.</p>
<p>My question to the Premier is, why push around a competitive, homegrown Nova Scotia industry by using their own tax dollars to compete against them?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Well, Madam Speaker, what we're actually doing is ensuring that there is a competitive process, so that the government is not left with no option in areas of the province where it is clear there has not been a competitive process over the years. What we can say is it's clear, given that the cost per kilometre of paving has come down, that that process works.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92">
            <from>MR. BAILLIE</from>
            <p>Well, Madam Speaker, if the problem is tendering, a better way would have been to work with this very industry on improving the government's tendering practices. The other benefit of that better way is it would have saved $3.7 million, which could have been spent on something like, say, a ferry for Yarmouth or applied against our debt. My question to the Premier is, why did he reject working with these important Nova Scotia suppliers, like our road pavers, on better tendering?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>The reality, Madam Speaker, is that we do work with all the members of that industry. In fact, in the capital plan that the member has just been criticizing and doesn't seem to support, there is a great deal of work that will be done by that very industry.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>MR. BAILLIE</from><p>Madam Speaker, there is a pattern here. The government didn't like the prices pharmacists were charging, so they legislated a solution. They don't like the way that non-unionized workplaces are organized in our province, so they legislate a solution. Now they don't like the prices that contractors are charging, and they reject working with them and instead use their own tax money against them to buy their own paving crew.</p>
<p>My final question to the Premier is, who is next on the NDP hit list?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, instead of taking the kind of hidebound, ideological approach that is taken by the Progressive Conservative Party, we look at this from a very practical perspective. The only question we seek to answer is, what is in the best interests of the people of Nova Scotia? We make our decision on that basis.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Richmond.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>JUSTICE - MACINTOSH CASE: SYSTEM BREAKDOWN - EXPLAIN</heading>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Madam Speaker, last week residents of the Strait area and all Nova Scotians were shocked to learn that the Nova Scotia Court of Appeal overturned Ernest Fenwick MacIntosh's convictions on 17 charges of indecent assault or gross indecency.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, the Court of Appeal ruled that Mr. MacIntosh's rights had been violated because prosecutors took too long to bring him to trial. My question is, will the Minister of Justice explain to Nova Scotians this breakdown in our justice system?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#d36a0432-7994-4030-ab00-b21fc858e7d2">
            <from>HON. ROSS LANDRY</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, the question is an interesting one in itself. The matter is very complex. It involved the federal government. It also is a matter that is before the court and is under appeal - it could potentially be under appeal, and it is being looked at by the Justice Department. I respect the process and will allow it to go its course.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>MR. SAMSON</from><p>Madam Speaker, Mr. MacIntosh was first charged in the 1990s. It wasn't until 2007 that he was brought to Canada from India to face these charges. His defence lawyer said that it took prosecutors over a year to provide full disclosure. It was July 2010, three years after Ernest Fenwick MacIntosh was brought back to Canada, before his first trial began.</p>
<p>My question is will the Minister of Justice explain to Mr. MacIntosh's victims, their families, and all Nova Scotians, what took so long for the Nova Scotia Public Prosecution Service to bring Ernest Fenwick MacIntosh to trial?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#d36a0432-7994-4030-ab00-b21fc858e7d2">
            <from>MR. LANDRY</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, the Public Prosecution Service is an independent arm process within government. As I say, the matter that they have 60 days in which to review the case, it would be inappropriate for me to take a position one way or the other on the matter while that process - I respect the judicial process and I would ask that the member across from me respect the process as well.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>MR. SAMSON</from><p>Madam Speaker, with all due respect to the minister, victims and their families right now feel the process broke down, and they feel that the process has not worked the way it should have worked for the fact that it took so long and, after a court found Mr. MacIntosh guilty, the Appeal Court has decided to overturn his convictions because it took our justice system too long.</p>
<p>Whether it is the federal justice system or the provincial justice system, victims were let down by what happened here. Nova Scotians are left to wonder what went wrong - more importantly, what can we learn from this exact case to ensure that such a situation does not happen again?</p>
<p>My final supplementary is will the minister order a full investigation and review into the conditions and events which led to the breakdown of our justice system that allowed the Court of Appeal to overturn Mr. MacIntosh's convictions on 17 charges?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#d36a0432-7994-4030-ab00-b21fc858e7d2">
            <from>MR. LANDRY</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I want to assure the families who were affected in this particular case, and all Nova Scotians, that their safety and their concerns are of the utmost importance of this Justice Department and this government. As I said before, it would be highly unprofessional and inappropriate for me to comment in regard to this matter until the respective processes in law are followed. I will respect that process and defend it.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Argyle.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>PREM. - CLARKE, RICK: APPOINTMENTS - EXPLAIN</heading>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>Madam Speaker, my question is to the Premier. In recent weeks we've raised serious concerns about one of the Premier's key economic advisers, Nova Scotia's Federation of Labour President Rick Clarke and his influence on the government. Last week Mr. Clarke misled a committee of the House when discussing his opinions about the Michelin Bill. We know now that Mr. Clarke was invited late last week to another NDP sham committee, the Finance Minister's Economic Outlook Conference. The minister seeks Mr. Clarke's advice on topics like the province's fiscal plan and taxation, where Mr. Clarke will undoubtedly continue to argue, as he has, for higher taxes.</p>
<p>My question to the Premier is, why does the Premier and members of his government continue to seek Mr. Clarke's advice and appoint him to more and more NDP committees, when he is so clearly committed to the serious events of misleading a committee of this House?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I believe the member opposite is just simply mischaracterizing what it is that Mr. Clarke has said over the years. I find a complete degree of consistency in the representations he has made. He volunteers his time, along with members of the business community, along with members of many other groups around the province in order to provide advice. It is the availability of a wide spectrum of advice on which people have particular areas of expertise that is important to this government, as it should have been to the former government, but apparently wasn't.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52">
            <from>MR. D'ENTREMONT</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I know many of us can list hundreds of people who can volunteer their time to tell the Premier what he should be doing or what he shouldn't be doing. I can tell you that there are thousands, thousands of Nova Scotians who would be willing to provide (Interruptions)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Order, please. The honourable member for Argyle has the floor.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>MR. D'ENTREMONT</from><p>&#x2026; would be willing to provide advice to the Premier. We know that on November 30<sup>th</sup>, in committee, Mr. Clarke said with regard to the possibility of repealing the Michelin Bill: I've been the president of the Nova Scotia Federation of Labour since 1989 and that issue has never come out of our lips in all those years.</p>
<p>But we now know that in a 2006 ChronicleHerald article he called the Michelin Bill a bad piece of legislation and said the Michelin Bill is still a sore issue that the organization raises with every new Minister of Labour.</p>
<p>My question to the Premier, when will the Premier fire Mr. Clarke and stop protecting this individual who has so clearly violated the trust of members of this the people's House, and therefore Nova Scotians?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>The question that is being put by the member opposite is clearly just a matter of rhetoric, and I'm sure it makes him feel good, but let me reassure him that Mr. Clarke is the president of the Federation of Labour. He is elected by the majority of the delegates to their annual convention. He, at least, is democratically elected, unlike the advisers that used to provide information to the former government.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>MR. D'ENTREMONT</from><p>The Premier knows that when someone calls a specific bill a sore issue, and something he raises with every Labour Minister, to repeal, to gut, to end run the bill and that no reasonable person would ever treat an answer in saying the issue has never come out of our lips as being the whole truth and nothing but the truth.</p>
<p>My final question, Madam Speaker, will the Premier set a higher standard - the truth, the whole truth and nothing but the truth - and fire Rick Clarke today?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Well if I set that standard there would be a few worried people that I know of. Madam Speaker, I tell you this, I want to thank all the people who serve on the various agencies, boards and commissions in this province; they work very hard to provide a service to the province. I want to thank the people who work on the Premier's Economic Council. They put aside big chunks of time in order to provide a valuable service to the people of Nova Scotia. They should be congratulated and I do so.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>HEALTH &amp; WELLNESS - HOME CARE SERV.: INCOME LEVELS - REVIEWS</heading>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>MS. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Madam Speaker, my question is for the Minister of Health and Wellness. I recently visited a couple in my riding who are seniors and have been receiving home care services from the Department of Health for a number of years. The housekeeping services that they receive are essential to allow them to remain independent and in their own home. Their income has grown marginally, very marginally, over the years and they are now slightly over the income threshold for receiving this service without a charge.</p>
<p>My question to the Minister of Health and Wellness is, can the minister tell the House when the income levels were last reviewed and adjusted for inflation for this very important service?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9">
            <from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from>
            <p>I thank the member for a very important question. I can't say when those rates were last reviewed, Madam Speaker, but what I am quite happy to tell the honourable member, and all members of the House, is that earlier this Fall I asked my department to do a review on those very fees and so that review is currently underway in the department.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2">
            <from>MS. WHALEN</from>
            <p>Well thank you very much, I'm happy to hear that. I wanted to point out to the minister in this question that a similar department in the Department of Health and Wellness, a similar area - the long-term care support - those income levels are adjusted annually. Every November, we hear of new levels and adjustments to the income and fee levels. So I would like to ask the minister if she will make this an annual review once she has the figures in hand so that we don't get behind in terms of inflation and people who would otherwise be able to remain independent, don't fall out of the service. They really are very reliant on this service to stay in their homes. So my question to the minster is would she make that an annual review at the same time that we review long-term care rates?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9">
            <from>MS. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, home care and long-term care are part of continuing care; they're part of the very important programs that we offer to seniors in Nova Scotia. The review that occurs with respect to long-term care is an annual review. The review that is going on around fees associated with home care is part of our pre-budget preparation and we will continue to review these matters and look at them in the totality of the government's priorities with respect to providing high-quality health care services to seniors in Nova Scotia.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Cape Breton North.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>ERDT: MIN. - FUNDING PRIORITIES</heading>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Madam Speaker, yesterday we learned the details around the cost of the NDP's new paving plan tender. The NDP are paying $3.6 million to an American company for the purchase of new equipment, which will be used to compete with Nova Scotia companies who have already proven they can do the work at a cheaper rate. With that money the NDP could have bought a ferry and brought tourists and investment to Nova Scotia, but rather they are spending $3.6 million of taxpayers' money in Florida.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, my question to the Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism is, why won't the minister get his priorities straight (Interruptions)</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>Order, please. It's difficult. I can't hear the question, and I need to know who he's asking it to. (Interruptions) Order, please.</p>
<p>I would ask the honourable member for Cape Breton North to repeat the question, please.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2">
            <from>MR. ORRELL</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, my question to the Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism is, why won't the minister get his priorities straight or does he have zero influence at the Cabinet Table when decisions are being made that could harm jobs and investment in our province?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#b1bb12cd-3928-4525-bab1-d76d28109b5b"><from>HON. PERCY PARIS</from><p>Madam Speaker, certainly, I don't know where one could buy a ferry for $3 million. I'm not convinced it would be floatable.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, this is a government that does have its priorities right when it comes to jobs because when we took over as government, when we took over the mess that this province was in, and when we sat down and we started consultations in collaboration with the business community, and with experts around the economy, that's why we developed the plan and it's called jobsHere.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. ORRELL</from><p>Madam Speaker, yesterday the minister announced he used taxpayers' money to host the World Skins golf game next summer in Nova Scotia. I and many golf enthusiasts welcome this event but this double-bogey minister didn't even know how the taxpayers' money would be spent. (Interruptions) I didn't say I was a good golfer, I said I'm a golf enthusiast.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, not only did he not know the business case for the money, he went as far as to say that Nova Scotia taxpayers will be helping fill the purse of millionaire golfers who make the winners circle. My question to the minister is, why did the minister approve this spending spree without even knowing what taxpayers' money was going to be used for and what the return would be on the investment?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#b1bb12cd-3928-4525-bab1-d76d28109b5b">
            <from>MR. PARIS</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I was asked the question yesterday and what I said with respect to the money that was invested in this worthwhile event, it was going to be used for marketing and advertising. In pursuit of the question, we were asked to go down into the weeds. Now, if one wants to get down in the weeds, I would be more than happy, I'm going to read to you - broadcast rights, verbal mentions throughout the telecast. (Interruptions)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Order. I recognize the honourable Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism to answer the question.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#b1bb12cd-3928-4525-bab1-d76d28109b5b"><from>MR. PARIS</from><p>Thank you, Madam Speaker. We were asked a question, and I'm about to answer that question. The province will be designated as the official host of the TELUS World Skins Game in 2012. The province will receive full rights to the TELUS World Skins Game logo for all advertising and communication purposes, and collective views of events, PGA participants, for marketing and advertising purposes.</p>
<p>The province will receive the right to execute promotions around the TELUS World Skins Game. The province will have the ability to cross-promote with other event partners. Projected attendance of 10,000 spectators over the two-day event (Interruptions)</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>Perhaps the minister can just table that.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cape Breton North has the floor.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. ORRELL</from><p>Madam Speaker, that was a question that was asked yesterday that he should have answered at that time. The fallout of this minister's decision to cut the funding to the Yarmouth ferry has put the economy of southwestern Nova Scotia in the bunker. This minister can't even hit the green on economic development, let alone score a hole in one. We've lost 6,500 jobs in rural Nova Scotia and the minister continues to ignore the concerns of job creators by making ad hoc spending decisions and damaging our investment climate. The minister needs to stop using his putter to hit the ball off the tee.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, my question through you to the minister is, since he does not understand how to create and maintain jobs &#x2026;</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>Order. I cannot hear the questions. (Interruptions) Order. If you guys can just let me handle this. I can hear the questions, I can proceed with the orders of the day.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cape Breton North, if you could ask a question.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. ORRELL</from><p>We've lost 6,500 jobs in rural Nova Scotia and the minister continues to ignore the concerns of job creators by making ad hoc spending decisions and damaging our investment climate. The minister needs to stop using his putter to hit the ball off the tee.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, my question to the minister is, since he does not understand how to create or maintain jobs, why will he not listen to those who do?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#b1bb12cd-3928-4525-bab1-d76d28109b5b"><from>MR. PARIS</from><p>Madam Speaker, what I will say is that when I hear that question, it's par for the course from that member over there. I kind of chuckled to myself yesterday as I observed the staff from the Third Party gathered around when I was being interviewed, and I said, you know what, maybe I will give them a question for tomorrow, and I think I did.</p>
<p>You know, Madam Speaker, we should be very happy. This is one of those things that we all should be applauding, because what this does is this brings global attention to the Province of Nova Scotia - something that we all need. There are going to be millions of viewers all over the world.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Kings West.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>AGRIC. - LAPLANCHE RIVER ABOITEAU:</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>REPLACEMENT STUDY - DELAY EXPLAIN</heading>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048"><from>MR. LEO GLAVINE</from><p>Thank you, Madam Speaker. My question is for a very busy Minister of Agriculture. Late last month the NDP Government announced it would be spending $500,000 on an engineering study to assess and design a replacement for the LaPlanche River aboiteau. While farmers in this area worry each year about their important land being destroyed by flooding, the NDP Government waited years to commission this study.</p>
<p>My question to the Minister of Agriculture is, why did the NDP Government wait so long to start this initiative?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#d6c0c78d-dcf3-456a-915c-a20ecb33050f">
            <from>HON. JOHN MACDONELL</from>
            <p>I guess it's because the members on the Opposition fought the case to keep the NDP out of government, Madam Speaker.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048">
            <from>MR. GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, many in the area are questioning the reasons behind doing the study in the first place. The $500,000 being used to create the assessment could be put to better use by actually going towards replacing the aboiteau. My question to the minister is, why is government wasting more taxpayer money on a study instead of putting the half million dollars towards actually replacing the aboiteau?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#d6c0c78d-dcf3-456a-915c-a20ecb33050f">
            <from>MR. MACDONELL</from>
            <p>Well I guess firstly, because it's not clear whether or not $500,000 will actually replace the aboiteau. The one that was put in previously by the previous administration, the staff who did that didn't really have the appropriate resources to do it. They kind of nickeled and dimed over three or four years trying to get resources to put that aboiteau in where it was. In less than a year the aboiteau was out and so it really calls for, I think, decisive action and putting the resources in place so we actually can do this and do it right.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048">
            <from>MR. GLAVINE</from>
            <p>If the Tories couldn't get the job done, I think we can count on the Acadians. This aboiteau protects the Town of Amherst and approximately 1,800 acres of marsh land; land crucial to the farming in this area. Since the minister and the NDP Government are committed to spending this money on the study, they should at least do it in a timely manner. Every Fall, farmers and residents in this region are concerned with flooding; the study and assessment won't be completed until the end of 2012. My question to the minister is, why is it taking another full year to arrange this study?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#d6c0c78d-dcf3-456a-915c-a20ecb33050f">
            <from>MR. MACDONELL</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I have to be honest to tell him that as far as the season to get the work done, the biggest part of it has passed. It would have been great to get at this sooner; that wasn't the case, but we're moving as quickly as we can. If it turns out that that timeline can be pushed up so we actually can accomplish the information we need sooner, the minister has my guarantee that I will certainly try to see that gets done.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>PUB. SERV. SUPERANNUATION PLAN - N.S. PENSION AGENCY:</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>FIN. UPDATE - PROVIDE</heading>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2">
            <from>MS. DIANA WHALEN</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, retired members of the public service have been expressing concern over the health of the public service Superannuation Plan. The last full financial update was at the end of the last fiscal year. Since that time, as we all know, markets have been volatile and unstable. With instability comes concern and members are rightly concerned over the health of their pension plan. My question through you to the Minister of Finance is, will the Minister of Finance direct that the Nova Scotia Pension Agency provide members of the plan with a full financial update as soon as possible?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#5e4eedce-ee17-4542-8b27-a1e87f85ec80">
            <from>HON. GRAHAM STEELE</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I'm pleased to say that as a result of the reforms brought in by this government, that plan is healthier than it has been in a very long time. I would also add that as it occurs every year (Interruptions) Apparently they don't want to hear the answer. (Interruptions) Madam Speaker, as happens every year, a full (Interruption) I don't think the members on the opposite side really want to hear the answer.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>I'm listening.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2">
            <from>MS. WHALEN</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I was listening to the answer that the minister was providing. What I wanted to point out was that members of the plan are concerned about talk involving the move towards joint trusteeship in order for them to make good decisions; they need up-to-date information. Their request is that there be information made available more frequently and I'm asking the minister if he will direct the staff at the pension agency to please make an update on the status of that fund so that the pensioners of the superannuation plan will have better information in order to go forward.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#5e4eedce-ee17-4542-8b27-a1e87f85ec80"><from>MR. STEELE</from><p>Madam Speaker, as happens every year, there will be a full valuation as of the end of December. We will &#x2026; (Interruptions) Okay, this is a very important topic, Madam Speaker; it affects literally tens of thousands of people and if the member for Halifax Clayton Park wants to hear the answer, perhaps she could start by controlling her own members.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, as happens every year, there will be a valuation as of the end of December. Pension plans, which are heavily invested in the market, of course, tend to go up, they tend to go down. It's not particularly helpful to provide unaudited, unofficial reports on the health of the fund monthly or quarterly or anything like that. The most useful thing is to do a full, complete, reliable evaluation as of December 31<sup>st</sup>; that is what has happened in every previous year and that is what will happen this year.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2">
            <from>MS. WHALEN</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I would just like to ask the minister, what steps will the minister take to ensure that all retired members have all the information that they need, financial and otherwise, as this plan moves toward joint trusteeship?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#5e4eedce-ee17-4542-8b27-a1e87f85ec80">
            <from>MR. STEELE</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, there is full, complete information available and I'm pleased to say that on the committee that is working toward joint trusteeship, there is full membership of the retired employees association. I don't think it would be possible from us to be more open than we are being already.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Inverness.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>JUSTICE - CROWN ATTORNEYS: CONTRACT TALKS - STATUS</heading>
          <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff">
            <from>MR. ALLAN MACMASTER</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, my question is for the Minister of Justice. In our justice system, Crown Attorneys play a vital role in the protection of the public. They represent the interests of the public at bail hearings, trials and appeals. Without their dedication and hard work our streets would be much less safe. Can the minister advise the current status of contract talks with our Crown Attorneys?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#d36a0432-7994-4030-ab00-b21fc858e7d2">
            <from>HON. ROSS LANDRY</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I, too, agree with you that the Crown Attorneys do an excellent job in this province and they are a valuable asset. The discussions and process from the administration of dealing with their contracts is outside of my immediate control and is being managed by the appropriate administrators within the system.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff">
            <from>MR. MACMASTER</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, the last time the pay and benefits of Nova Scotia's Crown Attorneys was an issue the matter went to binding arbitration and the prosecutors got a 15 per cent raise. Now that was a few years ago. Our information is that they are seeking another significant raise to keep their pay and benefits competitive. The federal government pays more, as do many other places, and these are highly educated, sought-after, mobile people. Does the minister have plans to offer the Crown Attorneys a significant raise or does he have a contingency plan on how to handle a complete work stoppage of our justice system?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#d36a0432-7994-4030-ab00-b21fc858e7d2">
            <from>MR. LANDRY</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I want to make a distinction between this government and the previous administration. It should be made clear, this government believes in honouring the collective bargaining process. We respect the people who have to negotiate and in here they have my utmost support and respect, and those people who are working in that industry, I support them and allow them to do their jobs. Unlike the Opposition Party themselves, they really don't care about the employees, they only want a show.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff"><from>MR. MACMASTER</from><p>Madam Speaker, the point I'm pointing out today is that the government, for its recent passing of first contract arbitration, may be getting caught with their own legislation and may impact their own government.</p>
<p>I don't know if the minister is aware, but there is discussion amongst Crown Attorneys, spurred on by this government's passing of the first contract arbitration legislation, of forcing the government into arbitration. Applying a leading case from the Supreme Court of Canada, Crown Attorneys feel they have been handed an opportunity, the argument that not only is the government obligated to bargain with them, as if they were permitted to have a union, but also to apply the same rules applicable to unions, meaning first contract.</p>
<p>My question for the minister is, had the minister even thought of this possibility and has he advised our Minister of Finance of the sizable financial exposure to the government if Crown Attorneys are able to force the government into first contract arbitration?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#d36a0432-7994-4030-ab00-b21fc858e7d2">
            <from>MR. LANDRY</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I'm going to keep this relatively simple. This government does not negotiate contracts on the floor of this House. We respect the process and we value people who work within it.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>JUSTICE - ANNA. RYL. FAM. COURT: SCHEDULING CHANGES - CONFIRM</heading>
          <speech by="#fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5">
            <from>HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL</from>
            <p>My question is for the Minister of Justice. Recently it has come to the attention of the Annapolis County barrister association that the Department of Justice is seeking to make changes to the dates and times of sittings of Family Court in the county. This would change from the present schedule of two Thursdays a month to a new schedule which would have the court sit on Mondays. The changes would have the number of sitting dates reduced so that in four months of the calendar year in 2012 there is only one court date available. My question to the minister is, will the Minister of Justice confirm whether the department is seeking scheduling changes to the Family Court in Annapolis Royal which would result in the reduction of sitting dates?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#d36a0432-7994-4030-ab00-b21fc858e7d2">
            <from>HON. ROSS LANDRY</from>
            <p>I thank the member for the question. In regard to the courts and scheduling of the courts, the third arm of the government, being the judiciary, they have the right to set and manage their court processes. Any impact on the community and the community as a whole, the department does take a look at and sees the impact but we respect the fact that there is an independent process there to make decisions on when they sit and how they sit.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5"><from>MR. MCNEIL</from><p>According to the barrister association this has been considered without any consultation, Madam Speaker. It seems the scheduling changes are done without the complete understanding of how the court operates. For many of the litigants who are represented by Nova Scotia Legal Aid and other lawyers who are from Kings and Digby Counties, Monday presents significant scheduling challenges. In addition earned days off for staff are normally taken on Mondays, in fact, to quote a letter from the minister on November 3, 2011: Having Family Courts sit on Mondays in Annapolis Royal is completely and utterly impractical and not workable.</p>
<p>My question to the minister, will the minister ensure that no changes are made to the scheduling of the Family Court in Annapolis Royal without first holding meaningful consultation with the affected stakeholders?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#d36a0432-7994-4030-ab00-b21fc858e7d2">
            <from>MR. LANDRY</from>
            <p>I believe that there should be consultations in any process with multiple clients and I believe that all sides need to have some flexibility when it comes to scheduling. Looking at efficiencies and workable aspects within any system is critical. We also have to look at what the economic impact each decision has on the province and in the system that is being affected. I encourage people to have open discussion and dialog.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5"><from>MR. MCNEIL</from><p>I'm encouraging the minister to follow the words of his letter that was written to the Annapolis County barrister society and ensure that court will not be sitting on Monday in Annapolis Royal but the present schedule will be maintained until there's meaningful consultation. According to the Annapolis County barrister association sittings in Annapolis Royal typically deals with 10 to 20 cases on any given day. Reducing the numbers of days in which court sits now will dramatically impact on access.</p>
<p>It is the barrister association's contention that these changes will result in the court being unable to meet the schedule mandatory dates as required by Children and Family Services Act. Access to courts is a serious issue and it is practically acute in rural areas. My question to the minister is, what steps will the minister take to ensure that the full consultation takes place and that access to justice is not adversely affected by any changes of scheduling in Family Court settings in Annapolis Royal?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#d36a0432-7994-4030-ab00-b21fc858e7d2">
            <from>MR. LANDRY</from>
            <p>I will definitely guarantee that looking at the issue that I will take a look at the matter but respect those that have responsibilities to make decisions and encourage the open dialogue in the flexibility within all.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Argyle.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>NAT. RES. - TICKS (YAR. CO.): PRESS RELEASE - CONSULTATION</heading>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>Thank you very much, Madam Speaker. Yesterday we learned that ticks carrying Lyme disease were found in Yarmouth County in my constituency. The Department of Natural Resources is doing ongoing field work and surveillance but it did not consult local MLAs, myself or the member for Yarmouth, or residents, prior to sending out this warning flag yesterday.</p>
<p>My question to the Minister of Natural Resources is why did the minister not consult with local MLAs or anyone else about his findings prior to the announcement yesterday so that they could collectively develop a strategy to release this information to the public?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#4fbcc786-c835-4a0e-bd05-40afb30e0683">
            <from>HON. CHARLIE PARKER</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, certainly blacklegged ticks are an issue of concern in our province. I think there are six areas now identified where these insects are found. Lyme disease is a serious disease that none of us want to see on any of our residents in the province. Basically we've gone from a system of passive surveillance to a system of active surveillance. It allows for a better way to determine whether the tick is located in any neighbourhood. It's certainly the last thing we want to see in any part of our province.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52">
            <from>MR. D'ENTREMONT</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, people don't appreciate finding things out in the news or the local paper or on the radio. It can cause a little bit of undue hysteria that can be avoided when everyone is properly informed. My question to the minister is, what consultation is the department going to do with the local community on ways to protect themselves from ticks and recognize the warning signs of Lyme disease?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#4fbcc786-c835-4a0e-bd05-40afb30e0683">
            <from>MR. PARKER</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, as I mentioned, active surveillance is a better way that the department has now to have access to the data, the results, and which communities are impacted by this insect and by this disease. It's a system where our department personnel go out into the various communities around the province and actively dragnet or trap small mammals to find the tick in the neighbourhood. It's a better way to determine the extent of the problem in our province. If the honourable member is interested in a briefing or an update from the department, we could certainly arrange to fill in and get more information for him.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>MR. D'ENTREMONT</from><p>Madam Speaker, in a rush to get this information out I feel the minister missed a very important step in properly consulting the local people of Yarmouth County. Like I said, it's not just one MLA but two. Gavelton is a beautiful community that has the line going up the middle of it. Part of it is in Yarmouth and part of it is in Argyle, and neither one of those members received any kind of heads-up or briefing or even a forward copy of a press release.</p>
<p>So my question through you to the minister is, what process will the minister put in place to help ensure this misstep does not happen in other communities across this province?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#4fbcc786-c835-4a0e-bd05-40afb30e0683"><from>MR. PARKER</from><p>Well, this insect - the blacklegged tick or deer tick - is a concern to all of us in our province. We have consulted with the general public. We've consulted with veterinarians and other doctors and other health care professionals, and we recognize it is a real threat to residents in our province.</p>
<p>We're doing our best to monitor it and keep a close eye on it, but again, honourable member, if you want an update, I would be more than willing to arrange for staff to sit down with you and perhaps the member for Yarmouth also. We'll give you the latest and all the good information that is available, and anybody else who is so interested.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Richmond.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>TIR - RTE. 4 PAVING: RESCHEDULING - CONFIRM</heading>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be">
            <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, work is still continuing on Route 4 between St. Peter's and Sydney during the winter months. Would the minister advise whether next year's section of that paving will be called earlier to avoid winter paving on Route 4?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#8dbda583-1553-4164-a616-3008fb0fdac4">
            <from>HON. WILLIAM ESTABROOKS</from>
            <p>Yes, yes, yes. (Applause)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The time allotted for the Oral Question Period has expired.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </questions>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT BUSINESS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Madam Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Private and Local Bills for Third Reading.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PRIVATE AND LOCAL BILLS FOR THIRD READING</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Madam Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 38 and I so move.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 38 - Yarmouth North Baptist Church Act.</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 99 - Archdiocese of Halifax-Yarmouth Act.</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 101 - Halifax Kennel Club Incorporation Act.</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 132 - Acadia Recreation Club Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motions are carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that these bills do pass. Ordered that the titles be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bills be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Public Bills for Third Reading.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PUBLIC BILLS FOR THIRD READING</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Madam Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 120.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 120 - Liquor Control Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I move third reading of Bill No. 120.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Bedford-Birch Cove.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>MS. KELLY REGAN</from><p>Thank you, Madam Speaker. As my colleague, the member for Halifax Clayton Park has articulated, the Liberals have some concerns with this bill, particularly the way it treats people who run U-Vins. We've been through this a number of times. What it does is criminalize people who are running a perfectly legitimate business that offers a service, frequently to people who are not able to haul the containers that hold the alcohol up and down. They perform this service for people in my riding, in the member's riding, and there has been no indication that there is any criminal activity associated with this in any way, shape, or form, yet the government persists in criminalizing what is a legitimate business activity.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I just want to go on record indicating that I do think that this particular part of the bill is punitive to a legitimate small business here in Nova Scotia and, quite frankly, I disagree with it and I think it's not necessary to go to these lengths.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, with that I will sit down. My colleague, the member for Halifax Clayton Park may have something to say on the matter, but I'll sit down now. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Inverness.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff"><from>MR. ALLAN MACMASTER</from><p>Madam Speaker, we will not be supporting this piece of legislation because there's a need for innovation, and I see that these small- business owners who are providing this service are creating innovation in the marketplace by helping people who may not have the space at home to brew - not to brew but, I guess, to make wine.</p>
<p>I guess I'm reminded of things that have happened in the recent past with the NSLC, like a movement towards agency stores. I know of a lot of communities, including my hometown of Judique, we have one in Whycocomagh. Madam Speaker, I recall the NSLC saying at one time that we could never have a store in Whycocomagh because it would never hit the threshold of sales required for a stand-alone store, which at the time was $1 million. In the very first year with an agency store, not even a full-fledged store, they achieved over $1 million in sales. Probably because Whycocomagh, especially in the summer, is an area that we have a lot of visitors travelling through along the highway.</p>
<p>My point is, government in the past has been open to innovation, with things like agency stores, open to innovation in terms of allowing Nova Scotian product to get on the shelves at the liquor commission. I think of just one example, Garrison Brewery. Once they had some placement on the shelf, they were able to start selling their product - look at that success story today. They have a number of product lines, it's creating jobs for Nova Scotians and that's because governments allowed innovation to happen.</p>
<p>We believe this bill goes against the idea of innovation and that's why we're not going to support it. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>MS. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Madam Speaker, I realize that the amendment I proposed during the Committee of the Whole House on Bills for this was not accepted by the House. The amendment would have allowed the bill to pass, giving the NSLC the power to seek an injunction against any anticipated or actual illegal activity that related to alcohol. At the time, I said I support that kind of power, provided it's going for things that are really detrimental, we're talking about bootlegging or stills in the woods or things that are dangerous to the health and safety and responsible drinking of the public.</p>
<p>When we're talking about U-Vins, I don't believe any of that is a factor. I thought that it was not wise to have taken the time of the chief public health officer to come to Public Accounts as the sole person speaking in favour of this bill because Dr. Strang said himself, he'd never had any complaints that linked directly irresponsible drinking to the operation of these little stores that sell kits to make your own wine and beer.</p>
<p>It was pointed out that if cost and cheap liquor is the problem, we should be looking at NSLC's current practice of advertising sales and marketing with flyers and big ads in the newspaper offering their gift cards now in other locations, you don't even have to go to a liquor store to buy gift cards. All those things are encouraging consumption. A small business like a U-Vin store is not going to be encouraging irresponsible drinking; in fact, they do the exact opposite.</p>
<p>Today I introduced a petition in the House and I wish I had it in front of me or I'd read the operative clause again, but it called on the government to allow U-Vins to operate in this province as they do in many other provinces in Canada. Most recently, Saskatchewan, P.E.I. and New Brunswick have made these operations perfectly legal. They've clarified any ambiguity in their Acts and made them legal.</p>
<p>Just to respond to one of the government's concerns or perhaps one of the - I would say fabricated - excuses for not doing this, there seems to be a concern for the local wine industry or the sale of wines as well at the NSLC. In the three provinces that have done this most recently, you see a steady increase in the number - it's measured in the litres of sales of wine and it has gone up and up every year. Consistently no change in that trend with the introduction of U-Vins in the stores.</p>
<p>So, I have to point out to the minister and to the other members of the Legislature, there is no detrimental effect to the sales at the NSLC and there is no detrimental impact on the small wineries - I know it is a small agricultural and tourist industry that we're trying to nurture. This will only encourage people to go to those wineries, it encourages people to try wine and to get more interested in the different varieties of wine and thereby they purchase more. I've said that in the past and I say today that the evidence is clear and you can see those charts and they support what I am saying.</p>
<p>What I see here is very much a David and Goliath scenario. We see a huge monopoly in our province - the NSLC - who have the total control over sales of liquor and the regulation, it appears, of liquor and now the enforcement of some of those regulations. Through this new bill, we've given them this entire range of activities going far beyond their role as a retailer. In my speaking in second reading I said, they're a giant retailer that is now going to be able to squash competition and to squash and hurt other players in that business. The minister says they're not just a retailer, they're a regulator and then I'd say, why is the regulator in charge of sales as well? There's not a good separation of the responsibilities here.</p>
<p>I don't think it's leading to a very sound policy, I think it's leading to policy that has been influenced by the NSLC and their own petty concerns. I actually asked the question, what about the other players? We were told there are 30 stores right now, little community stores, offering wine kits for sale. Five of them have been allowing their customers to brew on premise, to do the ferment on premise, which means only what the member for Bedford-Birch Cove was saying, that if you have difficulty handling the big vats and the big jugs that they use of product as they're being mixed up, you get help by leaving them in the store, by mixing them up and having space in the store to leave them.</p>
<p>Today's petition also included a column for comments and when I read through that I saw comments like, get with the 21<sup>st</sup> Century. Other comments said, just get it done. Why are we in Nova Scotia so determined to be behind everyone else, to be the last to adopt an innovation, to be the last to protect a monopoly, to hide behind false information? This is not evidence-based at all.</p>
<p>Going back to the 30 stores that exist in the province, if this were made legal and the ambiguity were taken away - and it has been described as a grey area in terms of the operation of the brew-on-premise and ferment-on-premise. If the minister would stand up and remove that ambiguity so that this was legal all 30 of those stores would be happy to participate. If they have complained to the minister it's only that they wanted the minister to make it clear and make it legal. He's had representation, Madam Speaker. People have gone - both the industry association, various national associations, various independent small-business people - to see the minister and written to the minister and appealed to him to show the leadership to put up on a firm footing into the 21<sup>st</sup> Century, to support what is a hobby, to help seniors who can't even participate in this unless they have the opportunity to do it in a store location, to help people in my riding who have said repeatedly, if you live in an apartment or a condominium you don't have the space to set aside for a big hobby and a bottling operation like this.</p>
<p>I think it's very clear to the members of this House who are thinking straight, that this is just a poorly-conceived bill. It may be something that the minister is pleased that he's now stomped on a little industry, stomped it right out, he hopes. In the provinces where this has come into play, where it has been allowed, it has come about because there have been retailers willing to question the current laws and to try to get their provinces to be more progressive.</p>
<p>We see an NDP Government here today that is being the opposite to progressive, it's regressive. I know I've spoken to members of the NDP and the government Party saying, how could you change your mind like this? A few years ago there were letters from the now-Premier, when he was Leader of the Official Opposition, that were sympathetic to this operation. There were people whose ridings either had these brew on premises or wine kit stores in their riding who also were sympathetic, who heard from their own constituents, as I've heard from mine, that this is something that they dearly want.</p>
<p>I'm going to tell you, if we make it illegal and if the NSLC chooses to use this heavy-handed power that I believe we're about to hand to them - and it will not be me adding my vote to that, I can assure you, Madam Speaker, the Liberal Party is not supporting this bill. But if the NDP are determined to stomp on a little business, a small business that shows innovation and stamp it out, you will continue to hear from disgruntled Nova Scotians who can't believe that what is legal in New Brunswick and legal in P.E.I. and has been legal for 20 years or more in Ontario, is not going to be allowed here.</p>
<p>As we try to encourage all of those people to come back to Nova Scotia and take up the jobs that we hope will materialize through the new contract that the Irving shipyard has won and we hope other spinoffs that come from that. They're going to return here and do exactly what we've heard already from Milton and others who moved to the province, when they walk through the doors of these stores and say, I'm here to brew some wine and I want to do it and how does it cost to set it on the shelf here? They're going to be told, you can't do it in Nova Scotia, we think that's bootlegging or we think that's illegal, we think that the kit you've just bought is - you know it's a grey area, it's been challenged in the court, Madam Speaker. It was not a straight-out loss, it was two counts that the store owners was found absolutely not guilty on.</p>
<p>The police themselves, Madam Speaker, have ceased to harass these small businesses because they know it's a grey area. That's why the minister is here today, bringing in a new Act that circumvents the police. Now we don't have to wait for the police to make a call about whether it's illegal or not, we're now going to ask the NSLC, the competing retailer with huge clout, huge dollars, huge monopoly, to move against small business. We're going to let them decide when they think it's illegal rather than waiting for the police.</p>
<p>The Minister for Communities, Culture and Heritage, who was speaking up here today, Madam Speaker, might be wise to think whether or not his constituents would like to see this service. Maybe there's some people who live in Sackville who would like to use this service and do you know what? They're not going to be allowed to. The people who move around the country, like our large military representation here in Nova Scotia, we have a lot of people moving into our province because they are transferred here with the military, they are astounded as well when they see that we are living in the past, that we have this regressive law for no apparent benefit to anybody but the NSLC, that we are protecting this monopoly, the Nova Scotia Liquor Commission, over the well-being of the people who live in the community who want this service, who see no harm, that we can measure other provinces that have it and we can see no harm is caused.</p>
<p>We know that you can get permits from the federal government, that you follow all the health regulations, that you're not selling to minors. In fact I must mention, Madam Speaker, there are even some rules in place in other provinces that don't allow you, in fact that make more restrictions on what you do with the wine that you brew in these premises. One is that often it says that you can't use that wine at a wedding and that is to help their sales of other wine, I assume, so that people don't rely on that for large gatherings, so events like weddings are precluded.</p>
<p>The government could have said in some of their own restrictions on this. I'm here today, Madam Speaker, just to speak on behalf of the 602 people who signed the petition that I introduced today and also I had introduced over 600 names on an earlier petition a couple of years ago. People have seen as well - I'm sure the members of the House have seen there have been letters to the editor and I know I've received letters at my constituency and I hope many of you have, too, because this is going to stomp on the rights of many people who see this as a very simple activity, a simple hobby that they have.</p>
<p>These are not young people. These are seniors, these are women, these are people who live in smaller apartments and homes, who don't have space. As I say, I'm offended for them that we are going to be such a backward location. This sends a signal - I've said it before, it's a small issue that's here on the table. This is only going to affect a small number of businesses, maybe hundreds, I would say hundreds and more customers but in the scheme of the business of the Government of Nova Scotia, this is not a big issue but believe me, it sends a big signal. It sends a signal of being backward, of going back in time to the exact same stance the Progressive Conservative Party had towards this.</p>
<p>It was much more understandable when it was a Progressive Conservative Government touting the dangers of something that is so clearly benign and not dangerous. However, the government today is just the same as the Progressive Conservative Government before them in their response, so I can only assume the minister is taking all his direction from the very same people. I don't see any evidence that the minister has used his own good sense to move on this and to correct what was obviously a mistake.</p>
<p>I'm very disappointed to see that that's the case and that there's an arrogance and a lack of concern for small businesses that could benefit. They could have more employment, they could be more profitable, they can provide a service that matters to people.</p>
<p>I can tell you and I would ask the minister to look at the petition and look at the comments that people put in there. Many of them lived in the Fairview riding in the petition that I brought forward today and they lived in other ridings in this province as well, and what you're going to do is drive some people out of the province, just as they have in the past, they will go to New Brunswick and they will enjoy just the same hobby that they, through this bill, will be denied again in Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I think I have said the major points that are necessary. This is a nasty bit of business right before us today, a nasty piece of legislation - petty, unnecessary, really uncalled for in this Legislature. It could have been completely reversed by the amendment that I suggested which would have said, yes, if the minister has some other big, illegal activities that he wants to get after through the NSLC's greater powers, by all means go for it, but exempt the "ferment on premises" which the Governments of P.E.I. and New Brunswick in just the last couple of years have clarified and made perfectly legal.</p>
<p>So once again, are we going to be the last province in Canada dragged kicking and screaming into the future. I think, looking at this bill, that the answer is yes. I am really disappointed in the government's response to what should have been a simple, straightforward yes. We need to have a province where the answer is, yes, we will see how that can be done. Let's see if we can work with business.</p>
<p>They have just shown themselves here - the government, Mr. Speaker. the government has shown itself to be much like the HRM government and business says here that when they come to HRM they have to jump through hoops and do this, do that, and nothing is ever good enough, and usually they end up going elsewhere to build where they want to build or to do their business. If they go to Moncton, they are told, how can we do it, let's work together, let's figure out a way, this is great, let's try and work on creating a little bit of economic activity. Now the government is doing the same thing here, the Government of Nova Scotia, slamming the door on a small business that is showing some innovation.</p>
<p>As I say, it is not even so dramatic, it is legal in more than five provinces; B.C., Saskatchewan, Ontario, P.E.I. and New Brunswick, and possibly others that I'm not aware of. But definitely those five and more 20 years, Mr. Speaker, in Ontario this has been allowed - for more than 20 years - and as we all know, Ontario has a growing and very strong wine industry, allowing a few stores to operate in communities and allowing people to enjoy the hobby of making their own wine is in no way going to harm the industry. It's going to create more people who enjoy wine in a responsible and sensible manner.</p>
<p>With that, Mr. Speaker, I will take my seat on third reading and I would like to reiterate that without the amendment in place that the Liberal caucus had suggested, we will not be supporting this bill. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Dartmouth North.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#4993eadf-848c-4786-8f94-855a5b2bc709"><from>MR. TREVOR ZINCK</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I will just take a couple of moments to speak to Bill No. 120 and I want to begin by thanking the honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park, who spoke quite passionately, as we're all aware here today, and who has taken up this fight on behalf of the local small business in her community and constituents who desire this service over the last number of years. So I want to congratulate her on taking a stance today, as the Opposition Party has as well.</p>
<p>My office over the last week, when this bill was first introduced, has been approached. E-mails and phone calls came in from around the province from a number of seniors who use this service who have made the point that economically it is a benefit to them. Seniors living on fixed incomes and pensions that aren't being indexed, seniors who are residing in apartment complexes.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, as we grow in HRM and we look at the developments and the future developments, especially in the Clayton Park area, but also in the downtown core in the future, we're talking about high-density complexes and luxury apartments and condominiums. We think of King's Wharf, the development in Dartmouth South, downtown Dartmouth. These are luxury apartments that seniors are going to move out of their homes and move into these complexes and the space just does not allow them to facilitate this kind of procedure. So there is a definite benefit here.</p>
<p>I want to go back to the Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism's jobsHere plan. I believe with the passing of Bill No. 102 on Friday - part of his plan was to help businesses be more competitive globally. Well, we shot that down with Bill No. 102 on Friday, and I believe here today with Bill No. 120, the minister's plan has a second hole in it because his plan calls for innovation and helping businesses be more innovative. Here is an opportunity for small business to be more innovative and grow in our province, to serve a population that is aging. Our seniors' population will age and will double in age over the next couple of years, and this is a service that we've obviously been contacted by a number of them that they use and they appreciate.</p>
<p>The member for Halifax Clayton Park had made mention of the monopoly of NSLC. Here we have a New Democratic Government that has always stood in their place and supported small business, or made mention that they have, and this is an affront to small business and to future small business. Not just with the Vin Art stores, but anybody in the future thinking about being innovative and bringing something new to this province as we grow.</p>
<p>You know, we talk about Ships Start Here and the Irving contract, and I've made mention in this House that when we're trying to invite former residents back here, they want to come back to something. What are they coming back to? Is it an economy that's booming, are there jobs, are there homes? What kinds of businesses and atmosphere, economically, are they coming to, entertainment wise? We're taking a step back and Nova Scotia, for some reason, we've always lagged behind. We were called back woods in some respects, but I did not expect to see this come from an NDP Government, an NDP Government that has always embraced small business, or at least spoke to that point. We've seen it time and time again, we've seen it with Bill No. 100, we've seen it with Bill No. 102, and here we are again with Bill No. 120.</p>
<p>It's disappointing, like I said, Madam Speaker, my office has been contacted by seniors - again, a Party that supported seniors on many different ventures over the years. And with an aging population and more high-density growth coming to the downtown core, these seniors rely on this type of service, but yet our government doesn't see fit to validate it.</p>
<p>It is a monopoly; it is the heavy-hand of government. It's not necessary, Madam Speaker, and I will not be supporting Bill No. 120. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Dartmouth East.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#1e5b7bdc-363b-4df4-8258-edcf8f2bf7fb"><from>MR. ANDREW YOUNGER</from><p>Madam Speaker, I was going to say I'm pleased to rise on this bill, but I'm not pleased because the bill shouldn't be here. At what point do we start giving Crown Corporations the power to go out and act as policemen in their own business? The member for Halifax Clayton Park was quite right when we heard the Minister of Communities, Culture and Heritage say they lost in court. Well, they did. It was actually a mixed ruling. In fact, that's why there hasn't been any future push forward on that issue because it ended up being a bit of a grey area.</p>
<p>So what's the response to the grey area? Well, we haven't been given a reason why the government is moving forward with this bill, so one can only surmise that it's because the Liquor Corporation is really upset that what's going on is people may wish to offer brewing on their premises. Now, what's next? We're going to stop the sale of wine kits and not allow people to sell in their homes? Let's be realistic here.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I got married in Ontario 10 years ago because my in-laws live in Ontario. So we went up there, and all the wine for the wedding was brewed on premises in a liquor store in Ontario. Why was that? Well, because at the time my mother-in-law lived in an apartment and she couldn't set up all the equipment that was necessary in her apartments, it just wasn't realistic. So now we look and say the regional plan here in HRM or even some of the plans in Windsor or in Cape Breton Regional Municipality, they're going towards the idea of having more dense living because it's better for an aging population, it's a better use of resources, it makes efficient use of transit, all those sorts of things. But that means you suddenly don't have the house where you have the basement and the space to do brewing or making of wine at home. It doesn't become realistic or possible.</p>
<p>What happens is the only other option to look at, other than buying commercial wine and beer and so forth, is to have the option of brewing on premises. Now, we know that's not allowed here at the moment. But instead of the government moving to allow that, and actually open up opportunities for economic development and small businesses - we already know there are businesses that would like to get into this across the province, which would mean additional tax dollars from the HST to the Minister of Finance, the accounts that the Minister of Finance takes care of. Yet, instead of going in that direction, he's putting a strangle hold on that market for no apparent reason.</p>
<p>There is no evidence that I'm aware of to suggest that there is any increase in drinking because you can brew on premises, people can already brew at home. There are many people in the House that I'm aware of on all sides who have made wine at home, or made beer, or those sorts of things. but what happens when you move to place that you don't have the space to do that, why shouldn't you be able to brew or make wine in a store that sell the kits under the supervision of people who know what they're doing? How many people have heard stories of oh gees it's it funny that Johnny makes wine and it tastes like vinegar or something. Wouldn't those people like the opportunity to brew or make the wine under the supervision of people who know what they're doing and can guide them through the process? Why is that a bad idea?</p>
<p>Why is it a bad area for something that has worked in other provinces as a small business, why is that such a bad area that we can't allow it here. Why is it such a bad idea that we would forgo the potential tax revenue that comes from that? You can't tell me that every one of those people are instead walking into the Liquor Commission and buying 30 bottles of a commercial wine instead of the 30 bottles that comes out of a carboy. That's not happening. When it came to my own wedding in Ontario that the fact was it allowed my mother-in-law to actually be able to provide all the quests with wine on their table, to be able to brew the wine there and put nice little labels on it and the whole bit. It was great, it was a great option.</p>
<p>Why wouldn't we want to allow that there? There is no other reason for this bill, there's no other reason for this bill other than the fact that the Liquor Commission is ticked off that there wasn't a defendant ruling from the courts and they're worried that the government may come along and allow it so instead they have asked the government to move ahead with this and low and behold they have.</p>
<p>There is no other reason for this. Is the next bill going to be to allow Kent to regulate what Home Depot sells? Why not? That's obviously the next step in this, it makes no sense. We have a court system for a reason and yet the government is introducing a bill, and it's going to pass the bill today, that they only thing it does is it allows the Nova Scotia Liquor Commission to avoid the court process, avoid the juror's prudence that would allow a full and fair hearing because they didn't like the answer they got from the court in the first place and they didn't like the answer that they got from the police when the police said we're not getting involved in this one anymore. Now we're going to turn the Nova Scotia Liquor Commission into the enforcement arm for the competition, give me a break. I sometimes got to wonder where these ideas come from and how they actually get this far. I mean I understand why the Liquor Corporation would ask for it, I completely understand that, but I don't understand why the government would say yes.</p>
<p>There is a small business just around the corner from my office called Wine Sippers and they're just a small business. They have travelled all over North America to different wine and beer shows to see the different kits and they love helping do that, and the one request that they get from people of different ages and different backgrounds coming in there and asking for is they say, listen I can't do it at home can I brew here on premises. The answer is no and now my goodness, can you imagine what will happen if the Liquor Corporation comes in and enforces this.</p>
<p>Here's another one for you, what happens now because we know &#x2013; listen this is illegal too but we know there are a lot of people whose neighbours get together because you get 30 bottles out of carboy and they go into someone's garage or basement and they put together, they all go in on a kit and they make the wine together. So is the Liquor Commission going to go up and start knocking on the doors and say, I'm sorry but you can't all do that because you're brewing on the neighbouring premises there, really? Like really, where does this stop?</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I just don't understand what the need for this is and I listened to the minister's comments when it was introduced and there was no real, rational reason given for why this was. This was - and I'm paraphrasing here - a routine thing that the Liquor Corporation felt they needed. This isn't routine, this has only one purpose, it's an end run around a court decision that they didn't like and that's all there is to it.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, this isn't a good bill, it doesn't make any sense, it doesn't do anything. I challenge the minister to explain how this one iota supports the development of small businesses in our province, how this one iota helps things in terms of economic development or increased potential HST revenue, all things which could have been done by passing the member for Halifax Clayton Park's bill which would allow on-premises brewing. I challenge him to explain that because he can't because the evidence shows that he can't. All you have to do is look at the other provinces to see that.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, here we are at third reading and I don't know if there's even been a sober second thought in the dying minutes of third reading for any bill, under any Party, under any government in the history of this Legislature but let's hope it's today because this cannot possibly be a hill that the government wants to die on. It can't be that important to them.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, with that I just hope that the government lets this sit and lets it die and actually thinks about it before they move forward with this. Or, if this is the hill they're going to die on and they're going to vote on it now, then at least think about it before you actually give Royal Assent and actually enact this legislation because you still have that one last opportunity to not enact this legislation after it comes in place. Thank you very much.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for third reading of Bill No. 120. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill do pass. Ordered that the title be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bill be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 126.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 126 - Police Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I move third reading of Bill No. 126.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for third reading of Bill No. 126. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill do pass. Ordered that the title be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bill be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 128.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 128 - Public Sector Lobbyists Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I move third reading of Bill No. 128.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Richmond.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Madam Speaker, I wanted to make a few remarks on this bill. First, I want to start on a positive note by congratulating the government for bringing forward this legislation. Unfortunately, I believe there are a few relevant institutions that may have been left out from this particular bill.</p>
<p>This issue came to the attention of Nova Scotians, Madam Speaker, I believe it was last year, where it was revealed that some health institutions in Nova Scotia were using the resources of lobbyists to try to convince the government to make investments in their institutions.</p>
<p>Now naturally, Madam Speaker, Nova Scotians were quite concerned at the thought that a publicly-funded institution was using public money with lobbyists to try to get more public money for their institution. Needless to say, it certainly did not make sense. Nova Scotians were very concerned that the precious dollars that should have been going to health care were somehow being used on lobbyists to try to lobby the government itself, which at the end of the day is responsible for these very institutions.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I would be remiss if I did not point out that the stories at the time indicated that there were individuals who were quite close to the government of the day who were doing this very lobbying. If I'm not mistaken I believe the stories indicated about Robert Chisholm and Paula Simon were hired by some of the health institutions to do lobbying on their behalf and, if I'm not mistaken, the former secretary of the NDP, Ed Wark, was also being employed to do lobbying for some of these institutions with the government.</p>
<p>Now regardless of the fact that these individuals obviously have very close ties to the government, the thought that public dollars would be used to hire lobbyists to lobby the government on behalf of public institutions just doesn't make sense, regardless of who the players are. Obviously, I certainly want to commend the government for taking the step but the problem is that there are some very important institutions - or I should say foundations - which are left off the list that is dealt with in Bill No. 128.</p>
<p>For example, it is my understanding that a few of the major health institutions here in Nova Scotia have these fundraising foundations. They are not covered under this bill. So, Madam Speaker, these are institutions that, while they are not public in nature, they are part of public health institutions that are trying to solicit funds on behalf of these institutions. So it wouldn't take much to be able to say that, in essence, they are quasi-public institutions, these foundations. Yet they are not covered by this legislation. It is my understanding that Mr. Ed Wark is still working on behalf of some of these foundations lobbying the government of the day.</p>
<p>Again, as I started, I wanted to be positive in my remarks, or at least part of them, in that I think the government took an important step today but I think there is more that could have been done. These fundraising foundations should be included in the legislation. I still don't think Nova Scotians believe, especially those many generous Nova Scotians who give money to foundations on behalf of health institutions would agree that using their money that they have donated for health institutions to pay for lobbyists to lobby the government is a proper use of the money which they have donated which should be going to those health institutions and providing better health care for Nova Scotians.</p>
<p>Government came close in this case. I think they missed an opportunity to cover off these fundraising foundations as well, which clearly, I believe, should also be covered under this legislation, it should not be using lobbyists to lobby government and using some of that fundraising money to do so.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I hadn't had the opportunity to raise these concerns at earlier stages of debate, so I do welcome the opportunity to put those concerns on the record. Maybe in the Spring the government will bring forward amendments to this legislation to cover off these fundraising foundations based on the concerns that I have raised here today.</p>
<p>With that, Madam Speaker, I thank you again for the opportunity to make those few remarks on Bill no. 128, the Public Sector Lobbyists Act. Merci.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for third reading of Bill No. 128. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill do pass. Ordered that the title be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bill be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 131.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 131 - Snow Sport Helmet Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, I move third reading of Bill No. 131.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for third reading of Bill No. 131. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill do pass. Ordered that the title be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bill be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, with the unanimous consent of the House, I would like to revert to the order of business, Presenting Reports of Committees.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <papers>
        <heading>PRESENTING REPORTS OF COMMITTEES</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Justice.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#d36a0432-7994-4030-ab00-b21fc858e7d2"><from>HON. ROSS LANDRY</from><p>Madam Speaker, as Chairman of the Committee on Law Amendments, I am directed to report that the committee has met and considered the following bill:</p>
<p><b>Bill No. 133 &#x2013; Bowater Mersey Pulp and Paper Investment (2011) Act.</b></p>
<p>and the committee recommends this bill to the favourable consideration of the House, with certain amendments.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>Ordered that this bill be referred to the Committee of the Whole House on Bills.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Madam Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Government Motions.</p>
        </speech>
      </papers>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT MOTIONS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.]</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Madam Speaker, would you please call Resolution No. 2920.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Res. 2920, re Fin.: Capital Plan (2012-2013) - Approve - notice given Dec. 8/11 &#x2013; (Hon Graham Steele)</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Hammonds Plains-Upper Sackville.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#de2082f3-cf3a-4955-8a4e-4f1bf0ac1301"><from>MR. MAT WHYNOTT</from><p>Madam Speaker, I'm certainly honoured to stand today to talk a little bit about this resolution. As we know, on Friday, December 9<sup>th</sup> we, as a government, released the 2012-2013 Jobs and Building Plan. Today I'm certainly pleased to present that plan to the House in detail.</p>
<p>Our Jobs and Building Plan is the right plan for these times that we are living in. The plan invests in projects right across this province that are so important to everyday Nova Scotian families, projects like emergency rooms, schools, roads and hospital equipment. Our Jobs and Building Plan invests $610 million to make life better for families from one end of the province to the other. The projects outlined in this plan will generate direct employment equal to 4,500 full-time jobs in the next fiscal year.</p>
<p>Now, Madam Speaker, we know the Opposition is against this plan; they don't like this plan; they don't like giving jobs to people across this province but we know that this government is behind that plan. These jobs, like the capital projects themselves, will be located in communities, as I said, from one end of the province to the other, from Yarmouth to Sydney. Our jobs and building plan will help grow our economy which is so important to Nova Scotians.</p>
<p>It will mean that government will also live within its means because that's what Nova Scotians want us to do and it will provide better health care to all Nova Scotians. Over the last three weeks my colleagues on this side of the House have travelled the province to share the details of this plan. They've been to Shelburne, to Sydney, to Digby, New Glasgow, Amherst, Liverpool, Annapolis Royal, Pugwash, Halifax, Lunenburg and Chester. Nova Scotians learned that the province is investing $22 million to upgrade aging health care facilities, to provide better care for patients, and an improved environment for health care professionals.</p>
<p>Nova Scotians also learned, Madam Speaker, that $526,000 was being invested to provide home hemodialysis machines for patients in Cape Breton District Health Authority and the Capital District Health Authority, and $420,000 for the expansion of the Renal Dialysis Unit in the Dickson Building in the Capital District Health Authority.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, Nova Scotians have also learned that an additional $100,000 will be invested to support the renovation of the Yarmouth Regional Hospital, to provide space for home dialysis training for patients in South West Health.</p>
<p>Tourism operators, businesses, and community members in Lunenburg learned that the province is providing $750,000 for a design study and structural repairs to upgrade the Fisheries Museum of the Atlantic - that will mean good jobs and more tourist activity right here in Nova Scotia; and students, parents, and teachers in more than 20 communities learned that the province is investing $79 million to construct, upgrade and modernize Nova Scotia's aging schools, creating hundreds of jobs for Nova Scotians. Madam Speaker, I know that that is so important for the people I represent in Hammonds Plains because a new school to be constructed there has already started.</p>
<p>These are just a few examples of how the Jobs and Building Plan is investing in the right projects for Nova Scotians, projects that are helping to create jobs and grow a strong economy.</p>
<p>As I mentioned earlier, the plan will generate direct employment equal to 4,500 full-time jobs. That is tremendous news for the people of this province. But there is more, Madam Speaker, and that is the spin-off jobs resulting from these projects are expected to employ a further 3,100 Nova Scotians. This is all part of our commitment to ensure Nova Scotians have access to good jobs that allow them to stay and build a life here at home.</p>
<p>The projects we have selected are smart, they are strategic, and they are innovative. Investments in information technology, and improved service delivery support innovation and make it easier for government to get back to balance. The Jobs and Building Plan includes $57.2 million for new and ongoing information technology projects throughout government - that's in our health care system, in our schools, in service delivery to businesses and to the public.</p>
<p>It is only the second time in the province's history that the capital plan is being released before the Spring budget; we are doing this because it sends a clear signal of what the province intends to do for the year ahead. This gives the private sector greater opportunity to prepare for upcoming projects, resulting in efficiencies and cost savings for the province. This is the way things should always have been done but, Madam Speaker, it was our government that did it and not those two Parties over there. For example, the early Fall capital budget, coupled with the Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal Department's five-year highway plan, enabled the department to prepare and issue tenders earlier than usual this year - and earlier tenders enabled contractors to better plan their work, which allows for better contract pricing.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, because of good contract pricing, the Department of Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal was able to issue tenders in 2011-12 originally slated for the 2012-13 construction season. These tenders were valued at $15 million, or 56.6 kilometres worth of roads. That means that more roads will be paved in Nova Scotia this year because of decisions made by this government. (Applause)</p>
<p>The 2012-13 capital plan will be subject to the approval of the Legislature, as part of the budget that will be delivered next Spring, of course. In the meantime, work will get underway as soon as possible to ensure prices for goods and services are fair and as low as possible. Our government continues to maximize every opportunity to get the best deal for Nova Scotians.</p>
<p>I encourage all members of the House and all Nova Scotians to take time to read our Jobs and Building Plan. It demonstrates first hand that our government's commitment to improve health care, to have good jobs and economic growth and to live within our means, and most importantly, Madam Speaker, to make life better for families and communities right across Nova Scotia, something that I will say again, that those two Parties are against, thank you very much Madam Speaker.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Kings North.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#22119b83-0505-4c62-95ff-e8c0e378764c"><from>MR. JIM MORTON</from><p>Thank you, Madam Speaker. I'm pleased to rise and say a few words about the resolution and to follow my colleague from Hammonds Plains-Upper Sackville, to talk a little bit about the Jobs and Building Plan, the resolution that was just explained in some detail. As my colleague pointed out, the Jobs and Building Plan intends to invest $610 million in more than 150 projects that will create up to 4,500 full-time jobs in communities across the province.</p>
<p>The plan invests in projects like hospitals, emergency rooms, schools, roads and equipment that are extremely important to Nova Scotians in every corner of our province. This, Madam Speaker, is the second time in the province's history, only the second time, that the government is releasing a capital plan before its Spring budget, a plan that gives those in the private sector, those who have in invested in projects of this kind, an opportunity to get ready to prepare for opportunities and to also give the government the opportunity to realize better savings.</p>
<p>I'd like to talk about a couple of examples that are close to me in the constituency of Kings North, the constituency that I represent. One of the projects in the capital plan for the coming year will be the Aldershot Elementary School where there are some additions and operations that are being planned. The Minister of Education recently announced an investment of $753 thousand in renovations to the Aldershot Elementary School. This is in addition to a previous investment to build a gymnasium which is now largely completed.</p>
<p>The Aldershot Elementary School is a Primary to Grade 5 school with roughly 300 students. This school year, because the school is out of circulation due to the renovations, the students and staff of Aldershot are being housed at the old Kings County Academy, a middle school located in the Town of Kentville. Principal Karen Dyke and the students and staff have been making excellent use of this year and adjusting to their altered surroundings but looking forward, I know, to returning to the new school when it's completed.</p>
<p>The final work on the gymnasium addition is underway, and you know, Madam Speaker, that new gymnasium is not a renovated gymnasium, it's not a replacement gymnasium, it is a new gymnasium. I know that for the last 40 years parents and those interested in the school have been working hard, drawing attention to the fact that they need such a facility and have finally been able to realize that dream. The new gymnasium is going to offer an opportunity for the children of the school to get more opportunities for exercise and fitness. It's going to create more opportunities for fun. It's going to be a resource that will help combat the epidemic of childhood obesity that occurs in my community as well as in communities all across Nova Scotia, and it's another resource for the community at large because gymnasiums offer sporting venues for many minor and other kinds of recreational and sports activities.</p>
<p>The gymnasium, as I said, that work is largely done but the second phase of the project has now has been tendered and the project was awarded to Rosco Construction Limited, a local family-owned business that will be doing that work. The second phase of the renovations to Aldershot Elementary will see upgrades to classrooms, a new learning centre, a library, a music room, an art room, as well as new offices and improvements throughout the building. Those improvements, Madam Speaker, include a new ventilation system as well as a new electrical system in that school which was built as part of a major upgrade of schools in our province in the late 1960s, does not have enough electrical outlets or the right kinds of electrical outlets to allow classroom teachers to use appropriate computer equipment in classrooms.</p>
<p>This is not just about making things safer or making the electrical system just a little better. It's about being able to provide more educational opportunities for the young people who use that school.</p>
<p>Schools are the centre of our communities, the place where we send our children to learn, to make friends, and to grow. In Kings County we recognize the central role that schools play in our children's lives. In recent years, Aldershot parents not only have continued to focus on the need for that gymnasium, but they've also - parents, PTA members, staff, and community groups - contributed their time and efforts to upgrading the school playgrounds. They certainly have been huge boosters of the school community.</p>
<p>Our government applauds this kind of local commitment to our young people. This work, as well as the renovations our government is moving forward on now, is an important investment in our young people. Those kinds of entrepreneurial investments on the part of parents and those friends of the school are very important to the overall welfare of our community. We need that kind of energy and enthusiasm in Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>I'd like to say that the improvements to Aldershot School - the renovations that are happening as part of the capital plan in the community of Aldershot - are just one example of things that have already been happening over a considerable period of time. We also saw a new school open in Kentville this year: a new Kings County Academy located about a kilometre from the previous school. Students have moved into that new building, about 590 of them.</p>
<p>Kings County Academy is a school with a long history. The new building is housing about 590 students from Grade Primary to Grade 8, with 40 teaching staff and 25 classrooms. When students complete Grade 8 in Kentville, they're part of the chain of a family of schools that includes the Northeast Kings Education Centre. Kids from KCA go to NKEC to complete their public school education.</p>
<p>The old KCA had a long and venerable history. There are many people who live in my area who can trace their most important memories to attendance at Kings County Academy, but the building itself was showing its age. It needed extensive renovations if it was to continue in use, and I think the new school was a wise decision. I was very pleased in 2009, just before the provincial election, to be present at the sod-turning of that school, there to support a commitment that we've kept in subsequent years.</p>
<p>The new facility, like the Aldershot School, is an investment in our young people. It's a draw for our community. Schools are one of those institutions that actually encourage young families to stay in our communities, to invest there, to move to Nova Scotia because they know they can provide their kids, the people they love, with appropriate education. As in Aldershot, the new KCA has actually sparked a round of intensive fundraising that's led to raising a considerable amount of money, well over $100,000, to install a new playground that will be of use for the new school. I think the installation of that new equipment is almost in place. The plan to install that equipment occurred during the week that we had quite a large snowstorm in Nova Scotia. Sometimes the best-laid plans of mice and men and school playground committees get side-railed by snowstorms.</p>
<p>I also want to mention that schools like KCA and Aldershot are important centres of community life. They're places where people meet; they're places where parents meet; they're places that draw individuals together. I think this new building and the renovated building in Aldershot will continue to do that for years to come.</p>
<p>Schools, of course, aren't the only kinds of infrastructure that the capital plan is concerned with. In Kings County, the capital plan last and the previous years' capital investment have also done other things. One of the things that I paid a lot of attention to this summer is renovations on the Gladys Porter Bridge in Port Williams, the structure that crosses the Cornwallis River, a tidal river, a river which makes some infrastructure work difficult.</p>
<p>That work is now completed. The new bridge has been completely renovated on the surface and underneath. It's been a challenge for the residents of Port Williams to watch that work unfold because during the course of much of this past summer and the previous summer, the bridge was reduced to one lane. That was a challenge to some of the local businesses that exist in the area and certainly created more waits for commuters who might be crossing the river to either return home to Port Williams or to Canning or to travel to Wolfville or to Halifax.</p>
<p>I think what people can be assured of, at this point, is that they have a safe structure; a structure that now looks like it is safe on the surface because it has new rails and is much more attractive than it was before. The Gladys Porter Bridge which, by the way, is named after a former Member of the Legislative Assembly, whose picture hangs in this room, is connected to part of Highway No. 358 which was resurfaced last summer.</p>
<p>What we were able to do in that resurfacing, also through the capital plan, was add wider shoulders to the road, which makes it safer for pedestrians and cyclists, people who ride bicycles. That's been very important to a community like Port Williams, which has many young families whose older kids travel to school at Horton. Many of the people who live in Port Williams have a strong relationship with the Town of Wolfville and use both the bridge and that road to either walk or cycle to destinations in Wolfville or in Horton, so those wide shoulders have been very important and appreciated by citizens of the area.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I want to mention just a couple more things before I sit down. This summer saw infrastructure work as well and some paving in the area that I represent. One of those areas was the Black Rock Road, which borders the constituencies of Kings North and Kings West. It's a road that has been in serious disrepair, and for probably 20 to 25 years people in the communities of Black Rock in the North Mountain, and the communities surrounding it, have been concerned about the condition of that road. They've complained about problems with their vehicles because of the potholes. Kids who ride school buses have talked about being shaken up. I've had a call from people who were concerned about the ambulances travelling over the road that couldn't use equipment on the trip to the hospital. All of those things, I think, made a very excellent case for the importance of resurfacing and rebuilding that road. That work was completed this summer.</p>
<p>I can assure you, Madam Speaker, the citizens of that area, those people who use that road frequently, certainly understand not only the jobs that were created but the lasting value of investments in infrastructure.</p>
<p>Now I can say that same thing about those people who live in that part of Kings County who use the Cambridge Road, a road that's also - it's part of Kings North, primarily in Kings South, but for many people who live in Wolfville and parts of the community that I represent who need to travel to Central Kings, another high school, or to Kentville or to the other side of the Cornwallis River, as I would say, the Cambridge Road, which was also in very bad repair, is now something that's a pleasure to drive over.</p>
<p>There are also a few people, quite a few people in fact, who live in Lakeville on the Pelton Mountain Road, who for years have been trying to negotiate very deep potholes on a sand-sealed road, the Pelton Mountain Road, who now were beneficiaries of some infrastructure work in a double chip-sealing project. They now can get their vehicles through that road on a regular basis without needing to worry too much about the problems they had before. I know they are extremely appreciative of that progress.</p>
<p>Madam Speaker, I think I've made the points that I wanted to make, the capital plan, our plan for jobs and building, is important because it does create jobs but it's even more important because of the lasting investments it makes in our community. I think that in Kings County we've benefited from a number of those things. I know that Nova Scotians in every part of the province will benefit from infrastructure, some which is highly visible like a new school; some which is less visible like investments in medical equipment; and some which you can hardly see at all because it's under the bridge in Port Williams, but nonetheless, extremely important to the safety and welfare of Nova Scotians in our province. Thank you, Madam Speaker, for the opportunity to say a few words here today. (Applause)</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, that concludes the government's business for today. Tomorrow is Opposition Day, but the hours will be from noon until 6:00 p.m. I believe the House Leader for the Official Opposition will bring some clarity to that. They will be providing us some time and within that time, we will be calling Public Bills for Second Reading, which will be Bill No. 136 and we'll be doing Committee of the Whole House on Bill Nos. 129 and 133. If the House Leader of the Official Opposition is gracious enough to give us that time, that's what we'll be doing.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Opposition House Leader.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#a5e0e841-506b-4c0b-a88e-c09691bd745b">
            <from>HON. MANNING MACDONALD</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, yes, we will complete our Opposition Day business by 4:00 p.m., which will give you two hours to conduct the other business of the House and hopefully move along. Tomorrow we will be calling Resolution Nos. 2886 and 2778. In the spirit of the Christmas season, we're going to forego our late debate tonight. (Interruptions) I move that we now adjourn until the hour of 12:00 noon tomorrow.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the House does now rise to meet again tomorrow, December 14<sup>th</sup> between the hours of 12:00 noon and 6:00 p.m.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
          <narrative>
            <p>The House rose at 5:02 p.m.</p>
          </narrative>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION UNDER RULE 32(3)</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3033">RESOLUTION NO. 3033</num>
          <speech by="#32a29c39-915c-40e7-b749-7c09299ed1f7"><from>Hon. David Wilson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas 16-year-old Katrina Cobean is a student at Sackville High School; and</p>
<p>Whereas Katrina has been a member of the Sackville Corps Sea Cadets since the age of 12 when she joined, following her sister; and</p>
<p>Whereas Katrina received the Top Cadet ANAVET (Army, Navy &amp; Air Force Veterans Medal) award in a Cornwallis service, which is awarded to the top cadet in each trade with exemplary dress, drill and deportment, overall achievements, leadership qualities, instructional abilities, motivation, co-operation with others, an award previously received by her older sister;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate 16-year-old Katrina Cobean who is a student at Sackville High School and who has been a member of the Sackville Corps Sea Cadets since the age of 12, for receiving the Top Cadet ANAVET Award in Cornwallis, and wish her future success in her endeavours.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3034">RESOLUTION NO. 3034</num>
          <speech by="#169d581a-9c34-47f3-9660-9ccb38d06bf4"><from>Mr. Harold Theriault</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on November 22, 2011 the Digby Area Board of Trade held their awards dinner; and</p>
<p>Whereas Jim Thurber received the Life Achievement Award, Digby Neck &amp; Islands Sea Scouts, Hospitality Award; Wharf Rat Rally, Tourism Excellence Award; Fancy Jewellers, Customer Service Award; and</p>
<p>Whereas in addition to these recipients, we also have the Digby Courier who received the Community Contribution (Business) Award; Town of Digby VIC project, Community Contribution (non profit) Award; Wild Rose Farm, Entrepreneur Award; and Sissiboo Investments, Business Excellence Award;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House congratulate each of these recipients on their awards and wish them continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3035">RESOLUTION NO. 3035</num>
          <speech by="#169d581a-9c34-47f3-9660-9ccb38d06bf4"><from>Mr. Harold Theriault</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Taste of Nova Scotia has gone sappy over Sledding Hill's lavender syrup; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Bear River-based company was among more than 900 nominations received for the Taste of Nova Scotia Prestige Awards; and</p>
<p>Whereas Sledding Hill has been singled out for having the province's most innovative product of the year;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly commend Sledding Hill's Martin McGurk and Gordon Tingley on this most impressive product and award.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3036">RESOLUTION NO. 3036</num>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>Ms. Kelly Regan</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Saturday, December 10<sup>th</sup>, the 36 Canadian Brigade Group Band, under the direction of Captain Patrick Forde, CD, presented the Tunes 'n' Tins Family Festive Event, a concert in support of the Halifax &amp; Region Military Family Resource Centre; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Halifax &amp; Region Military Family Resource Centre collected non-perishable or "tinned" food items, as well as $220 in cash donations at the door as a goodwill offering to help support programs and services for military families within the community; and</p>
<p>Whereas the concert provided the audience with entertainment by the members of the 36 Canadian Brigade Group Band, including soloists, a women's choir, and a special reading of <i>The Night Before Christmas</i> by Captain Stephen Morris from FADO/Formation Chaplain;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the members of the 36 Canadian Brigade Group Band for a successful event and thank the Halifax &amp; Region Military Family Resource Centre for important work that they do for military families in the community every day.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3037">RESOLUTION NO. 3037</num>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>Ms. Kelly Regan</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas &#xC9;cole Grosvenor Wentworth Park Elementary School has provided its students with a new computer lab, which includes 28 refurbished terminals acquired from Computers for Schools, a government and industry program; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Parent Teacher Group at the school raised $17,000 to pay for wiring and computer tables; and</p>
<p>Whereas the computers are available to all students at all levels, and there are enough terminals for students to study as a group;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate everyone at Grosvenor Wentworth School who made this computer lab a reality, allowing every student at the school access to the information highway.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3038">RESOLUTION NO. 3038</num>
          <speech by="#169d581a-9c34-47f3-9660-9ccb38d06bf4"><from>Mr. Harold Theriault</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Nova Scotia Youth Orchestra provides students with educational opportunities not available at any university, public school, or conservatory in the province, and is celebrating its 35<sup>th</sup> Anniversary this year; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Nova Scotia Youth Orchestra has been described as one of the finest training orchestras in the country and is currently under the baton of Music Director Dinuk Wijeratne; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Nova Scotia Youth Orchestra is celebrating their 35<sup>th</sup> Anniversary season with concerts in communities in Nova Scotia and with guests including Rory McLeod, Ria Kim, Buck 65, Ben Duinker, Symphony Nova Scotia, and Jonathan Keijser;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the members of the Nova Scotia Youth Orchestra, their music director, board, and staff, and the volunteers past and present who have made this organization a success for 35 years.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3039">RESOLUTION NO. 3039</num>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048"><from>Mr. Leo Glavine</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Jane Warren of Wolfville was honoured on July 2011 by the Nova Scotia League for Equal Opportunities; and</p>
<p>Whereas Jane was recognized for her long-standing and effective leadership within the disability community in Nova Scotia; and</p>
<p>Whereas Jane is a tireless advocate for both persons with disabilities and person living in poverty - often, sadly, the same populations - as well as being a founding member of the Annapolis Valley Brain Injury Association of Nova Scotia;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House recognize Jane Warren of Wolfville for her continued advocacy on behalf of persons with disabilities.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3040">RESOLUTION NO. 3040</num>
          <speech by="#aef785d7-7697-4453-8f9c-eef26e4928c3"><from>Hon. Keith Colwell</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on July 16, 2011, the East Preston Seniors Club celebrated their 21<sup>st</sup> Anniversary; and</p>
<p>Whereas the founding members of the club were Doris Evans and the club's first president, Ida Clayton, and initial meetings were held at the Sarah Jane Clayton Manor until the East Preston Recreation Centre was built, where they then moved into their own room; and</p>
<p>Whereas the club holds fundraising luncheons and dinners to raise money to enable two or three out-of-town trips for their members, and a visitation committee who travels to various nursing homes in and around the area;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating the East Preston Seniors Club for a wonderful 21 years and wish them every future success.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3041">RESOLUTION NO. 3041</num>
          <speech by="#b723d7ff-ed62-4b67-ae5f-83b903707923"><from>Ms. Vicki Conrad</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Queens Learning Network is such an important part of the Queens community; and</p>
<p>Whereas with Literacy Action Week being held the week of November 6<sup>th</sup> to 12<sup>th</sup>, it is important to celebrate the learners and the workers of this very important organization; and</p>
<p>Whereas during the 2011-12 school year a number of Queens students have passed their GED, attained school credits, and moved on to higher education at the community college level;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly recognize and congratulate the Queens Learning Network and all of the students who have benefited from the work of this very important organization.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3042">RESOLUTION NO. 3042</num>
          <speech by="#b723d7ff-ed62-4b67-ae5f-83b903707923"><from>Ms. Vicki Conrad</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas music plays such an important role in the education and growth of our youth; and</p>
<p>Whereas the opportunity for youth to learn to play musical instruments in a jazz stage band setting is a unique and enriching experience; and</p>
<p>Whereas Scott MacDonald of Liverpool has taken the initiative to form, instruct, and direct the Mersey Youth Jazz Band;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the Nova Scotia House of Assembly recognize and congratulate Scott MacDonald for his dedication to providing our youth with unique musical experiences.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3043">RESOLUTION NO. 3043</num>
          <speech by="#b723d7ff-ed62-4b67-ae5f-83b903707923"><from>Ms. Vicki Conrad</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas we know that in the past year, approximately 2,750 Nova Scotians lost their lives to cancer and approximately 6,200 new cases were diagnosed; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Smiley family of Queens County and their relatives have held numerous fundraising events for cancer research, including participation as a team in the CIBC Run for the Cure in Halifax every year since 2001; and</p>
<p>Whereas over the past 10 years the Smiley family has raised approximately $100,000 for cancer research through their fundraising events;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly recognize and congratulate the Smiley family of Queens County for their dedication to ongoing fundraising efforts to benefit cancer research.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3044">RESOLUTION NO. 3044</num>
          <speech by="#b723d7ff-ed62-4b67-ae5f-83b903707923"><from>Ms. Vicki Conrad</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas music plays such an important role in the education and growth of our youth; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Queens County Girls Choir provides the opportunity for girls from Grades 7 to 12 to not only perform on stage but also to compete and record; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Queens County Girls Choir is celebrating its 10<sup>th</sup> year of sharing its talent and music with the community of Queens and beyond;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly recognize and congratulate the Queens County Girls Choir on 10 years of contributing to the cultural education of the youth of Queens.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3045">RESOLUTION NO. 3045</num>
          <speech by="#b723d7ff-ed62-4b67-ae5f-83b903707923"><from>Ms. Vicki Conrad</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas more than 11,000 working Nova Scotians do not hold a high school diploma; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Queens Learning Network is one of over 30 community-based organizations in Nova Scotia to offer adult learning literacy programs from basic level to high school; and</p>
<p>Whereas it is the mission of the Queens Learning Network to provide the opportunity for adults to upgrade their education, to raise awareness of available programs, and to promote the value of literacy and lifelong learning in society;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly recognize and congratulate the Queens Learning Network for its contribution to adult literacy and its promotion of adult learning.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3046">RESOLUTION NO. 3046</num>
          <speech by="#b723d7ff-ed62-4b67-ae5f-83b903707923"><from>Ms. Vicki Conrad</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Options and Opportunities Program provides students with practical experience in their interests as well as giving them job readiness skills, with the goal of promoting teamwork and developing active citizenship in the community; and</p>
<p>Whereas Grade 10 students at North Queens Community School are participating in this program, having already assisted with the setup of the Queens County Fair, with plans to make regular visits to the North Queens Nursing Home, in addition to helping with the maintenance of the Westfield Hall; and</p>
<p>Whereas the North Queens Community School is one of only a handful of schools that involves its entire Grade 10 class in the Options and Opportunities Program;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly recognize and congratulate the Grade 10 students of North Queens Community School for their commitment to their community through their involvement in the Options and Opportunities Program.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3047">RESOLUTION NO. 3047</num>
          <speech by="#b723d7ff-ed62-4b67-ae5f-83b903707923"><from>Ms. Vicki Conrad</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on October 2, 2011, Greenfield, Queens County, held its first Greenfield Salmon Run; and</p>
<p>Whereas 65 runners and walkers from ages seven to 65 from around the province participated in the Greenfield Salmon Run, which included a planked salmon dinner; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Greenfield Salmon run has successfully combined community promotion and publicity with physical activity through its 1.5 and 5.0 kilometre events;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly recognize and congratulate the first Greenfield Salmon Run for its accomplishment of pairing community promotion and publicity with physical activity.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3048">RESOLUTION NO. 3048</num>
          <speech by="#b723d7ff-ed62-4b67-ae5f-83b903707923"><from>Ms. Vicki Conrad</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas 60 singers from 40 countries are performing as the World Youth Choir at the Nobel Peace Prize celebrations in Oslo, Sweden, between December 9-11, 2011; and</p>
<p>Whereas event organizers are joining past World Youth Choir members with present members for the honour and privilege to perform for dignitaries and world leaders at this ceremony of international distinction and respect; and</p>
<p>Whereas past World Youth Choir member Kristopher Snarby of Liverpool is one of only three Canadians invited to participate in this prestigious event;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly recognizes and congratulates Kristopher Snarby for his participation in the World Youth Choir at the 2011 Nobel Peace Prize celebrations in Oslo, Sweden.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3049">RESOLUTION NO. 3049</num>
          <speech by="#b723d7ff-ed62-4b67-ae5f-83b903707923"><from>Ms. Vicki Conrad</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the N.F. Douglas Store was a staple in the community of North Queens for over 130 years; and</p>
<p>Whereas the North Queens Heritage House Museum received a donation of a large collection of merchandise, ledgers, records and memorabilia of the N.F. Douglas Store from the North Queens Heritage Society; and</p>
<p>Whereas on August 18, 2011 the North Queens Heritage House Museum held the grand opening of a new N.F. Douglas Store display, which includes this complete collection in a recreated store;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly recognizes and congratulates the North Queens Heritage House Museum for making this archive of the history of North Queens available to the public.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3050">RESOLUTION NO. 3050</num>
          <speech by="#b723d7ff-ed62-4b67-ae5f-83b903707923"><from>Ms. Vicki Conrad</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Progress Women of Excellence Awards is a prestigious recognition from the Canadian Progress Club's Halifax-Cornwallis Chapter; and</p>
<p>Whereas Nancy Pynch-Worthylake, Superintendent of Schools for the South Shore Regional School Board, received the 2011 Progress Women of Excellence Award for Education and Research; and</p>
<p>Whereas for the past 22 years these awards have helped celebrate the achievements of women in six business sectors who have made a powerful impact on the community through their career, community involvement and personal accomplishments;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly recognizes and congratulates Nancy Pynch-Worthylake for the Progress Women of Excellence Award in the Research and Education category.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3051">RESOLUTION NO. 3051</num>
          <speech by="#b723d7ff-ed62-4b67-ae5f-83b903707923"><from>Ms. Vicki Conrad</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas kidney disease is a serious health concern in our province with approximately 570 Nova Scotians undergoing dialysis; and</p>
<p>Whereas raising awareness of organ and tissue donation is crucial as a kidney transplant can drastically change the life of a dialysis patient; and</p>
<p>Whereas Elaine Park of Queens General Hospital organized Queens County's third annual give the Gift of Life walk to raise money for the Kidney Foundation of Canada, held on October 16<sup>th</sup>, 2011;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly recognizes and congratulates Elaine Park for her initiative and efforts in raising awareness and funds for the Kidney Foundation of Canada.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3052">RESOLUTION NO. 3052</num>
          <speech by="#b723d7ff-ed62-4b67-ae5f-83b903707923"><from>Ms. Vicki Conrad</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Key Club International is a student-led organization whose goal is to teach leadership through serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Key Club at Liverpool Regional High School is involved in several activities throughout the community, including hosting bingo at the Queens Manor in Liverpool and putting on a monthly Crime Prevention Breakfast; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Key Club at Liverpool Regional High School, which includes 35 members, marked their 10<sup>th</sup> anniversary on October 25<sup>th</sup>, 2011;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly recognizes and congratulates the Key Club at Liverpool Regional High School for 10 years of service in their community.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3053">RESOLUTION NO. 3053</num>
          <speech by="#b723d7ff-ed62-4b67-ae5f-83b903707923"><from>Ms. Vicki Conrad</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on October 2<sup>nd</sup>, 2011 Greenfield, Queens County, held its first Greenfield Salmon Run; and</p>
<p>Whereas 65 runners and walkers from ages seven to 65 from around the province participated in the Greenfield Salmon Run, which included a planked salmon dinner; and</p>
<p>Whereas Brad Toms of Caledonia won the fastest male category and placed second overall;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly recognizes and congratulates Brad Toms for his success at the first Greenfield Salmon Run.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3054">RESOLUTION NO. 3054</num>
          <speech by="#b723d7ff-ed62-4b67-ae5f-83b903707923"><from>Ms. Vicki Conrad</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas community involvement is an essential component of our public libraries; and</p>
<p>Whereas Barbara Jones, the South Shore Public Libraries' children's programmer, is facilitating the Brown Bag 'N Learn series at the Thomas H. Raddall Library in Liverpool; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brown Bag Lunch 'N Learn series brings members of the community together with a guest speaker in the informal and informative atmosphere of our public libraries;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly recognize and congratulate Barbara Jones for her initiative in facilitating the Brown Bag Lunch 'N Learn series at the Thomas H. Raddall Library in Liverpool.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3055">RESOLUTION NO. 3055</num>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a"><from>Hon. Ramona Jennex</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Canadian Deep Roots Music Festival in Wolfville, Nova Scotia celebrates Nova Scotia's rich and diverse musical traditions; and</p>
<p>Whereas the 2011 edition of the Deep Roots Music Festival took place September 24<sup>th</sup> to September 25<sup>th</sup>; and</p>
<p>Whereas the festival brings together some of the finest folk and roots singers, songwriters and musicians in the world for a weekend of concerts, workshops and celebration;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House recognizes the work of the volunteers, staff and performers at the Canadian Deep Roots Music Festival, and wishes them continued success.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3056">RESOLUTION NO. 3056</num>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a"><from>Hon. Ramona Jennex</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nancy McBay, of Gaspereau, Nova Scotia was awarded the Nova Scotia Medal of Bravery at a ceremony at Province House on November 16, 2011; and</p>
<p>Whereas Nancy McBay was enjoying a hike in the Kejimkujik National Park along Nova Scotia's South Shore on August 25, 2010 when she noticed people in distress in the ocean; and</p>
<p>Whereas Nancy McBay, recovering from surgery just weeks before, jumped into the water and swam through a massive surge to rescue Maggie Winstanley;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly recognize Nancy McBay's act of bravery and recognize the selflessness she demonstrated to save the life of another.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3057">RESOLUTION NO. 3057</num>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a"><from>Hon. Ramona Jennex</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Wolfville Farmer's Market, which is open year round for vendors to sell goods and services and fresh, local fruits and vegetables, celebrated their grand opening on June 29, 2011; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Wolfville Farmer's Market began with three vendors and has grown to over 60 vendors since 1992; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Wolfville Farmer's Market promotes healthy relationships between vendor and customer, vendor and vendor, vendor and organization, organization and organizations and is welcoming, supportive and inclusive;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly congratulate the Wolfville Farmer's Market for supporting their community and for promoting fair market practice for local foods and services.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3058">RESOLUTION NO. 3058</num>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a"><from>Hon. Ramona Jennex</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the West Nova Scotia Regiment is one of the oldest regiments on the Canadian Militia List, formed from both the 69<sup>th</sup> Annapolis Regiment (1717), and the 75<sup>th</sup> Lunenburg Regiment (1870) in 1936, celebrated their 75<sup>th</sup> anniversary on the weekend of September 9<sup>th</sup> to 11<sup>th</sup>, 2011; and</p>
<p>Whereas when World War II broke out on the 1<sup>st</sup> day of September, 1939 the West Nova Scotia Regiment was mobilized as an active service force battalion and was the first allied unit to land and stay on the continent of Europe for the entire duration of the war; and</p>
<p>Whereas the West Nova Scotia Regiment won 26 theatre and battle honours in addition to the Distinguished Service Order, the Military Cross, Distinguished Conduct Medal and many others; and a monument to the regiment was unveiled on September 11<sup>th</sup> in a ceremony at Camp Aldershot;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly recognizes the West Nova Scotia Regiment, a unit of the Canadian Armed Forces Reserves, for their bravery and their contribution as soldiers to the UN peacekeeping tours and continuous unit training across Canada, United States and Great Britain.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3059">RESOLUTION NO. 3059</num>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a"><from>Hon. Ramona Jennex</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas David McKeage is the executive director and founder of the Brigadoon Children's Camp Society; and</p>
<p>Whereas David used his own experience to recognize the need for children living with a chronic illness the opportunity to be "just a kid"; and</p>
<p>Whereas David works tirelessly to realize the dream of a camp for children;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly recognize David McKeage for his vision, fortitude, tenacity and his love to bring Camp Brigadoon to reality for children who live with chronic illness.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3060">RESOLUTION NO. 3060</num>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a"><from>Hon. Ramona Jennex</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Kings Transit Authority is a public transit bus service that celebrated their 30<sup>th</sup> anniversary in May of 2011; and</p>
<p>Whereas Kings Transit also serves Annapolis County areas, the towns of Bridgetown, Middleton, Annapolis Royal and extends to Cornwallis Park and Upper Clements Park as well as Digby County to Weymouth; and</p>
<p>Whereas Kings Transit is a vital bus services for persons with disabilities by providing low bus floors, a ramp for safe wheelchair use and welcomes seeing-eye dogs;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly congratulate Kings Transit on their 30 years of successful transportation service in the Valley and wishes them continued success.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3061">RESOLUTION NO. 3061</num>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a"><from>Hon. Ramona Jennex</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas K-Rock 89.3 FM is a local radio station located in New Minas, Nova Scotia, that has supported and helped students expand their knowledge and develop the love of music for the fourth year; and</p>
<p>Whereas with the funds from the Canadian Content Development Initiative, K-Rock has donated $36,000 to AVRSB schools on a per-student basis to purchase new instruments and related equipment, or to repair and refurbish existing instruments; and</p>
<p>Whereas many elementary schools have used these funds for instruments such as African drums and hand bells, which are accessible and fun for students of all ages and abilities, and middle schools and high schools acquire new band equipment, including drum kits and keyboards;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly recognize the generosity and contribution of K-Rock in supporting students of the AVRSB music programs and share the expression K-Rock Rocks!</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3062">RESOLUTION NO. 3062</num>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a"><from>Ramona Jennex</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas L'Arche Homefires, located in Wolfville, celebrated their 30<sup>th</sup> Anniversary the weekend of October 7 with an open house at the Applewicks headquarters; and</p>
<p>Whereas all visitors and families enjoyed a fun weekend with live band music, square dancing, face painting, and a turkey dinner at St. Joseph's Church Hall in Kentville; and</p>
<p>Whereas L'Arche Homefires was started in 1982 and has grown to include 21 members housed in five homes and two apartments, enabling residents to live a happy, independent life;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly congratulate L'Arche Homefires as they celebrate their landmark 30<sup>th</sup> Anniversary on the weekend of October 7, 2011.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3063">RESOLUTION NO. 3063</num>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a"><from>Ramona Jennex</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Marilyn Manzer of Wolfville, Nova Scotia, was the recipient of this year's Valley Arts Award during the Deep Roots Music Festival, held in Wolfville from September 23 to 25, 2011; and</p>
<p>Whereas Marilyn sings and plays piano, harp, and recorder, has been a music director with Women of Wolfville, has directed student musicals at Wolfville schools, organizes theatre camps for teenagers, and leads neighborhood carol singing at Christmas; and</p>
<p>Whereas Marilyn has her own music studio and also teaches Kindermusik, is a Raging Granny, has volunteered with Deep Roots Music Festival since its inception, and is past president of the Valley Chapter of the Nova Scotia Registered Music Teachers Association;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly recognize the musical contribution of Marilyn Manzer and express appreciation for her work providing the joy of music for her community.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3064">RESOLUTION NO. 3064</num>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a"><from>Ramona Jennex</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Old Orchard Inn is an all-season resort and spa hotel for over thirty years, located in the scenic Annapolis Valley minutes from Grand Pre, Wolfville, New Minas, and Kentville, Nova Scotia; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Old Orchard Inn staff take pride in providing a warm and hospitable welcome to meet the requirements of guests and families with clean, spacious rooms for romantic getaways, conventions, or business travel; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Old Orchard Inn has two restaurants that serve in an Acadian dining room, which highlight specials on lobsters and Digby scallops, as well as promoting gold award-winning wines from Nova Scotia wineries;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly congratulate the Old Orchard Inn for their contributions to the tourism industry in the Annapolis Valley for 30 years.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3065">RESOLUTION NO. 3065</num>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a"><from>Ramona Jennex</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the New Minas Sunrise Rotary Club has initiated the Purple Pinkie campaign in the New Minas area and every purple pinkie is meant to represent the finger of a child in a country where polio is still an epidemic; and</p>
<p>Whereas Rotary Clubs around the world are promoting the Purple Pinkie campaign to raise funds for vaccinations and to educate people about polio around the world; and</p>
<p>Whereas when a child is vaccinated for polio in a third-world country, the end of his or her little finger is dipped in purple ink to let everyone know he or she has received his or her vaccination;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly congratulate the New Minas Sunrise Rotary Club for its promotion of the Purple Pinkie campaign.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3066">RESOLUTION NO. 3066</num>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a"><from>Ramona Jennex</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 6<sup>th</sup> Annual Tools for Life Conference was held October 28, 2011, at Horton District High School in Greenwich, Nova Scotia; and</p>
<p>Whereas the theme for the Tools for Life Conference was "Together we build stronger, inclusive communities, making living, learning, and working easier" for children, youth, adults and seniors; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Tools for Life Conference offered to the public a wide range of community resources, presenters, and exhibitors, and over 100 local and provincial organizations, agencies, government departments, educational institutions, and businesses who offer information, programs, products, and services to help persons of all ages and abilities;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly congratulate the organizers of the Tools for Life Conference for the positive impact the conference had on all participants and guests and wish them continued success as they plan for next year's conference.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3067">RESOLUTION NO. 3067</num>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a"><from>Ramona Jennex</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Stoney Hill Cemetery in Lockhartville has a new sign that will prompt passersby to remember the remains of a number of folks of all ages, from all walks of life, who have passed on in their final resting place for more than 100 years; and</p>
<p>Whereas money left over from fundraising efforts for a headstone for Ben Jackson and the sale of a DVD celebrating the Ben Jackson ceremony helped in raising funds for this sign; and</p>
<p>Whereas many consider the Stoney Hill Cemetery sign as a visible reminder of a deep history associated with this area;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly congratulate this small five-member committee for their tremendous efforts in having a sign erected for Stoney Hill Cemetery.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3068">RESOLUTION NO. 3068</num>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a"><from>Ramona Jennex</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Valley Harvest Festival celebrates the rich and bountiful Annapolis Valley harvest across the Valley during the month of October with fun activities; and</p>
<p>Whereas each town creates its own unique event for the public's enjoyment, such as the pumpkin fest race, the pumpkin people display, food and wines festivals at vineyards and pubs, the valley pumpkin hunt contest, corn mazes, and harvest teas; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Valley is rich in history and agriculture and is recognized as the ideal climate in Canada for growing tree fruits, grapes, and many vegetables, which can be purchased at local farm markets;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly recognize the Valley Harvest Festival for fun and unique entertainment in the Annapolis Valley for the month of October.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3069">RESOLUTION NO. 3069</num>
          <speech by="#aefec392-99d6-4923-8d87-227e50d567e8"><from>Ms. Pam Birdsall</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Lunenburg resident Elisabeth Bailey has had a lifelong passion for good food made from fresh local ingredients, as well as a strong background as a food and gardening writer, including work for the <i>Canadian Farmer's Almanac</i>; and</p>
<p>Whereas Elisabeth Bailey has just launched her first cookbook, entitled <i>A Taste of the Maritimes</i>, published by Nimbus Publishing and featuring five sections highlighting recipes created with ingredients related to Spring, early summer, late summer, Fall, and winter; and</p>
<p>Whereas <i>A Taste of the Maritimes</i> also features numerous local food producers, including Lunenburg's Ironworks Distillery and Kevin's Natural Meats in West Northfield;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly congratulate Lunenburg resident Elisabeth Bailey on the launch of her cookbook <i>A Taste of the Maritimes,</i> published by Nimbus Publishing.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3070">RESOLUTION NO. 3070</num>
          <speech by="#aefec392-99d6-4923-8d87-227e50d567e8"><from>Ms. Pam Birdsall</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the South Shore Players was established in 1993 to bring a high standard of live theatrical production to the South Shore, and to encourage and provide opportunities for talented amateurs in the field of the performing arts; and</p>
<p>Whereas this December the South Shore Players are presenting their adaptation of "Annie - The Musical", the hugely popular 1970's production based on the Little Orphan Annie comic strip created by Harold Gray and published through the 1920s and 30s; and</p>
<p>Whereas this holiday performance of Annie is taking place at the Pearl Theatre in Lunenburg, with a budget of $12,000, the group's highest budget to date, and a cast of 31 performers and 24 support crew, with six shows over two weekends;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly congratulate the South Shore Players Theatre Group for undertaking their production of "Annie - The Musical" at the Pearl Theatre in Lunenburg for the 2011 holiday season.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3071">RESOLUTION NO. 3071</num>
          <speech by="#aefec392-99d6-4923-8d87-227e50d567e8"><from>Ms. Pam Birdsall</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Emma Beaton and Meghan Broadman, youth board members of the Lunenburg County United Way, travelled to Calgary this past Spring to participate in the United Way Biennial National Convention; and</p>
<p>Whereas local sponsorship allowed the two young women to attend the conference and have a chance to discuss up-and-coming issues with the United Way, share ideas and join discussions about what other United Way groups are doing, listen to guest speakers, and participate in "think-tank" style interaction; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ms. Beaton and Ms. Broadman were given a special honour as the two youngest participants and were asked to introduce and thank the Right Honourable David Johnson, Governor General of Canada, who made the plenary address to the conference;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly recognize Emma Beaton and Meghan Broadman for their participation in the United Way Biennial National Conference in the Spring of this year, and recognize the important role the United Way plays in communities across Nova Scotia.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3072">RESOLUTION NO. 3072</num>
          <speech by="#aefec392-99d6-4923-8d87-227e50d567e8"><from>Ms. Pam Birdsall</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Lunenburg Folk Harbour Festival, started in 1986, is an organization that brings the joy of traditional and contemporary folk music to audiences from around the world, while showcasing the charms of the historic Town of Lunenburg; and</p>
<p>Whereas the book <i>Folk Harbour- The First 25 Years of the Lunenburg Folk Harbour Festival</i>, was launched on November 25<sup>th</sup> of this year, chronicling one of Eastern Canada's most popular musical events; and</p>
<p>Whereas local author and historian Tom Sheppard details the festival, from its beginnings in 1986 to its present form, through a series of photographs, quotes and interviews with founding members that captures the spirit and energy of the festival;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly congratulate the Folk Harbour Society on the publication and launch of <i>Folk Harbour - The First 25 Years of the Lunenburg Folk Harbour Festival</i>.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3073">RESOLUTION NO. 3073</num>
          <speech by="#aefec392-99d6-4923-8d87-227e50d567e8"><from>Ms. Pam Birdsall</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Thailand has experienced some of the worst floods in the last 50 years, losing as much as 15 per cent of their rice crop, causing the disruption of factory operations, and causing widespread unemployment and hardship; and</p>
<p>Whereas Alleson Kase and Ellen Agger of Mahone Bay are the co-owners of TAMMACHAT Natural Textiles, a fair trade company that supports women artisans in Laos and Thailand; and</p>
<p>Whereas TAMMACHAT Natural Textiles is providing much-needed additional income for women and families living in flooded areas of Thailand through fair trade;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly commend Alleson Kase and Ellen Agger of TAMMACHAT Natural Textiles, and wish them safe travels as they return to Thailand to continue to work with women's artisan groups in that country.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3074">RESOLUTION NO. 3074</num>
          <speech by="#20520cce-c7eb-4da6-bc5e-8e9f24f3db6b"><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Philip (Flip) Hochman, the recreation director for the Municipality of the District of Guysborough, was presented with an Honorary Life Membership Award by Recreation Nova Scotia at its annual conference this past October; and</p>
<p>Whereas this award is the highest award presented to individuals with over 20 years of dedication to recreation programs for Nova Scotians; and</p>
<p>Whereas this award was one of only 10 awards given to organizations, community groups and individuals to acknowledge their outstanding contributions to the field of recreation in the Province of Nova Scotia;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolve that the members of this House of Assembly recognize and congratulate Flip Hochman for over 37 years of dedicated commitment to providing quality recreation programs for the residents of the Municipality of the District of Guysborough and many other municipal units located in eastern Nova Scotia.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3075">RESOLUTION NO. 3075</num>
          <speech by="#20520cce-c7eb-4da6-bc5e-8e9f24f3db6b"><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Erinville Volunteer Fire Department, and all volunteer fire departments, provide a critical and selfless community service; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Erinville Volunteer Fire Department celebrated 25 years of such service on October 25<sup>th</sup>, 2011; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers, especially volunteer firefighters, are deeply valued in all aspects of our Nova Scotia lifestyle;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly extend congratulations to the past and present membership of the Erinville Volunteer Fire Department on the occasion of their 25<sup>th</sup> anniversary and wish them every success as they continue their much-valued and well-respected community service.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3076">RESOLUTION NO. 3076</num>
          <speech by="#20520cce-c7eb-4da6-bc5e-8e9f24f3db6b"><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on November 6<sup>th</sup>, 2011 Chris Cook hosted the Route 16 Geocaching expedition; and</p>
<p>Whereas Chris Cook set up the Route 16 Geocaching event online by entering the coordinates of the meeting place and hiding caches for the geocachers to find, with the aid of GPS enabled devices; and</p>
<p>Whereas the 25 participants of the Route 16 Geocaching expedition met, as arranged online, at the Guysborough Courthouse Museum, and took part in this family exploration event travelling to places of scenic and historic interest in the area;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Chris cook on the success of the Route 16 Geocashing event and wish him luck in his future event planning.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3077">RESOLUTION NO. 3077</num>
          <speech by="#20520cce-c7eb-4da6-bc5e-8e9f24f3db6b"><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Conservatory Canada hosted an award ceremony and reception on Saturday, November 19<sup>th</sup>, in London, Ontario, and Guysborough County native Rebecca MacKeen was named as one of the recipients; and</p>
<p>Whereas at the Grade 1 level in her subject, Rebecca MacKeen, daughter of Bruce and Angela MacKeen, earned the highest grade in the province on her singing exam; and</p>
<p>Whereas Rebecca MacKeen, student of vocalist teacher Ursula Ryan, attended the Conservatory Canada award ceremony where she received a Medal of Excellence for her singing exam results;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Rebecca on her high level of achievement within Conservatory Canada and wish her well with her future music competitions.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3078">RESOLUTION NO. 3078</num>
          <speech by="#20520cce-c7eb-4da6-bc5e-8e9f24f3db6b"><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on November 6th, 2011 the Goshen Community and Recreation Centre's 20<sup>th</sup> Anniversary celebration included a presentation of plaques, a power point presentation, a tour and a reception; and</p>
<p>Whereas a plaque awarded in memory of Harold Sinclair was presented to Mina Sinclair and family at the Goshen Community and Recreation Centre's 20<sup>th</sup> Anniversary celebrations in recognition of his contributions to the community centre and the fire department; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Goshen Community and Recreation Centre took over the location of Goshen Consolidated School in 1991 and underwent extensive expansion and improvements and supplied the community with a venue for local events;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly acknowledge the dedication and contributions that Harold Sinclair made to both the Goshen Community and Recreation Centre and the community fire department.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3079">RESOLUTION NO. 3079</num>
          <speech by="#20520cce-c7eb-4da6-bc5e-8e9f24f3db6b"><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on November 6, 2011, a celebration was held at the Goshen Community and Recreation Centre on the occasion of the centre's 20<sup>th</sup> Anniversary; and</p>
<p>Whereas Lewis MacIntosh was the master of ceremonies for the event and he is the MC at most events in the community, as well as serving as the chair of the board for the Goshen Community and Recreation Centre and being very involved in the Kings United Church; and</p>
<p>Whereas Lewis MacIntosh, through his leadership and organizational skills, has dedicated more than 15 years as a volunteer and leader in this community, and his service is greatly appreciated by the residents of Goshen and surrounding communities;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate and thank Lewis MacIntosh for his years of volunteer service and dedication to the residents of Goshen and surrounding communities.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3080">RESOLUTION NO. 3080</num>
          <speech by="#20520cce-c7eb-4da6-bc5e-8e9f24f3db6b"><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on November 6, 2011, a celebration was held at the Goshen Community and Recreation Centre on the occasion of the centre's 20<sup>th</sup> Anniversary; and</p>
<p>Whereas Marie Sinclair's service to the community and the Goshen Community and Recreation Centre has included everything from serving on the executive, event planning, fundraising, organizing, and keeping the centre clean and in good repair; and</p>
<p>Whereas Marie Sinclair, was presented with a certificate of appreciation in recognition of her outstanding volunteer service and her 20 years of dedication, guidance, and leadership provided to the Goshen Community and Recreation Centre Board;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate and thank Marie Sinclair for her years of volunteer work and her unwavering dedication to the residents of Goshen and surrounding communities.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="3081">RESOLUTION NO. 3081</num>
          <speech by="#20520cce-c7eb-4da6-bc5e-8e9f24f3db6b"><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on November 6, 2011, at the Goshen Community and Recreation Centre's 20<sup>th</sup> Anniversary celebration there was a presentation of plaques, a Power Point presentation, a tour, and a lunch to follow; and</p>
<p>Whereas a plaque was awarded in memory of Wilfred MacKeen to his wife Barbie and family at the Goshen Community and Recreation Centre 20<sup>th</sup> Anniversary celebrations, in recognition of his contributions to the community and the fire department; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteer firefighters and their selfless service to their community is much valued and respected by all residents and their respective families;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly acknowledge the dedication and contributions that Wilfred MacKeen made to his community, especially the local volunteer fire department.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </noticesOfMotion>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
