<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.christopher.a.dentremont" showAs="HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="aef785d7-7697-4453-8f9c-eef26e4928c3" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.keith.colwell" showAs="HON. KEITH COLWELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="d36a0432-7994-4030-ab00-b21fc858e7d2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.ross.landry" showAs="HON. ROSS LANDRY"/>
        <TLCPerson id="e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.eddie.orrell" showAs="MR. EDDIE ORRELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.allan.gerard.macmaster" showAs="MR. ALLAN MACMASTER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.chuck.porter" showAs="MR. CHUCK PORTER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="1e5b7bdc-363b-4df4-8258-edcf8f2bf7fb" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.andrew.younger" showAs="MR. ANDREW YOUNGER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8834559e-ddf7-4ac7-9b30-8ada0eb9a7ca" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.zach.churchill" showAs="MR. ZACH CHURCHILL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.karen.casey" showAs="Hon. Karen Casey"/>
        <TLCPerson id="250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.keith.bain" showAs="MR. KEITH BAIN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.leo.glavine" showAs="MR. LEO GLAVINE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="22119b83-0505-4c62-95ff-e8c0e378764c" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.jim.morton" showAs="MR. JIM MORTON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.kelly.regan" showAs="MS. KELLY REGAN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="de2082f3-cf3a-4955-8a4e-4f1bf0ac1301" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.mat.whynott" showAs="MR. MAT WHYNOTT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="e23caf06-dcf3-42a5-8a00-f4435df40350" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.alfie.macleod" showAs="MR. ALFIE MACLEOD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.jamie.baillie" showAs="HON. JAMIE BAILLIE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.michel.p.samson" showAs="HON. MICHEL SAMSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="5c3f8e78-5002-4c61-9c57-730090867f1b" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.wayne.j.gaudet" showAs="HON. WAYNE GAUDET"/>
        <TLCPerson id="08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.diana.whalen" showAs="MS. DIANA WHALEN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.ramona.jennex" showAs="HON. RAMONA JENNEX"/>
        <TLCPerson id="fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.stephen.mcneil" showAs="HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="20520cce-c7eb-4da6-bc5e-8e9f24f3db6b" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.jim.boudreau" showAs="MR. JIM BOUDREAU"/>
        <TLCPerson id="803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.frank.corbett" showAs="HON. FRANK CORBETT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="b1bb12cd-3928-4525-bab1-d76d28109b5b" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.percy.paris" showAs="HON. PERCY PARIS"/>
        <TLCPerson id="a5e0e841-506b-4c0b-a88e-c09691bd745b" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.manning.macdonald" showAs="HON. MANNING MACDONALD"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MR. SPEAKER"/>
        <TLCRole id="clerk" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.clerk" showAs="THE CLERK"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 5 December 2011</docTitle>
      <docNumber>11-59</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2011-12-05">Monday, December 5, 2011</docDate>
      <docProponent>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docProponent>
      <legislature value="61">61st General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="3">3rd Session</session>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>Order, please. We will begin the daily routine.</p>
      </speech>
      <petitions>
        <heading>PRESENTING AND READING PETITIONS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Inverness.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff"><from>MR. ALLAN MACMASTER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I beg leave to table a petition. There were 571 signatures on this petition. It was passed around to food banks across the province, and we've recognized that 40,000 people receive food assistance each month in Nova Scotia. The operative clause in this case is:</p>
<blockquote>&#x201C;THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED THAT the undersigned urge the legislature to pass The Food Bank Donation Tax Credit for Farmers Act to provide support 
				to Nova Scotia&#x2019;s farmers, our food banks and the people who rely on them.&#x201D;</blockquote>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I will affix my own signature, to make it 572 signatures, and I will table it here.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The petition is tabled.</p>
        </speech>
      </petitions>
      <papers>
        <heading>PRESENTING REPORTS OF COMMITTEES</heading>
      </papers>
      <papers>
        <heading>TABLING REPORTS, REGULATIONS AND OTHER PAPERS</heading>
      </papers>
      <ministerialStatements>
        <heading>STATEMENTS BY MINISTERS</heading>
      </ministerialStatements>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2740">RESOLUTION NO. 2740</num>
          <speech by="#b1bb12cd-3928-4525-bab1-d76d28109b5b"><from>HON. PERCY PARIS</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the following individuals have been recognized by the Tourism Industry Association of Nova Scotia with a 2011 Pineapple Award; and</p>
<p>Whereas Becky Tucker of the Holiday Inn Express Hotel &amp; Suites Halifax Airport, the guest services team at Atlantica Hotel &amp; Marina Oak Island, Cameron MacDonald of Harbour Light Campground, and Bill and Ann Marie Monk of A Seafaring Maiden Bed &amp; Breakfast have been celebrated as part of TIANS' recognition of the spirit of service in Nova Scotia; and</p>
<p>Whereas each of these winners has been nominated by ballot in hundreds of establishments throughout the province for going above and beyond to enrich visitor experiences in Nova Scotia;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House congratulate these winners on their Crystal Tourism Awards, and wish all of them continued success well into the future.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Education.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2741">RESOLUTION NO. 2741</num>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a"><from>HON. RAMONA JENNEX</from><p>Mr. Speaker, on behalf of the honourable Minister of Health and Wellness, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas in April of last year the government partnered with the QEII Foundation to invest in improving cancer care and wait times in Nova Scotia, with the foundation setting a fundraising goal of $4 million; and</p>
<p>Whereas the foundation's fundraising campaign, Cancer Never Waits, has already surpassed half of its goal; and</p>
<p>Whereas the construction of the new radiation therapy bunker, which will improve access to care for Nova Scotians, is on budget and on schedule and will begin treating patients next year;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in commending the hard work and commitment of the QEII Foundation to providing better health care for Nova Scotians and their families, and also thank Nova Scotians for their generous support of the QEII Foundation as it works to complete its fundraising for this important initiative.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>There has been a request to revert to the order of business, Presenting Reports of Committees.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <papers>
        <heading>PRESENTING REPORTS OF COMMITTEES</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Justice.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#d36a0432-7994-4030-ab00-b21fc858e7d2"><from>HON. ROSS LANDRY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, as Chairman of the Committee on Law Amendments, I am directed to report that the committee has met and considered the following bill:</p>
<p><b>Bill No. 100 - Municipal Elections Act and Municipal Government Act.</b></p>
<p>and the committee recommends this bill to the favourable consideration of the House, without amendment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Ordered that this bill be referred to the Committee of the Whole House on Bills.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Bedford-Birch Cove on an introduction.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728">
          <from>MS. KELLY REGAN</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker if I could beg leave to make an introduction, I would like to direct the members' attention to the west gallery where Jennifer Cleator is with us today. Jennifer is with Credit Counselling Services of Atlantic Canada, and I'd like her to please rise and accept the warm welcome of the House. (Applause)</p>
        </speech>
      </papers>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>INTRODUCTION OF BILLS</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 127 - Entitled an Act Respecting Debt Settlement Agencies. (Ms. Kelly Regan)</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 128 - Entitled an Act to Prohibit the Use of Consultant Lobbyists by Designated Public Sector Organizations. (Hon. John MacDonell)</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Ordered that these bills be read a second time on a future day.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Hants West.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2742">RESOLUTION NO. 2742</num>
          <speech by="#72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7"><from>MR. CHUCK PORTER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas once a year the wheelchair-accessible Murphy Lake Boardwalk behind the Mount Uniacke Fire Hall becomes filled with people elated to have an opportunity to fish in an annual fishing derby; and</p>
<p>Whereas Owen Greeno from Cheverie and Norman Greeno from Bramber dedicated their time for the entire four-day event helping to bait hooks, cast rods, untangle lines, and handle fish; and</p>
<p>Whereas the fishing derby sponsored by the Mount Uniacke Heritage Society allowed approximately 350 people with a mental or physical disability from all across Nova Scotia the opportunity to try their hand at trout fishing;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly thank Owen and Norman Greeno for their dedication and commitment to ensuring a safe and fun-filled environment for these aspiring anglers, and wish them all the best for future fishing events.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Kings North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2743">RESOLUTION NO. 2743</num>
          <speech by="#22119b83-0505-4c62-95ff-e8c0e378764c"><from>MR. JIM MORTON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas despite their lifelong contributions to our great province, Nova Scotia seniors have been forgotten by previous governments; and</p>
<p>Whereas the NDP committed in the 2009 provincial election to give seniors the option to stay in their homes and communities longer; and</p>
<p>Whereas the NDP Government is fulfilling this commitment by investing $1.8 million to expand the Caregiver Benefit Program, $100,000 in the Personal Alert Assistance Program, ending security deposits for seniors in long-term care facilities, and hiring more nurse practitioners to improve access to primary care;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all Members of the Legislative Assembly acknowledge that the NDP Government is keeping our commitments to Nova Scotia seniors.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Dartmouth East.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2744">RESOLUTION NO. 2744</num>
          <speech by="#1e5b7bdc-363b-4df4-8258-edcf8f2bf7fb"><from>MR. ANDREW YOUNGER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Dartmouth Seniors Service Centre held its 5<sup>th</sup> Annual Community Leadership Recognition Dinner on September 29<sup>th</sup>; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Jack MacNeil was honoured at the dinner for his achievements and his high degree of success both with the Department of Community Services for over 30 years, as a member of the Board of Metro Turning Point for 21 years, and as a deacon of the Roman Catholic Church, currently serving at St. Peter's Church on Maple Street in Dartmouth; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. MacNeil will celebrate this month his 25<sup>th</sup> year as a deacon, having been ordained in December 1986;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Mr. Jack MacNeil on his long-standing and continuing career and for his significant contribution to both Nova Scotia and the Dartmouth community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2745">RESOLUTION NO. 2745</num>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Norma Wasson of Parrsboro understands that Christmas is about giving and has decided this is the perfect time for her to give back to the program that supported her in her time of need; and</p>
<p>Whereas Norma has put a lot of work into decorating her home this season and is holding an open house with proceeds going to the Cumberland Health Care Foundation's Cancer Assistance Fund, which helps Cumberland County cancer patients with costs related to travelling for treatment, nutritional assistance, and medical supplies; and</p>
<p>Whereas Norma battled cancer 10 years ago and again last year, and made numerous trips to Halifax, where she made use of the Cancer Assistance Fund;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House congratulate Norma Wasson on this incredible opportunity to give back, and wish her all the best of health and happiness in the future.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Hammonds Plains-Upper Sackville.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2746">RESOLUTION NO. 2746</num>
          <speech by="#de2082f3-cf3a-4955-8a4e-4f1bf0ac1301"><from>MR. MAT WHYNOTT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Maskwa Aquatic Club athletes dedicate themselves to their sport, competing at Nationals and providing a positive example of healthy living and good sportsmanship; and</p>
<p>Whereas Jacob Steele and Robin Kendall achieved gold in the Midget Men K-2 at the competition; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ciara Jerrett, Jillian Steele, Natalie Miller, and Alexa Irvin won gold in the Junior Women's K-4 500 metre;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House join me in congratulating Maskwa Aquatic Club athletes Jacob Steele and Robin Kendall for winning gold in the Midget Men K-2 and athletes Ciara Jerrett, Jillian Steele, Natalie Miller, and Alexa Irvin for winning gold in the Junior Women's K-4 500 metre at the 2011 Nationals competition.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2747">RESOLUTION NO. 2747</num>
          <speech by="#fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5"><from>HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Saltzman family in Melvern Square was devastated two years ago when fire swept through their family dairy barn, burning it to the ground; and</p>
<p>Whereas out of the ashes arose a new modern dairy barn which contributes to healthier cows and top-quality milk, said third-generation dairy farmer Kevin Saltzman; and</p>
<p>Whereas K&amp;J Farms Ltd. was recognized for their hard work and attention to quality when the family was awarded the Florence Cox Award for Excellence, presented at Farmers Dairy's annual general meeting recently;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating the Saltzman family on being honoured for being tops in their industry.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Victoria-The Lakes.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2748">RESOLUTION NO. 2748</num>
          <speech by="#250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e"><from>MR. KEITH BAIN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas in 1985, the United Nations designated December 5<sup>th</sup> as International Volunteer Day, a day to recognize the many contributions volunteers make to their communities; and</p>
<p>Whereas December 5<sup>th</sup> also marks the 10<sup>th</sup> Anniversary of the International Year of Volunteers, a year-long celebration of volunteerism and volunteers; and</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia is fortunate to have one of the highest rates of volunteerism in Canada, with hundreds of Nova Scotians freely giving their time and talents to improve the lives of those who need a helping hand;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly extend a heartfelt thank you to Nova Scotia's many volunteers and recognize them for their generosity that makes our towns, cities and villages stronger and better.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Guysborough-Sheet Harbour.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2749">RESOLUTION NO. 2749</num>
          <speech by="#20520cce-c7eb-4da6-bc5e-8e9f24f3db6b"><from>MR. JIM BOUDREAU</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas during the 2009 provincial election, the NDP promised to increase the budget for secondary road resurfacing by 50 per cent and to undertake a five-year paving plan so road builders could work more efficiently and communities could count on the roads being improved; and</p>
<p>Whereas rural roads keep most Nova Scotians connected to jobs, markets, health care and education, to their family and to businesses, but after many years of disregard, secondary roads were in terrible condition and presented a challenge for rural communities; and</p>
<p>Whereas since this NDP Government has been elected we did increase the budget for secondary road resurfacing by 50 per cent, we did undertake a five-year paving plan, and we are committed to building stronger communities and making life better for all Nova Scotians;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly acknowledge that the NDP Government has kept this commitment to fix rural roads throughout Nova Scotia and keep communities strong.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2750">RESOLUTION NO. 2750</num>
          <speech by="#fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5"><from>HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Laurie McGowan of Moschelle has not let living in a rural area hold him back from realizing his dream of opening his own home-based marine design business; and</p>
<p>Whereas through patience, technology and his experience in sailing and construction, Laurie is able to employ 3-D software to create detailed blueprints for boat designs that can be marketed to customers all over the world through the Internet; and</p>
<p>Whereas Laurie has successfully taken his dream and turned it into a viable entrepreneurial endeavour in Annapolis County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in congratulating Laurie McGowan on being able to find success in a rural area during these difficult economic times.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cape Breton West.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2751">RESOLUTION NO. 2751</num>
          <speech by="#e23caf06-dcf3-42a5-8a00-f4435df40350"><from>MR. ALFIE MACLEOD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Scott Morrison, of Flavor Catering and Fine Foods in Sydney, recently received the Persons with Disabilities Employer Partnership Award from the Sydney and Area Chamber of Commerce; and</p>
<p>Whereas this award acknowledges and honours employers who have promoted employment, independence and service to persons with disabilities; and</p>
<p>Whereas Flavor was nominated by the Sydney-based EmployAbility partnership for hiring six individuals with disabilities over the last three years;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Scott Morrison and his business, Flavor Catering and Fine Foods, for winning this award, and his commitment to people with disabilities.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Kings West.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2752">RESOLUTION NO. 2752</num>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048"><from>MR. LEO GLAVINE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, on behalf of the honourable member for Digby-Annapolis, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas in the past year the Valley region has lost 1,800 people from the labour force; and</p>
<p>Whereas in the past year there have been 600 people in the Valley who have lost their jobs under this NDP Government; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism has been operating under a strategy with no targets and no measurable outcomes for the past year, which has resulted in rural Nova Scotia suffering from double-digit unemployment rates;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly urge the Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism to start including hard economic targets and measurable outcomes in his strategy and get the people of the Valley back to work.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Inverness.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2753">RESOLUTION NO. 2753</num>
          <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff"><from>MR. ALLAN MACMASTER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Inverness County Literacy Council and their Raise a Reader campaign contribute to improving literacy; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Inverness County Literacy Council runs adult literacy upgrading including small group instruction, preparation for GED, developing skills in math, reading and computer; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers exchange newspapers for donations and were pleasantly surprised with the generosity shown by Inverness County members;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly acknowledge the Inverness County Literacy Council volunteers for their dedication and fundraising efforts to contribute to literacy in their community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2754">RESOLUTION NO. 2754</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>MS. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas in the Spring of 2011 Kristen Cameron of Clayton Park created the grassroots organization Wake Up! as a motivational, environmentally-friendly group, and began by organizing cleanups within our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas over the course of two days in the summer Kristen and her volunteers set out to clean up Eagle's Rock in Bedford and they removed over 14 bags of garbage, six blue bags, and over 50 pounds of broken glass; and</p>
<p>Whereas Kristen has created the Web site <a href="http://www.wakeupns/">www.wakeupns</a> to encourage more people to get involved, contribute their time and ideas, and help clean up their communities;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly join me in thanking Kristen Cameron for her passion and hard work in cleaning up our community and inspiring others to help, and wish her every success in the future.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cape Breton North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2755">RESOLUTION NO. 2755</num>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas thesaurus.com lists commitment and promise as being synonyms and Nova Scotians understand that commitment and promise mean the same thing; and</p>
<p>Whereas it is essential that members use words in the same way Nova Scotians understand them; and</p>
<p>Whereas most, if not all, members of this House, at heart, believe that a promise and a commitment are the same thing;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly declare that promise and commitment mean the same thing and a reference to one cannot somehow exclude the other.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Clare.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2756">RESOLUTION NO. 2756</num>
          <speech by="#5c3f8e78-5002-4c61-9c57-730090867f1b"><from>HON. WAYNE GAUDET</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas each year on December 5<sup>th</sup>, the United Nations observes International Volunteer Day; and</p>
<p>Whereas this day is designed to heighten people's and government's awareness of the invaluable contributions volunteers make to their communities, province and country; and</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia volunteers contribute $1.8 billion worth of services to our economy, with youth participation in volunteer activities making up the highest rate of volunteerism in all age groups in our province;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly acknowledge December 5<sup>th</sup> as International Volunteer Day and extend our appreciation to all volunteers right across this province who sacrifice so much to make Nova Scotia the great province that it is.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Argyle.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2757">RESOLUTION NO. 2757</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, &#xE0; une date ult&#xE9;rieure, je demanderai l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu que Peter Boudreau de Wedgeport a &#xE9;t&#xE9; honor&#xE9; par le Conseil acadien de Par-en-Bas lors d'une r&#xE9;ception le 15 ao&#xFFFD;t 2011, F&#xFFFD;te des Acadiens; et</p>
<p>Attendu que Peter Boudreau a &#xE9;t&#xE9; un b&#xE9;n&#xE9;vole infatigable pendant de nombreuses ann&#xE9;es, de fa&#xFFFD;on extensive et sous plusieurs formes, dans et &#xE0; l'ext&#xE9;rieur de sa communaut&#xE9;; et</p>
<p>Attendu que Peter Boudreau a &#xE9;t&#xE9; engage dans des organisations vou&#xE9;es au d&#xE9;veloppement &#xE9;conomique, au tourisme et aux arts ainsi que dans la F&#xE9;d&#xE9;ration acadienne de la Nouvelle-&#xC9;cosse, qu'il a contribu&#xE9; &#xE0; la promotion et &#xE0; la promotion et &#xE0; la pr&#xE9;servation de la culture acadienne et la langue fran&#xFFFD;aise;</p>
<p>Par cons&#xE9;quent, qu'il soit r&#xE9;solu que tous les membres de cette Assembl&#xE9;e f&#xE9;licitent Peter Boudreau en le reconnaissant et le remerciant de tout son travail et son d&#xE9;vouement au b&#xE9;n&#xE9;volat et l'encouragent &#xE0; continuer son travail dans les ann&#xE9;es &#xE0; venir.</p>
<p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, je demande l'adoption de cette r&#xE9;solution sans pr&#xE9;avis et sans d&#xE9;bat.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Peter Boudreau was named Volunteer of the Year by the Conseil Acadien de Par-en-Bas and was honoured with an award on National Acadian Day, August 15<sup>th</sup>, at a reception held in Wedgeport; and</p>
<p>Whereas Peter Boudreau has been a tireless volunteer for many years and for many causes with his community and beyond; and</p>
<p>Whereas Peter has been involved in organizations focused on economic development, tourism, and arts, and through Nova Scotia's Acadian Federation has contributed to the promotion and preservation of Acadian culture and the preservation of the French language;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Peter Boudreau on receiving this recognition, thank him for all his hard work and dedication to volunteerism, and encourage him to continue his work in the coming years.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Preston.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2758">RESOLUTION NO. 2758</num>
          <speech by="#aef785d7-7697-4453-8f9c-eef26e4928c3"><from>HON. KEITH COLWELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Edie Rossiter was born in Jollimore, Nova Scotia, and moved to Chezzetcook in 1975, and it was there that she raised her three sons and one daughter; and</p>
<p>Whereas Edie and her husband were involved in delivering bread to local food banks and soup kitchens when she and her MLA at the time saw a great need for a food bank to be set up in the Chezzetcook area, and then proceeded to put this idea into motion by obtaining a building and moving it to the present home at the Chezzetcook Fire Hall; and</p>
<p>Whereas Edie and her five permanent, dedicated volunteers, along with various church youth groups, supply food to some 76 families, which represents about 200 to 250 persons, on a regular basis;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly acknowledge Edie Rossiter's many contributions to her community and to her province.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2759">RESOLUTION NO. 2759</num>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas David Moore, a Westchester District volunteer firefighter, was honoured when his peers gave him the title of Firefighter of the Year; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters were honoured by their peers, friends, family and their community in Westchester on November 23<sup>rd</sup> with a meal and acknowledgement of their dedication and sacrifice; and</p>
<p>Whereas David Moore is a dedicated member of the Westchester Volunteer Fire Department who always goes above and beyond for his community to help protect the families and homes in Westchester and the surrounding area;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House congratulate David Moore on being named Firefighter of the Year for the Westchester Volunteer Fire Department, and thank him for his dedicated service to his community and to his province.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Colchester North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2760">RESOLUTION NO. 2760</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>HON. KAREN CASEY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 11<sup>th</sup> annual Nova Scotia Recycles Contest was sponsored by the Resource Recovery Fund Board of Nova Scotia; and</p>
<p>Whereas the contest is designed to encourage students to take a leadership role in improving the environment by promoting waste diversion; and</p>
<p>Whereas this year's students in Grade 12 were asked to submit a research essay on opportunities existing in waste reduction that may pertain to businesses, communities, individuals, and government;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Hannah Kienzle, a Cobequid Educational Centre student from Valley, Colchester North, who won first place for the region and received a $1,500 scholarship.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Victoria-The Lakes.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2761">RESOLUTION NO. 2761</num>
          <speech by="#250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e"><from>MR. KEITH BAIN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Bras d'Or Lakes was officially designated as a United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization MAB Biosphere Reserve in late June of this year; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Bras d'Or Lakes is now part of a global network of biosphere reserves and is one of only 16 found in Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Highland Village Museum in Iona held a celebration ceremony in mid-September, which included the display of a Bras d'Or Lakes art exhibit;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize the significant UNESCO designation bestowed upon the Bras d'Or Lakes.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Bedford-Birch Cove.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2762">RESOLUTION NO. 2762</num>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>MS. KELLY REGAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Donna Alteen is the founder of Time + Space Media, a strategic media services agency in Halifax; and</p>
<p>Whereas when Donna founded the company over 20 years ago, Time + Space Media was the only media services sector company in Atlantic Canada and now is the largest independent agency east of Montreal; and</p>
<p>Whereas Donna currently serves on the boards of Phoenix House and the Christian Children's Fund of Canada and has in the past been a hands-on board member with the Halifax Chamber of Commerce, Ward 5 Community Centre, IWK Grace Health Centre Foundation, National Advertising Benevolent Society, and the Progress Club Halifax-Cornwallis;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Donna Alteen on being named a Woman of Excellence in the Entrepreneur/Innovator category by the Canadian Progress Club Halifax-Cornwallis and wish her every success in her future endeavours.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cape Breton West.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2763">RESOLUTION NO. 2763</num>
          <speech by="#e23caf06-dcf3-42a5-8a00-f4435df40350"><from>MR. ALFIE MACLEOD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Donkin Citizens Brass Band, formed on July 22, 1919, has been going strong for the last 92 years; and</p>
<p>Whereas today the band has 20 members and practises weekly in their band hall, which was built by the Dominion Coal Company and still stands on the original site; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Donkin Citizens Brass Band plays for many events in Donkin, such as Remembrance Day services, Sea Cadets inspections, and churches, as well as their own concerts for the general public;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Donkin Citizens Brass Band as they continue to entertain many people with their wonderful music.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Yarmouth.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2764">RESOLUTION NO. 2764</num>
          <speech by="#8834559e-ddf7-4ac7-9b30-8ada0eb9a7ca"><from>MR. ZACH CHURCHILL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Yarmouth's Dave Hall has enjoyed a long and accomplished career in sales, which includes working for E.K. Spinney and in the automobile industry; and</p>
<p>Whereas Dave Hall began his career at CJLS Radio on December 1, 1986, and is now the station's general sales manager; and</p>
<p>Whereas on December 1, 2011, the staff and management of CJLS Radio recognized Dave Hall's dedicated service, enthusiasm, and initiative as they commemorated his 25 years at CJLS Radio;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Dave Hall on a remarkable 25 years at CJLS Radio, and recognize him and thank him for his commitment to his community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Inverness.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2765">RESOLUTION NO. 2765</num>
          <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff"><from>MR. ALLAN MACMASTER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Lake Ainslie Weavers and Crafts Guild celebrates 20 years of operation at the Scotsville School of Crafts; and</p>
<p>Whereas over the years, hundreds of people have taken classes on weaving, spinning, and other textile crafts, and classes continue to be offered on a regular basis; and</p>
<p>Whereas members of the Scotsville School of Crafts purchased their facility from Inverness County 20 years ago for the sum of $1, and with the help of community volunteers made all the necessary renovations to make the school what it is today;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Lake Ainslie Weavers and Crafts Guild on marking 20 years of operation and acknowledge their passion for arts and crafts.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cape Breton South.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2766">RESOLUTION NO. 2766</num>
          <speech by="#a5e0e841-506b-4c0b-a88e-c09691bd745b"><from>HON. MANNING MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Cape Breton Screaming Eagles began in 1997; and</p>
<p>Whereas over the years the club has been promoting healthy living and have been role models for youth of the island; and</p>
<p>Whereas this year the Cape Breton Screaming Eagles will mark their 15<sup>th</sup> year in the Quebec Major Junior Hockey League;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate the Cape Breton Screaming Eagles for 15 years of success.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cape Breton North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2767">RESOLUTION NO. 2767</num>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Northside Sports Hall of Fame opened its doors in October, thanks to the efforts of a small group of sports-minded citizens who wanted to recognize the accomplishments of notable athletes and builders from the north side of the Sydney Harbour; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Board of Directors of the Civic Centre offered a home for the Hall of Fame inside the new sports arena, and a logo was selected from an elementary school competition; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Northside Sports Hall of Fame will be the first dedicated, self-contained sports hall of fame on Cape Breton Island;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate everyone who worked so tirelessly to make the Northside Sports Hall of Fame a reality.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Kings West.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2768">RESOLUTION NO. 2768</num>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048"><from>MR. LEO GLAVINE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 1966-67 Berwick Shell Juniors hockey team was crowned Provincial and Maritime Junior Champions; and</p>
<p>Whereas head coach Laurie Jordan of Kentville and assistant coach Gary Whittier of Berwick provided the leadership on the bench; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Berwick Shell Juniors hockey team was pleased and honoured to be inducted into the Berwick Sports Hall of Fame in 2011;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly recognize and congratulate the coaches and members of the 1966-67 Berwick Shell Juniors hockey team.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Hants West.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2769">RESOLUTION NO. 2769</num>
          <speech by="#72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7"><from>MR. CHUCK PORTER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas many volunteer instructors across the province give freely of their time to deliver hunter education programs throughout the year; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mike O'Brien from Windsor was awarded the 2011 Hunter Education Instructor of the Year Award by the Department of Natural Resources; and</p>
<p>Whereas the efforts of the more than 160 volunteers who deliver these programs have helped to decrease the number of incidents and make hunting a safe and enjoyable activity;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Mike on receiving this award and thank him for his dedication and commitment to hunter safety.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2770">RESOLUTION NO. 2770</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>MS. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Terry Bremner, a Clayton Park resident who lives with chronic pain, advocates for others who endure daily pain as the president of the Chronic Pain Association; and</p>
<p>Whereas Terry is also president of Action Atlantic, a volunteer group working to raise awareness about chronic pain which affects one in five Canadians, and is the most frequent reason given by Canadians for seeing a doctor; and</p>
<p>Whereas Terry took part in information sessions on chronic pain across Atlantic Canada from November 6<sup>th</sup> to November 12<sup>th</sup> as part of National Pain Awareness Week;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly join me in recognizing Terry Bremner for the important and dedicated work he does in advocating for so many Canadians who are suffering from chronic pain.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Argyle.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2771">RESOLUTION NO. 2771</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, &#xE0; une date ult&#xE9;rieure, je demanderai l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu que le 11 octobre 2011, Greg Kerr, d&#xE9;put&#xE9; de Nova-Ouest, &#xE9;tait &#xE0; Tusket afin d'annoncer un financement f&#xE9;d&#xE9;ral de 34 750 $ pour le March&#xE9; des fermiers et artisans d'Argyle; et</p>
<p>Attendu que ce financement sera utilis&#xE9; pour cr&#xE9;er une exp&#xE9;rience de march&#xE9; public enrichie, tant pour les marchands que leurs clients, en rendant possible l'achat d'une tente de 2400 pieds carr&#xE9;s, le d&#xE9;veloppement du site actuel en ajoutant de l'espace suppl&#xE9;mentaire, du branchement &#xE9;lectrique, de la r&#xE9;frig&#xE9;ration, effectuant des am&#xE9;liorations au stationnement et une meilleure accessibilit&#xE9; au march&#xE9;; et</p>
<p>Attendu que les fonds proviennent du gouvernement f&#xE9;d&#xE9;ral par l'entremise du Fonds des collectivit&#xE9;s innovatrices (FCI) de l'Agence de promotion &#xE9;conomique du Canada atlantique (APECA) en plus d'une contribution mon&#xE9;taire de la Municipalit&#xE9; d'Argyle;</p>
<p>Par cons&#xE9;quent, qu'il soit r&#xE9;solu que tous les membres de cette Assembl&#xE9;e se joignent &#xE0; moi pour f&#xE9;liciter le March&#xE9; des fermiers et artisans d'Argyle sur l'acquisition de ces fonds et leur souhaiter le succ&#xE8;s continu Durant les prochaines ann&#xE9;es.</p>
<p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, je demande l'adoption de cette r&#xE9;solution sans pr&#xE9;avis et sans d&#xE9;bat.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on October 11, 2011, West Nova MP Greg Kerr was in Tusket to announce $34,370 in federal funding for the Argyle Farmers' and Artisanal Market; and</p>
<p>Whereas the funding will be used to create a better market experience for both the vendors and its customers by enabling them to purchase a 2,400 square foot tent, develop the site to allow for additional space, electrical hookups and refrigeration, improved parking and accessibility; and</p>
<p>Whereas the funds come from the federal government's Innovative Communities Fund at ACOA, and is in addition to a contribution from the Municipality of Argyle;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Argyle Farmers' and Artisanal Market on acquiring these funds, and wish them continued success in the coming years.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Richmond.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2772">RESOLUTION NO. 2772</num>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on November 5, 2011, the 824 Silver Dart Royal Canadian Air Cadets took part in Nova Scotia Provincial Cadet Day; and</p>
<p>Whereas the 824 Silver Dart Royal Canadian Air Cadets conducted a three-hour food drive, setting a goal of obtaining 1,000 non-perishable food items for the local food bank; and</p>
<p>Whereas 824 Silver Dart Royal Canadian Air Cadets exceeded their initial goal and were able to gather 1,200 food bank items for the St. Peters Food Bank;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly commend 824 Silver Dart Royal Canadian Air Cadets for their hard work and, as well, for being role models in the community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Clare.</p></speech>
          <speech>
<p>Attendu que Molson Canadian Nova Scotia Music Gala Awards &#xE0; pris place a Yarmouth le 6 novembre; et</p>
<p>Attendu que le gala &#xE0; &#xE9;tabli une cat&#xE9;gorie francophone; et</p>
<p>Attendu que M. Luc Tardif s'est m&#xE9;rite le prix pour l'enregistrement francophone pour l'ann&#xE9;e 2011;</p>
<p>Qu'il soit r&#xE9;solu que tous les d&#xE9;put&#xE9;s &#xE0; cette assembl&#xE9;e l&#xE9;gislative expriment toutes leurs f&#xE9;licitations &#xE0; M. Tardif et lui souhaite un succ&#xE8;s continu dans la musique</p>
<p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, je propose l'adoption de cette r&#xE9;solution sans pr&#xE9;avis et sans d&#xE9;bat.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Molson Canadian Nova Scotia Music Gala Awards were held on Sunday, November 6<sup>th</sup>, in Yarmouth; and</p>
<p>Whereas Francophone Recording was recognized as a separate category; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Luc Tardif won the 2011 Francophone Recording Award;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Mr. Luc Tardif for winning the prestigious award, and wish him continued success in the future.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Preston.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2774">RESOLUTION NO. 2774</num>
          <speech by="#aef785d7-7697-4453-8f9c-eef26e4928c3"><from>HON. KEITH COLWELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Wednesday of last week a point of order was raised by the House Leader for the Official Opposition regarding the curtailment of debate on Bill No. 102, in the Law Amendments Committee, by the NDP; and</p>
<p>Whereas instead of the member for Pictou East responding on behalf of the government caucus, it was the Minister of Communities, Culture and Heritage who stood to defend the NDP's decision to try and curtail debate on Bill No. 102 in the Law Amendments Committee; and</p>
<p>Whereas the member for Pictou East should be speaking to the Cabinet on behalf of his constituents against Bill No. 102, but has clearly been excluded from access to the inner circle of the NDP;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly urge the member for Pictou East to finally speak up on behalf of his constituents who stand to lose if the NDP is to proceed with this first contract arbitration in its current form.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Colchester North.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2775">RESOLUTION NO. 2775</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>HON. KAREN CASEY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the 11<sup>th</sup> annual Nova Scotia Recycles Contest was sponsored by the Resource Recovery Fund Board of Nova Scotia; and</p>
<p>Whereas the contest is designed to encourage students to take a leadership role in improving the environment by promoting waste diversion; and</p>
<p>Whereas this year's students in Grade 12 were asked to submit a research essay on opportunities existing in waste reduction that may pertain to business, community, individuals and government;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Arriel Tucker of North Colchester High School in Tatamagouche, Colchester North, who won 2<sup>nd</sup> place for the region and received a $750 prize.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Bedford-Birch Cove.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2776">RESOLUTION NO. 2776</num>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>MS. KELLY REGAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Tracy Cipryk has spent 25 years working as a fitness entrepreneur; and</p>
<p>Whereas Tracy has owned a fitness franchise, was a business partner with Nubody's Fitness Centre for nearly 20 years and has represented the Canadian Fitness Professionals Organization as a PRO trainer, CEC provider and presenter for the past 12 years; and</p>
<p>Whereas Tracy was the creative force behind the Bust a Move Flash Mob and is the creative director and fitness chair for Bust a Move for Breast Health, the co-organizer for the Yoga Atlantic Conference and the creator of the Living Life series;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Tracy Cipryk on being named a 2011 Women of Excellence in the Health, Sport and Wellness category and wish her well in all her future physical fitness endeavours.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Yarmouth.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2777">RESOLUTION NO. 2777</num>
          <speech by="#8834559e-ddf7-4ac7-9b30-8ada0eb9a7ca"><from>MR. ZACH CHURCHILL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas in the past year, the southern region of Nova Scotia has lost 4,300 people from the labour force; and</p>
<p>Whereas in the past year there have been 2,500 people in the southern region who have lost their jobs under this government; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism has been operating for the past year under a strategy with no targets and no measurable outcomes and therefore no accountability to the public;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly urge the Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism to start including hard, economic targets and measurable outcomes in his strategy to get the people of the southern region back to work and to ensure that his department and government are accountable to Nova Scotians.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cape Breton South.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2778">RESOLUTION NO. 2778</num>
          <speech by="#a5e0e841-506b-4c0b-a88e-c09691bd745b"><from>HON. MANNING MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas in the past year, Cape Breton has lost 2,300 people from the labour force; and</p>
<p>Whereas in the past year, there have been 2,100 people in Cape Breton who have lost their jobs under this NDP Government; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism has been operating under a strategy with no targets and no measurable outcomes for the past year, which has resulted in Cape Breton suffering an unemployment rate of 15.8 per cent;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly urge the Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism to start including hard economic targets and measurable outcomes in his strategy, and get the people of Cape Breton back to work.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Kings West.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2779">RESOLUTION NO. 2779</num>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048"><from>MR. LEO GLAVINE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Robert Clarke of Berwick excelled in track and field and earned top marks in both provincial and Canadian competitions; and</p>
<p>Whereas Robert Clarke earned trophies at the Highland Games for his prowess in basketball, volleyball, and track and field; and</p>
<p>Whereas Robert Clarke also competed for a berth on the Canadian Olympic Track and Field Team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly acknowledge the accomplishments of Robert Clarke as one of the finest athletes of his generation from his hometown of Berwick, Nova Scotia, and congratulate him on induction into the Berwick Hall of Fame.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Richmond.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2780">RESOLUTION NO. 2780</num>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the L'Ardoise Friends of Palliative Care group have worked very hard fundraising this year for the Strait Richmond Palliative Care Society; and</p>
<p>Whereas over the past five years the L'Ardoise Friends of Palliative Care group has donated a generous amount of $15,989; and</p>
<p>Whereas the L'Ardoise Friends of Palliative Care group recently donated $7,089 to the Strait Richmond Palliative Care Society, which will be used to purchase a new patient-controlled pain pump;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of the House of Assembly commend the L'Ardoise Friends of Palliative Care group for their great fundraising efforts over the past five years.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Bedford-Birch Cove.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2781">RESOLUTION NO. 2781</num>
          <speech by="#a48067d1-5e84-46e6-907e-76a541767728"><from>MS. KELLY REGAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, on behalf of the member for Digby-Annapolis, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Paul Volenik began collecting memorabilia and other vintage items while in his 20s; and</p>
<p>Whereas after retiring, Mr. Volenik turned his hobby into a business venture when he opened up Bear River Bargains and Books; and</p>
<p>Whereas over the years, through Mr. Volenik's unique marketing style and atmosphere, Bear River Bargains and Books continues to be a success story in the riding of Digby-Annapolis;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Mr. Paul Volenik on the success of his hobby-turned-business.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Yarmouth.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2782">RESOLUTION NO. 2782</num>
          <speech by="#8834559e-ddf7-4ac7-9b30-8ada0eb9a7ca"><from>MR. ZACH CHURCHILL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, on behalf of the honourable member for Glace Bay, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas areas in Africa such as Kenya are some of the poorest in the world; and</p>
<p>Whereas earlier this year motivational speaker Spencer West, of the Me to We organization, came to speak to students of Glace Bay High School about his life and trip to Kenya; and</p>
<p>Whereas after hearing his talk, students have teamed up with the organizations Me to We and Free the Children to make a trip to Kenya in March to help build a new school;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly thank the students and staff of Glace Bay High School for their great efforts in helping to improve the lives of others.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Yarmouth.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2783">RESOLUTION NO. 2783</num>
          <speech by="#8834559e-ddf7-4ac7-9b30-8ada0eb9a7ca"><from>MR. ZACH CHURCHILL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, again on behalf of the honourable member for Glace Bay, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Habitat for Humanity is a non-profit organization that works to mobilize volunteers and community partners in the efforts of building affordable housing and promotion of homeownership as a means to break the cycle of poverty; and</p>
<p>Whereas earlier this year, the Habitat for Humanity Nova Scotia Cape Breton Project Committee came together under the guidance of chair Eldon MacDonald; and</p>
<p>Whereas the committee and volunteers have rebuilt a home on Mechanic Street in Glace Bay;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize and congratulate Eldon MacDonald and his volunteers on their hard work and dedication to bettering the lives of their neighbours.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I move that you do now leave the Chair and the House resolve itself into a Committee of the Whole House on Bills.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Before I leave the Chair for the Committee of the Whole House on Bills, I'm going to appoint the honourable member for Halifax Citadel-Sable Island to be chairman of the Committee of the Whole House in the absence of the Deputy Speaker for the government. Thank you.</p>
<p>[Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.]</p></speech>
          <narrative>
            <p>3:00 p.m. The House resolved itself into a CWH on Bills with Acting Deputy Speaker Mr. Leonard Preyra in the Chair.</p>
          </narrative>
          <narrative>
            <p>11:03 p.m. CWH on Bills rose and the House reconvened with Deputy Speaker Ms. Becky Kent in the Chair.</p>
          </narrative>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The Chairman of the Committee of the Whole House on Bills reports:</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined">
            <from>THE CLERK</from>
            <p>That the committee has met and made progress and begs leave to sit again.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23"><from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from><p>Madam Speaker, that concludes the government's business for today. I move that the House do now rise.</p>
<p>After the daily routine, we will be doing the order of business, Public Bills for Third Reading, Bill Nos. 72, 81, 86, 93, 94, 95, 98, 104, 108, 111 and 112. Time permitting, Committee of the Whole House on Bills will be considering Bill Nos. 55, 102, 106, 109, 115, 116 and 100 and, time permitting, Bills for Second Reading, Bill Nos. 126 and 128.</p>
<p>I move that the House do now rise to meet again tomorrow from 12:00 noon to 10:00 p.m.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the House do now rise to meet again tomorrow at the hour of 12:00 noon.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
          <narrative>
            <p>The House rose at 11:05 p.m.</p>
          </narrative>
        </debateSection>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION UNDER RULE 32(3)</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2784">RESOLUTION NO. 2784</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Lieutenant Governor's Education Medal is presented annually to one male and one female student in Grade 11 from every high school in the province; and</p>
<p>Whereas students are nominated by their school, based on academic performance and qualities of leadership and service demonstrated in their school and community; and</p>
<p>Whereas this year the students in the Chignecto Central Regional School Board were presented with their medals by Her Honour Lieutenant Governor Mayann E. Francis at a ceremony held in the Oxford Regional Education Centre;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Matthew Allen of North Colchester High School, in Tatamagouche, for receiving the prestigious Lieutenant Governor's Education Medal.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2785">RESOLUTION NO. 2785</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas eight-year-old Abigael Brownell of North River, Colchester North, had a very busy summer competing in several highland dance competitions; and</p>
<p>Whereas Abigael won a number of awards at the Gaelic College Highland Dance Competitions in Saint Annes, Cape Breton, the Festival of Tartans in New Glasgow, the Prince Edward Island Highland Games, and the Hector Festival in Pictou; and</p>
<p>Whereas Abigael tied for first place at the Hector Festival, winning the High Aggregate Trophy for her category;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate this energetic and talented eight-year-old dancer, especially for her first high aggregate win on August 13<sup>th</sup>, in the intermediate category, since moving up from novice on July 4<sup>th</sup> .</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2786">RESOLUTION NO. 2786</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Alexander Chiasson, 13, of Belmont, Colchester North, suffers from spastic quadriplegic cerebral palsy; and</p>
<p>Whereas Alexander had to be lifted into a vehicle, his wheelchair driven to the back, and the process reversed when he needed to get out; and</p>
<p>Whereas over the past year the family has fundraised $38,000 to put toward a BraunAbilty van, which cost $54,000;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Alexander's family for their work and resourcefulness in providing a suitable vehicle for Alexander's needs, and wish Alexander many happy journeys in the family's new van.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2787">RESOLUTION NO. 2787</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Brandon Fillmore, a Grade 9 student at Bible Hill Junior High titled his science fair project L.B.S. "A Turn for the Better"; and</p>
<p>Whereas Brandon invented the Lateral Balance System to fit a major need in vehicle safety; and</p>
<p>Whereas Brandon's plan for the Lateral Balance System is to use pneumatics to eliminate the need for a stabilizer bar, while actively helping prevent vehicular rollover and loss of control;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate this remarkable young man for his creativity and for winning the Excellence Award Intermediate Bronze Medal $300, and the University of Western Ontario $1,000 entrance scholarship.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2788">RESOLUTION NO. 2788</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Terry Langille of Tatamagouche, Colchester North, had given his family CDs which were copies of a collection of eight-millimetre home videos filmed by his father, Andy; and</p>
<p>Whereas Langille's daughter Becky compiled a five-minute clip which takes viewers back more than 40 years when her father was a boy; and</p>
<p>Whereas Langille submitted his video to the Lotto Max Cavendish Beach Music Festival Super Fan Contest, and became its winner of 2011;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Terry Langille for winning the contest, which saw him and a guest as VIPs for the weekend, enjoying the best seats in the house, a Confederation Bridge pass, accommodations, VIP parking, backstage tours, and much more - including having his video shown on the big screen during the music festival.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2789">RESOLUTION NO. 2789</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Courtney Lynds of North River, Colchester North, not only holds down a full- time job, is a talented fiddle player and step dancer, but is very community minded, often using her talents to entertain residents at local nursing homes, helping raise money for organizations in the area, or volunteering at camps for children; and</p>
<p>Whereas Courtney began her post-secondary studies at Saint Francis Xavier University in 2010 where she became a member of the math society and the equity representative for her campus residence; and</p>
<p>Whereas Courtney plans to become a pediatrician - she will be transferring to Dalhousie University this fall to continue to work towards her Bachelor of Science degree;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly congratulate this very deserving 19 year old for being chosen from applicants throughout the province to receive one of nine $3,000 scholarships from Wilson Fuels.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2790">RESOLUTION NO. 2790</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Nova Scotia Designer Crafts Council has been the driving force in building the craft community into an economic and cultural force in the province; and</p>
<p>Whereas jurying is required for participation in NSDCC markets, the assessment is undertaken by the standards committee, which consists of seven respected craftspeople representing a variety of media elected annually by the NSDCC membership; and</p>
<p>Whereas Wanda MacInnis, who launched Annabelle Design Apparel which specializes in loungewear, lingerie, and sleepwear, submitted several designs to the NSDCC, and successfully completed the standards jurying process;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Wanda MacInnis for successfully completing the standards jurying process on her first attempt, and wish her continued success with her expanding business.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2791">RESOLUTION NO. 2791</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Pearl and Daisy Soap Company, founded in 2009, makes handcrafted soap and bath products that are sold in more than 85 stores across Canada and the United States; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Truro and District Chamber of Commerce presented this year's award for Exporter of the Year to Rebecca Taylor, owner of the Pearl and Daisy Natural Soap Company in Debert, Colchester North; and</p>
<p>Whereas Taylor emphasized that she had received help from organizations and individuals who are dedicated to helping small business grow, and that there is no better place to start a business than Colchester County, Nova Scotia;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that Rebecca Taylor be congratulated for her entrepreneurial skills, hard work and dedication to developing her small business, and for its growth and success which is signified by the award presented to her by the Chamber of Commerce.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2792">RESOLUTION NO. 2792</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteer fire departments bring security and comfort to the members of their communities; and</p>
<p>Whereas the members of these fire departments are the first to respond, day or night, and put themselves in harm's way for the well-being of others; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Salmon River Fire Brigade is celebrating its 50<sup>th</sup> Anniversary;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Salmon River Fire Brigade for a half-century of dedicated service.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2793">RESOLUTION NO. 2793</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Ian Stewart of North River, Colchester North, is a master hypnotist and a skilled juggler; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ian has been juggling chainsaws, three at a time with the motors running, for about 15 years; and</p>
<p>Whereas on September 25, 2011, Ian successfully made 94 tosses and catches at the Hants County Exhibition;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ian Stewart for now being the Guinness World Record Holder for Chainsaw Juggling.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2794">RESOLUTION NO. 2794</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Cassandra Teed of East Mountain, Colchester North, one of the top volleyball players in the province, is currently a member of the NSAC Rams; and</p>
<p>Whereas Teed played beach volleyball for four summers for Volleyball Nova Scotia, and believes the sport produces a better all-around player; and</p>
<p>Whereas Teed and her family recently opened two beach volleyball courts at their East Mountain home, and the courts are quickly being booked up with playing spots;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate this enterprising athlete for her commitment to promoting beach volleyball as a sport, physical fitness, exercise, and healthy entertainment.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="2795">RESOLUTION NO. 2795</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas rural Nova Scotians for many years have depended on the members of volunteer fire brigades to keep their families and properties safe from fire; and</p>
<p>Whereas fire department members, in recent years, have also taken on the role of first responders because the need for medical assistance has increased throughout the province; and</p>
<p>Whereas many additional responsibilities such as fundraising, training, first aid, recruitment, and public relations are also part of a firefighter's commitment;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Charlie MacKenzie for receiving a 40-year, Long-Term Service Award from the Onslow-Belmont Fire Brigade.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </noticesOfMotion>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
