<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="graham.steele" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.graham.steele" showAs="HON. GRAHAM STEELE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="marilyn.more" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.marilyn.more" showAs="HON. MARILYN MORE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="stephen.mcneil" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.stephen.mcneil" showAs="HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="jamie.baillie" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.jamie.baillie" showAs="HON. JAMIE BAILLIE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="michel.p.samson" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.michel.p.samson" showAs="HON. MICHEL SAMSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="keith.bain" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.keith.bain" showAs="MR. KEITH BAIN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="christopher.a.dentremont" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.christopher.a.dentremont" showAs="HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="leo.glavine" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.leo.glavine" showAs="MR. LEO GLAVINE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="eddie.orrell" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.eddie.orrell" showAs="MR. EDDIE ORRELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="wayne.j.gaudet" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.wayne.j.gaudet" showAs="HON. WAYNE GAUDET"/>
        <TLCPerson id="keith.colwell" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.keith.colwell" showAs="HON. KEITH COLWELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="karen.casey" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.karen.casey" showAs="HON. KAREN CASEY"/>
        <TLCPerson id="andrew.younger" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.andrew.younger" showAs="MR. ANDREW YOUNGER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="zach.churchill" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.zach.churchill" showAs="MR. ZACH CHURCHILL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="diana.whalen" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.diana.whalen" showAs="MS. DIANA WHALEN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="kelly.regan" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.kelly.regan" showAs="MS. KELLY REGAN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="harold.theriault" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.harold.theriault" showAs="MR. HAROLD THERIAULT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="frank.corbett" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.frank.corbett" showAs="HON. FRANK CORBETT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="mat.whynott" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.mat.whynott" showAs="MR. MAT WHYNOTT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="howard.epstein" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.howard.epstein" showAs="MR. HOWARD EPSTEIN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="chuck.porter" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.chuck.porter" showAs="Mr. Chuck Porter"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MR. SPEAKER"/>
        <TLCRole id="member" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.member" showAs="AN HON. MEMBER"/>
        <TLCRole id="clerk" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.clerk" showAs="THE CLERK"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 27 April 2012</docTitle>
      <docNumber>12-20</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2012-04-27">Friday, April 27, 2012</docDate>
      <docAuthority>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docAuthority>
      <legislature value="61">61st General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="4">4th Session</session>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://nslegislature.ca/index.php/proceedings/hansard/C89/house_12apr27/"/>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>Order, please. We'll begin the daily routine.</p>
      </speech>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Finance.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#graham.steele"><num title="427">RESOLUTION NO. 427</num><from>HON. GRAHAM STEELE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, on behalf of the honourable Premier, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas every day Nova Scotians go to work to provide for themselves and their loved ones; and</p>
<p>Whereas tragically, last year 27 individuals did not make it home to see their friends and families; and</p>
<p>Whereas tomorrow, April 28<sup>th</sup>, marks the National Day of Mourning, where we take the time to remember those who have fallen at work;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House recognize April 28<sup>th</sup> as the National Day of Mourning, take the time to reflect on how the loss of these 27 workers has affected their families and communities, and renew their commitment to continuing to build and ingrain a culture of safety in all our workplaces.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Labour and Advanced Education.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#marilyn.more"><num title="428">RESOLUTION NO. 428</num><from>HON. MARILYN MORE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas tomorrow, April 28<sup>th</sup>, marks the National Day of Mourning, a time to reflect on the importance of safety in the workplace and remember those who have been lost; and</p>
<p>Whereas this year we have already seen too many Nova Scotians tragically lose their lives on the job; and</p>
<p>Whereas all deaths and injuries on the job are preventable, and safety is a shared responsibility that must be renewed each day;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House mark the National Day of Mourning, April 28<sup>th</sup>, as a time to reaffirm our commitment to continue to work with our safety partners to reduce the risks of workplace incidents with the ultimate goal of eliminating injuries and deaths completely.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>INTRODUCTION OF BILLS</heading>
        <other>
          <p>
            <b> Bill No. 65 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 92 of the Revised Statutes of 1989. The Consumer Protection Act, to Ensure Fairness in Cellular Telephone Contracts. (Hon. John MacDonell)</b>
          </p>
        </other>
        <other>
          <p>
            <b> Bill No. 66 - Entitled an Act to Establish Clinical Trials Respecting Multiple Sclerosis Liberation Therapy and Observation of Multiple Sclerosis Patients in Receipt of Liberation Therapy. (Mr. Leo Glavine)</b>
          </p>
        </other>
        <other>
          <p>
            <b> Bill No. 67 - Entitled an Act to Require the Government of Nova Scotia to Purchase Agricultural Products from Nova Scotia Producers. (Mr. Chuck Porter)</b>
          </p>
        </other>
        <other>
          <p>
            <b>Bill No. 68 - Entitled an Act to Provide for the Establishment of Strategic Planning and Performance Measurement in the Government of Nova Scotia. (Mr. Allan MacMaster)</b>
          </p>
        </other>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>Ordered that these bills be read a second time on a future day.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#stephen.mcneil"><num title="429">RESOLUTION NO. 429</num><from>HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas tomorrow, April 28<sup>th</sup>, workers across the province, throughout Canada and around the world, will be gathered to remember workers killed, injured, or made sick on the job; and</p>
<p>Whereas in 2011, 27 Nova Scotians tragically lost their lives due to workplace fatalities, leaving behind family and friends whose lives were ever-changed as a result of these tragedies; and</p>
<p>Whereas the International Day of Mourning enables us to remember those who lost their lives, we must never lose sight of the daily efforts required for everyone to make the workplace safe for workers throughout the province;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly extend our appreciation to the organizers of the International Day of Mourning events throughout Nova Scotia, and renew our commitment to bring the message of the importance of safety to workplaces across the province.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#jamie.baillie"><num title="430">RESOLUTION NO. 430</num><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas tomorrow Nova Scotia, with the rest of Canada, joins more than 80 countries worldwide in the International Day of Mourning to remember those who died, were injured, or became ill at work; and</p>
<p>Whereas in 2011 more than 27,000 Nova Scotians were injured at work and, tragically, 27 died; and</p>
<p>Whereas the International Day of Mourning is an opportunity for employees and employers to publicly renew their commitment to improve health and safety in the workplace;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House mark the Day of Mourning by remembering those who have died while at work, and offer our support to keep workplaces safe.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Richmond.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="431">RESOLUTION NO. 431</num><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas prosperity starts in the classroom, and Nova Scotia's future rests on the shoulders of our students; and</p>
<p>Whereas students are losing the very services and resources that will support them in reaching their full potential; and</p>
<p>Whereas the impact of this NDP Government's $65 million in funding cuts to education is being felt in every classroom in the province;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the member for Shelburne stand up for education and call on the NDP Premier and the NDP Education Minister to invest in the future of Nova Scotia and restore funding to education now.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Victoria-The Lakes.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#keith.bain"><num title="432">RESOLUTION NO. 432</num><from>MR. KEITH BAIN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas May 26<sup>th</sup> and May 27<sup>th</sup> marks the 25<sup>th</sup> Anniversary of the well-known annual Cabot Trail Relay; and</p>
<p>Whereas since its humble beginnings in 1988 that featured only six teams, the race has grown to 70 teams, with more than 1,000 runners from across Canada and parts of the eastern United States; and</p>
<p>Whereas the event is a 298-kilometre, 17-stage relay race that begins at the Gaelic College in St. Anns and goes around the clock, concluding at the Baddeck Court House;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly commend the work of race chairman Dave Parkinson and all members of his committee, and wish them the very best in the relay on May 26<sup>th</sup> and May 27<sup>th</sup>.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Richmond.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="433">RESOLUTION NO. 433</num><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas teachers are the foundation of a quality education system; and</p>
<p>Whereas teachers across Nova Scotia have called on this government to restore funding to education because they see the true impact of funding cuts on the lives of our students; and</p>
<p>Whereas yesterday the Minister of Education said in this House that teachers are more interested in themselves than the children when she said that the Nova Scotia Teachers Union are looking (Interruptions)</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>Order, please. The honourable member for Richmond has the floor.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><from>MR. SAMSON</from><p>Whereas yesterday the Minister of Education said in this House that teachers are more interested in themselves than the children when she said that the Nova Scotia Teachers Union are looking after themselves while the government is looking after kids;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the Minister of Education recognize the dedication teachers show to kids every day and apologize for yesterday's insulting statement.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Argyle.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><num title="434">RESOLUTION NO. 434</num><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on February 23, 2012, Wedgeport Boats launched their first boat from the newly-acquired LeBlanc Brothers Boatbuilding yard; and</p>
<p>Whereas Wedgeport Boats bought the company from its founders - Neil, Leo, and Kevin LeBlanc - at the end of 2011 and will continue to produce boats using the LeBlanc Brothers' distinctive design as well as their own; and</p>
<p>Whereas Wedgeport Boats, established in 1988, is part of a 75-year tradition of building boats for pleasure or commercial use in Wedgeport;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Wedgeport Boats on their recent acquisition and the launch of their new boat and thank them for keeping this time-honoured tradition alive and well.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Kings West.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#leo.glavine"><num title="435">RESOLUTION NO. 435</num><from>MR. LEO GLAVINE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas prosperity starts in the classroom and Nova Scotia's future rests on the shoulders of our students; and</p>
<p>Whereas students are losing the very services and resources that will support them in reaching their full potential; and</p>
<p>Whereas the impact of this NDP Government's $65 million in funding cuts to education is being felt in every classroom in the province;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the member for Lunenburg West stand up for education and call on the NDP Premier and the NDP Education Minister to invest in the future of Nova Scotia and restore funding to education now.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cape Breton North.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#eddie.orrell"><num title="436">RESOLUTION NO. 436</num><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Paul MacKenzie, a science teacher at Memorial High School in Sydney Mines, built a mobile sugar shack with the help of students at the school; and</p>
<p>Whereas Paul also runs a maple sugar operation and the mobile sugar shack travels around Cape Breton showing people how to make maple syrup and provides free samples; and</p>
<p>Whereas Paul's operation can produce as much as 3,000 litres in a season;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in saluting Paul MacKenzie and his innovative idea to promote the maple syrup industry.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Clare.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#wayne.j.gaudet"><num title="437">RESOLUTION NO. 437</num><from>HON. WAYNE GAUDET</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Education Week is an opportunity to recognize teachers and education partners' commitments for their outstanding work and dedication to public education; and</p>
<p>Whereas the theme of this year's Education Week is Educating Students For Life; and</p>
<p>Whereas Shawn Comeau, a Digby high school teacher and student council advisor, is the recipient of an Education Week Award for 2012;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Shawn Comeau and acknowledge his contribution to the public education system in Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cape Breton North.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#eddie.orrell"><num title="438">RESOLUTION NO. 438</num><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Bruce Evans, a North Sydney native, has used his MBA from Dalhousie University to work in construction finance, acquisitions, complex restructurings, lending syndicate formation and business guidance in the international market place; and</p>
<p>Whereas three years ago Bruce moved home to Nova Scotia and recently became the executive vice-president with Lucent Capital in Los Angeles; and</p>
<p>Whereas Bruce's expertise will be put to use with this nationwide financial intermediary assisting developers, investors and financial partners;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Bruce and his wife Donna, as they start this exciting new chapter in their lives.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Preston.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#keith.colwell"><num title="439">RESOLUTION NO. 439</num><from>HON. KEITH COLWELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Lake Echo Seniors' Club was formed in 1989 with their first president Stanley Vaughn presiding, and it has now grown to 52 members who meet monthly in the seniors' room located at the Lake Echo Community Centre; and</p>
<p>Whereas the club is now open daily and the members meet to chat and work on crafts such as a quilt they make every year to sell tickets on at their annual craft sale and luncheon held in October to raise money for day trips; and</p>
<p>Whereas they have just finished their first book, entitled <i>Memories from the Lake Echo Seniors</i>;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House recognize the many accomplishments and dedication of the president, Doreen Matthews, and the members of Lake Echo Seniors' Club.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Argyle.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><num title="440">RESOLUTION NO. 440</num><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, &#xE0; une date ult&#xE9;rieure, je demanderai l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu que le 8 f&#xE9;vrier 2012, durant la s&#xE9;rie de conf&#xE9;rences patrimoniales de f&#xE9;vrier au Mus&#xE9;e et Archives du comt&#xE9; de Yarmouth; et</p>
<p>Attendu que M. Donnie Jacquard, de Wedgeport, a parl&#xE9; de l'histoire de Wedgeport &#xE0; l'&#xE9;poque int&#xE9;ressante et prosp&#xE8;re de l'&#xE2;ge de la voile et transport maritime; et</p>
<p>Attendu que M. Jacquard, un enseignant et directeur d'&#xE9;cole &#xE0; la retraite, fait des recherches sur ce sujet en pr&#xE9;paration d'un livre qu'il &#xE9;crit;</p>
<p>Par cons&#xE9;quent, qu'il soit r&#xE9;solu que tous les membres de cette Assembl&#xE9;e remercient Donnie Jacquard pour son temps et d&#xE9;vouement dans la recherche de l'histoire de notre pass&#xE9; et lui souhaitent du succ&#xE8;s avec son livre.</p>
<p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, je demande l'adoption de cette r&#xE9;solution sans pr&#xE9;avis et sans d&#xE9;bat.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on February 8<sup>th</sup>, the February Heritage Talk Series took place at the Yarmouth County Museum and Archives; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Donnie Jacquard, a Wedgeport native, spoke about the history of Wedgeport during an interesting and prosperous time when the shipping era and the age of sail were dominant; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Jacquard, a retired school teacher and principal, has conducted extensive research on this topic in preparation for a book that he's writing;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly thank Donnie Jacquard for the dedication he has shown in documenting the history of our past and wish him success with his book.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Colchester North.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="441">RESOLUTION NO. 441</num><from>HON. KAREN CASEY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Independent Order of Odd Fellows was created in 18<sup>th</sup> Century England by working class men to provide aid to their neighbours, help the unemployed find work, take care of families who lost their patriarch or matriarch, educate orphans and build camaraderie; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Tatamagouche Branch of the Independent Order of Odd Fellows, Liberty Lodge No. 120, was founded in 1912; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Tatamagouche IOOF gives a bursary to a North Colchester graduating student, sends youth who are at risk or are from families experiencing financial difficulty to day camps, helps those who need medical equipment or medication but cannot afford it, provides all the essentials for Christmas for a family experiencing difficulties and more;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Tatamagouche branch of the Independent Order of Odd Fellows, Liberty Lodge No. 120, which is celebrating its 100<sup>th</sup> Anniversary for active work in the community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Dartmouth East.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="442">RESOLUTION NO. 442</num><from>MR. ANDREW YOUNGER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since taking office the NDP Government has broken a promise and hiked the HST, increased over 1,400 user fees, and ensured that the people of Nova Scotia get an income tax hike every year by breaking a promise to end bracket creep; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Premier and the NDP have done nothing to stop the ever-increasing price of power and ensured students paid higher tuition every year and have broken a promise to take the tax off tax when it comes to gasoline; and</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotians face higher prices for food, power and gasoline every day as life becomes less and less affordable under the NDP;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly remind the member for Guysborough-Sheet Harbour that the decisions the Premier and the NDP Government have taken since taking office have made life less affordable for Nova Scotians as they continue to face high prices for everyday essentials, gasoline and power, with no relief in sight under this NDP Government.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Yarmouth.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#zach.churchill"><from>MR. ZACH CHURCHILL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas prosperity starts in the classroom and Nova Scotia's future rests on the shoulders of our students; and</p>
<p>Whereas students are losing the very services and resources that will support them in reaching their full potential; and</p>
<p>Whereas the impact of this NDP Government's $65 million in funding cuts to education are being felt in every classroom in the province;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the member for Lunenburg West stand up for education and call on the NDP Premier and the NDP Education Minister to invest in the future of Nova Scotia and restore funding to education now.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#diana.whalen"><num title="443">RESOLUTION NO. 443</num><from>MS. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas people have been enjoying the music and mirth of Gilbert and Sullivan since the late 1800s and the founding of the Gilbert and Sullivan Society of Nova Scotia in January 1977 is a testament to their enduring popularity; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Gilbert and Sullivan Society is now celebrating 35 years of entertaining Nova Scotians in theatres around the province with these endearing comic operettas; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Gilbert and Sullivan Society members include many who have been involved for years and through the long rehearsals and the excitement of performing, a close fellowship has been fostered among the performers and their families;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House congratulate Susan Woodbury, founding president and honorary life member, and Katie Roode, current president on the 35<sup>th</sup> Anniversary of the Gilbert and Sullivan Society of Nova Scotia and wish them many more years of entertaining performances and camaraderie.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Order, please.</p>
<p>I just realized that the resolution by the honourable member for Yarmouth was identical to the resolution by the honourable member for Kings West. So I rule the resolution by the honourable member for Yarmouth out of order. They're identical and it cannot be done.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Bedford-Birch Cove.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#kelly.regan"><num title="444">RESOLUTION NO. 444</num><from>MS. KELLY REGAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the NDP Government refuses to see how their cuts are affecting classrooms across Nova Scotia; and</p>
<p>Whereas despite the NSTU's "Kids not cuts" petition, Take Your MLAs To School Day, and recent rallies at NDP MLA offices across the province, this government remains blind to the needs of students in Nova Scotia; and</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotians deserve better and demand better for their children;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the member for Dartmouth South-Portland Valley stand up for education and call on the NDP Premier and the NDP Education Minister to make the students a priority and reinstate funding to education.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Bedford-Birch Cove.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#kelly.regan"><num title="445">RESOLUTION NO. 445</num><from>MS. KELLY REGAN</from><p>I think they'll like this one better, Mr. Speaker. I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Bedford volunteer recognition reception is held annually to recognize the exceptional volunteers of Bedford; and</p>
<p>Whereas Bev Grace was a founding member of the Catholic Women's League at St. Ignatius Church in 1983, serving as chair, hosting funeral receptions, and contributing to the many projects the CWL undertakes, as well as teaching Sunday school for 40 years, serving on the St. Ignatius Education Committee and the church's various prayer groups, as well as visiting the elderly and ill; and</p>
<p>Whereas Bev has also been a volunteer mentor to and teacher of children with learning disabilities, hosted a night school class for mentally-challenged adults for years, served on a board of a group home for those recovering from mental illness, volunteered with the Cancer Society, the Multiple Sclerosis Society, Big Brothers, the Diabetes Association, Girl Guides, the Kinettes, and the local figure-skating club, to name just a few;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly thank Bev Grace for her devotion to students, the ill, the elderly and, indeed, all the people of Bedford who have been touched by her generosity and thoughtfulness, and congratulate her on being named Bedford's Adult Volunteer of the Year for 2012.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Preston.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#keith.colwell"><num title="446">RESOLUTION NO. 446</num><from>HON. KEITH COLWELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the NDP said they would make life better for families and yet, since the NDP took power, families have been finding life less affordable and are left wondering why; and</p>
<p>Whereas the NDP hiked the HST, broke a promise to index income tax brackets, failed to remove what they called the immoral tax on tax on gasoline, have failed to rein in the exceedingly high power prices, and imposed a tax on every electricity bill in the province; and</p>
<p>Whereas with the hike in the HST and failure to index income tax brackets, Nova Scotians have been spending more and keeping less and less of their income, while power rates and gas prices continue to climb;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly remind the NDP that it was their decision to hike taxes and fees, and their failure to take measures to control power rates and provide relief from gasoline prices have been making life very expensive for Nova Scotians.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Colchester North.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="447">RESOLUTION NO. 447</num><from>HON. KAREN CASEY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Sarah Fougere, a Grade 7 student at Redcliffe Middle School in Valley, Colchester North, has been dancing since the age of three; and</p>
<p>Whereas Fougere is going into her 10<sup>th</sup> year of instruction with the Truro Dance Academy; and</p>
<p>Whereas Fougere tried out for the Royal Winnipeg Ballet with the idea that it would be a great experience;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate Sarah Fougere for being accepted into the prestigious Royal Winnipeg Ballet's summer school program in July and wish her continued success with her dancing.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Yarmouth.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#zach.churchill"><num title="448">RESOLUTION NO. 448</num><from>MR. ZACH CHURCHILL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas prosperity starts in the classroom and Nova Scotia's future rests on the shoulders of our students; and</p>
<p>Whereas students are losing the very services and resources that will support them in reaching their full potential; and</p>
<p>Whereas the impact of this NDP Government's $65 million cuts in funding to education are being felt in every classroom in the province;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the member for Lunenburg stand up for education and call on the NDP Premier and the NDP Education Minister to invest in the future of Nova Scotia and restore funding to education now.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Digby-Annapolis.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#harold.theriault"><num title="449">RESOLUTION NO. 449</num><from>MR. HAROLD THERIAULT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas teachers are the foundation of our education system and a good teacher can instill values of lifelong learning in a student; and</p>
<p>Whereas teachers and education partners in Nova Scotia's public education system are concerned about the government's cuts to public education; and</p>
<p>Whereas this NDP Government has not made education a priority and continues to gouge public education despite concerns of parents, teachers, and students;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the member for Queens stand up for education and call on the NDP Premier and NDP Education Minister to stop balancing the books on the backs of our students and restore funding to education.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#diana.whalen"><num title="450">RESOLUTION NO. 450</num><from>MS. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Michael Campbell was a pillar of his community in Halifax, spending 35 years at St. Patrick's High School in Halifax where he worked as a science teacher and as the long-time school principal; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Campbell devoted his career to education, was beloved by his students and family and was respected for his committed volunteer work in his community, with his church, the Halifax School Administrators Association, and the Halifax Housing Commission, among others; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Campbell's passionate volunteerism was honoured with awards from the Archdiocese of Halifax and his alma mater St. Francis Xavier University;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly join me in sending sincere condolences to the family of Michael Campbell, his wife Anne, children Michael, Peter and Courtney, and his grandchildren, siblings and extended family, and recognize the passing of a beloved member of the Halifax community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Clare.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#wayne.j.gaudet"><num title="451">RESOLUTION NO. 451</num><from>HON. WAYNE GAUDET</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Johann Robicheau of Saulnierville was recently honoured for her 40 years of service as an employee with the Municipality of Clare; and</p>
<p>Whereas shortly after graduating from Clare District High School, Johann began her secretarial career in October 1971; and</p>
<p>Whereas Johann's career began as secretary receptionist and is now recreation assistant for the municipality's Recreation Department;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Johann Robicheau on her 40 years of dedicated service with the Municipality of Clare.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Yarmouth.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#zach.churchill"><num title="452">RESOLUTION NO. 452</num><from>MR. ZACH CHURCHILL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, on behalf of the honourable member for Glace Bay, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas teachers are the foundation of our education system and a good teacher can instill values of lifelong learning in a student; and</p>
<p>Whereas teachers and education partners in Nova Scotia's public education system are concerned about this government's cuts to public education; and</p>
<p>Whereas this NDP Government has not made education a priority and continues to gouge public education despite concerns of parents, teachers, and students;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the member for Pictou East stand up for education and call on the NDP Premier and the NDP Education Minister to stop balancing the books on the backs of our students and restore funding to education.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Dartmouth East.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="453">RESOLUTION NO. 453</num><from>MR. ANDREW YOUNGER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Mining Society of Nova Scotia was founded in 1887 and was originally known as the Gold Miners Club; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Mining Society of Nova Scotia supports their membership in the mining, metallurgy, petroleum, and related industries through hosting technical forums, social networking, and educational outreach programs; and</p>
<p>Whereas mining in Nova Scotia is directly and indirectly responsible for 6,300 jobs, mostly in rural Nova Scotia;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly congratulate the members of the Mining Society of Nova Scotia on their 125<sup>th</sup> annual meeting being held in Ingonish, Nova Scotia, this June.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT BUSINESS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#frank.corbett">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Government Motions.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT MOTIONS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#frank.corbett">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, I move that you do now leave the Chair and that the House resolve itself into a Committee of the Whole House on Supply unto Her Majesty.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Preston.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#keith.colwell"><from>HON. KEITH COLWELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I realize this will be the last time we can talk going into Supply as the Budget Estimates will be finished today. So I just wanted to stand up again and remind Nova Scotians of what has happened with this government since they've been elected and how it is negatively affecting their pocketbooks.</p>
<p>I've talked to a lot of people who are finding it very difficult to make ends meet now and do the things that they would normally do, and what they would normally do, in most cases or in a lot of cases, is buy groceries, heat your home, pay your electric bill, travel back and forth to work, and hopefully have some money left over so you can put your children into organized sports or have a modest vacation in the summertime, never mind all of the things &#x2026;</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Order, please. I'm having a hard time hearing the honourable member for Preston with all the chatter in the Chamber this morning. I would remind all honourable members to please take your conversations outside the Chamber so I can listen to the honourable member for Preston. Thank you.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Preston has the floor.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#keith.colwell"><from>MR. COLWELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, when families normally do these things, indeed they always have a struggle, there has always been a struggle to balance what you have from your income based on what you have to do with that income to ensure that you look after your family properly and enjoy life a bit, as hopefully we all manage to do. Unfortunately, since this government has increased the GST by 2 per cent, costing Nova Scotians $1 million a day, since they've put the fees up on everything and in some cases twice in one month they've put fees up since they were elected, things they said they wouldn't do, it has made it more expensive for people to register their vehicles, get birth certificates, pretty well everything that you would get from the province that would require a fee, so you have that added to the cost of what you do.</p>
<p>The Premier said many times, the immoral tax on tax on gasoline - and he was referring to the GST and the way it's calculated on gasoline - that it should be removed, it should be gone. The Finance Minister made the same kinds of comments when they were in Opposition. Not only did they not remove the immoral tax on tax but they also increased the GST that made the immoral tax on tax even worse, so when you buy gasoline now it costs you more in tax. They maintain the regulation on gasoline, which costs us just around a cent a litre, and the cost of regulating the gasoline is over $1 million a year now, so that has added a cost to gasoline, which is taxed by the way, with the GST, so that's another immoral tax on tax. When you look at all of these things and see what they've done, basically what has happened is they have taken money out of our pockets, out of every Nova Scotian's pocket.</p>
<p>When people are wondering why they don't have the same amount of money they had, they really have to look at the tax they're paying on things, as compared to three years ago when this government took power in 2009. The gasoline, I believe at that time - and I'm just going from memory - was about $1.05 a litre and today, when I drove by the pumps, I believe it was $1.42 now. That is almost a 40 per cent increase in the price of gasoline. If you look at the price of heating oil and see what heating oil has gone to, that's absolutely outrageous. When you go through all of this and see you've reduced your income because of an increase in income tax, you reduced your disposable income by increasing the GST, and at the same time the cost of gasoline and heating fuel has gone up; therefore, you have less disposable income to spend on the things, the essentials, you need for life.</p>
<p>Then we look at electricity, that's a whole other ball of wax. I can remember this year, in January, getting the highest power bill I have ever, ever seen in all the years I've been paying power bills, and that's for quite a few years. I'm sure that the Opposition will take advantage of my age and say, well, that has been many, many years, but it's the highest power bill I've ever seen. When I ran my business, everything was electric in my business and the bill was actually higher than my business power bill used to be. I'm in a residential area, I heat my home with wood and don't have a lot of electrical items in my home, no more than anyone else would have, so the power bill has gone up.</p>
<p>What has this government done to do anything about that? Nothing, they haven't even intervened when the Utility and Review Board comes along. They go over and watch to see what's going on. In the meantime people are paying more and more for power, and that again takes away more of your disposal income. So when the members of the NDP caucus are over there making fun of what I'm saying and chirping and doing all the things that they do so well - talk to their constituents and actually see who can't pay their property taxes on their homes anymore.</p>
<p>While I'm talking about property taxes, the government also cancelled the memorandum of understanding where they would take some of the costs back from the service exchange, and that has cost municipalities. The minister clearly stated many times in Question Period that the taxes will not go up because of the MOU. Well, unfortunately, some of the municipalities have raised taxes and made it very clear that they raised them because of the MOU.</p>
<p>This is an election year for all municipalities, and the municipalities really don't want to raise taxes this year because they may not get re-elected. So when they raise taxes in an election year, it shows how dire the situation is, and how much more expensive it is for property owners to stay in their homes. Everything this government has done has taken more money out of the pockets of people who are trying to struggle and survive.</p>
<p>I've had people in my office - more than one - actually, you see the ads on TV and the guy turns on the light switch and his apartment disappears, turn it back off and the apartment comes back. It's either shelter or electricity. Sometimes it's either shelter or food, or electricity or food. I've got people coming into my office who are very upset, very concerned, and saying we have to make those choices now, under this government. So much for the better deal for today's families. Little did Nova Scotians realize that the better deal for Nova Scotia families was tax, tax, tax. That's what this government has done.</p>
<p>When people in the province finally realize who has been taking the money out of their pocket and who has been taking away the money that they used to pay for essential services, there's going to be a lot of empty seats over there in that NDP caucus, come the next election. We're going to see a totally different situation in the province - hopefully we will. We can't afford this any longer.</p>
<p>Then if you look at what they've done to the businesses in the province, they tout a tax reduction for small business. Well, if small businesses can't make money, a tax reduction doesn't do anything for them - absolutely nothing. At the same time, you see businesses are paying higher power rates, they are paying higher fuel rates, they are paying higher labour rates now, and the cost goes up and up.</p>
<p>We've asked questions here about the safety inspections, which are very important, but instead of working with employers, what are they doing? They are levying fines to generate more revenue for the province - penalizing the company right away, instead of going with the company and working with them to make sure all the safety hazards they have are removed, so we can make sure that Nova Scotians live in a very safe environment and work in a safe environment in this province.</p>
<p>Look at all these things combined. One thing at a time doesn't make a lot of difference, you slowly change things, but when you combine all these things, Nova Scotia businesses are going to be less competitive. That means they can't pay their employees as much as they should be paying them, possibly. That means they may even realize it's cheaper to move somewhere else and set up their business somewhere else. If that happens, that means there will be no employment here and there will be no tax revenue for the province, and that has a double impact.</p>
<p>When they go through all this stuff and you see the job numbers have decreased in rural Nova Scotia, the employment has decreased - we've got something like 43 per cent of our total population working for government - 43 per cent. I've talked about that before. The more people you have working for government - those people only recirculate money. They don't generate new money in the province. Now, they do important jobs in this province, but we need more industry, small business and large business, whatever the case may be, to really put more money back in the economy in the Province of Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>It just is not happening under this government. There's no direction whatsoever for economic development, none. There are no new, innovative approaches to anything - there's none. You see they've cancelled the ferry in Yarmouth and they said, well, there would be no impact; that would be fine, everything will be fine.</p>
<p>Well, I only have a very few bed and breakfasts in my location, in my riding, very few, but every single one of them has seen a major reduction in the room-nights stayed, in other words the income they make, and when their income goes down, they hire fewer people, they pay less taxes back into the system, and eventually some of them will close. There are two or three of them now that I know are seriously considering closing. That will have a very negative impact on the economy in our province and that is only a small area. Anywhere you go in the province and you talk about tourism, the numbers are down. That's probably the first time ever that I can recall that the numbers are down in tourism &#x2013; really good economic development from this government.</p>
<p>They really don't understand what economic development is about and when you go and look and see how poorly they've done, how poorly the people are being treated in this province as far as taxes are concerned and the problems that they've got, they will realize, the people in the province are realizing. If you talk to many small business owners today, and some of them that I talked to supported this government, they say, well, you know, we made a major mistake last time around in the election and it's really costing us now in our business. I don't know what they will do when the next time comes and the NDP knocks on the door and says, help us out and re-elect us, I don't know, but hopefully they realize what they've done to them and that they will look and see that it is time, possibly, to change what's going on in the province because if they don't, they're going to be finished.</p>
<p>When you talk about some of the bills they've passed here, like Bill No. 100, well, I can tell you in a small business, when a small business gets unionized, it could be the end of the business. It really could be the end of the business. Most businesses in this province treat their employees very well and indeed have a very thin profit margin. If that profit margin disappears because a contract is imposed upon them by a negotiator, or whatever you want to call them, or an arbitrator, that means that business probably will close and then we go down even further in the economy of the province. We see how we can compete.</p>
<p>I already talked about the MOU and the property taxes increasing. As business taxes increases, again, you become less and less competitive. As businesses become less and less competitive, it means they employ fewer people, pay fewer taxes, and at the end of the day what happens is our economy suffers. We've already seen major job losses in this province and we're going to see many, many more before we see the end of this government. Hopefully, in the near future, whenever the Premier decides he's going to call an election, Nova Scotians will take all this into consideration and realize what a horrible mistake they made in 2009.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Argyle.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, it's a pleasure to stand to speak for a few moments as we move into the final phase of our estimates. It was really interesting, of course, to listen to the member for Preston and it was more interesting to listen to the comments that were coming from the government side who seem to take an opposite view of the way regular Nova Scotians are taking the view of their government and the direction that this government has been taking us down for the last three years.</p>
<p>People are looking at this and saying, oh, this is the government of take, take, take, or tax, tax, tax, and I hope that turns around. I mean we have seen some movement from these but it's all about down the road, three years, we'll do it, it's in the future, but then again this is the government that said we wouldn't hike the HST, we wouldn't hike your taxes, yet they did. So, if they find that Nova Scotians might tend to be a little cynical, well, there's a reason for it because you broke that promise.</p>
<p>I want to take this opportunity to speak a little bit about the wonderful community of Argyle and what I'm hearing from the people I speak to, and I know the member for Guysborough-Sheet Harbour would understand many of these things because he represents a community that's very similar to mine. He might have a few more kilometres of coastline, but I think the communities in the bays and the inlets and the fishing villages throughout Guysborough are very much the same and have the same heart and mind of the individuals that I am lucky to represent in the constituency of Argyle.</p>
<p>The first thing I want to talk about quickly is just to say how proud I am to be an Acadian. (Applause) As many of you know, the Electoral Boundaries Commission has been going around Nova Scotia looking for Nova Scotians' input on what the new set of constituencies should be looking for after the next election. As you know, there has been a lot of representation around the province. Of course I thank the Electoral Boundaries Commission members for volunteering their time to go and listen to Nova Scotians.</p>
<p>The reason I'm proud to be an Acadian is because as they visited southwestern Nova Scotia, as they were able to listen to the needs and concerns of the community in Argyle, well over 200 people showed up to tell the Electoral Boundaries Commission how upset they were with the terms of reference that they saw, how they felt that after a hard-fought battle to get the Acadian seats in the first place they couldn't believe that they were at it all over again. Over 200 people in the small communities of Argyle to come out and talk about something like that is absolutely phenomenal, and I want to thank each and every one of those people for taking the time to be there, to express themselves - and not only that, but for the 23 presentations that happened that evening that, of course, all spoke to the responsibility of the Electoral Boundaries Commission of not just sticking to the terms of reference, but also to listen to Nova Scotians.</p>
<p>I also want to thank the over, I would say, 500 people who showed up in Clare the next night, who very emotionally expressed themselves, all wearing their colours, all making noise, all expressing themselves and letting all of Nova Scotia know that we, the Acadians, are still here and truly believe that we deserve to have the same number of seats in this Legislature that we've had since the protection of the seats in 1992.</p>
<p>Again, to hear the number of presentations in Clare, of which I believe there were 23 or 24 or 25 representations, they all sang from the same song sheet about the protection of the seats as they are, to continue the good representation that the members of the Legislature who have been elected for those areas have provided to them over a number of years.</p>
<p>So to move on a little bit to what I've been hearing, because I think we all have that wonderful opportunity to travel through our constituencies, to stop at the coffee shops, to stop for breakfast, to stop for lunch or whatever it is - it seems like my job does revolve a little bit around eating and it's really starting to show lately, with all the dinners and lunches that I am having to attend these days, and hopefully the summer will give me a summer that I'll be able to get back on the bicycle and get back to eating correctly. But for the time being my job is here and, of course, keeping this government to account throughout this session.</p>
<p>You know you ask people the question, what do (Interruption) I have you running; I don't know if I'm running. I mean that's the problem with this - to the Minister of Agriculture and to the member for Lunenburg West. As much as I'd like to go on some kind of a health kick with you, I guess our job is here sitting around and listening to, I believe, very interesting dissertations in this House of Assembly - I hear giggling over there, so I think he's agreeing with me here.</p>
<p>But, anyway, the issue is that we go to coffee shops and we ask: What do you feel that this government is doing for you? I mean we hear it every day, we hear advertisements on the radio, we hear advertisements on TV, and we see advertisements in the paper trying to convince that this government is doing something good for us. But when you go to the coffee shops, when you speak to people on the street, they are very disappointed in what continues to happen by this government. I can tell you that southwestern Nova Scotia - and I would guess that's from Shelburne around to Digby and probably further up into the Valley - are extremely disappointed in what has happened to a number of issues that I believe have been pushed forward by this government.</p>
<p>I know the member for Preston spoke about the ferry, and I'm not going to get into that too much. I think you all know what my feeling is about the ferry in Yarmouth. I do want to quickly say that the announcement on Monday is an interesting one. I'll reserve my complete comments on that except to say that it's a couple of years late. It would have been nice had we had a true look at the ferry service in Yarmouth to see if it's truly viable, if we can actually get a ferry to establish itself there again to continue into the future.</p>
<p>I believe it can, and I think to have these kinds of professionals look at it is a valuable exercise. It is one that we can all support. It's like what I and the member for Yarmouth have been saying - why didn't we do this a little sooner? Why couldn't we have done that a couple of years ago? Unfortunately, that didn't happen, but I am going to reserve it. I'm going to say, listen, let's see what this board is saying, what this commission is going to do, and I'm hopeful that their findings or recommendations will be such that this government will move forward.</p>
<p>I've been talking to fishermen across southwestern Nova Scotia lately. They complain about the cost of fuel, the difficulty that they are having in trying to go out every day with diesel at the price that it's at. The input costs right now into fishing is tremendously difficult for them to make a go of it at the price of lobster as it is. As we know, the added problems will start to happen as the other districts in Nova Scotia start to open. Not only are Districts 34, 35, and 36 sort of competing with themselves, they're going to be competing with many of the other districts across Nova Scotia. So we're going to see a price that I believe is at $5 now, or somewhere near there - we're going to see that price continue to fall.</p>
<p>Today marks the first day of strike by fishermen. It's only happened a few times that the fishermen have decided to work together to come to a common decision that they can't go fishing right now. The price is not such that they can go fishing. There are 1,700 fishermen or licence holders that are now tied up to the wharf. We'll see how long that goes. It could be something that lasts a few days; it could be something that lasts a few weeks. I'm hoping, of course, for the sake of southwestern Nova Scotia, that it doesn't go on too long, because what ends up happening is that the cash flow within the area tends to start to diminish when that happens, when everybody ties up.</p>
<p>What happens is the fish isn't caught, the fish isn't sold, the bait isn't sold, the fuel isn't sold, and all those things. So everybody within that system which our area is so dependent upon will start to suffer because of that cash flow. We all know as the year comes to an end - we have until the end of May, as we start to move out, that catches start to go up right about now. This is when we start to see the flow of lobster happen in southwestern Nova Scotia. To have our boats tied up means simply that there will be a lot of people who are going to have an uncertain future as to where their next paycheque comes from.</p>
<p>I hope this government is doing something to it. I know the minister had spoken about this a little bit, and I hope his department is working with fishermen to make sure that they may have a better outcome or better outlook when it comes to the pricing of lobster in southwestern Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>The last thing I want to quickly talk about, before my time gets done, is the issue of the school community centre in southwestern Nova Scotia, in Tusket which is in my constituency. As you know, we've spoken to the issue of the unpaid tenders in that, where the school community centre was constructed. It's a wonderful school community centre, the Par-en-Bas school community centre. It has a wonderful theatre, something that we have never had in our area. We have a French preschool, Garderie. We have community space. We have a beautiful art gallery, something that we in southwest Nova Scotia, we in Tusket, in the Acadian region of Argyle, didn't have. The community worked so hard to make sure that it was built and put in place.</p>
<p>We know that Garian Construction - the company that did win the tender, that did do that work - is still owed somewhere close to $300,000, if not $400,000. I'm not saying that this government needs to pay for it, but I wish they would work with someone to say, listen, we all dropped the ball on this. Somebody wasn't paying attention to the way the bills were being paid or handled. We need to try to find a resolution because Garian Construction is an important business in my community that employs a number of people, and for a guy like Ian McNicol to be carrying $300,000 to $400,000 in debt, with absolutely no way of getting it, is really hard for a business like that.</p>
<p>I know the Minister of Finance, the Minister of Acadian Affairs, and the Minister of Communities, Culture and Heritage have all had the opportunity to visit our school community centre. I think they understand the importance of it to our community. I ask them and government to say, let's try to find a way to get it done. Three years have now gone by. It's time to get this over with. I know that there is a legal action that is going on with this one, but I think government still has it within their purview to come up with a solution.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, as we move forward in the budgeting process, I know that there are many things in here that are important to Nova Scotians, yet I think this government could have done a much better job for the constituents of Argyle. Thank you very much.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Hammonds Plains-Upper Sackville.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#mat.whynott"><from>MR. MAT WHYNOTT</from><p>Thank you very much, Mr. Speaker, and I'm certainly glad to stand today in my place to talk a little bit about what will be the last estimates debate going into Supply. I'm glad to stand today to talk a little bit about what it means for Nova Scotians who voted in our government in 2009.</p>
<p>I guess one of the things that I do want to start with is that I know the member from Preston was talking about some of the things that - they are so doom and gloom in this province, and he always talks about all of the things, about energy costs and everything. Well, Mr. Speaker, I have a quote from the member, from Hansard, from Public Accounts Committee on Wednesday, April 11, 2012.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#member" status="undefined">
          <from>AN HON. MEMBER</from>
          <p>2012?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#mat.whynott"><from>MR. WHYNOTT</from><p>Yes, 2012. This is only a couple of weeks ago. The quote goes like this - and it's taken from Hansard, Mr. Speaker - it says, "Just before I ask Mr. Crandlemire &#x2026;" - who is the CEO of Efficiency Nova Scotia - "&#x2026; for closing comments, I would like to personally say that I've made renovations on my home at my own expense. I had the energy audit done and didn't get anything done in time to get rebates from it. I went from burning about eight to nine cords of wood a year down to about two-and-a-half cords a year to heat my home. So it really does pay off."</p>
<p>Then he goes on to say, "I want to thank you and your staff for the fantastic job you are doing working with Nova Scotians &#x2026;" - now get this, Mr. Speaker - "&#x2026; to make life more affordable here while at the same time other factors are creating a great deal of financial grief."</p>
<p>He says, "To make life more affordable." (Applause) And he goes on to say, "I want to commend you and your staff and the work you've done with my constituency office, too, to help local constituents." I'd like to table that, Mr. Speaker. (Interruptions) That was the member for Preston.</p>
<p>I just wanted to get up and lay it on the table here, in the record, that the member for Preston thanked the government, many people, for making life more affordable for Nova Scotian families.</p>
<p>I want to talk a little bit, Mr. Speaker, about the budget that we have today that will be before us later on, on a budget vote. I want to talk a little bit about some of the things that are in the budget. Now we know that this vote will come today, it will come to a vote in the House, but I want to kind of take us back to where we came from. Let's not forget when we came into government in 2009, if this province had used the status quo of departments continuing to increase by 9 per cent annually, we would have seen our provincial debt go from $12.8 billion to over $17 billion, if things had not changed.</p>
<p>We turned this ship around, Mr. Speaker, we turned the ship around. So it's the other two Parties who have created this massive debt that we've had.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#member" status="undefined">
          <from>AN HON. MEMBER</from>
          <p>How much? How much?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#mat.whynott"><from>MR. WHYNOTT</from><p>Currently we have a $12.8 billion debt and, from my understanding, 75 per cent of that debt is from the Progressive Conservative Party and 25 per cent of that debt is from the Liberal Party of Nova Scotia. This is back in the day when those two Parties across the way would spend, spend, spend and spend.</p>
<p>So, Mr. Speaker, my question to the Opposition is, what are they against in this budget? Are they against $281 million of building and maintaining roads, roads in constituencies that they represent that need the work that needs to be done, taking the politics out of paving, through the five-year road plan? Are they against $281 million to build roads, maintaining our infrastructure?</p>
<p>What about $150 million invested in new buildings such as schools, courts, and health care facilities - are they against that? I think they are because that's what is going to happen today. We know, Mr. Speaker, those two Parties over there will more than likely vote against the budget, but obviously they are against the things that I'm reading here today. What about improving IT in our hospitals, in our schools? Another $52.7 million investment. Maintaining vehicles and equipment, purchasing land that is so important to Nova Scotians.</p>
<p>The purchasing of land - I know that the two Parties sitting over there said they are against it because all it is, is dirt. We know on this side, Mr. Speaker, that we need to do the investments, we need to ensure that the land that needs to be purchased. What about providing capital grants? All of those things, Mr. Speaker, $113.8 million - are they against that? I would say they are.</p>
<p>What about ensuring, Mr. Speaker - over here now - I know they are also against investments in Bowater and in NewPage. I know they don't want to keep jobs, they don't want 2,000 jobs, spinoff jobs, that if that mill had closed we would have seen a decrease in how many people are working in this province. We also know that they are against the NewPage investment, they are against the Ships Start Here, they are against Irving, because they don't want to see the prosperity of this province that has never been.</p>
<p>Let's remember, Mr. Speaker, for 20 years Nova Scotia had the worst economic growth in Canada. We know that the Conference Board of Canada has said that Nova Scotia will see economic prosperity that we have never seen before in this province for the next 30 years under the NDP Government. They're against the investments in the Irving Shipbuilding, especially down in Shelburne County. They are against the Shelburne Shipyard. Those investments will ensure that hundreds of Nova Scotians in the southwestern portion of this province will have jobs.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I encourage all Nova Scotians who are listening today, the many who are home watching Legislative TV - we want to set this record straight on the other two Parties. (Interruption) You know, that was the other thing that the Opposition said. I remember one of the members across the way, when we were talking about places like Bowater and NewPage, they said that that industry is a dinosaur. Do you know what? I think that we need to ensure that we invest in our primary industries through forestry, through farming and through fishing. That's what this government stands for.</p>
<p>I want to move on, Mr. Speaker, to health care, an issue that we know all Nova Scotians cherish, something that I think we know is the number-one issue for many Nova Scotians, ensuring that they get the care where they live and when they need it. For many, many years we have had long waits and closures that have plagued Nova Scotia's health care system for many years. So my question is, are those two Parties against a $3 million investment in meeting our emergency room standards? I think they are. I know that they are against providing new dollars to provide for physician oversight at our collaborative emergency centres. I know they're against that.</p>
<p>What about increasing the number of paramedics and nurses in our collaborative emergency centres? That's a $1.4 million investment. They are against that. They are against it and we know it. Are they against increasing funding to meet growing caseloads for home support visits? They are against it and that's an $11.8 million investment. Providing additional in-home nursing care services - $6.5 million - are they against it? Yes. Providing more money for home improvements to support accessibility - a $1.5 million investment - are they against that? Yes. What about helping seniors manage their mobility and medications, more money into that, are they against it? Absolutely.</p>
<p>I hear all the time from the Opposition that we need to ensure that we are building and replacing our nursing home beds. This year alone we are investing 76 new ones and 440 replacement nursing home beds in communities across Nova Scotia. How much is that - $8 million - and are they against it? Yes. I know that they're against the fair drug plan, saving $17 million, ensuring that Nova Scotians who are on Pharmacare pay less for their prescription drugs, they are against that.</p>
<p>They are against providing funding for Lucentis, a $1 million investment, something I know they touted and said they supported all the time but, no, they're going to vote against a $1 million investment. I know that they're against, as I mentioned earlier, building more hospitals and buildings. They're against upgrading the Cape Breton Regional Hospital, the South Shore Regional Hospital and other health care facilities across. Purchasing new hospital equipment, they're against that - a $15 million investment - they're against it.</p>
<p>So, Mr. Speaker, my question is, the Opposition continues to - you know, as they say, hold the government accountable - but they never say what they would do if they were on this side of the House. They never say it. You just can't oppose things, you have to give (Interruptions)</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Order, please. Order, please.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Preston had the floor. He had his say. The honourable member had his say for 15 minutes so the honourable member for Hammonds Plains-Upper Sackville will have his say. Thank you.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Hammonds Plains-Upper Sackville has the floor.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#mat.whynott"><from>MR. WHYNOTT</from><p>Thank you very much, Mr. Speaker, and I know my time is coming to an end but I can tell you right now that the members on this side of the House, this government has a plan to ensure that Nova Scotia, this province, is going back to balance and moving this province forward. I know they had no plan when they were in government, but this government does.</p>
<p>Something else - in regard to the people who are at the lowest income levels in this province - is to ensure that we can make their life just a little bit more affordable. I know that when the two Parties opposite vote against the budget, when they vote against the budget that is going to be put on the floor today, they will vote against providing personal income reductions for 78,000 Nova Scotians. They're against helping immigrants and their families access the services they need to transition to here in Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>Offering more relief for new home purchases for first-time homebuyers, they are against that tax reduction. They are against it. They're against addressing ambulance fees with emphasis on journeys involving seniors and long-term care facilities. They talked about it for many years. They are against the fact that we held the line on 1,400 user fees such as vehicle registration and fishing licences. They are against returning the provincial income tax for low-income seniors in receipt of the Guaranteed Income Supplement, putting an average of $450 back in the pockets of 17,000 seniors.</p>
<p>I know, as I stand here in my place, when those two Parties vote against the budget today, they will vote against something that is helping seniors in this province. They are against investing a further $5.5 million in student assistance. They are against increasing the income assistance personal allowance by $9 a month, building on last year's investment of $15 a month, putting more money into the people who need it the most - those two Parties are against these things.</p>
<p>It increased the Affordable Living Tax Credit amount for individuals, for adults - $255 and for a dependent child - $60 more into the pockets of the people who need it the most. And they are against the increase in the Poverty Reduction Credit to $250 per year, helping approximately 15,000 families that need and deserve it the most.</p>
<p>We have a plan. This Party, this government is going to move this province forward. We are proud and optimistic about Nova Scotia's future, the first time ever that a government has ensured that Nova Scotia will see prosperity for decades to come. Thank you very much.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Halifax Chebucto.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#howard.epstein"><from>MR. HOWARD EPSTEIN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, thank you. It gives me a great deal of pleasure to draw the attention of members of this House to the presence in the gallery opposite of visitors from Grade 3 at St. Catherine's School, a school located in my constituency. These are students who are in the French Immersion Program, the very program and at the very school that both of my children attended, I'm happy to say. Along with the 30 students are a number of their parents. We have Andrew Noseworthy, Debbie Hynes, Heather Hanson, Deirdre Evans, Nancy MacLeod and Karen Boyd. The members of the House will be especially interested to take note that the teacher of these students is Jacklyn O'Leary, who is a former Page and will be familiar to many of us.</p>
<p>I would ask the members of the House to give all of these visitors a very warm welcome to our proceedings. (Applause)</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>We welcome all of our guests to the gallery and hope they enjoy this morning's proceedings.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>10:24 a.m. The House resolved itself into a Committee of the Whole House on Supply with Deputy Speaker Ms. Becky Kent in the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <narrative>
          <p>12:23 p.m. Committee of the Whole House on Supply rose and the House reconvened. Mr. Speaker, Hon. Gordon Gosse, resumed the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The Chairman of the Committee of the Whole House on Supply reports:</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined">
          <from>THE CLERK</from>
          <p>That the Committee of the Whole House on Supply has met and has come to agreement on 47 estimate resolutions, including votes on business plans and on capital. The chairman has been instructed to recommend these estimates to the favourable consideration of the House, each without amendment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the House concurs on the report of the Committee of the Whole House on Supply.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>A recorded vote has been called.</p>
<p>Ring the bells. Call in the members.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>The Division bells were rung.</p>
        </narrative>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>Are the Whips satisfied?</p>
        </speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>The Clerk calls the roll.</p>
        </narrative>
        <other><table>
<tr>
<td>
<b>YEAS</b>
</td>
<td>
<b>NAYS</b>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. Landry<br/> Ms. More<br/> Mr. Estabrooks<br/> Ms. Peterson-Rafuse<br/> Mr. Corbett<br/> Mr. Steele<br/> Ms. Maureen MacDonald<br/> Mr. Paris<br/> Ms. Jennex<br/> Mr. MacDonell<br/> Mr. Belliveau<br/> Mr. Preyra<br/> Ms. Zann<br/> Ms. Kent<br/> Ms. Conrad</td>
<td>Mr. Gaudet<br/> Mr. Glavine<br/> Ms. Whalen<br/> Mr. McNeil<br/> Mr. Samson<br/> Mr. d'Entremont<br/> Mr. Baillie<br/> Mr. Bain<br/> Mr. Porter<br/> Mr. MacMaster<br/> Mr. Orrell<br/> Mr. Younger<br/> Ms. Regan<br/> Ms. Casey<br/> Mr. Colwell</td>
</tr>
</table>
</other>
        <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined">
          <from>THE CLERK</from>
          <p>For, 29. Against, 19.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#frank.corbett">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Introduction of Bills.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>INTRODUCTION OF BILLS</heading>
        <other>
          <p>
            <b> Bill No. 69 - Entitled an Act to Provide for Defraying Certain Charges and Expenses of the Public Service of the Province. (Hon. Graham Steele)</b>
          </p>
        </other>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PUBLIC BILLS FOR SECOND READING</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Finance.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#graham.steele">
          <from>HON. GRAHAM STEELE</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, I move second reading of Bill No. 69, the Appropriations Act, 2012.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for second reading of Bill No. 69. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PUBLIC BILLS FOR THIRD READING</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Finance.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#graham.steele">
          <from>HON. GRAHAM STEELE</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, I move third reading of Bill No. 69, the Appropriations Act, 2012.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for third reading of Bill No. 69. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>A recorded vote is being called for.</p>
<p>Ring the bells. Call in the members.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>The Division bells were rung.</p>
        </narrative>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>Are the Whips satisfied?</p>
        </speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>The Clerk calls the roll.</p>
        </narrative>
        <other><table>
<tr>
<td>
<b>YEAS</b>
</td>
<td>
<b>NAYS</b>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ms. More<br/> Mr. Estabrooks<br/> Ms. Peterson-Rafuse<br/> Mr. Corbett<br/> Mr. Steele<br/> Ms. Maureen MacDonald<br/> Mr. Paris<br/> Ms. Jennex<br/> Mr. MacDonell<br/> Mr. Belliveau<br/> Mr. Preyra<br/> Ms. Zann<br/> Ms. Kent<br/> Ms. Conrad<br/> Mr. Wilson<br/> Mr. Parker<br/> Mr. MacKinnon<br/> Ms. Raymond<br/></td>
<td>Mr. Gaudet<br/> Mr. Glavine<br/> Ms. Whalen<br/> Mr. McNeil<br/> Mr. Samson<br/> Mr. d'Entremont<br/> Mr. Baillie<br/> Mr. Bain<br/> Mr. Porter<br/> Mr. MacMaster<br/> Mr. Orrell<br/> Mr. Younger<br/> Ms. Regan<br/> Ms. Casey<br/> Mr. Colwell<br/> Mr. Zinc<br/> Mr. Theriault<br/> Mr. MacLellan<br/></td>
</tr>
</table>
</other>
        <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined">
          <from>THE CLERK</from>
          <p>For, 28, Against, 19.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill do pass. Ordered that the title be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bill be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#frank.corbett"><from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I would like to thank the members of the House for another enjoyable week - mostly on behalf of the Minister of Community Services, she had such an enjoyable week.</p>
<p>That concludes the government's business for the day and the week. I move that the House do now rise, to meet again on Monday between the hours of 2:00 p.m. and 10:00 p.m. After the daily routine, we will call Public Bills for Second Reading, Bill Nos. 5, 9, 11, 13, 17, 20, 22, 24, 30, 32, 37, 39, 52, 55, 59, 61, and 65. For greater certainty, the first bill we will do is Bill No. 17, Financial Measures (2012) Act, and then back to the Education Act.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the House rise, to meet again on Monday from 2:00 p.m. to 10:00 p.m. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>The House rose at 1:42 p.m.</p>
        </narrative>
      </debateSection>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION UNDER RULE 32(3)</heading>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="454">RESOLUTION NO. 454</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Denis Clay, a member of Faith Baptist Church in Great Village, is one of the founders of a group called The Woodchucks, created to help church members as well as other community members who are unable to handle the work involved with processing wood due to illness or loss of a spouse; and</p>
<p>Whereas each job is advertised for volunteers at the church, participation is open to anyone who can carry a stick of wood- the men are Woodchucks, the women are Chuckettes and the children are Woodchips; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Woodchucks do not accept financial contributions, do not involve religion, and do welcome helpers from outside their church;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate this dedicated group of volunteers who annually process approximately 120 cord of wood and willingly give of their time and energy to benefit the lives of so many.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="455">RESOLUTION NO. 455</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Jack Sibley, age 74 and a retired Agricultural Department employee, started teaching the fiddle in 1987 but his main focus shifted to youth in the 1990s; and</p>
<p>Whereas Sibley has passed his love of fiddle music on to hundreds of youth and many adults; and</p>
<p>Whereas Sibley is a past president and lifelong member of the Maritime Fiddlers Association and has been given the Curtis Hicks Memorial Award and the Tara Lynne Touesnard Memorial Award in recognition of his contribution to the preservation of fiddle music;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jack Sibley of Earltown, Colchester North, for receiving the Rotary Club of Truro's Youth Leadership Award and thank him for his many years of commitment to teaching others to play the fiddle.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="456">RESOLUTION NO. 456</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on March 10<sup>th</sup> and March 11<sup>th</sup> the Cobequid Dog Club held a dog show at the AgriDome in Bible Hill, with more than 300 dogs at the event; and</p>
<p>Whereas Maria Forman of Debert, Colchester North, showed her dog Bella, a 20-month-old Keeshond, from her first litter; and</p>
<p>Whereas Bella won the title in the non-sporting conformation category;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Maria Forman and her Keeshond, Bella, for their 1<sup>st</sup> place win at the Cobequid Dog Club Show.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="457">RESOLUTION NO. 457</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas stick curling makes use of a device called a stick that enables a curler to deliver a rock from a standing position; and</p>
<p>Whereas a good curling delivery with a stick requires proper setup, correct aim and weight control just as in slide delivery; and</p>
<p>Whereas in February two men from Colchester County, Ron Crowe from Onslow and Bill Spinney from Truro, were crowned the Nova Scotia Stick Curling Champions;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ron Crowe and Bill Spinney for winning this prestigious title and wish them continued success as they move on to the Maritime Championships.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="458">RESOLUTION NO. 458</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the West Colchester Well Within Chiropractic Cobras participated in the Peewee B Division of the Bob Morgan Memorial Hockey Tournament, in Digby, in February; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Cobras posted a 2-1 record in the round-robin with a 4-2 setback to the TASA Black Ducks but going on to a 12-1 victory over the Shelburne Flames and a 9-1 win over the host Ravens; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Cobras blanked the West Hants Warriors 3-0 in the final;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the West Colchester Well Within Chiropractic Cobras for winning gold at the Bob Morgan Memorial Hockey Tournament and wish them continued success.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="459">RESOLUTION NO. 459</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Cassandra Teed from East Mountain, Colchester North, transferred from Acadian to the NSAC a year ago, Coach Paul Settle of the NSAC Rams women's volleyball team knew he had the foundation he needed to build the team into what it is already this season, second place in the seven-team circuit; and</p>
<p>Whereas Teed, who last year only played half a season for the NSAC Rams, was named to the conference all-star team as selected by the circuit's judges; and</p>
<p>Whereas this season she leads the country in kill percentage, averaging 4.36 per set;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Cassandra Teed for her hard work and determination to use her excellent athletic abilities to push herself and her teammates as far as they can go, hopefully to bring the NSAC its first conference title.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="460">RESOLUTION NO. 460</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Angela Woods needed a kidney transplant for the second time in her life; and</p>
<p>Whereas Jamie, her husband, hoping to give her one of his, was tested and found to have a cancerous tumor in his stomach, which ruled him out as a donor and led to him losing his stomach; and</p>
<p>Whereas Andrew Woods, Angela's brother-in-law from Onslow, Colchester North, travelled to Alberta to undergo the testing to determine if he were a match for organ donation;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Andrew Woods for his generous donation of a kidney to save the life of his sister-in-law, and commend him for his willingness to make such a personal sacrifice for the welfare of another.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="461">RESOLUTION NO. 461</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas 81-year-old Marion Usher breeds, sells and owns champion poodles, operates Tinkilee Kennel in Colchester North, and has dogs in most parts of the world; and</p>
<p>Whereas Usher has won eight medallions in the American Kennel Club's bred by exhibitor class; and</p>
<p>Whereas in February, 2012, at the Westminster Kennel Club Dog Show held in Madison Square Garden in New York City, Tinkilee's Drama Queen, a toy poodle bred and co-owned by Usher, was awarded best in breed;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Marion Usher for receiving this outstanding recognition from the most prestigious dog show in North America and wish her continued success and enjoyment with her poodles.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="462">RESOLUTION NO. 462</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Colchester Historical Society has celebrated Heritage Night for 30 years to recognize people who preserve and promote local heritage; and</p>
<p>Whereas Dale Swan, from Tatamagouche, Colchester North, was honoured with the Individual Heritage Award; and</p>
<p>Whereas Dale received this award for his volunteering with the Anna Swan Museum, North Shore Archives and Creamery Square;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Dale Swan for receiving the Heritage Award from the Colchester Historical Society and for his efforts to maintain our heritage and make it accessible to the general public.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="463">RESOLUTION NO. 463</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas small business operators are the backbone of Nova Scotia's economy; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ron and Linda Cavanaugh purchased Grant's Grocery in North River, Colchester North, 33 years ago; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Cavanaughs have generously supported their community, and have provided excellent customer service for over three decades;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ron and Linda Cavanaugh for their business acumen and their commitment to customers and community.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="464">RESOLUTION NO. 464</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Colchester-Cumberland Windfield is a Nova Scotia corporation, which strives to realize the vision of community-owned, renewable electricity generation; and</p>
<p>Whereas Colchester-Cumberland Windfield is the first registered CEDIF, Community Economic-Development Investment Funds, in Nova Scotia contracted to generate electricity by Nova Scotia Power; and</p>
<p>Whereas the company's first 800 kW wind turbine was installed on Spiddle Hill near Tatamagouche, Colchester North, and began operation in July 2011;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Colchester-Cumberland Windfield shareholders for their efforts to bring economic benefit and environmental pride to the region, for the installation of the company's first wind turbine, and for recently being awarded another contract to install more on Spiddle Hill.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="465">RESOLUTION NO. 465</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Prudential Atlantic Provinces Award Gala was held in Halifax on February 23<sup>rd</sup>, 2012; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Rising Star of the Year Award was presented to the top new Prudential associate in Atlantic Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas Tom Taggart, from Bass River, Colchester North, recently employed by Prudential Woods Realty Limited, Truro, was the recipient of this award;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Tom Taggart for receiving this prestigious award and wish him continued success.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="466">RESOLUTION NO. 466</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the outdoor rink in Five Islands, Colchester North, was started 40 years ago; and</p>
<p>Whereas interest in the upkeep of the rink began to wane in recent years, some new volunteers were able to revive interest in the community project; and</p>
<p>Whereas the distance from an indoor rink, the high price of gas and the time required for travel are all contributing factors to the popularity of having a rink in their own community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the residents of Five Islands, Colchester North, for vitalizing interest in their outdoor rink and taking the initiative to provide a place for family members of all ages to enjoy the fresh air and exercise.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="467">RESOLUTION NO. 467</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Ray Smith, from Colchester North, has driven a milk collection truck for the last 40 years for Farmers Cooperative Dairy; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ray daily makes many stops at farms around the region collecting producers' milk; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ray only missed three days of work during his 40 years of service, once when he had pneumonia and again when his home burnt down about 20 years ago;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ray Smith for his years of service and commend him for setting such an admirable example of a positive work ethic.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="468">RESOLUTION NO. 468</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Bethan Cripps, a Grade 12 student at North Colchester High School, is a member of the Girls Leadership Program, a mentor for Big Brothers/Big Sisters, a representative on student council, a leader at the After School Program, and an organizer for fundraisers and winter carnival events; and</p>
<p>Whereas Bethan, an excellent soccer player who spends her summers coaching for the Tatamagouche Soccer Club, started the season on Colchester North's team as a striker and played every position, including goalie, before the season ended; and</p>
<p>Whereas Bethan's organizational skills are clearly shown by her ability to participate in so many school activities, hold down a part-time job, volunteer in her community, and earn Honours With Distinction every year since Grade 7, even achieving the highest average in Grade 11;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate this outstanding student, Bethan Cripps, for her academic excellence, her involvement in school and community, her athletic ability, and for being named Student of the Month for September 2011 at North Colchester High School.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="469">RESOLUTION NO. 469</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Taylor Smith, a Grade 8 student at North Colchester High School, has shown his academic ability by achieving Honours With Distinction in Grade 7; and</p>
<p>Whereas Taylor's extracurricular activities include golf and hockey, and his athletic ability is apparent since he earned a spot on the Major Bantam Bearcats team that plays out of Truro; and</p>
<p>Whereas his teachers and peers describe Taylor as a good role model who uses his time well, is polite and respectful, and always puts forth his best effort;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Taylor Smith for his academic excellence, his athletic skills, and for being named Student of the Month for September 2011 at North Colchester High School.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="470">RESOLUTION NO. 470</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Jasmine Swan is a conscientious, reliable, responsible Grade 12 student at Colchester North High School in Tatamagouche, Colchester North; and</p>
<p>Whereas Jasmine is noted for being hardworking, kind, and helpful in the classroom, and for always being respectful, positive, and encouraging with other students; and</p>
<p>Whereas her work placement employers are pleased with her organizational skills, honesty, dependability, friendliness, and contributions;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jasmine Swan for her many desirable character traits and for being selected as the Student of the Month for October 2011.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="471">RESOLUTION NO. 471</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Dwayne Heighton is a Grade 9 student at North Colchester High School in Tatamagouche, Colchester North; and</p>
<p>Whereas Dwayne is noted for being hardworking and determined to do well in all his classes; and</p>
<p>Whereas another outstanding feature is Dwayne's willingness to volunteer or to help others;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Dwayne Heighton for his many desirable character traits and for being selected as Student of the Month for October 2011.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="472">RESOLUTION NO. 472</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Rebecca von Kintzel, a Grade 9 student at North Colchester High School in Tatamagouche, Colchester North, is an excellent academic student, having earned Honours With Distinction in both Grade 7 and Grade 8; and</p>
<p>Whereas Rebecca volunteers, takes lessons in horseback riding, and holds a part-time job; and</p>
<p>Whereas Rebecca is often described as quiet, studious, and very courteous and polite by her teachers and her peers;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Rebecca von Kintzel, an excellent choice for the November 2011 Student of the Month at North Colchester High School.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="473">RESOLUTION NO. 473</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Whitney Tattrie, a Grade 12 student at North Colchester High School in Tatamagouche, Colchester North, is described by her teachers as a top student, a great critical thinker, an amazing writer and literary role model, and a strong female presence in the classroom; and</p>
<p>Whereas Whitney plays on North Colchester High's basketball, volleyball, and soccer teams, holding the co-captain title for both soccer and basketball; and</p>
<p>Whereas Whitney also helps with winter carnival and dance committee, prom, STOP and Safe Grad, holds down a part-time job and volunteers at such places as Tim Horton's camp and Willow Lodge;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Whitney Tattrie, an excellent choice for the November 2011 Student of the Month at North Colchester High School.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="474">RESOLUTION NO. 474</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Leah Sabine is a Grade 9 student at North Colchester High School in Tatamagouche, Colchester North; and</p>
<p>Whereas Leah is a conscientious, hard-working, talented student who is very gifted artistically; and</p>
<p>Whereas Leah's work ethic and commitment are also shown in her extracurricular activities, which include playing on the girls' basketball team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Leah Sabine for being named Student of the Month at North Colchester High School for December 2011.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="475">RESOLUTION NO. 475</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas John Hunt is a Grade 9 student at North Colchester High School in Tatamagouche, Colchester North, who shows dedication and commitment to his studies and his extracurricular activities; and</p>
<p>Whereas John is very talented musically and a strong academic student, earning honours in both Grades 7 and 8; and</p>
<p>Whereas John is an organized student who maintains excellent marks while also taking part in extracurricular activities - playing point guard for the basketball team and mid-field position for the soccer team, as well as serving as captain of the team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate John Hunt for being named Student of the Month at North Colchester High School for December 2011.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="476">RESOLUTION NO. 476</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Channing Hines is a Grade 12 student at North Colchester High School in Tatamagouche, Colchester North; and</p>
<p>Whereas Channing is very popular with his teachers and his peers because he is focused, hard- working, helpful, kind, mature, and has a great sense of humour; and</p>
<p>Whereas Channing's extracurricular activities include playing basketball, for which he is noted as a very skilled force to be reckoned with on the court;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Channing Hines for being named Student of the Month at North Colchester High School for January 2012.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="477">RESOLUTION NO. 477</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Emily Galvao is a Grade 12 student at North Colchester High School in Tatamagouche, Colchester North, and also a new student to the school; and</p>
<p>Whereas Emily is a good student academically because she is eager to learn, takes pride in her work, loves a challenge, and is not afraid of hard work; and</p>
<p>Whereas Emily is a popular student due to her being kind- hearted, friendly, positive in outlook, and eager to participate;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Emily Galvao for being named Student of the Month at North Colchester High School for January 2012, and wish her continued success in her graduating year.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#chuck.porter"><num title="478">RESOLUTION NO. 478</num><from>Mr. Chuck Porter</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas motocross is a form of motorcycle racing held on enclosed off-road circuits; and</p>
<p>Whereas in a series of six races, spread throughout the Maritimes, Mount Denson resident Randy Dunbar captured first place in the MXI Junior Spring Series last Fall; and</p>
<p>Whereas with eight years experience on the track and a junior series win under his belt, Randy is ready to join his brother, Jon, at the intermediate level next season;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Randy on his successful motocross season and wish him continued success.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#chuck.porter"><num title="479">RESOLUTION NO. 479</num><from>Mr. Chuck Porter</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Duke of Edinburgh's Award was founded in 1956 by His Royal Highness Prince Philip, Duke of Edinburgh, and the award came to Canada in 1963; and</p>
<p>Whereas Steven Wu of Windsor was recently recognized as a Bronze Award Achiever after completing the required activities for the bronze level; and</p>
<p>Whereas the goal of the Duke of Edinburgh's Award is to encourage young people to be active, to participate in new activities and to pursue current interests in the areas of community service, personal skill development, physical recreation, and an advantageous journey;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Steven Wu on being a Bronze Award Achiever of the Duke of Edinburgh's Award and wish him all the best.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#keith.bain"><num title="480">RESOLUTION NO. 480</num><from>Mr. Keith Bain</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Gaelic College of Celtic Arts and Crafts, founded in 1938, began as a school of Gaelic language in a small log cabin overlooking St. Anns Bay; and</p>
<p>Whereas although today the college has expanded greatly, the traditions and devotion to the study and preservation of the Gaelic language, arts, and culture has stayed strong and true; and</p>
<p>Whereas 111 students of all ages benefited from the college's traditions by taking part in a variety of March Break programs, which included Gaelic song, drama, dance, fiddle, piano, and much more;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly applaud and provide thanks to the Gaelic College of Celtic Arts and Crafts CEO Rodney MacDonald, Director of Education Tracey Dares MacNeil, and staff for their efforts to preserve the Gaelic language, art, and culture in our area.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#jamie.baillie"><num title="481">RESOLUTION NO. 481</num><from>Hon. Jamie Baillie</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Oxford Golden Bears Senior Girls are regional basketball champions, securing the regional banner in February as they hosted the 2011-2012 Northumberland Region Championship Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas Oxford's first game matched them up with the Lady Warriors from Parrsboro, where Oxford scored often and took the game by a wide margin, leading to a game against the defending Northumberland Region champions, the Pugwash Panthers, which the Oxford girls won with a score of 86 to 44; and</p>
<p>Whereas as regional champions, the Oxford Golden Bears earned themselves a bye straight through to Provincials in March at Armbrae Academy, in Halifax;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Oxford Golden Bears Senior Girls basketball team on this great accomplishment and wish them continued success.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#leo.glavine"><num title="482">RESOLUTION NO. 482</num><from>Mr. Leo Glavine</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Fred Whalen was first elected as municipal councillor to represent Polling District 21 in 1997 and was re-elected in 2000, 2004, and 2008; and</p>
<p>Whereas Fred was a member of the Atlantic Mayor Congress and was formerly the chair of the Rural Caucus on the UNSM Board, but his political career was most distinguished by five consecutive terms as warden of the Municipality of Kings; and</p>
<p>Whereas Fred Whalen's political career was his third, having served with the RCAF and Canadian Forces for 21 years and as an employee of the House of Commons for 15 years;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Fred on his careers of service and wish him and his wife, Anne, a wonderful retirement in Somerset, Kings County.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="483">RESOLUTION NO. 483</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking D'Escousse Civic Improvement Society Volunteer of the Year, Doreen Gallant, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="484">RESOLUTION NO. 484</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Dr. W.B. Kingston Memorial Community Health Centre Volunteer of the Year, Elsie Deveau, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="485">RESOLUTION NO. 485</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Coastal Riders ATV Association Volunteer of the Year, Ewan MacDonald, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="486">RESOLUTION NO. 486</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking 2842 L'Ardoise Army Cadets Corps Volunteer of the Year, Francis Doucette, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="487">RESOLUTION NO. 487</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking 824 Silver Dart Squadron, Royal Canadian Air Cadets Volunteer of the Year, James Mullin, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="488">RESOLUTION NO. 488</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Canadian Red Cross, Isle Madame Volunteer of the Year, Janet Landry, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="489">RESOLUTION NO. 489</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking 235 Arrow Royal Canadian Sea Cadets Volunteer of the Year, Jarrod David, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="490">RESOLUTION NO. 490</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Bonnie Brae Seniors Club Volunteer of the Year, Joe Stone, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="491">RESOLUTION NO. 491</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Bras d'Or Lakers Seniors Volunteer of the Year, Kay Magdy, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="492">RESOLUTION NO. 492</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Bonnie Brae Seniors Club Volunteer of the Year, Monica Stone, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="493">RESOLUTION NO. 493</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Comit&#xE9; R&#xE9;gional des A&#xEE;n&#xE9;s de RANE Volunteer of the Year, Patrick Pertus, for his hard work and commitment.</p>
<p>&#xFFFD; une date ult&#xE9;rieure, je demanderai l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu que les b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles sont vraiment au c&#xFFFD;ur de notre communaut&#xE9;; et</p>
<p>Attendu que les b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles donnent librement de leur temps pour aider les organismes &#xE0; l'&#xE9;chelle de notre pays; et</p>
<p>Attendu que le vendredi 20 avril 2012, je me suis joint au personnel et aux conseillers municipaux lors d'un souper de reconnaissance des 140 b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles du comt&#xE9; de Richmond; et</p>
<p>Par cons&#xE9;quent, il est r&#xE9;solu que les membres de cette Assembl&#xE9;e se joignent &#xE0; moi pour remercier Patrick Pertus, b&#xE9;n&#xE9;vole de l'ann&#xE9;e du Comit&#xE9; r&#xE9;gional des a&#xEE;n&#xE9;s du RANE, pour son travail et son d&#xE9;vouement.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="494">RESOLUTION NO. 494</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Canadian Cancer Society Volunteer of the Year, Pierre Samson, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="495">RESOLUTION NO. 495</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Development Isle Madame Association Volunteer of the Year, Robert Samson, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="496">RESOLUTION NO. 496</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking District #10 Volunteer Fire Department Volunteer of the Year, Scott Madgy, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="497">RESOLUTION NO. 497</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Acadiaville Community Centre Society Volunteer of the Year, Sheri Samson-Dorey, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="498">RESOLUTION NO. 498</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Black River United Church Volunteer of the Year, Shirley Burke, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="499">RESOLUTION NO. 499</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Centre La Picasse Volunteer of the Year, Th&#xE9;r&#xE8;se Benoit, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="499">RESOLUTION NO. 499</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>&#xFFFD; une date ult&#xE9;rieure, je demanderai l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu que les b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles sont vraiment au c&#xFFFD;ur de notre communaut&#xE9;; et</p>
<p>Attendu que les b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles donnent librement de leur temps pour aider les organismes &#xE0; l'&#xE9;chelle de notre pays; et</p>
<p>Attendu que le vendredi 20 avril 2012, je me suis joint au personnel et aux conseillers municipaux lors d'un souper de reconnaissance des 140 b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles du comt&#xE9; de Richmond; et</p>
<p>Par cons&#xE9;quent, il est r&#xE9;solu que les membres de cette Assembl&#xE9;e se joignent &#xE0; moi pour remercier Th&#xE9;r&#xE8;se Benoit, b&#xE9;n&#xE9;vole de l'ann&#xE9;e du centre La Picasse pour son travail et son d&#xE9;vouement.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="500">RESOLUTION NO. 500</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Basin River Inhabitants Historical Society Volunteer of the Year, Victoria Jenssen, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="501">RESOLUTION NO. 501</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Conseil Pastoral, St. Joseph Volunteer of the Year, Ben Samson, for his hard work and commitment.</p>
<p>&#xFFFD; une date ult&#xE9;rieure, je demanderai l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu que les b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles sont vraiment au c&#xFFFD;ur de notre communaut&#xE9;; et</p>
<p>Attendu que les b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles donnent librement de leur temps pour aider les organismes &#xE0; l'&#xE9;chelle de notre pays; et</p>
<p>Attendu que le vendredi 20 avril 2012, je me suis joint au personnel et aux conseillers municipaux lors d'un souper de reconnaissance des 140 b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles du comt&#xE9; de Richmond; et</p>
<p>Par cons&#xE9;quent, il est r&#xE9;solu que les membres de cette Assembl&#xE9;e se joignent &#xE0; moi pour remercier Ben Samson, b&#xE9;n&#xE9;vole de l'ann&#xE9;e du Conseil pastoral Saint-Joseph, pour son travail et son d&#xE9;vouement.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="502">RESOLUTION NO. 502</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking 235 Arrow Royal Canadian Sea Cadets Volunteer of the Year, Cassandra David, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="503">RESOLUTION NO. 503</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking East Novability for Persons with Disabilities Volunteer of the Year, Madaline Libbus, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="504">RESOLUTION NO. 504</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking &#xC9;cole Beau-Port volunteer of the year, Margaret Ann Landry, for her hard work and commitment.</p>
<p>&#xFFFD; une date ult&#xE9;rieure, je demanderai l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu que les b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles sont vraiment au c&#xFFFD;ur de notre communaut&#xE9;; et</p>
<p>Attendu que les b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles donnent librement de leur temps pour aider les organismes &#xE0; l'&#xE9;chelle de notre pays; et</p>
<p>Attendu que le vendredi 20 avril 2012, je me suis joint au personnel et aux conseillers municipaux lors d'un souper de reconnaissance des 140 b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles du comt&#xE9; de Richmond; et</p>
<p>Par cons&#xE9;quent, il est r&#xE9;solu que les membres de cette Assembl&#xE9;e se joignent &#xE0; moi pour remercier Margaret Ann Landry, b&#xE9;n&#xE9;vole de l'ann&#xE9;e de l'&#xC9;cole Beau-Port, pour son travail et son d&#xE9;vouement.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="505">RESOLUTION NO. 505</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Fourchu Development Association Volunteer of the Year, Margie Rafuse, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="506">RESOLUTION NO. 506</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Fourchu United Church U.C.W. Volunteer of the Year, Mildred MacIntyre, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="507">RESOLUTION NO. 507</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Fourchu United Church Volunteer of the Year, Neil Tonet, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="508">RESOLUTION NO. 508</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Felix Marchand Education Centre Volunteer of the Year, Shauna Mills-Giggey, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="509">RESOLUTION NO. 509</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Friends of Isle Madame Provincial Parks Volunteer of the Year, Susan Marchand-Terrio, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="510">RESOLUTION NO. 510</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking East Richmond ATV Riders Society Volunteer of the Year, Ann L. Carter, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="511">RESOLUTION NO. 511</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking East Richmond Education Centre Volunteer of the Year, Ann Marie Sampson, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="512">RESOLUTION NO. 512</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Immaculate Conception Parish Barra Head Volunteer of the Year, Bill Stone, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="513">RESOLUTION NO. 513</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Grand River Volunteer Fire Department Volunteer of the Year Billy MacLeod for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="514">RESOLUTION NO. 514</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Framboise-Fourchu Volunteer Fire Department Volunteer of the Year Blair Gwynn for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="515">RESOLUTION NO. 515</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Head of the Bay Seniors Volunteer of the Year Catherine Skinner for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="516">RESOLUTION NO. 516</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Festival Acadien de Petit de Grat Volunteer of the Year Charlene Bonin for her hard work and commitment.</p>
<p>A une date ult&#xE9;rieure, je demanderai l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu que les b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles sont vraiment au c&#xFFFD;ur de notre communaut&#xE9;; et</p>
<p>Attendu que les b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles donnent librement de leur temps pour aider les organismes &#xE0; l'&#xE9;chelle de notre pays; et</p>
<p>Attendu que le vendredi 20 avril 2012, je me suis joint au personnel et aux conseillers municipaux lors d'un souper de reconnaissance des 140 b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles du comt&#xE9; de Richmond; et</p>
<p>Par cons&#xE9;quent, il est r&#xE9;solu que les membres de cette Assembl&#xE9;e se joignent &#xE0; moi pour remercier Charlene Bonin, b&#xE9;n&#xE9;vole de l'ann&#xE9;e du Festival acadien de Petit-de-Grat, pour son travail et son d&#xE9;vouement.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="517">RESOLUTION NO. 517</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Immaculate Conception Parish Barra Head Volunteer of the Year Chris Stone for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="518">RESOLUTION NO. 518</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Holy Guardian Angel Parish Council Volunteer of the Year Elaine Sampson for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="519">RESOLUTION NO. 519</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 145 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking EnRoute Isle Madame Access Association Volunteer of the Year Joan Clannon for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="520">RESOLUTION NO. 520</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 145 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Framboise Community Centre Volunteer of the Year John James MacLeod for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="521">RESOLUTION NO. 521</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Holy Guardian Community Centre Volunteer of the Year Ken Pottie for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="522">RESOLUTION NO. 522</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 145 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Janvrin's Island Sports and Recreation Association Volunteer of the Year Augustine Chiasson-MacDonald for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="523">RESOLUTION NO. 523</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Immaculate Conception Parish CWL, West Arichat, Volunteer of the Year, Carl Ann Hayne, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="524">RESOLUTION NO. 524</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Isle Madame Small Options Home Society Volunteer of the Year, Chuck Boudreau, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="525">RESOLUTION NO. 525</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Isle Madame Lighthouse Preservation Society Volunteer of the Year, Claire Doyle, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="526">RESOLUTION NO. 526</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Knights of Columbus Volunteer of the Year, Claude J. A. Lavoie, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="527">RESOLUTION NO. 527</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Island View Health Services Auxiliary Volunteer of the Year, Colleen Morgan, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="528">RESOLUTION NO. 528</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Lakeside &amp; Area Seniors Club Volunteer of the Year, Ida Kelly, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="529">RESOLUTION NO. 529</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Lakeside Community Association Volunteer of the Year, Irene Carter, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="530">RESOLUTION NO. 530</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Isle Madame Boat Club, Volunteer of the Year, Kevin Samson, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="531">RESOLUTION NO. 531</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Lakeside 4-H Club Volunteer of the Year, Leona Collier, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="532">RESOLUTION NO. 532</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Janvrin's Island Community Centre Volunteer of the Year, Lorena Landry, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="533">RESOLUTION NO. 533</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Janvrin's Fest Volunteer of the Year, Madison Gaudet, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="534">RESOLUTION NO. 534</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Isle Madame Historical Society Volunteer of the Year, Margaret Herdman, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="535">RESOLUTION NO. 535</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking L'Ardoise Acadian Festival Volunteer of the Year, Nils Adamsson, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="536">RESOLUTION NO. 536</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Isle Madame Garden Club Volunteer of the Year, Phyllis Martell, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="537">RESOLUTION NO. 537</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Isle Madame Tourism and Trade Volunteer of the Year, Sarah Nettleton, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="538">RESOLUTION NO. 538</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking la Coop&#xE9;rative Radio Richmond Lt&#xE9;e. Volunteer of the Year, Th&#xE9;r&#xE8;se Beno&#xEE;t, for her hard work and commitment.</p>
<p>A une date ult&#xE9;rieure, je demanderai l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu que les b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles sont vraiment au c&#xFFFD;ur de notre communaut&#xE9;; et</p>
<p>Attendu que les b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles donnent librement de leur temps pour aider les organismes &#xE0; l'&#xE9;chelle de notre pays; et</p>
<p>Attendu que le vendredi 20 avril, 2012, je me suis joint au personnel et aux conseillers municipaux lors d'un souper de reconnaissance des 140 b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles du comt&#xE9; de Richmond; et</p>
<p>Par cons&#xE9;quent, il est r&#xE9;solu que les membres de cette Assembl&#xE9;e se joignent &#xE0; moi pour remercier Th&#xE9;r&#xE8;se Beno&#xEE;t, b&#xE9;n&#xE9;vole de l'ann&#xE9;e de la Coop&#xE9;rative Radio Richmond Lt&#xE9;e, pour son travail et son d&#xE9;vouement.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="539">RESOLUTION NO. 539</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Isle Madame Volunteer Fire Department Volunteer of the Year, Alfred Richard, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="540">RESOLUTION NO. 540</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking L'Ardoise Jolly Club Volunteer of the Year, Quentin Mombourquette, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="541">RESOLUTION NO. 541</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking L'Association des Femmes Acadiennes en Marche de Richmond Volunteer of the Year, Shirley Martell, for her hard work and commitment.</p>
<p>A une date ult&#xE9;rieure, je demanderai l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu que les b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles sont vraiment au c&#xFFFD;ur de notre communaut&#xE9;; et</p>
<p>Attendu que les b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles donnent librement de leur temps pour aider les organismes &#xE0; l'&#xE9;chelle de notre pays; et</p>
<p>Attendu que le vendredi 20 avril, 2012, je me suis joint au personnel et aux conseillers municipaux lors d'un souper de reconnaissance des 140 b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles du comt&#xE9; de Richmond; et</p>
<p>Par cons&#xE9;quent, il est r&#xE9;solu que les membres de cette Assembl&#xE9;e remercient Shirley Martell, b&#xE9;n&#xE9;vole de l'ann&#xE9;e l'Association des femmes acadiennes en marche de Richmond, pour son travail et son d&#xE9;vouement.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="542">RESOLUTION NO. 542</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Louisdale Girl Guides Volunteer of the Year, Stephanie Marchand, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="543">RESOLUTION NO. 543</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Oceanview Wildlife Museum Volunteer of the Year, Stuwart Carter, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="544">RESOLUTION NO. 544</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Les Amis de La Picasse Volunteer of the Year, Sylvia Boudreau, for her hard work and commitment.</p>
<p>&#xFFFD; une date ult&#xE9;rieure, je demanderai l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu que les b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles sont vraiment au c&#xFFFD;ur de notre communaut&#xE9;; et</p>
<p>Attendu que les b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles donnent librement de leur temps pour aider les organismes &#xE0; l'&#xE9;chelle de notre pays; et</p>
<p>Attendu que le vendredi 20 avril 2012, je me suis joint au personnel et aux conseillers municipaux lors d'un souper de reconnaissance des 140 b&#xE9;n&#xE9;voles du comt&#xE9; de Richmond; et</p>
<p>Par cons&#xE9;quent, il est r&#xE9;solu que les membres de cette Assembl&#xE9;e se joignent &#xE0; moi pour remercier Sylvia Boudreau b&#xE9;n&#xE9;vole de l'ann&#xE9;e du Amis de La Picasse, pour son travail et son d&#xE9;vouement.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="545">RESOLUTION NO. 545</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking North Side Seniors Club Volunteer of the Year, Tena Britten, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="546">RESOLUTION NO. 546</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Louisdale Lions Club Volunteer of the Year, Adrian Boudreau, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="547">RESOLUTION NO. 547</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Little Anse Sampson's Cove Social Action Centre Volunteer of the Year, Amanda Martell, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="548">RESOLUTION NO. 548</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking L'Ardoise Friends of Palliative Care Volunteer of the Year, Anne M. Bona, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="549">RESOLUTION NO. 549</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Louisdale and District Volunteer Fire Department Volunteer of the Year, Arthur Boudreau, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="550">RESOLUTION NO. 550</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Loch Lomond Volunteer Fire Department Volunteer of the Year, Brian Brown, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="551">RESOLUTION NO. 551</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Our Lady of Assumption CWL Volunteer of the Year, Donna Power, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="552">RESOLUTION NO. 552</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking L'Ardoise Men's Club Volunteer of the Year, John Matthews, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="553">RESOLUTION NO. 553</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking L'Ardoise Economic Association for Development Volunteer of the Year, Kevin Lewis, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="554">RESOLUTION NO. 554</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking L'Ardoise Ladies Social Club Volunteer of the Year, Marcella Adamsson, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="555">RESOLUTION NO. 555</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Louisdale Fleur de Lis Seniors Club Volunteer of the Year, Mary Polegato, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="556">RESOLUTION NO. 556</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking New Horizon Seniors Club Volunteer of the Year, Paul Boudreau, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="557">RESOLUTION NO. 557</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking River Bourgeois Mariners Society Volunteer of the Year, Patricia Burke, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="558">RESOLUTION NO. 558</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Richmond Villa Recreation Department Volunteer of the Year, Paula LaFantasie, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="559">RESOLUTION NO. 559</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Richmond County 4-H Council Volunteer of the Year, Peter LeBlanc, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="560">RESOLUTION NO. 560</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Richmond Academy Volunteer of the Year, Phil Samson, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="561">RESOLUTION NO. 561</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Riverdale Community Services Society Volunteer of the Year, Sharon Christena MacNamara, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="562">RESOLUTION NO. 562</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Riverdale Computer Centre Society Volunteer of the Year, Tim Laborie, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="563">RESOLUTION NO. 563</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking River Bourgeois Economic Development Volunteer of the Year, Tina Coleman, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="564">RESOLUTION NO. 564</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Our Lady of Assumption Parish Council Volunteer of the Year, Valerie Boudreau, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="565">RESOLUTION NO. 565</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Richmond Minor Baseball Association Volunteer of the Year, Beryl Boudreau, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="566">RESOLUTION NO. 566</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking River Bourgeois Community Services Society Volunteer of the Year, Conrad Fougere, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="567">RESOLUTION NO. 567</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Richmond Community Access Society Volunteer of the Year, Francine Boudreau, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="568">RESOLUTION NO. 568</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Richmond County Early Childhood Education Association (Isle Madame) Volunteer of the Year, Gail Gallant, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="569">RESOLUTION NO. 569</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking River Bourgeois Mariners Society Volunteer of the Year, Gilbert Burke, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="570">RESOLUTION NO. 570</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking River Bourgeois Technology and Training Centre Volunteer of the Year, Holly Burke, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="571">RESOLUTION NO. 571</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking River Bourgeois 50+ Seniors Club Volunteer of the Year, Janet Nordin, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="572">RESOLUTION NO. 572</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Richmond County Early Childhood Education Association (St. Peter's) Volunteer of the Year, Jennifer Burke, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="573">RESOLUTION NO. 573</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Potlotek Education Volunteer of the Year, Lori Doucette, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="574">RESOLUTION NO. 574</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Richmond County Literacy Network Volunteer of the Year, Lynn Wambolt, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="575">RESOLUTION NO. 575</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking River Bourgeois Community Services Society Volunteer of the Year, Marie Fougere, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="576">RESOLUTION NO. 576</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Point Tupper Heritage Association Volunteer of the Year, Marie Langley, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="577">RESOLUTION NO. 577</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. Hyacinth Parish Council volunteer of the year, James Bowen, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="578">RESOLUTION NO. 578</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. Hyacinth Parish Council Volunteer of the Year, Joan Bowen, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="579">RESOLUTION NO. 579</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. Hyacinth Parish CWL Volunteer of the Year, Kathleen MacDonald, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="580">RESOLUTION NO. 580</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Riverdale Seniors Club 55 Volunteer of the Year, Margaret Johnson, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="581">RESOLUTION NO. 581</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Development Isle Madame Association Volunteer of the Year, Robert Samson, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="582">RESOLUTION NO. 582</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councilors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. John's Anglican Church Volunteer of the Year, Warren Mauger, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="583">RESOLUTION NO. 583</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Roddie's Square Dancing Society Volunteer of the Year, Al Martin, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="584">RESOLUTION NO. 584</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. John the Baptist CWL Volunteer of the Year, Alma Burke, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="585">RESOLUTION NO. 585</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. Anne Community and Nursing Care Centre Ladies Auxillary Volunteer of the Year, Brenda Boudreau, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="586">RESOLUTION NO. 586</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Royal Canadian Legion Branch 110 Volunteer of the Year, Carol Sampson, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="587">RESOLUTION NO. 587</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. Anne Community and Nursing Care Centre Volunteer of the Year, Cornelia Perry, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="588">RESOLUTION NO. 588</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Rocky Bay Irish Club Volunteer of the Year, Dee Keating, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="589">RESOLUTION NO. 589</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. Francis De Sales CWL Volunteer of the Year, Delima Scanlan, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="590">RESOLUTION NO. 590</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Royal Canadian Branch 150 Ladies Auxiliary Volunteer of the Year, Diane Samson, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="591">RESOLUTION NO. 591</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Royal Canadian Legion Branch 150 Volunteer of the Year, Donald Goyetche, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="592">RESOLUTION NO. 592</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 Ladies Auxiliary Volunteer of the Year, Donna Mackie, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="593">RESOLUTION NO. 593</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. Andrews Presbyterian Church Volunteer of the Year, Douglas Morrison, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="594">RESOLUTION NO. 594</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Royal Canadian Legion Branch 47 Volunteer of the Year, George MacPhee, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="595">RESOLUTION NO. 595</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking South Mountain Arm of Gold Association Volunteer of the Year, Jack Armitage, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="596">RESOLUTION NO. 596</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Strait Richmond Healthy Care Foundation Volunteer of the Year, Patricia Burns, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="597">RESOLUTION NO. 597</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. Peter's Lions Marina Volunteer of the Year, Ray Jeffrey, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="598">RESOLUTION NO. 598</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Village of St. Peter's Volunteer of the Year, Robert Wambolt, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="599">RESOLUTION NO. 599</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. Peter's Scottish Country Dance Group Volunteer of the Year, Rosemary MacLean, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="600">RESOLUTION NO. 600</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking West Bay United Church Volunteer of the Year, Ross Leonard, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="601">RESOLUTION NO. 601</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. Joseph's CWL Volunteer of the Year, Shirley George, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="602">RESOLUTION NO. 602</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Strait Richmond Palliative Care Volunteer of the Year, Theresa Boudreau, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="603">RESOLUTION NO. 603</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Stirling, Framboise, Fourchu Seniors Volunteer of the Year, Vange Wareham, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="604">RESOLUTION NO. 604</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. Louis Parish Volunteer of the Year, Warren Sampson, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="605">RESOLUTION NO. 605</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. Peter's and District Volunteer Fire Department Volunteer of the Year, Wayne Skinner, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="606">RESOLUTION NO. 606</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking West Bay Pastoral Charge Volunteer of the Year, Wesley Peeples, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="607">RESOLUTION NO. 607</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. Peter's and District Volunteer Fire Department Ladies Auxiliary Volunteer of the Year, Allison Martell, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="608">RESOLUTION NO. 608</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking West Arichat and District Village Circle Society Volunteer of the Year, Brian Rose, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="609">RESOLUTION NO. 609</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking the Strait Richmond Seniors Advisory Volunteer of the Year, Chuck Davenport, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="610">RESOLUTION NO. 610</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking the Strait Richmond Seniors Advisory Volunteer of the Year, Edith Burton, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="611">RESOLUTION NO. 611</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Zachery Hall Memorial Society Volunteer of the Year, Evelyn Boudreau, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="612">RESOLUTION NO. 612</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Village on the Canal Association Volunteer of the Year, Evelyn O'Leary, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="613">RESOLUTION NO. 613</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. Peter's/Sampsonville &amp; Area Water Utility Volunteer of the Year, Georgette Burke, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="614">RESOLUTION NO. 614</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. Louis CWL Volunteer of the Year, Irene Sampson, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="615">RESOLUTION NO. 615</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Telile Community TV Volunteer of the Year, Jackie Hopkins, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="616">RESOLUTION NO. 616</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. Louis Community Service Volunteer of the Year, Joan Samson, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="617">RESOLUTION NO. 617</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking West Richmond Education Centre Volunteer of the Year, Laurie MacNeil, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="618">RESOLUTION NO. 618</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. Peter's Lions Club Volunteer of the Year, Lawrence Digout, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="619">RESOLUTION NO. 619</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Strait Richmond Minor Hockey Volunteer of the Year, Lian Sampson, for his hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="620">RESOLUTION NO. 620</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking St. Joseph's Services Petit de Grat Volunteer of the Year, Lucille Samson, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="621">RESOLUTION NO. 621</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking West Bay Community Association Volunteer of the Year, Marguerite Leonard, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="622">RESOLUTION NO. 622</num><from>Hon. Michel Samson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our county; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Friday, April 20, 2012, I joined municipal councillors and staff at a supper to recognize the 140 volunteers from throughout Richmond County;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly join me in thanking Terry Fox Foundation Volunteer of the Year, Meghan Madden, for her hard work and commitment.</p></speech>
      </noticesOfMotion>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
