<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="482af266-32b5-4e7b-b041-5825dfcaa07f" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.ross.landry" showAs="HON. ROSS LANDRY"/>
        <TLCPerson id="90d8e39b-06a0-43d3-8ec8-8e2a42d902cd" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.stephen.mcneil" showAs="MR. MCNEIL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8588925f-80f9-4646-9a9b-b69640e9148a" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.brian.skabar" showAs="MR. BRIAN SKABAR"/>
        <TLCPerson id="ff6e42ca-5ef8-4ebd-a08f-3edab6a6ec5d" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.frank.corbett" showAs="HON. FRANK CORBETT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="14ec3253-c3e6-4d10-8c3d-6370348053b8" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.darrell.dexter" showAs="HON. DARRELL DEXTER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="939f3659-7945-4fc2-9903-f54f81c4501a" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.gary.burrill" showAs="MR. GARY BURRILL"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MR. SPEAKER"/>
        <TLCRole id="#member" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.#member" showAs="AN HON. MEMBER"/>
        <TLCRole id="clerk" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.clerk" showAs="THE CLERK"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 29 March 2012</docTitle>
      <docNumber>12-01</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2012-03-29">Thursday, March 29, 2012</docDate>
      <docProponent>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docProponent>
      <legislature value="61">61st General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="4">4th Session</session>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Please be seated.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Justice.</p></speech>
      <speech by="#482af266-32b5-4e7b-b041-5825dfcaa07f">
        <from>HON. ROSS LANDRY</from>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, I beg leave to introduce a bill entitled An Act Respecting Oaths of Office.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Ordered the bill be read a second time on a future day.</p>
<p>Her Honour the Lieutenant Governor has been pleased to make a Speech to the members met in General Assembly of which, for greater accuracy, I have obtained a copy which the Chief Clerk will now read. (Interruptions)</p>
<p>SOME HON. MEMBERS: Hear! Hear! (Applause)</p></speech>
      <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined">
        <from>THE CLERK</from>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, members of the Legislature, ladies and gentlemen, Nova Scotians &#x2026;</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="#14ec3253-c3e6-4d10-8c3d-6370348053b8">
        <from>HON. DARRELL DEXTER</from>
        <p>Regretfully, Mr. Speaker, I move that the Speech be taken as read. (Laughter)</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the Throne Speech be taken as read. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cumberland North.</p></speech>
      <speech by="#8588925f-80f9-4646-9a9b-b69640e9148a"><from>MR. BRIAN SKABAR</from><p>Mr. Speaker, it's an honour to be here today to rise in this Fourth Session of the Sixty-first General Assembly of the Nova Scotia Legislature, to move the Address in Reply to the Speech from the Throne as read by Her Honour the Lieutenant Governor Mayann Francis.</p>
<p>I would like to begin my response by thanking Her Honour for her words and for the excellent job she has done representing Her Majesty the Queen across Nova Scotia. The Lieutenant Governor has worked with great dedication throughout our province and touched the lives of many with her presence at important events. I know that this will be the last Throne Speech for Her Honour and I wanted to take this opportunity to thank her for her work over the last several years. Her poise and dignity are a credit to all Nova Scotians and I thank her for that. (Applause)</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I'd like to make a number of remarks but before I would begin, I'd like to acknowledge a couple of people in the gallery and some people who I know are watching at home. Mr. Earl Dow and Mr. Andrew Melanson, two friends and colleagues, supporters of mine from very early on, I'd like to acknowledge and thank for being who you are, guys.</p>
<p>Past that, I'd like to acknowledge my four children - five children (Laughter): my son Thomas, a university student pursuing his Education Degree at Crandall University; my daughter Margaret, first year in university at St. Francis Xavier; my daughter Lauren, in Grade 9 at Amherst Regional High School; my daughter Lindsay, in Winnipeg at this moment; and my daughter Jennifer, in Calgary. (Applause) I can explain that later. (Laughter)</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, the Speech from the Throne builds on the theme that we've presented to Nova Scotians since we formed the government in 2009. Our priorities have been clear and focused. We are committed to getting the financial affairs back to balance and building a future in which Nova Scotia will live within its means. We are working to create better health care now and care that is available when it is needed. We have dedicated ourselves to creating good jobs and growing the economy.</p>
<p>Our government has spent the last two and a half years working to establish a stable financial foundation on which to build our future and our children's future. One of our key building blocks has been getting our province's finances in order. For example, this government reduced the provincial debt during our first full year in office. As we learned from the Finance Minister last week, this will be the third year in a row that department spending will come in below estimates. (Applause)</p>
<p>This government is doing the heavy lifting now to get our province back to balance. Of course, Mr. Speaker, the purpose of a sound financial plan is to create a strong, stable foundation that will help provide improved programming and services that make life better for all Nova Scotians, services like health care, education and infrastructure. We know that Nova Scotians value their health care and recognize the importance of accessible and reliable health care, so we have been taking action to make sure the system in place works better. Families want to know that health care will be available to them when and where they need it.</p>
<p>Our government has a plan for health care. Better Care Sooner ensures that when people need care, it is available to them. Nova Scotia's and Canada's first ever Collaborative Emergency Centre was opened in Cumberland County, in Parrsboro. This CEC has been running since the summer and has treated many, many patients since. In my own constituency, Cumberland North, a CEC is in the works in Pugwash. This centre, which will be housed in the brand new North Cumberland Memorial Hospital building, will ensure that emergency care is there for the residents of Pugwash and area when and where they need it. Across the province, five CECs have been announced and more will be announced this year in communities that have faced chronic ER closures.</p>
<p>Better Care Sooner is about providing a multi-disciplinary approach to health care. As part of that approach, our government has extended the role of paramedics and increased the number of nurse practitioners around the province, including Cumberland North, where a new position has been established recently in Pugwash. This approach to health care is ensuring that more and more Nova Scotians can be assured that the resources they need are there when and where they need them.</p>
<p>The Speech from the Throne today highlighted some of the major goals and accomplishments of our government. These include the province's jobsHere plan to create good jobs and grow the economy; our education plan, Kids and Learning First; and the consistent and dedicated effort to make life better for all Nova Scotians. For the people in Cumberland North, these initiatives have played out in many different ways.</p>
<p>Our jobsHere plan has seen innovative and exciting companies in Cumberland North get the support they need to flourish. Our government's investments in LED Roadway Lighting have not only helped this company expand but have helped our province become greener while utilizing local resources and workers. (Applause) I miss few opportunities, public or private, to reinforce that the Province of Nova Scotia was stated as one of the five best initiatives by the David Suzuki Foundation for its efforts in reducing greenhouse gases and effect.</p>
<p>Investments in IMP Aerospace Components and PolyCello are helping these companies expand, train their workers, buy equipment, and continue to play a positive role in the community. More productive, new equipment at PolyCello will improve productivity by 50 per cent and will make them second to nobody on the continent for producing their product.</p>
<p>In education infrastructure, the Premier announced last year a replacement for the school of West Highlands Elementary. Investing in new schools is the right decision for families in the Amherst area because it will provide students with a modern learning centre. Our government committed to building this school in the 2009 election, and last year's announcement is a great example of the follow-through in this government and our commitment to students and families.</p>
<p>Response to stakeholders in the area is another issue. There was an issue with the proposed school location in Amherst, and after concerns from parents in the West Highlands area - and particularly of Councillor Terry Rhindress - we were able to revisit, or perhaps restart, the whole selection process for the West Highlands school. This is something that, frankly, I'm very proud that we were able to have done. A decision had been made, and it turned out to be the wrong decision for many of the stakeholders who had less input than they would have liked, and we got a chance to revisit it.</p>
<p>Just on the theme of education for a moment, I'd like to take an opportunity to acknowledge and thank the Grade 3 class at Spring Street Academy and their teacher, Ms. Cheryl Davis, for sharing their day with me at Take Your MLA to School Day. Thank you, guys. I hope you invite me back, and "Bark, bark, bark." (Interruptions) Those kids will know what I mean.</p>
<p>Last year, I had the pleasure to announce a $500,000 government investment in a study to assess the design and replacement for the LaPlanche River Aboiteau. Anyone from Cumberland County knows that marshlands and the aboiteaus and dykes that support them are an important part of the infrastructure and landscape in Nova Scotia. This investment is an important step in protecting Nova Scotia's valuable shoreline and agricultural resources. The engineering study will help ensure that any future aboiteau is built to last.</p>
<p>As encapsulated in the Speech from the Throne, a key goal for this government is to help make life easier for Nova Scotians. Across the province, Nova Scotians are benefiting from 1,500 new child care subsidies, from the cap on student debt, and from the Affordable Living Tax Credit. Our government removed the requirement for seniors to pay income tax on the Guaranteed Income Supplement. This meant that approximately $9 million was returned to seniors, putting more money back in the hands of Nova Scotians who need it most.</p>
<p>We took the provincial portion of the HST off essentials such as home heating and energy, children's clothing and footwear, feminine hygiene products - and each of these initiatives on the part of our government helped to make life better for families, seniors, and individuals across our province.</p>
<p>Inherent strengths like the volunteers and the generous spirit of Nova Scotians is clear to all of us in 2012. The Amherst Relay for Life raised $183,000 in 2011, $154,000 in 2010, and $163,000 in 2009 - that's $500,000 in three years raised by the generosity of people in Amherst and area in the battle against cancer. (Applause) My most sincere congratulations and thanks to all who took part.</p>
<p>For my own part, I'll try to contribute to this in 2012. I'm going to take a walk from Pugwash to Amherst, approximately 51 kilometres, on Relay for Life day, on Friday, June 1<sup>st</sup>, and I do this to raise awareness for the cause - there are few of us in this room who have not been touched by cancer. I invite all of you to join me on this, maybe not for the whole thing but for a portion. Everyone in Amherst has an open invitation and perhaps will try to raise a couple of dollars for this as well. We'll be leaving at 7:00 a.m. from the Pugwash Village Commission Office and hope to get to Amherst by 7:00 p.m. for the opening statements for the Relay for Life on June 1<sup>st</sup>. Everyone please mark that on your calendar.</p>
<p>Speaking of Pugwash, Pugwash is famous for peace - I might also add famous for volunteerism. It's constantly able to draw on immense support for any event that comes through and it draws attention to the North Shore of Nova Scotia. This year the tall ships will be visiting Pugwash - they will be in Pugwash Harbour from July 27<sup>th</sup> to July 29<sup>th</sup>. The event this year is chaired by Claude Hudson, with at least two able associates that come to mind immediately, Dennis Brown and Bill Kempt.</p>
<p>The last time the tall ships came to Pugwash 10,000 people passed through the gates of the Pugwash Marina to see the tall ships. It's amazing. The Gathering of the Clans is always a big day in Pugwash as well, July 2<sup>nd</sup>. The Gathering of the Clans features Highland Games, dragon boat races - all volunteer driven - and this event was initially started as a fundraiser for the Pugwash Hospital. That was in 1961, and I believe it's time for a new one. Of all my announcements to date, none was more rewarding than the announcement of a new primary health care facility in Pugwash. (Applause) So this is an example of strengthening the health infrastructure in rural Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>The community college presence in Amherst wasn't far behind.</p>
<p>Sticking with the theme of infrastructure, roads and bridges are being built - we'll soon be able to drive to Malagash and visit the Jost Winery and actually enjoy the ride, not just the scenery. By initiating our own chip seal operation, this government can reduce the cost of chip seal from $91,000 per kilometre to $40,000 per kilometre. This will help us get to more rural roads faster. (Applause) The five-year road plan is our map to get there, and available to all.</p>
<p>Sticking with the theme of transportation and infrastructure, there was an issue with the Northport Bridge, but now it's built - and I would like to mention that I will be presenting a petition to this Legislature, with over 400 names on it, requesting that it be named the Larry Brander Bridge. A joint letter of support by myself and Cumberland County Warden Keith Hunter will be accompanying this petition. This letter will be forwarded to the Minister of TIR to this end. Keith, I'm sorry to say this in front of your friends across the hall but there are a couple of things we actually do agree on.</p>
<p>Pugwash - famous for peace and home of the first-ever peace conference, a peace conference dealing with nuclear armaments; underwritten by Cyrus Eaton, a son of Pugwash. I'm aware of at least one other person who attended that event. My friend, Paolo Brenciaglia, was 15 years old at the time and he was actually a gofer for the scientists who took part in that first event. So we do have the history of world peace right there in Pugwash.</p>
<p>Pugwash is also home to the Nobel Peace Prize awarded to Dr. Joseph Rotblat for his efforts in world peace and another Nobel Prize is right there, 22 kilometres away, in Wallace, Nova Scotia, where Dr. Boyle, a son of Wallace, was awarded the Nobel Prize in Physics. The Wallace men's service club has been diligently pursuing formal recognition by way of a monument to Dr. Boyle in Wallace. They will succeed. The Wallace Museum, another jewel of the North Shore, will house exhibits of Dr. Boyle's accomplishments.</p>
<p>In the arts and culture, transportation and infrastructure, in immigration, in so many avenues, our NDP Government has come to Nova Scotia with a plan, a plan to make life better. We've approached each new endeavour with fresh eyes and come up with strategies to help propel Nova Scotia and Nova Scotians forward while building on the inherent strength of our people and our communities.</p>
<p>I strongly believe, Mr. Speaker, that it is this commitment to methodical, logical, planned progress that will ensure Nova Scotia embraces new opportunities, like the Irving Shipbuilding contract, and continue to build on a province that our children and our grandchildren can call home. With confidence in the future, I move the Speech from the Throne as presented by Her Honour, the Honourable Mayann Francis, be accepted as read. (Standing Ovation)</p></speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>The honourable member for Colchester-Musquodoboit Valley.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="#939f3659-7945-4fc2-9903-f54f81c4501a"><from>MR. GARY BURRILL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I am pleased to rise in the place of the people of Colchester-Musquodoboit Valley to second the Speech from the Throne. As members will be aware, there are two different approaches to this matter of seconding a motion. There is the approach, first, we would call the pro forma approach. That's when you're at a meeting and perhaps the chair is trying to get a motion onto the floor; things might not be going too excitedly and he'll say, will somebody please second that motion? You kind of raise your hand as though to say, well yes, but it's not with any great excitement or conviction - second. But there's a second way of seconding. The second way of seconding is when you hear something that you have a definite sense of deep agreement with and you want, right off the bat, to express your personal alignment with that view, so you say, I second that. (Applause)</p>
<p>So it is this second kind of seconding, if I can call it that, that I wanted to bring to the Speech from the Throne this afternoon and I would like to do that, briefly, by drawing attention, just for a couple of moments, to a matter or two raised in the Speech from the Throne which has particular resonance for the communities I serve, beginning with the subject of forestry.</p>
<p>The paragraphs in the Speech from the Throne on this important subject speak of several different facets of forestry. They speak about the maximizing of value, they speak about innovation, and they speak about markets. All of these, of course, our government recognizes as important, but as we look now toward year two of the Natural Resources Strategy, one dimension of forestry which is brought forward in the speech, which speaks with particular resonance to us in this moment, is the matter of sustainability.</p>
<p>The community I live in, Upper Musquodoboit, is a community that probably is as defined by the woods economy as any community in the province. I came there 22 years ago to serve as the community's minister, knowing nothing whatsoever about this subject which was so pivotal to the community I had come to serve - a fact which was brought helpfully home to me one evening by one of my children, who said, you know, Dad, you're the only man in Upper who can't run a chainsaw. (Laughter)</p>
<p>So in an effort to improve my usefulness to the people there, over a lot of years I asked a lot of forestry-related questions and listened to the answers. I asked questions of people at the old MacAulay sawmill in the upper end of the Musquodoboit Valley, and people who work on what is called "the wheel" in the Taylor Lumber mill in Middle Musquodoboit. I also asked questions of those people who now operate that incredibly technically-sophisticated computerized equipment that is required in order to operate a contemporary sawmill. I asked questions of people who years ago had yarded in the woods with horses, and also of contractors and operators now with this equipment that costs pretty near $0.5 million a unit, the harvesters and the processors and the feller bunchers.</p>
<p>Listening to the answers to these questions over a great many years, there is one unequivocal conclusion I came to, which is that everybody knowledgeable about the woods is of one mind about one thing: that the rate at which the forests were being harvested could not be kept up for very long. This is true for everybody, with the sole exception of those who were, in fact, being paid to say otherwise.</p>
<p>I hear the Lieutenant Governor speak about the government being committed to sustaining Nova Scotia's forests for the benefit of future generations and, in the second way of seconding, I want to say I second that. I would also like to do the second kind of seconding to the speech's words on the subject of, as the Lieutenant Governor has read it, reducing the burden for those most in need.</p>
<p>Economist after economist after economist in these years since the great recession began in 2008 have pointed out for us the connection between the rise of serious income inadequacy amongst literally the 99 per cent and the fact that the wealthiest 1 per cent of income-earners in Canada have seen their incomes more or less double over the last two and a half decades. By means of such provisions as increasing provincial income taxation for those who earn more than $150,000 a year and eliminating altogether provincial income taxation for seniors receiving the supplement, the government is addressing what the Speech from the Throne calls putting more money back into the hands of low-income Nova Scotians, and I second that.</p>
<p>Lastly, I second the concluding policy reference in the speech, what the Lieutenant Governor refers to as anticipated regulatory improvements for firefighters throughout Nova Scotia. Nothing expresses the ethics of community which define the best of Nova Scotia any more clearly than the volunteer fire brigades at the heart of communities across the province. One author about firefighting, named Norman Maclean, says that if you want to understand firefighting the main thing you need to understand is pride - pride of service, pride of purpose, pride of community. This kind of pride calls out for a response, as is recognized in the words of the speech, that the government will bring Nova Scotia's benefits for firefighters back in line with our neighbours across Canada, and with the second kind of seconding, I second that.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby second the motion that the Speech from the Throne be accepted as read, thank you. (Standing Ovation)</p></speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition. (Applause)</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="#90d8e39b-06a0-43d3-8ec8-8e2a42d902cd"><from>HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL</from><p>Thank you Mr. Speaker. I'll try to somehow top that enthusiasm coming from the member from Colchester-Musquodoboit Valley.</p>
<p>I'm pleased to rise to say a few remarks today. I'll finish my formal remarks tomorrow but I do want to recognize and highlight the Lieutenant Governor, not only for her work here in this legislature but for the way she has made us all proud as she has represented the Queen across this province. Each Lieutenant Governor has made their own mark in that role.</p>
<p>One of the things that I'm reminded of when I think of our Lieutenant Governor today was when she was in my riding of Annapolis Royal. She had an opportunity to come and help celebrate some of the traditions and as she was there she had some time and she was walking around our community. As she was walking around, she noticed some families with young children were working and developing a park. They were developing a roller skate park just outside of the Town of Annapolis Royal. Her Honour stopped by and chatted with those young people and the young people asked her to return for the official opening. In the way she has done in so many places across Nova Scotians in support of young people, she responded in the affirmative, and to their surprise, upon the competition they called and she arrived back in our community and helped those young people officially open that skate park.</p>
<p>The pride that they had in that project that they presented with their family was only heightened by the fact that Her Honour had taken the time to come and join them. That speaks to Her Honour and the commitments she has made to the people of Nova Scotia. (Applause) Not to mention, Mr. Speaker, she comes from Whitney Pier and I'm sure that really has a special place.</p>
<p>I want to recognize members of our community who have come here today to participate in the opening of this session of the House. I want to thank them for their commitment to our province, to our country, to the work that you do unselfishly on behalf of all of us. We in this House are grateful to you and all Nova Scotians are grateful to the effort that you - you are the people who build our communities, the very reason why we try to get elected to come into this House so that we can help you improve our communities. (Applause)</p>
<p>I want to thank the member for Cumberland North for his remarks. I also want to acknowledge his children who are here today. (Interruption) I want to congratulate and thank all of them. But I want to recognize them because many of us who run for this office have children and make a great sacrifice, and our families make a great sacrifice, so that we have the privilege to be here and sit in this House and work on behalf of our collective communities. So I want to acknowledge them, on behalf of all of our families and all of our children, for their commitment that they've made to their father and to their community. (Applause)</p>
<p>What can I say about the seconder of the Speech from the Throne? I'm a Catholic boy who goes to church in St. Alphonsus in Bridgetown but I think I might end up going to your service from now on. I was expecting the collection plate to be coming around here at anytime. (Laughter)</p></speech>
      <speech by="" as="##member" status="undefined">
        <from>AN HON. MEMBER</from>
        <p>Perhaps we can do that next week. (Applause)</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="#90d8e39b-06a0-43d3-8ec8-8e2a42d902cd"><from>MR. MCNEIL</from><p>That's it for sure, Mr. Speaker, don't recognize him again if he decides to get up. (Laughter)</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, like many Speeches from the Throne there are things in this that we can agree with. There are things in this Speech from the Throne that we can agree with. I think all Nova Scotians are proud and willing to support Irving and their commitment to make sure that they deliver on that contract for our national government, making sure that the Navy ships that are built here will be built on time and that we as a community will benefit from that contract in a large way.</p>
<p>We can agree - maybe not all of us, but most of us - that the Lower Churchill Falls is an important project that I believe will allow us to move towards a more renewable, sustainable energy market in Atlantic Canada. For those who are confused about the fact that it potentially may cost Nova Scotians too much, the inaction on energy will cost Nova Scotians much more. (Applause) I believe the best part of that contract, of that project will be the transmission lines that will connect Nova Scotia not only to Newfoundland and Labrador, but will enhance our transmission capacity with the rest of Canada. It will give us an opportunity to buy cheap energy in Quebec and other places; it will give us an opportunity to open up the energy market in Nova Scotia to allow us to grow a renewable energy sector; and it's my hope it will allow us to finally break the monopoly of Nova Scotia Power and allow competition to happen inside the province. (Applause)</p>
<p>We also can agree with and will work with government to support our firefighters across Nova Scotia. All of us know the sacrifices they make, that their families make, coming to us, coming to the members of our communities at our most vulnerable time and helping us try to save our property or even save the lives of our loved ones. Anything we can do to support the men and women who are volunteering in our firefighting departments across this province is a good thing and our caucus will fully support it.</p>
<p>But it probably won't come as a surprise to you, Mr. Speaker, that there are things in this document that we don't agree with, and no matter how many times you repeat something it doesn't make it true. A year ago I stood and said I wanted to speak to the piece of fiction created by the Premier. No matter how many times you read a piece of fiction, it's still a piece of fiction.</p>
<p>I want to talk about a couple of things that the government has highlighted that made life better for families in Nova Scotia. They talked about changes, to bringing Nova Scotia Better Care Sooner - closing emergency rooms across this province is not providing better health care sooner. Many wait times across this province are well above the national average - that is not providing better health care sooner. (Applause)</p>
<p>Not too long ago we laid off 22 mental health youth support workers in Nova Scotia who were working with the most vulnerable youth in our province. We laid them off; we left those families adrift. We are not providing them with the support that they need, the lifeline, the bit of hope that they had when they needed support with an adolescent with mental health issues - that is not providing better health care sooner.</p>
<p>Changes to put kids and learning first - cuts to education is not putting education first, it's not putting our children first. (Applause) This is the first time in our history that a government is asking our children to pay for their mistakes. What's interesting through this whole document - not one mention of special needs. The very children in our public education system who are going to be hit the hardest are the cuts that have happened under this NDP Government. (Applause)</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, they talk about making life more affordable for Nova Scotians. Since June 9<sup>th</sup> energy prices have gone up 20 per cent, power rates. Gasoline prices have increased 37 cents a litre. How is that making life more affordable for Nova Scotians? Since they've taken power they increased the HST by 2 per cent - that's $1 million a day out of the pockets of Nova Scotians and out of the economy of Nova Scotia. A million dollars a day - how is that making life more affordable for Nova Scotians?</p>
<p>They talk about creating good jobs. There are fewer full-time jobs in the Province of Nova Scotia now. The Premier's right, employment is up - in part-time work. But I'm not sure that many Nova Scotians feel secure with a part-time job. I'm not sure many Nova Scotians feel the same optimism that the Premier does when they know their job could be gone tomorrow.</p>
<p>I was surprised - I almost said I was shocked and appalled but I didn't want to say that in the House today- but I was surprised with the reference of Michelin. It was about six months ago when the largest private sector employers in this province came here with a moderate request from government, it was Bill No. 102, first contract arbitration. Mr. Speaker, I'm sure you remember the debate and Michelin was one of them. We, in this House, said to the Premier, Michelin sent you a warning that first contract arbitration would affect future investment in Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>The Premier said it wasn't the case. Well the President, Dana LeBlanc, said something very different outside of this House - he said it would affect future investment. No, it wouldn't mean they would close tomorrow but it would make it extremely difficult to attract investment into the Province of Nova Scotia under the labour legislation that was being proposed. Every one of those private sector employers said the same thing - it will affect our ability to grow. It will affect our ability to create good jobs in the Province of Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>This Premier and the NDP Government ignored their plight. So to somehow suggest and put their name in this document as a positive that they are going to bring and grow future investment, when they warned this government about the public policy positions they had, would have a negative impact on them.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, these are but a few examples. I know you are going to give me the privilege to stand again tomorrow as I further go through this document to highlight the real story that Nova Scotians hear.</p>
<p>I heard someone outside - there's a lot of sleight of hand inside of this document. Well, we'll expose it tomorrow morning. With those few remarks I adjourn debate. (Applause)</p></speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>The honourable Premier.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="#14ec3253-c3e6-4d10-8c3d-6370348053b8">
        <from>HON. DARRELL DEXTER</from>
        <p>Thank you, Mr. Speaker. At the conclusion of the session this afternoon, on your behalf and on mine, sir, I would like to invite all members of the House and all guests in the gallery to the Red Chamber for a reception. I would like to point out that this is a very special occasion as we will be paying our respects to Her Honour, the Lieutenant Governor, as she finishes her vice-regal term.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="#ff6e42ca-5ef8-4ebd-a08f-3edab6a6ec5d">
        <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
        <p>Thank you, Mr. Speaker. That concludes the government's business for the day. I move that the House do now rise to meet again on the morrow at the hour of 9:00 a.m. The House will sit until 12:00 noon or until the conclusion of business. I move the House do now rise.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is to adjourn.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
      <narrative>
        <p>The House rose at 4:03 p.m.</p>
      </narrative>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
