<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="8d3f2e85-b724-4554-980d-02c64fb4603a" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.clarrie.mackinnon" showAs="MR. CLARRIE MACKINNON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.jim.boudreau" showAs="Mr. Jim Boudreau"/>
        <TLCPerson id="5db3f08e-219e-4ab3-a082-7bcc7ed081b1" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.frank.corbett" showAs="HON. FRANK CORBETT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="3663e5bf-7f5e-4b7d-a021-669a4f8ab4bc" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.maureen.macdonald" showAs="HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="54c01d3a-9d00-4849-8acd-59f8efd8a2f9" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.christopher.a.dentremont" showAs="HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="ea522cb5-76c2-4f6d-920c-5b1835704b1a" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.leo.glavine" showAs="MR. GLAVINE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="5c567fec-a071-45dc-bccd-c81ad2bb492a" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.ramona.jennex" showAs="HON. RAMONA JENNEX"/>
        <TLCPerson id="c3649928-ebf2-462c-bc99-d3e36c4653ef" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.lenore.zann" showAs="MS. LENORE ZANN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="cfb3bc32-2d05-41ad-a115-6bddf2118033" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.keith.colwell" showAs="HON. KEITH COLWELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="d71ee75b-be72-47ba-8de2-ba81296d67ec" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.brian.skabar" showAs="MR. BRIAN SKABAR"/>
        <TLCPerson id="a841369d-b3a6-4df9-af76-53c4f9eab8cf" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.pam.birdsall" showAs="MS. PAM BIRDSALL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="58b01541-6697-4dbd-830c-6cec0d4c4825" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.diana.whalen" showAs="MS. DIANA WHALEN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="23484f25-d8f5-4e64-8e5f-4bd7e91f5410" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.ross.landry" showAs="HON. ROSS LANDRY"/>
        <TLCPerson id="53fc39ac-a3be-4439-b810-cf2a8cd8b016" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.michel.p.samson" showAs="HON. MICHEL SAMSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="dfa6c79b-dda1-4b1a-9850-3edfb6f1b3aa" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.kelly.regan" showAs="MS. KELLY REGAN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="e4bb1b3c-5932-453f-a1d7-d5db05f5871e" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.darrell.dexter" showAs="HON. DARRELL DEXTER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="310e08cc-3724-403f-821e-1a1076a68e6c" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.chuck.porter" showAs="Mr. Chuck Porter"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MR. SPEAKER"/>
        <TLCRole id="chairman" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.chairman" showAs="MR. CHAIRMAN"/>
        <TLCRole id="clerk" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.clerk" showAs="THE CLERK"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 4 May 2012</docTitle>
      <docNumber>12-25</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2012-05-04">Friday, May 4, 2012</docDate>
      <docProponent>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docProponent>
      <legislature value="61">61st General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="4">4th Session</session>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>Order, please. We will begin the daily routine.</p>
      </speech>
      <papers>
        <heading>PRESENTING REPORTS OF COMMITTEES</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Justice.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#23484f25-d8f5-4e64-8e5f-4bd7e91f5410"><from>HON. ROSS LANDRY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, as Chairman of the Committee on Law Amendments, I am directed to report that the committee has met and considered the following bills:</p>
<p><b>Bill No. 5 - Municipal Government Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 13 - Education Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 34 - Matrimonial Statutes Repeal Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 37 - Interjurisdictional Support Orders Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 39 - Maintenance and Custody Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 41 - Grandparents' Rights Affirmation Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 59 - Fish Harvesters Registration and Certification Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 61 - Fisheries and Coastal Resources Act.</b></p>
<p>and the committee recommends these bills to the favourable consideration of the House, each without amendment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>Ordered that these bills be referred to the Committee of the Whole House on Bills.</p>
        </speech>
      </papers>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Education.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#5c567fec-a071-45dc-bccd-c81ad2bb492a"><num title="829">RESOLUTION NO. 829</num><from>HON. RAMONA JENNEX</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Aaron Stevens, of Dartmouth, and Paige Zwicker, of Fletchers Lake, are active high school students who work to make life better for their peers and others in their communities; and</p>
<p>Whereas Paige started a Leadership Mentor Program for students who are disadvantaged in their community and co-founded a Free the Children group at Lockview High School, while Aaron serves as co-premier of the Nova Scotia Secondary Schools Association and has worked with the Youth Project to connect Gay/Straight Alliances across Nova Scotia; and</p>
<p>Whereas Aaron and Paige are two of 20 students across Canada who will receive a 2012 TD Scholarship for Community Leadership, which is awarded to students who demonstrate innovation and initiative while making a difference in their community, and is valued up to $70,000;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the Legislature join me in congratulating Aaron Stevens, of Dartmouth, and Paige Zwicker, of Fletchers Lake, for being very deserving recipients of the 2012 TD Scholarship for Community Leadership, and wish them well in their future studies.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Deputy Premier.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#5db3f08e-219e-4ab3-a082-7bcc7ed081b1"><num title="830">RESOLUTION NO. 830</num><from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, on behalf of the Premier, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Irving Shipbuilding has been named the top aerospace defence company in the nation by Canadian Defence Review magazine; and</p>
<p>Whereas the company was lauded for its commitment and sticking to its plan to become Canada's shipbuilder of $25 billion in combat ship contracts; and</p>
<p>Whereas these contracts will create thousands of jobs for Nova Scotians and billions of dollars in economic spinoffs over the next 30 years - money that can be reinvested in important public services like health and education;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this Legislature congratulate Irving Shipbuilding and the workers of the Halifax Shipyard on this latest honour, and for their commitment to the building of the best ships in the world.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>INTRODUCTION OF BILLS</heading>
        <other>
          <p>
            <b> Bill No. 78 - Entitled an Act Respecting the Administration of Justice. (Hon. Ross Landry)</b>
          </p>
        </other>
        <other>
          <p>
            <b> Bill No. 79 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 1 of the Acts of 1995-96. The Education Act. (Hon. Ramona Jennex)</b>
          </p>
        </other>
        <other>
          <p>
            <b>Bill No. 80 - Entitled an Act to Establish the Office of the Child and Youth Advocate. (Mr. Zach Churchill)</b>
          </p>
        </other>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>Ordered that these bills be read a second time on a future day.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Preston.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#cfb3bc32-2d05-41ad-a115-6bddf2118033"><num title="831">RESOLUTION NO. 831</num><from>HON. KEITH COLWELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Herman Pye was born in Ecum Secum and moved to Dartmouth with his parents as a small child; and</p>
<p>Whereas he was educated in Dartmouth and worked in the financial field until he was permanently hurt in an automobile accident; and</p>
<p>Whereas despite his disability he still manages to volunteer in the Lawrencetown Community Centre, helping with fundraising at various functions and assisting them in their activities whenever he can;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House recognize Herman Pye's contribution to his community and friends.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Premier.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#e4bb1b3c-5932-453f-a1d7-d5db05f5871e"><num title="832">RESOLUTION NO. 832</num><from>HON. DARRELL DEXTER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, on your behalf, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Sydney Kiwanis Squadron of the Royal Canadian Air Cadets will be holding their annual ceremonial review on May 19, 2012, and this year marks 70 years of continuous service to the industrial Cape Breton area; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Royal Canadian Air Cadets learned about aviation and air element by participating in a variety of hands-on activities, exciting challenges, and leadership opportunities; and</p>
<p>Whereas when a squadron celebrates such an important milestone it becomes clear to everyone the long-standing commitment of the staff, the program, and the cadets who are involved in the program;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly congratulate the Sydney Kiwanis Squadron of the Royal Canadian Air Cadets on their 70<sup>th</sup> year of continuous service.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without delay. (Laughter)</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Preston.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#cfb3bc32-2d05-41ad-a115-6bddf2118033"><num title="833">RESOLUTION NO. 833</num><from>HON. KEITH COLWELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Helen Sparks has lived in Lake Loon all her life, and where she and her husband raised their nine children, including a set of twins; and</p>
<p>Whereas she was one of the founding members of the Lake Loon Seniors' Community Club, and was secretary of the group for many years; and</p>
<p>Whereas she is a member of the Cherry Brook Baptist Church and was choir director of the senior choir for many years, as well as a member of the Women's Missionary Group and the Ladies' Auxiliary;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize Helen Sparks for her dedication and for the many contributions she has made to her family and to her community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Truro-Bible Hill.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#c3649928-ebf2-462c-bc99-d3e36c4653ef"><num title="834">RESOLUTION NO. 834</num><from>MS. LENORE ZANN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas today marks a very special day in the lives of the students at the Nova Scotia Agricultural College in Truro - today is the 107<sup>th</sup> graduation at the Nova Scotia Agricultural College; and</p>
<p>Whereas each year many students from all over Nova Scotia, from all over Canada, and from all over the world, come together to attend the internationally recognized Nova Scotia Agricultural College and participate in their world-class educational programs; and</p>
<p>Whereas the 2012 graduates will be the last graduating class of the Nova Scotia Agricultural College before it becomes a faulty of the esteemed Dalhousie University, the students having reached one of their major goals in life as they celebrate their graduation and are ready to take on the challenges that life brings their way;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this Nova Scotia Legislature congratulate the 2012 graduating class of the Nova Scotia Agricultural College on this very special day.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cumberland North.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#d71ee75b-be72-47ba-8de2-ba81296d67ec"><num title="835">RESOLUTION NO. 835</num><from>MR. BRIAN SKABAR</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the need for financial assistance for charitable organizations is an ever-present challenge; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Amherst Weston Bakeries employees raised $25,889.11 in a one-month period in December 2011, through the Children's Charity of Choice campaign and this amount was matched by George Weston Limited as part of the company-wide Wonder Cares campaign, bringing the grand total to $51,778.22, the highest amount raised in the 40 plants across Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas the 2011 Children's Charity of Choice for employees of the Amherst Weston Bakeries was the Cumberland Early Intervention program and this substantial donation will be a tremendous asset to promote recreational programs for children who have special physical and intellectual needs;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly join me in congratulating the employees of the Amherst Weston Bakeries in going above and beyond their Children's Charity of Choice campaign fundraiser of 2011, raising more money than any other Weston Bakery plant across Canada and donating $51,778.22 to the Cumberland Early Intervention Program.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Lunenburg.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#a841369d-b3a6-4df9-af76-53c4f9eab8cf"><num title="836">RESOLUTION NO. 836</num><from>MS. PAM BIRDSALL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Bill Lutwick of Indian Point, with assistance from Ross MacDonald and Andrew Forbes, began the process of restoring a centuries-old barn overlooking Lantz Cove in Oakland this past winter; and</p>
<p>Whereas the barn, thought to be originally constructed between 1758 and 1760, was originally used as a stagecoach stop where horses were freshened en route through the main road from Mahone Bay to Halifax; and</p>
<p>Whereas the restoration retained original materials wherever possible using hemlock, the same wood used in the original construction, maintaining the original feeling of the building;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly recognize the restoration efforts of Bill Lutwick, Ross MacDonald and Andrew Forbes in restoring the centuries-old barn in Oakland and preserving the local heritage of the area.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Bedford-Birch Cove.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#dfa6c79b-dda1-4b1a-9850-3edfb6f1b3aa"><num title="837">RESOLUTION NO. 837</num><from>MS. KELLY REGAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Radio and Television News Directors Association recently honoured CTV Atlantic News anchor Steve Murphy with its Lifetime Achievement Award; and</p>
<p>Whereas Steve began his broadcasting career in 1977 at CFBC Saint John, moving on to CJCH-AM in Halifax in May 1980 to work as a reporter/news reader and then host of the Hot Line call-in show; and</p>
<p>Whereas Steve then began commentaries on Live at 5 in 1982, moving to that show as co-host in 1986 and then to the ATV Evening News in 1993 and has written two books and is deeply involved in the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Steve Murphy on the Radio and Television News Directors Association Lifetime Achievement Award and wish him continued success.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Truro-Bible Hill.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#c3649928-ebf2-462c-bc99-d3e36c4653ef"><num title="838">RESOLUTION NO. 838</num><from>MS. LENORE ZANN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Elaine MacQuarrie, a resident of Bible Hill, has been volunteering in her community for over 30 years; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mrs. MacQuarrie, in her capacity as volunteer, has helped her community in a variety of ways including 27 years with St. David's United Church, visiting members at their homes and in hospital, serving on the UCW Hannah Unit, assisting with fundraising and making bonnets for babies baptized at the church, 30 years as an active member of the IOOF Rebekah Lodge, as well as assisting with local youth groups including Scouts, Cubs and Guides; and</p>
<p>Whereas the village of Bible Hill has honoured Elaine MacQuarrie for her volunteer work by naming her their volunteer of the year;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the Nova Scotia Legislature congratulate Elaine MacQuarrie for receiving the Village of Bible Hill Volunteer of the Year Award and thanks her for her outstand contributions to her community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#58b01541-6697-4dbd-830c-6cec0d4c4825"><num title="839">RESOLUTION NO. 839</num><from>MS. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a following day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Doreen Crick is a contributing member of the Rockingham Community, Rockingham United Church, the Nova Scotia Liberal Party and the Rockingham Grannies, part of the Stephen Lewis Foundation; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Nova Scotia Human Rights Commission presented awards at the International Human Rights Day at Park West School in Halifax with the theme celebrating 25 years of partnerships for Human Rights raising awareness through education in our communities; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Human Rights Commission presented an award to Doreen Crick for her work in organizing an anti-racism committee at Rockingham United Church, in hosting events to raise awareness about racial discrimination and in speaking at schools about humanitarian issues;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House congratulate Doreen Crick on her award and thank her for years of volunteer service to promote human rights and make life better for Nova Scotians and others around the world.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#5db3f08e-219e-4ab3-a082-7bcc7ed081b1">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, before I call the business of the day, with the indulgence of the House, may I make one short little statement. I realized today that one of our very hard working Pages will be leaving as of today. She's been a hard-working, longstanding friend to many in this House. She has the dubious distinction of being related to one of the members of this House, but I've got to say it's been thoroughly an enjoyable experience having that person around. I really wish, on behalf of the government and I'm sure of all Parties, to thank Colleen McNeil for all of her hard work that she did at serving this House as a Page with the respect and the dignity that she has. Thank you very much Colleen. (Standing Ovation)</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable House Leader of the Official Opposition.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#53fc39ac-a3be-4439-b810-cf2a8cd8b016"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Thank you, Mr. Speaker and I certainly want to thank the Government House Leader for his kind comments and certainly want to join in that and I'm sure on behalf of the member that she is related to, who is otherwise occupied at the moment, certainly we also want to extend our sincerest thanks to Colleen and all of the Pages who do such a wonderful job for us as members.</p>
<p>We certainly wish Colleen great success in the future and I'm quite confident that we'll be seeing much more of her, certainly on our side of the House, thank you.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable House Leader for the Progressive Conservative Party.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#54c01d3a-9d00-4849-8acd-59f8efd8a2f9">
          <from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from>
          <p>Thank you very much, Mr. Speaker. For our caucus as well, we want to throw our kind words into this as well to thank Colleen for all of the good work that she has done over the last few years. As we look at all the Pages that have gone on to continue to work, either in the galleries or right here on the floor of the Legislature, I wish her, of course, all the best and all the benefit of what she's learned over the last number of years here. So, Colleen, thank you so much on behalf of our caucus as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>I also, as the Speaker of the Legislature, have the final word and also would like to say thank you Colleen for all your years and all the best in whatever your future lies ahead; thank you.</p>
        </speech>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT BUSINESS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#5db3f08e-219e-4ab3-a082-7bcc7ed081b1"><from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, if she wants to return here as a member we've set the bar low. (Laughter)</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I move that you do now leave the Chair and the House resolve itself into a Committee of the Whole House on Bills.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>9:25 a.m. The House resolved itself into a CWH on Bills with Deputy Speaker Ms. Becky Kent in the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <narrative>
          <p>9:35 a.m. CWH on Bills rose and the House reconvened. Mr. Speaker, Hon. Gordon Gosse, resumed the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <speech by="" as="#chairman" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. CHAIRMAN</from>
          <p>The Chairman of the Committee of the Whole House on Bills reports:</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined"><from>THE CLERK</from><p>That the committee has met and considered the following bills:</p>
<p><b>Bill No. 1 - Status of the Artist Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 9 - Canada-Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Resources Accord Implementation (Nova Scotia) Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 11 - Nova Scotia Tartan Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 20 - Public Trustee Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 22 - Mortgage Regulation Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 32 - Securities Act.</b></p>
<p>and the chairman has been instructed to recommend these bills to the favourable consideration of the House, each without amendment.</p>
<p>Further, Mr. Speaker, that the committee has met and considered the following bill:</p>
<p><b>Bill No. 24 - Purchasing Management Association of Canada Act.</b></p>
<p>which was reported with certain amendments by the Committee on Law Amendments to the Committee of the Whole without further amendments, and the chairman has been instructed to recommend this bill to the favourable consideration of the House.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Ordered that these bills be read a third time on a future day.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#5db3f08e-219e-4ab3-a082-7bcc7ed081b1">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, I will be asking for permission from all sides of the House to move these bills that have just returned from Committee of the Whole House on Bills for third reading today, if possible.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is to move these bills on to third reading today, if possible. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#5db3f08e-219e-4ab3-a082-7bcc7ed081b1">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Public Bills for Third Reading.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PUBLIC BILLS FOR THIRD READING</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 1.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 1 - Status of the Artist Act.</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 9 - Canada-Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Resources Accord Implementation (Nova Scotia) Act.</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 11 &#x2013; Nova Scotia Tartan Act.</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 20 - Public Trustee Act.</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 22 - Mortgage Regulation Act.</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 24 &#x2013; Purchasing Management Association of Canada Act.</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 32 - Securities Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motions are carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that these bills do pass. Ordered that the titles be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bills be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#5db3f08e-219e-4ab3-a082-7bcc7ed081b1"><from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from><p>Thank you, Mr. Speaker, I appreciate the expeditious way the House dealt with those.</p>
<p>Would you please call the order of business, Public Bills for Second Reading.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PUBLIC BILLS FOR SECOND READING</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#5db3f08e-219e-4ab3-a082-7bcc7ed081b1">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 74.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 74 - Patient Safety Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Minister of Health and Wellness.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#3663e5bf-7f5e-4b7d-a021-669a4f8ab4bc"><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I'm pleased to rise and move second reading of the Patient Safety Act. The long title of this bill is an Act to Improve Patient Safety and Health Systems Accountability. It's a bill that will provide greater public accountability to the patients who rely on our health care system for safe care. Patient safety is a priority for this government and this legislation will support our efforts to make care safer for Nova Scotians. Nova Scotia will be the second province in Canada, the first in the Atlantic Provinces, to take a strong, legislated position for public reporting. Ontario introduced similar reporting requirements in 2008, under the Public Hospitals Act.</p>
<p>Under this proposed legislation, district health authorities and the IWK Health Centre will be required to report publicly and to the Department of Health and Wellness, on a number of patient safety indicators. Our goal is to introduce regulations requiring the reporting of hand hygiene adherence rates this Fall, with reporting to begin in April of next year.</p>
<p>Other important patient safety indicators, such as rates of health care-associated infections, like C. difficile and MRSA, as well as health care worker influenza immunization rates, will be added over time.</p>
<p>We have chosen to start with hand hygiene adherence rates because it is considered by many experts to be one of the best measures of patient safety overall. We all know that hand washing is important in the fight against infections but, Mr. Speaker, what you may not know is that good hand hygiene is, in fact, considered the single most important way to prevent the spread of infections, so it makes good sense that hospitals with better rates of hand hygiene adherence have lower rates of infections.</p>
<p>To be clear, Mr. Speaker, health care providers are washing their hands but good hand hygiene means that health care providers are cleaning their hands at the right times during patient care and in the right way every time. This is an ongoing challenge for us and, indeed, the rest of the world with rates globally averaging between 40 to 50 per cent. While districts do monitor these rates, there has been no requirement for them to share their results with the Department of Health and Wellness or with the public, so we have no way to know for certain how we compare.</p>
<p>What we do know, Mr. Speaker, is that there is always room for improvement. The reality is that despite ongoing efforts to educate and remind health care professionals, patients and the public about the importance of regularly and thoroughly cleaning their hands, we continue to see a growing numbers of infections in hospitals across Canada and unfortunately right here in Nova Scotia. This is concerning to me, as Minister of Health and Wellness, to the public we serve and, of course, most importantly to the patients and families who rely on our health system for care.</p>
<p>Getting an infection, while in hospital, for some other illness or injury can have a devastating impact on patients resulting in longer stays, complications and, unfortunately, in some cases even death. While infections are reality for all hospitals, prevention is a shared responsibility. Patient safety is about managing and reducing risk to ensure that the care patients receive is as safe as possible.</p>
<p>We know that many infections could be prevented if basic infection prevention and control practices, including good hand washing, were constantly implemented. Monitoring hand hygiene adherence and providing health care workers with feedback regarding their performance are considered integral parts of a successful hand hygiene promotion program. Mr. Speaker, that's exactly what this legislation will do.</p>
<p>As Dr. Peter Vaughan, the vice-president of Medicine and incoming CEO of South Shore Regional Health, said, in support of this legislation, everyone wants to go to a good job. Increasing knowledge of our own performance can foster and inform our quality improvement activities by appealing to everyone's motivation to provide better care. Dr. Vaughan, a passionate leader and advocate for quality improvement, also reminded us that we can't know how well we're doing if we don't measure what we're doing. Measuring is a building block of quality health care. This applies to other patient safety indicators as well.</p>
<p>District health authorities and the IWK have many initiatives in place to improve patient safety. They have programs in place to reduce the risk of falls, medication errors and infections. They are already monitoring and reporting many of these patient safety indicators to their boards, to Accreditation Canada and to other agencies such as Safer Healthcare Now! But since there have been no requirements for them to share these rates with the Department of Health and Wellness, or with the public, we don't necessarily know how they are measuring or reporting them and how they compare across the province.</p>
<p>That is why we are committed to working with the district health authorities and the IWK to develop consistent collection methods and reporting processes that will ensure data can be compared across the province. Under the health authorities bill the Department of Health and Wellness has a legislated role to be aware of quality issues facing the health system: to monitor, measure and evaluate the quality of health services, to report to the public on the quality of the health care system and work with stakeholders to address quality issues at the system level.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, this Act will support and enhance our ability to meet our legislative responsibility to oversee health system quality. While mandatory public reporting should be considered only one element of an effective strategy for quality rates, we believe it will help ensure that patient safety continues to get the attention it deserves.</p>
<p>As well-known author, writer and self-described social ecologist Peter Drucker has said, what gets measured gets managed.</p>
<p>This legislation will serve as a valuable tool for moving the patient safety agenda forward. It will allow us to monitor rates over time, track improvements, and develop strategies to address areas of concern. It will strengthen the public's confidence in our hospitals and it will enable better and safer patient care for Nova Scotians.</p>
<p>In closing, Mr. Speaker, I want to say that this is a bill that I think my Aunt Mary would be very happy with and other members of this House probably have Aunt Marys, who during recent outbreaks of C. difficile are really, I think, seriously concerned, and rightly concerned, about infections in our acute care facilities and what we can do to prevent them. So this is a bill for my Aunt Mary and all of the Aunt Marys in the province. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Kings West.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#ea522cb5-76c2-4f6d-920c-5b1835704b1a"><from>MR. LEO GLAVINE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I want to first say yesterday I guess kind of went back almost, if you wish, to an elementary school moment where we were learning to wash our hands. I was pleased to join the minister yesterday when she first announced Bill No. 74. It was a very enlightening moment to find out that what you take for granted in washing your hands, everything is good to go.</p>
<p>In the hospital setting as we know, where infections can be passed so easily, to do it properly at the right time during patient care and consistently, as the minister says, is what it truly is all about. It was also a d&#xE9;j&#xE0; vu moment because my wife, a nurse, was a clinical site manager and when a staph infection breaks out in a hospital and you have to then deal with enhancing the cleaning of one's hands and person and also, of course, cleaning staff, it brings back those kinds of moments when, really, staff need to be taking all kinds of precautions.</p>
<p>Now when it comes to the bill, it's interesting that in Ontario they moved this through amendments to both the Health Promotion and Protection Act and the Public Hospitals Act, and perhaps in some ways here we could have used amendments to the Health Authorities Act in order to accomplish this. I know that as a stand-alone bill, it does draw attention to the need to improve this aspect of preventing infections, reducing, as much as possible, infections in our hospitals.</p>
<p>In many ways the one concurrence yesterday was among those presenting Dr. Vaughan and also department people realized that it's part of a process and, in fact, the bill is a good first start. However, as with many pieces of legislation that come before us in the House, there are oftentimes many questions, sometimes more than we have answers.</p>
<p>Patient safety is important, no question, and any bill that begins to address patient safety, even in an incremental way, is, indeed, a good step forward. It is hoped that reporting and accountability will inspire improved performance, enhance patient safety and with the end goal of strengthening public confidence.</p>
<p>I think there was no more telling moment during the C. difficile outbreak, when I spoke with the CEO and with several families in the Cape Breton area, who were actually wondering about having their loved one go to the regional hospital. Especially, you know, an elderly person needing hip surgery or knee surgery, going in for something that's very treatable and perhaps run the risk of getting C. difficile during the outbreak. There's no question it is unfortunate when confidence is lost.</p>
<p>However at this time, the bill is looking for the DHAs to report adherence rates and I do have a question though as the bill is not clear in terms of reporting to whom. Report to the minister, report to the public via a Web site, like Ontario does? I think having the reporting for the public to know the rates of adherence - and, of course, we're going to need to know rates of infection as well. I assume the plan of the minister is to address this in regulations. However, as of right now, it is not clear to the public whether the minister intends to publicly report the rates. If she does, she should put that in legislation, not in regulation.</p>
<p>While handwashing in our health care facilities is vitally important, it is vitally important for a number of people who are in our health care facilities - health care professionals, workers who work in the facilities who do not have direct patient contact and visitors to facilities. While reporting adherence rates is important, what is even more crucial from a public confidence point of view is what is being done not only to increase these rates but what is being done to deal with the infection rates.</p>
<p>I know that the reporting of infection rates are in the works for this legislation, just not at this point in time. I happen to believe that there are benefits in releasing both adherence rates and infection rates simultaneously. I think if we have both of these, that's where real public confidence will dramatically be improved and we would certainly recommend that to take place. First, the data released in tandem will enable us to determine which districts require attention and which districts are doing good jobs, so that lessons can be shared and whether initiatives to improve rates correspond with a reduction in the rates of infection. As we all know, we can collect data but how strongly do we address the infection rates and make sure that, in fact, there is a substantial reduction, there's good improvement taking place.</p>
<p>Actually interesting enough, in Ontario, the province which has similar legislation, the incident rates of infection such as C. difficile, MRSA and VRE were posted first with indicators such as handwashing hygiene following later. I think that's where we would really see substantive movement here on improvement. What's more interesting, when you look at the Web site in Ontario, is there are fact sheets about the various infections. Fact sheets which speak to the symptoms, which speak to what family members should be asking health care officials and guidance to family members on what to ask health care officials about - what they are doing to reduce the risk of infection. I do hope these types of fact sheets are part of this government's accountability to patient safety. I'm not sure if that will be the case but certainly hope that they will be.</p>
<p>I also note when you look at the Ontario Web site, data for adherence rates for handwashing are measured at two distinct points - before providing care to patients and after providing care. I'm wondering whether similar data will be made publicly available here in Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>Another question I have is whether similar applicable adherence rates and infection rates from nursing homes will also be subject to the same reporting mechanisms. I think for a very high-standard, high-quality job to be done here, when you think of the vulnerability in our nursing homes, to me this would be an important aspect to include in this legislation. We know that often infections showing up in hospitals are not necessarily acquired in hospitals. Let's not forget, Mr. Speaker, the role that cleaning plays in the risk of the spread of infection in any and in all our facilities. When you have sufficient staff numbers to clean facilities, you also enhance patient safety.</p>
<p>There are other provinces - Manitoba, for example - that have passed legislation around the issue of patient safety, that also warrants mentioning. In Manitoba there is a no-fault, mandatory critical incident reporting process whereby health authorities are mandated to report and deal with incidents that are reported either by health care workers, patients or family members, that involve harm or death of the patients. These incidents must be dealt with and must be reported to Manitoba Health.</p>
<p>It's important to stress that the purpose is not to find fault; other mechanisms in Manitoba remain when it comes to finding fault. The purpose is to deal with issues in an open, accountable way so that mistakes aren't repeated.</p>
<p>Finally, I noted the fact that there are no timelines associated with the bill. The minister indicated in press briefings that the bill will be in place in the Fall, with reporting responsibilities to be in place by April. If we're going to have a bill that has the ability to do good, let's at least tell Nova Scotians when they can expect such information, even if it's only the first small step. It is the very least that government can do.</p>
<p>I did want to add these comments because I believe that any time we debate a piece of legislation, there should be full debate and recognition that the bill may not necessarily be as strong as it could be, when it appears on the floor of the House. So this is a good first step but that's what it is - a good first step. We have no idea when or what other patient safety adherents are going to be added and we have no idea when infection rates are to be added.</p>
<p>We support the bill, we believe it's a small step but a step needed, nonetheless. I note, Mr. Speaker, in a final manner, we've had to deal here in our province with a very serious C. difficile outbreak &#x2026;</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Order, please. The chatter is getting very high and it's quite hard to hear the honourable member.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Kings West.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#ea522cb5-76c2-4f6d-920c-5b1835704b1a"><from>MR. GLAVINE</from><p>Thank you, Mr. Speaker, and as always, a good Speaker, from his previous days, of course, as Speaker of the House.</p>
<p>You know Cape Breton went through a very difficult time with C. difficile and again, lots of information was passed on to the Department of Health and Wellness, probably directly to the minister, and with any information, whether it's this accounting process through Bill No. 77, the Medical Society Act - as we look at rates of adherence to hand washing because we know what can happen through the spread of infectious disease.</p>
<p>When that outbreak came, the district health authority and John Malcom, the Cape Breton Regional Health Authority, asked government for a certain amount of money to deal with the problem. They knew some of the areas of the hospital that needed to be updated where, in fact, perhaps infection controls weren't at their very best. We know that it came in increments, small amounts, compared to what was required. So it's very important that we take information, we act on it and we act authoritatively and directly, to make sure that something as serious as infections are dealt with.</p>
<p>Once again, Mr. Speaker, I do believe that this is a step in the right direction and we look forward to this bill moving through the law amendments process. Thank you, Mr. Speaker.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Argyle.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#54c01d3a-9d00-4849-8acd-59f8efd8a2f9"><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, before I really get going on the bill I wanted to just mention somebody who is in the gallery today, somebody of course who is important to our caucus - Sarah Reeves who, of course, is in communications in our caucus. It's her birthday today so I just want to wish Sarah a happy birthday and of course to spend it with us during this special day, so thank you, Sarah. (Applause)</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I'll speak for a few moments to this bill. Number one, of course, is the issue of patient safety is paramount, so anything that the government will bring forward that will be focused on the safety of the patient, I think, is one that will receive support from this side of the House, but should also receive support from Nova Scotians as we look forward to a day where we don't have to worry about some of these infections and some of these issues that continue to happen in our health system.</p>
<p>Far too often we hear of reports of MRSA, VRE and at its worst C. difficile, getting hooked into a hospital and, of course, having a whole array of reasons as to why it is in our health system. If there is a way to try to mitigate that it's to make sure that all opportunities are taken to make sure it's not in our hospital. Of course, handwashing is one method that is one of those no-brainers that should be happening but apparently does not happen as vigorously in our health system as it should.</p>
<p>I know we all have a story about handwashers and mine, I don't have to go very far in my life, is of course my wife. My wife continues to tell our children at every instance to go wash their hands. It's the first thing they need to do before doing anything to make sure that when they come in from playing, before they eat, to make sure that their hands are washed. When she took over the charge of the Grade 1s in the Wedgeport school, knowing the difficulty she was going to have in getting those children to wash their hands, I made a number of phone calls to the hospital system. We chased around Burnside trying to find the right company that sold those little squirt bottles of antibacterials so that she was able to provide some kind of handwashing capability to those children in Grade 1 before they went off to eat. I can tell you the result of that was actually quite good because she looked at the absences in her class versus the absences in other classes and her class did very well.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, it might be only a little example of how handwashing works but if it's working with kids in Grade 1, certainly it will work with the professionals and the public that visit the hospital system in Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>The only thing that we see in this one is the devil is in the details. Exactly how are we going to ensure that handwashing is one thing that's going to be followed within our system? In our caucus we have two health professionals who can talk about this on a regular basis of how you actually try to get the washing to be done. Sometimes you don't have the time to do the washing but being able to use the antibacterial is one method. But the issue is, how are you going to actually practise?</p>
<p>Is it going to create a situation where we're providing more paperwork to our health professionals who are, in my estimation, overworked at this time in just filling out forms? Are they going to have to have a punch card and punch that card every time they wash their hands? Actually, the member for Richmond just commented to me a few moments ago and sort of said, well, maybe it could be a little bit like when he's potty training his daughter. Of course, Satine is growing up and having to go through potty training and what they do is provide a sticker to her if she does her business. Well, is that going to happen in our health system, where we are going to give a sticker to doctors and nurses as they wash their hands and maybe mark that down when the time comes?</p>
<p>That is the detail issue that we haven't heard from government at this point and one I hope will become more apparent as time goes on because I know from speaking to health professionals across this province that they are overworked. Their regulatory burden, I guess is what you would call it, their paperwork is such that it is very difficult to get everything done. I just hope that this won't create another layer of paperwork for them.</p>
<p>To sum it all up, again, patient safety is number one and if it is to make our hospitals safer, to make our patients healthier, to make sure that they do not have to respond to issues of MRSA, of VRE and as I said, God forbid, C. difficile, we hope that this will do that for them. Again, the devil is in the details and we hope to see more of that from this minister as we roll along, but as it stands right now, we are in support of the bill as it stands.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>If I recognize the minister it will be to close the debate.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Health and Wellness.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#3663e5bf-7f5e-4b7d-a021-669a4f8ab4bc">
            <from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from>
            <p>I just wanted to thank my colleagues for their thoughtful comments on the bill and, Mr. Speaker, I move second reading of Bill No. 74</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for second reading of Bill No. 74. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill be referred to the Committee on Law Amendments.</p>
<p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#8d3f2e85-b724-4554-980d-02c64fb4603a">
            <from>HON. CLARRIE MACKINNON</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 76.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 76 - Personal Health Information Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Minister of Health and Wellness.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#3663e5bf-7f5e-4b7d-a021-669a4f8ab4bc"><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I rise to move second reading of Bill No. 76, an Act to amend the Personal Health Information Act.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, as you may recall, the Personal Health Information Act was passed in December 2010 to provide clear, consistent rules for the management of personal health information.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>I would just remind the minister that she does have to move second reading as well. We didn't hear that.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#3663e5bf-7f5e-4b7d-a021-669a4f8ab4bc">
            <from>MS. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from>
            <p>I thought I had.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>We didn't hear it. I mean you may have but we didn't hear it.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#3663e5bf-7f5e-4b7d-a021-669a4f8ab4bc"><from>MS. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>I would like to move second reading of Bill No. 76. So as I was saying, you may remember that the Personal Health Information Act was passed in December 2010 to provide clear, consistent rules for the management of personal health information. Since that time staff in the Department of Health and Wellness have been working with our partners in the health sector to develop regulations for the Act, which is expected to come into effect early next year.</p>
<p>We have also been working to develop information for the public and for the people and organizations that have responsibility for managing personal health information to support them in meeting their obligations under the Act. Through that work with our partners, we have identified some minor errors and omissions that will be addressed through the eight housekeeping amendments we are proposing today in this bill. The amendments will not change the intent of the Act in any way but will add clarity to the legislation.</p>
<p>While they are minor amendments, Mr. Speaker, the Personal Health Information Bill is important legislation for Nova Scotians. It will allow for appropriate information sharing and support better care while ensuring that a patient's privacy is better protected. Under the legislation every health care provider who has access to personal health information will need to follow clear practices and policies designed to protect patient privacy. In Nova Scotia personal health information has been governed by a mix of federal and provincial legislation, health profession codes, and organizational policies and procedures. The Personal Health Information Bill brings all of these protections and rules under one piece of legislation. It is consistent with other health information legislation already in place in many - in fact, in most - other provinces. Nova Scotians expect that their personal health information will be kept private and treated securely.</p>
<p>At the same time, Mr. Speaker, health care professionals must be able to share information in ways that can improve care. The Personal Health Information Bill balances the right of individuals to ensure their personal health information is protected and the need of the health sector to collect, use, and disclose personal health information to provide support and manage good health care.</p>
<p>This is what is contained in the bill and I look forward to the thoughts of my colleagues as this bill proceeds through this Chamber. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Kings West.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#ea522cb5-76c2-4f6d-920c-5b1835704b1a"><from>MR. LEO GLAVINE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I'm pleased to rise and add a few comments around Bill No. 76, the Personal Health Information Act. It changes references from "Minister of Health Promotion and Protection" to "Minister of Health and Wellness" and it deals with housekeeping measures that have surfaced through the very long process of making regulations.</p>
<p>I can't help but comment on the fact that debate on the Personal Health Information Act concluded on December 9, 2010, one year and 125 days ago. We all know that when the bill was finally debated in 2010, we were debating a bill that had previously been tabled by the government in the Fall of 2009 and ultimately dies on the order paper. At the time of debate in 2010, government indicated that once the legislation was passed, government would have fulfilled one of the recommendations of the February 2010 Auditor General's Report. It's safe to say Nova Scotians aren't the only ones waiting.</p>
<p>I understand this legislation is complicated, personal health information is sensitive information, and a bill and its regulations will require a great deal of staff, training and familiarization before the bill actually comes into force which, if I understood the press release correctly, is early 2013. However, I would be remiss if I didn't mention the fact that Nova Scotia was not charting new territory with personal health information in 2010. We were one of two provinces that did not have personal health information so I think the minister would agree we weren't necessarily starting from square one.</p>
<p>Having said all that we agree with the amendments, understand their need, but we would just like to see details around the regulations and see this bill come into force. As the minister has indicated, these are housekeeping amendments that add clarity to the bill and we support them. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Argyle.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#54c01d3a-9d00-4849-8acd-59f8efd8a2f9"><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, of course we too support these changes in Bill No. 76. I know I spent a lot of time talking about health information and how it's collected in this province and how, as we move along in computerized systems and availability, more and more people have the opportunity to access it. Of course, being able to restrict it and have clear regulations around it, I think are paramount.</p>
<p>Of course this bill is mostly housekeeping and adjusting certain issues that came up during regulation-setting meetings. It's something that is taking far too long as my honourable colleague just mentioned. It has been here for a long time and to see some changes to it are accepted. Again, we should have the bill in place by now.</p>
<p>I've mentioned this and I did this during estimate debates, it would be good to have a further discussion around the electronic medical record and its availability to doctors and patients across this province. I hope the minister is continuing to focus in on that to make sure that Nova Scotians have access to an EMR from one end of the province to another in case they get sick. We know how the health system here in Nova Scotia works, that you might get sick in Yarmouth but chances are you're going to have your surgery or other issues dealt with here in Halifax, so the transfer of that information is, of course, always very important. There may be a day when, in Canada, that information can go from province to province, and that will be of the utmost importance as well.</p>
<p>With that, I thank the minister for her comments on this bill and we'll be supporting this one through the next processes of the House.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>If I recognize the minister it will be to close the debate.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Health and Wellness.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#3663e5bf-7f5e-4b7d-a021-669a4f8ab4bc">
            <from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I'd like to thank my colleagues for their comments, and I now move that we close debate on second reading and have the bill proceed to the Law Amendments Committee.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for second reading of Bill No. 76. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill be referred to the Committee on Law Amendments.</p>
<p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#8d3f2e85-b724-4554-980d-02c64fb4603a">
            <from>MR. CLARRIE MACKINNON</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 77.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 77 - Medical Society Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Minister of Health and Wellness.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#3663e5bf-7f5e-4b7d-a021-669a4f8ab4bc"><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I would like to move second reading of Bill No. 77, an Act to Amend Chapter 12 of the Acts of 1995-96, the Medical Society Act.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, the role of Doctors Nova Scotia is an important one in the health of our province. As the medical association that represents physicians in contract negotiations and the body that acts as physicians' united voice in advancing patient care, they also promote healthy living throughout our province.</p>
<p>The proposed amendments will allow Doctors Nova Scotia to continue providing the same level of support and services to physicians and Nova Scotians. In 2004, Mr. Speaker, the Medical Society of Nova Scotia changed its name to Doctors Nova Scotia. These proposed amendments will legally make this name change and continue to provide that physicians shall be members of the association.</p>
<p>By design, the new Medical Act passed in December 2011 fosters more separation between the College of Physicians and Surgeons and Doctors Nova Scotia. These proposed amendments for the Medical Society Act include provisions regarding membership and payment of dues for Doctors Nova Scotia, and will replace the provisions for these matters in the existing Medical Act, which will be repealed when the new Medical Act is proclaimed.</p>
<p>It is important that these amendments be made so that we may officially recognize Doctors Nova Scotia as the society they have become today, so that physicians understand that as members of this association they are entitled to programs and benefits provided by Doctors Nova Scotia. Other jurisdictions have similar legislation that allows their respective medical societies to govern their own membership. This has been the case in Nova Scotia, and through these amendments we are ensuring that it will continue to be the case.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Kings West.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#ea522cb5-76c2-4f6d-920c-5b1835704b1a"><from>MR. LEO GLAVINE</from><p>Thank you, Mr. Speaker. I am pleased to rise in my place and speak for a few minutes on Bill No. 77, the Medical Society Act. Of course we know that the Medical Society changed to Doctors Nova Scotia - it was a name change occurring in about 2004.</p>
<p>I'd be remiss if I did not take a couple of minutes to speak about the great work of Doctors Nova Scotia. Besides providing a valuable service to its members, they provide invaluable information and guidance to Nova Scotia - they educate the public on the importance of leading a healthy lifestyle, including getting active, eating healthy, choosing not to smoke, getting an annual flu shot, and the importance of regular pap test screening.</p>
<p>While all of this advocacy and support for the public is important to me, some of the greatest work being done is their sponsorship and ongoing support of the school-based Kids' Run Club. The Kids' Run Club, now in its eighth year, has 190 schools and groups registered.</p>
<p>Now back to the business at hand, today we are dealing with a bill that incorporates both housekeeping changes, as well as what I presume to be changes requested from Doctors Nova Scotia themselves.</p>
<p>In terms of housekeeping, we have an amendment to the bill which will change the name to Doctors Nova Scotia and respecting the rights of Doctors Nova Scotia to self-govern. I can only assume the change is around whom they can accept as members and clarification around consequences for the non-payment of fees as requested by Doctors Nova Scotia and if that's to be the case, we have no problem with these amendments.</p>
<p>Having had the opportunity to meet with the current head of Doctors Nova Scotia, Dr. John Chiasson from Antigonish, it's certainly very, I guess, strong to see one of their own members take the helm, a doctor who has an active practice and for a certain period of time is not as fully engaged in his practice but is guiding the work of Doctors Nova Scotia. Taking that application of practice to the larger body, I think is very valuable to the profession, valuable to all Nova Scotians. So we do commend the work of Doctors Nova Scotia and, indeed, to see through Bill No. 77, the Medical Society Act, that in fact some updating and good change is taking place on their behalf. With that, I take my place.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Argyle.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#54c01d3a-9d00-4849-8acd-59f8efd8a2f9"><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>I'm very pleased to stand to speak for a few moments on Bill No. 77, as our Health Critic for the Progressive Conservative caucus. Doctors Nova Scotia has been a tremendous power in Nova Scotia for a number of years, whether it's under the old name or the new name, and have been wonderful advocates for healthy living and, of course, so many initiatives in this province when it comes to health care.</p>
<p>I can say that during my time as minister I enjoyed the friendship, the help that I did receive from Doctors Nova Scotia at the time, and no different today with the leadership of Dr. Chiasson as well as Nancy MacCready-Williams as the executive director. I think they are phenomenal individuals as well as the staff who do work there. The member just previous to me, the member for Kings West, mentioned the issue of the run program that has been so well received by Nova Scotians and I can say that both of my sons, Andr&#xE9; and Alec, participate in Courir pour le plaisir, which is, of course, the French version of Kids' Run Club. I was very happy, even during my time, to have provided them with a translation of that so that, of course, the CSAP could participate in that program as well.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, this is one that I think is an easy one to support because, of course, all of us do know Doctors Nova Scotia now is Doctors Nova Scotia. I think the whole society thing has been forgotten over the last number of years as they've become so much more important. So with those very short words, I can assure the minister that we'll be supporting this bill through its process because of the help that Doctors Nova Scotia gives to all Nova Scotians.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>If I recognize the minister it will be to close the debate.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Health and Wellness.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#3663e5bf-7f5e-4b7d-a021-669a4f8ab4bc">
            <from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, again I would like to thank my colleagues for their comments and with that, I would move second reading of Bill No.77.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for second reading of Bill No. 77. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill be referred to the Committee on Law Amendments.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#5db3f08e-219e-4ab3-a082-7bcc7ed081b1">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, that concludes the government business for today. I thank everybody for their participation and debate. I move that the House do now rise to meet from the hours of 4:00 p.m. to 10:00 p.m. on Monday. After the daily routine we will be doing Committee of the Whole House on Bills and Bills for Second Reading and Address in Reply to the Speech from the Throne, if need be, but with that said I move that the House do now rise.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the House now rise to meet again on Monday at the hour of 4:00 p.m.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
          <narrative>
            <p>The House rose at 10:30 a.m.</p>
          </narrative>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION UNDER RULE 32(3)</heading>
        <speech by="#310e08cc-3724-403f-821e-1a1076a68e6c"><num title="840">RESOLUTION NO. 840</num><from>Mr. Chuck Porter</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Drew MacCormack, of Falmouth, could one day take his spot at a Brier, the symbolic event of the Canadian Men's Curling Championship; and</p>
<p>Whereas Drew, from the Windsor Curling Club, eliminated near the end of the Nova Scotia Junior Curling Championship, held Christmas week in Windsor; and</p>
<p>Whereas Drew also skipped Avon View High School to a silver medal in the Nova Scotia Schools Athletic Federation Curling Championship, held at the Mayflower Curling Club in Halifax, after winning the Western Zone Championship in Windsor;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly extend congratulations to Drew, his Head Coach and dad, Ron MacCormack, and his Avonview team of Ryan Whitehead, Jordan Cassidy and Jimmy Huard on a great year of curling.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0"><num title="841">RESOLUTION NO. 841</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Margaret Publicover welcomed her great-great grandson, Rocky Thomas Pye, into the family; and</p>
<p>Whereas Rocky Thomas Pye's birth on January 17, 2012, at Saint Martha's Regional Hospital, marked a total of five generations in Margaret Publicover's family; and</p>
<p>Whereas Trevor and Jennifer Pye welcomed their son into the family and made Margaret Publicover a great-great grandmother, creating a five generation family;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Margaret Publicover on the newest addition to her family and hope she will enjoy his company for years to come.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0"><num title="842">RESOLUTION NO. 842</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the weekend of January 13<sup>th</sup> to 14<sup>th</sup> was the Guysborough Invitational Basketball Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas eight Nova Scotia school teams participated in the Guysborough Invitational Basketball Tournament, where the Guysborough Academy Boys Team secured a hard earned second place finish; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Guysborough Invitational Basketball Tournament was deemed a success due to the support of the officials, volunteers, and parents, and of course the participating students;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Guysborough Academy Boys Team on their hard work and team spirit which earned them a second place finish at the Guysborough Invitational Basketball Tournament.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0"><num title="843">RESOLUTION NO. 843</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the weekend of January 13<sup>th</sup> to 14<sup>th</sup> was the Guysborough Invitational Basketball Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas eight Nova Scotia school teams participated in the Guysborough Invitational Basketball Tournament, where the Guysborough Academy Girls Team secured a hard earned third place finish; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Guysborough Invitational Basketball Tournament was deemed a success due to the support of the officials, volunteers, and parents, and of course the participating students;</p>
<p>Whereas be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Guysborough Academy Girls Team on their hard work and team spirit which earned them a third place finish at the Guysborough Invitational Basketball Tournament.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0"><num title="844">RESOLUTION NO. 844</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas sisters Mallori Nickerson and Alisha Sangster started their breast cancer awareness fundraising group, Breast Foot Forward on March 19, 2011 and marked their first full year with a dance hosted by Scottie O. from the local radio station 101.5 the Hawk; and</p>
<p>Whereas breast cancer awareness group Breast Foot Forward was created by sisters Mallori Nickerson and Alisha Sangster from the inspiration they received from their grandmother Ella Langley, a nine year breast cancer survivor; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Breast Foot Forward one year anniversary dance was held on March 24, 2012 with proceeds going towards the Canadian Cancer Society for breast cancer research;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Mallori Nickerson and Alisha Sangster on their dedication to raising awareness of breast cancer throughout their community as well as making much appreciated donations to the Canadian Cancer Society for breast cancer research.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0"><num title="845">RESOLUTION NO. 845</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas during Christmas week the Sheet Harbour Red Hatters delivered handmade Christmas gifts to the residents of the Duncan MacMillan Nursing Home; and</p>
<p>Whereas the local Sheet Harbour Red Hatters visited with the residents of the Duncan MacMillan Nursing Home and together with another local women's group delivered Christmas gifts of handmade lap robes; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Sheet Harbour Red Hatters were funded for materials and then held sewing sessions to design and make enough lap robes for residents of the Duncan MacMillan Nursing Home;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly acknowledge the dedication to community that the local Sheet Harbour Red Hatters displayed when designing and making each resident of the Duncan MacMillan Nursing Home a special lap robe for Christmas.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0"><num title="846">RESOLUTION NO. 846</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Canso and Area arena has started their 2011-12 year fundraising campaign in which they are attempting to raise $15,000 to $20,000; and</p>
<p>Whereas fundraising events so far have been very successful, including the November 13<sup>th</sup> Telethon which surpassed $5,000 and the December 9<sup>th</sup> high calibre match between the Junior B League teams, the Saint Margaret's Bay Ducks and the Strait Pirates; and</p>
<p>Whereas supporters of the Canso and Area Arena hosted a Route 16 Party on February 11<sup>th</sup> at the Fairview Legion in Halifax which included a dance, a silent auction as well as entertainment provided by the band Big Jib and several down home musicians;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Canso and Area Arena on their successful fundraising events and wish them every success as they strive to provide the greater community with local arena services.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0"><num title="847">RESOLUTION NO. 847</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas schools in the Strait Regional School Board have been undertaking Service Learning Initiatives, "learning by doing", and helping important causes locally and globally; and</p>
<p>Whereas Chedabucto Education Centre/Guysborough Academy took part in the Service Learning Initiatives and participated in collecting funds for the local food bank to buy Christmas turkey dinners for those in need, hosted the annual Tribute to the Troops Concert and the annual Christmas Tea, hosted a sing-a-long at the Milford Haven Nursing Home, held a poetry reading session, and grew and harvested vegetables for local use; and</p>
<p>Whereas Monica William, director of programs and services, congratulated the students and staff for the thoughtful and meaningful ways in which they gave to their neighbours by taking part in local, national and international initiatives;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Chedabucto Education Centre/Guysborough Academy students and staff for their active role in Service Learning Initiatives throughout the school year and wish them well as they continue to provide leadership to these important causes.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0"><num title="848">RESOLUTION NO. 848</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas January 27, 2012, was Family Literacy Day and Guysborough Adult Learning Association joined in the celebrations; and</p>
<p>Whereas to celebrate Family Literacy Day, Guysborough Adult Learning Association co-hosted a Family Games event with a light supper, games, free books and prize draws, which was held in New Harbour at the Harbourview Community Centre; and</p>
<p>Whereas Guysborough Adult Learning Association hosted this Family Games event to promote the importance of literacy and to encourage families to spend time together learning as a family;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Guysborough Adult Learning Association on their continued community dedication and on their efforts to promote family engagement in lifelong learning.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0"><num title="849">RESOLUTION NO. 849</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Sceles Realty Limited Antigonish has opened an office in Boylston, Guysborough County; and</p>
<p>Whereas Giselle Sceles, owner/broker of Sceles Realty Limited Antigonish, has opened Sceles Realty Limited Boylston, in the heart of the community of Boylston; and</p>
<p>Whereas after extensive renovations to the new office location, Sceles Realty Limited Boylston is now up and running;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Giselle Sceles on the recent expansion of her business and wish her and her staff every success for their future in the community of Boylston.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0"><num title="850">RESOLUTION NO. 850</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Canso Minor Hockey Association will offer additional instruction to local players at a mini hockey school; and</p>
<p>Whereas Canso Minor Hockey Association will host a mini hockey school with instruction from John VanKessel, a former LA Kings player, drafted in 1988 and currently residing in Antigonish; and</p>
<p>Whereas players in the Peewee, Bantam and Midget Divisions will be able to attend the mini hockey school, along with their coaches, at the Canso and Area Arena;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Canso Minor Hockey Association on the opportunities they are offering their young hockey players and wish them every success for the future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0"><num title="851">RESOLUTION NO. 851</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas schools in the Strait Regional School Board have been undertaking Service Learning Initiatives, "learning by doing" and helping important causes locally and globally; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mulgrave Memorial Education Centre took part in the Service Learning Initiatives and raised money for the local food bank with a hat and pajama day and a food drive during their Christmas concert; and</p>
<p>Whereas Monica William, director of programs and services, congratulated the students and staff for the thoughtful and meaningful ways in which they gave to their neighbours, taking part in local, national and international initiatives;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Mulgrave Memorial Education Centre students and staff for their active role in Service Learning Initiatives throughout the school year and wish them well as they continue to participate in these important causes.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0"><num title="852">RESOLUTION NO. 852</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas schools in the Strait Regional School Board have been undertaking Service Learning Initiatives, "learning by doing" and helping important causes locally and globally; and</p>
<p>Whereas Canso Academy took part in the Service Learning Initiatives and participated in the Great Canadian Shoreline Community Clean Up, organized activities to get the pre-school children active, encouraged the school Green Team and industrial arts students to build planters for the Fanning Education Centre's Gardening Program; and</p>
<p>Whereas Monica William, director of programs and services, congratulated the students and staff for the thoughtful and meaningful ways in which they gave to their neighbours, taking part in local, national and international initiatives;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Canso Academy students and staff for their active role in Service Learning Initiatives throughout the school year and wish them well as they continue to provide leadership to these important causes.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0"><num title="853">RESOLUTION NO. 853</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Christmas Day, 2011, Canso RCMP detachment officers made a visit to the Canso Seaside Manor; and</p>
<p>Whereas Cpl. Danny Thompson went to visit the residents of the local Canso Seaside Manor to spread a little Christmas cheer and serve the residents their Christmas dinner; and</p>
<p>Whereas a great visit with dinner and a few good laughs was enjoyed by Canso RCMP officers and Canso Seaside Manor residents;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly acknowledge the dedication to the community shown by Canso RCMP detachment officer Cpl. Danny Thompson, who willingly gave some of his Christmas Day to serve dinner and visit with the residents of the Canso Seaside Manor.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0"><num title="854">RESOLUTION NO. 854</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Christmas Day, 2012, local RCMP detachment officers made a visit to the Milford Haven Home for Special Care; and</p>
<p>Whereas Sgt. Miller went to visit the residents of the local Milford Haven Home for Special Care, to spread a little Christmas cheer and serve the residents their Christmas dinner; and</p>
<p>Whereas a great visit with dinner and a few good laughs was enjoyed by the local RCMP officers and Milford Haven Home for Special Care residents;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly acknowledge the dedication to the community shown by local RCMP detachment officer Sgt. Miller, who willingly gave some of his Christmas Day to serve dinner and visit with the residents of the Milford Haven Home for Special Care.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0"><num title="855">RESOLUTION NO. 855</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Christmas Day, 2012, local RCMP detachment officers made a visit to the Milford Haven Home for Special Care; and</p>
<p>Whereas Sgt. Justin Simpson went to visit the residents of the local Milford Haven Home for Special Care, to spread a little Christmas cheer and serve the residents their Christmas dinner; and</p>
<p>Whereas a great visit with dinner and a few good laughs was enjoyed by the local RCMP officers and Milford Haven Home for Special Care residents;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly acknowledge the dedication to the community shown by local RCMP detachment officer Justin Simpson, who willingly gave some of his Christmas Day to serve dinner and visit with the residents of the Milford Haven Home for Special Care.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0"><num title="856">RESOLUTION NO. 856</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Christmas Day, 2011, Canso RCMP detachment officers made a visit to the Canso Seaside Manor; and</p>
<p>Whereas Cst. Ron Hines went to visit the residents of the local Canso Seaside Manor to spread a little Christmas cheer and serve the residents their Christmas dinner; and</p>
<p>Whereas a great visit with dinner and a few good laughs was enjoyed by Canso RCMP officers and Canso Seaside Manor residents;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly acknowledge the dedication to the community shown by Canso RCMP detachment officer Cst. Ron Hines, who willingly gave some of his Christmas Day to serve dinner and visit with the residents of the Canso Seaside Manor.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0"><num title="857">RESOLUTION NO. 857</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas January 1, 2012, saw a Canso tradition reach its 22<sup>nd</sup> year as white caps and 70 kilometre wind gusts welcomed approximately 20 Polar Bear Dip swimmers; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the swimmers was June Jarvis Richard who, at the age of 73, was the oldest participant in the annual Canso Polar Dip Group since she considers the polar dip a "life affirming event"; and</p>
<p>Whereas the first Canso Polar Bear Dip, which originated from jokes about swimming in Canso's cold winter waters and since that time the event has captured the interest of many spectators, with over 100 people gathering this year to witness this 22<sup>nd</sup> Annual Canso Polar Bear Dip;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly acknowledge June Jarvis Richard for her ongoing commitment to the local polar dip tradition and hope she enjoys continued good health which will allow her to participate in the future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0"><num title="858">RESOLUTION NO. 858</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas January 1, 2012, saw a Canso tradition reach its 22<sup>nd</sup> year as white caps and 70 kilometre wind gusts welcomed approximately 20 polar bear dip swimmers; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the swimmers was Lucy Avery, one of the original members of the Canso Polar Dip Group, who hasn't missed out once in the 22 years; and</p>
<p>Whereas the first Canso Polar Bear Dip, which originated from jokes about swimming in Canso's cold winter waters and since that time the event has captured the interest of many spectators, with over 100 people gathering this year to witness this 22<sup>nd</sup> Annual Canso Polar Bear Dip;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly acknowledge Lucy Avery's commitment to the local polar dip tradition and hope she will continue to participate in the years to come.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#98fd525a-b480-446d-8a4d-f002d18eb5c0"><num title="859">RESOLUTION NO. 859</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas January 1, 2012, saw a Canso tradition reach its 22<sup>nd</sup> year as white caps and 70 kilometre wind gusts welcomed approximately 20 polar bear dip swimmers; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the swimmers was Mike Geddes, one of the original members of the Canso Polar Dip Group, who hasn't missed a dip in the 22 years; and</p>
<p>Whereas the first Canso Polar Bear Dip, which originated from jokes about swimming in Canso's cold winter waters and since that time the event has captured the interest of many spectators, with over 100 people gathering this year to witness this 22<sup>nd</sup> Annual Canso Polar Bear Dip;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly acknowledge Mike Geddes' commitment to the local polar dip tradition and wish him well as he continues to take future plunges in the cool and refreshing Canso water.</p></speech>
      </noticesOfMotion>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
