<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="keith.colwell" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.keith.colwell" showAs="HON. KEITH COLWELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="frank.corbett" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.frank.corbett" showAs="HON. FRANK CORBETT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="jamie.baillie" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.jamie.baillie" showAs="HON. JAMIE BAILLIE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="allan.gerard.macmaster" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.allan.gerard.macmaster" showAs="MR. ALLAN MACMASTER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="christopher.a.dentremont" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.christopher.a.dentremont" showAs="HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="keith.bain" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.keith.bain" showAs="MR. KEITH BAIN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="marilyn.more" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.marilyn.more" showAs="HON. MARILYN MORE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="karen.casey" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.karen.casey" showAs="HON. KAREN CASEY"/>
        <TLCPerson id="kelly.regan" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.kelly.regan" showAs="Ms. Kelly Regan"/>
        <TLCPerson id="zach.churchill" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.zach.churchill" showAs="Mr. Zach Churchill"/>
        <TLCPerson id="diana.whalen" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.diana.whalen" showAs="Ms. Diana Whalen"/>
        <TLCPerson id="stephen.mcneil" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.stephen.mcneil" showAs="Hon. Stephen McNeil"/>
        <TLCPerson id="leonard.preyra" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.leonard.preyra" showAs="Hon. Leonard Preyra"/>
        <TLCPerson id="andrew.younger" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.andrew.younger" showAs="Mr. Andrew Younger"/>
        <TLCPerson id="jim.boudreau" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.jim.boudreau" showAs="Mr. Jim Boudreau"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MR. SPEAKER"/>
        <TLCRole id="sergeant-at-arms" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.sergeant-at-arms" showAs="SERGEANT-AT-ARMS"/>
        <TLCRole id="clerk" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.clerk" showAs="THE CLERK"/>
        <TLCRole id="administrator" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.administrator" showAs="THE ADMINISTRATOR"/>
        <TLCRole id="premier" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.premier" showAs="THE PREMIER"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 10 May 2013</docTitle>
      <docNumber>13-32</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2013-05-10">Friday, May 10, 2013</docDate>
      <docAuthority>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docAuthority>
      <legislature value="61">61st General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="5">5th Session</session>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://nslegislature.ca/index.php/proceedings/hansard/C90/house_13may10/"/>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Order, please.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Preston.</p></speech>
      <speech by="#keith.colwell"><from>HON. KEITH COLWELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I rise to raise a question of privilege and I am doing so at the earliest opportunity. Yesterday in the House of Assembly I was assaulted and threatened by the Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism; he is also the member for Waverley-Fall River-Beaver Bank.</p>
<p>O'Brien and Bosc defines a specific category of privilege which speaks directly to this event, to describe this as "Freedom from Obstruction, Interference, Intimidation, and Molestation" and states: "Speakers have consistently upheld the right of the House to the services of its Members, free from intimidation, obstruction and interference."</p>
<p>Furthermore, Maingot states that "Members are entitled to go about their Parliamentary business undisturbed. The assaulting, menacing, or insulting of any Member &#x2026; while he is coming or going to or from the House, or an account of his behaviour during a proceeding in Parliament, is a violation of the rights of Parliament. Any form of intimidation &#x2026; of a person for or on account of his behaviour during a proceeding in Parliament could amount to contempt."</p>
<p>This improper behaviour by the minister was quite clearly an execution of a threat and intimidation in an attempt to prevent me from performing my function as a legislator, an elected representative for my constituents, and a member of this Assembly.</p>
<p>With the above explanation, it is to you, as Speaker, that I have raised this <i>prima facie</i> question of privilege, I shall move the following resolution:</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the member for Waverley-Fall River-Beaver Bank be admonished by the Speaker for threats and intimidation and violating the rights of all members of the House of Assembly, through his actions, and that the matter be referred to the Committee on Internal Affairs and the committee's findings be reported back to the House without delay.</p>
<p>In light of the urgency of this matter, Mr. Speaker, I would please ask you to temporarily suspend the proceedings of the House until such time as you can rule on this matter.</p></speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="#frank.corbett">
        <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, we realize that the matter brought up by the member is, indeed, a serious one and a grave one in many respects, but the only thing I would like to put on the record for the House is that the member did take it upon himself to resign as a member of Executive Council and I would hope that would weigh in your decision. Thank you.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>Thank you. I will take a recess and consult with my staff on this matter and report back to the House as early as possible, so I'll suspend the proceedings for a time, until I can meet with my staff and make the decision. Thank you.</p>
      </speech>
      <narrative>
        <p>9:12 a.m. The House recessed.</p>
      </narrative>
      <narrative>
        <p>10:43 a.m. The House reconvened.</p>
      </narrative>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Order, please.</p>
<p><b>SPEAKER'S RULING:</b> Matter of privilege and contempt (Pt. of privilege by Hon. K. Colwell [Hansard p. 2347, May 10/13]) a <i>prima facie</i> case of breach of privilege and of contempt.</p>
<p>The member for Preston has raised a matter of privilege and contempt. Members will remember that I outlined the principles surrounding a finding of a <i>prima facie</i> case of privilege on April 23, 2013. This is an un-rebutted allegation of assault of obstruction. According to the authorities, this is a matter of contempt and breach of privilege.</p>
<p>Following the principles I set out for the House, this constitutes a <i>prima facie</i> case of breach of privilege and of contempt. I considered the member for Waverley-Fall River-Beaver Bank's resignation from the Executive Council, as raised by the honourable Government House Leader, and while it did not go to the question of whether this is a <i>prima facie</i> case, it may be something the House may wish to take into consideration.</p>
<p>I have considered the proposed resolution and I understand that the member for Preston has agreed to restrict the motion to a referral to the Committee on Internal Affairs.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Preston.</p></speech>
      <speech by="#keith.colwell">
        <from>HON. KEITH COLWELL</from>
        <p>Therefore be it resolved that the matters related to the actions of the member for Waverley-Fall River-Beaver Bank be referred to the Committee on Internal Affairs and that the committee's finding be reported back to the House without delay.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>I direct the matter to be referred to the Committee on Internal Affairs.</p>
<p>We'll begin the daily routine.</p></speech>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#jamie.baillie"><num title="1669">RESOLUTION NO. 1669</num><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas family caregivers provide a crucial service to their loved ones in their time of need; and</p>
<p>Whereas May is Caregiver Awareness Month, a time devoted to showing gratitude and appreciation to those who work so hard to protect and care for our loved ones; and</p>
<p>Whereas Caregivers Nova Scotia will hold caregiver appreciation events across the province throughout the month of May to show how important the work they do is;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House recognize May as Caregiver Awareness Month, and the individuals who dedicate their days to protecting and caring for vulnerable Nova Scotians across the province.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Inverness.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#allan.gerard.macmaster"><num title="1670">RESOLUTION NO. 1670</num><from>MR. ALLAN MACMASTER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Larch Wood Canada of Margaree has been recognized, in the 29<sup>th</sup> Annual Nova Scotia Export Achievement Awards, for its excellence in achievement and exporting; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Nova Scotia Export Achievement Awards recognize the province's top exporters and celebrates excellence in Nova Scotia's export community; and</p>
<p>Whereas Larch Wood Canada has been acknowledged not only for contributions to the community but also to our province;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Larch Wood Canada on its recognition in the 29<sup>th</sup> Annual Nova Scotia Export Achievement Awards, and wish them many future years of success.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Argyle.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><num title="1671">RESOLUTION NO. 1671</num><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas May is Celiac Awareness Month; and</p>
<p>Whereas celiac disease is recognized as one of the most common chronic diseases in the world, and can only be treated by maintaining a gluten-free diet; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Acadian Celiac Association is the national voice for people who are adversely affected by gluten, and the Nova Scotia chapter has over 300 members and support groups in Baddeck, Cheticamp, Pictou County, and Sydney;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly mark May as Celiac Awareness Month, and recognize the Canadian Celiac Association for their dedication in raising awareness, understanding, and acceptance of this disease.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Victoria-The Lakes.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#keith.bain"><num title="1672">RESOLUTION NO. 1672</num><from>MR. KEITH BAIN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas May is Speech and Hearing Awareness Month; and</p>
<p>Whereas for 35 years the Speech and Hearing Association of Nova Scotia has represented professionals in the areas of speech, language, and hearing as they dedicate their lives to bettering the communications of Nova Scotians; and</p>
<p>Whereas communication challenges can have a significant impact on the daily lives of those individuals;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize May as Speech and Hearing Awareness Month and do our part to be advocates for individuals with communication challenges, and thank the dedicated professionals in their field.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT BUSINESS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#frank.corbett">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Public Bills for Third Reading.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PUBLIC BILLS FOR THIRD READING</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#frank.corbett">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 61.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 61 - Cyber-safety Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Minister of the Public Service Commission.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#marilyn.more"><from>HON. MARILYN MORE</from><p>Thank you, Mr. Speaker. I ask for, through you, the indulgence of the House, because this could possibly be the last time I have the opportunity to address my colleagues. And so in the spirit of that, I would just ask for perhaps a little more attention than one usually gives to third reading speeches.</p>
<p>So, Mr. Speaker, I move that Bill No. 61 be now read a third time.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, cyberbullying has been very much on all Nova Scotians' minds over the last few weeks, and this issue has touched so many people very deeply; emotions are high. We have all in this Chamber collectively worked to address this issue and ensure Nova Scotians are protected. And I've spoken with many people - parents, teenagers, educators, members of this House - who have all been asking themselves, what can I do?</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, it's not every day that we see this kind of united focus on an important problem. Nova Scotians have told us that they want us to address this issue, and I have found their concern and their determination inspiring - I think we all have. It is the determination of Nova Scotians to see lasting change that has inspired this groundbreaking legislation. We want, and need, to protect Nova Scotians from on-line bullying, which has become a major issue for our young people, in particular, in recent years. Other provinces have introduced legislation to deal with this problem but, for the most part, their legislation deals only with bullying in schools. And as we know, while cyberbullying affects the school environment, it doesn't stop when the three o'clock bell rings.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, we have worked hard to address the problem from a system-wide perspective. Nova Scotians told us that there's often a gap between on-line behaviour that is considered criminal, and cyberbullying that is clearly designated to harm someone, but is not covered by the Criminal Code of Canada. When that happens, families have told us, they don't know where to turn. They are upset; they are frustrated; and they often feel like no one can help.</p>
<p>We believe this legislation will give victims and their families the tools they need to address cyberbullying when it happens; we also believe the measures we have introduced in this bill will help discourage people from engaging in cyberbullying behaviour. Mr. Speaker, the Cyber-safety Bill would allow victims and their families to go to the court to get a protection order if someone is repeatedly harassing them on-line. The protection order could demand simply that a person stop talking to or about another person on-line and, in more extreme cases, a judge could also order that a person give up their computer, smart phone, or any other electronic device - or even that they cut off their Internet connection. And violating a protection order would carry a penalty of up to $5,000 or a jail term of up to six months.</p>
<p>Those victim protection orders are a section of this legislation that could take effect quite quickly. The Cyber-safety Bill also makes it possible for victims and their families to sue in civil court. And if the person accused of cyber-bullying is a minor their parents could be held liable for damages - parents would then have to prove to the court that they made reasonable efforts to ensure their child did not engage in this behaviour.</p>
<p>In today's world, most parents know they need to teach their children about proper on-line behaviour, and I believe many Nova Scotian parents are having these conversations with their children on a regular basis, especially in the last few weeks. There are materials already available, and being developed, to support parents regarding responsible use and reasonable monitoring.</p>
<p>The Cyber-safety Bill simply makes it clear that there can be financial consequences for those who engage in cyberbullying or those who don't properly monitor their children's on-line behaviour. This bill also establishes Canada's first investigative unit dedicated to cyberbullying. People have told us that when they or a loved one are bullied on-line they don't know where to turn for help, so put simply, this unit is a place where anyone can take their concerns over cyberbullying and know they will be heard.</p>
<p>The final piece of this legislation that I'd like to talk about is an amendment to the Education Act. Nova Scotians have told us that it was not always clear who could address an issue of cyberbullying if it happened outside school hours or off school grounds. The Act will clarify that principals can deal with a situation of cyberbullying if it affects the school environment and it will ensure that principals and school boards are able to co-operate with provincial agencies like the Cyber SCAN Unit.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, we are moving ahead in consultation with all Parties, and I thank everyone for their input and their advice. I think it's important to note that we have made amendments to the legislation as requested by the Opposition. We know this issue is important to members on all sides of the House and we have taken your views into account. Over the last few weeks especially many Nova Scotians who have experienced bullying and cyberbullying have told their stories. They often feel helpless, they feel as though no one is listening and no one can help. This Act will help to alleviate the terrible feeling of powerlessness in situations like this. But it is not all that we are doing to address this important issue. We have asked the federal government for changes to the Criminal Code of Canada that would make it a crime to distribute intimate pictures without consent for a malicious or sexual purpose.</p>
<p>We've been meeting with community and women's groups, youth, health and educational professionals, and others to identify gaps in services for those affected by cyberbullying and sexual assault. We've made an additional $900,000 available for programs across the province to support victims of sexual violence, and we are reviewing the actions of all agencies involved and coordinating a provincial education campaign to ensure Nova Scotians know where to get help if they need it.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, we will not stop there. We are committed to making changes across this province wherever they are needed. This legislation and the work that has supported it, and the work that will come, is a reminder to us all inside and outside of this House that if we stand together we can accomplish great things. Nova Scotians are watching what we're doing together, Canada is watching and the world is watching, and we will do what is needed to support Nova Scotians struggling to deal with the issues of sexual violence and cyberbullying. We want to make Nova Scotia a more supportive and stronger province for everyone.</p>
<p>I just want to add with the House's indulgence that this has been a life-transforming experience for me over the past month. I have met with so many people who work so hard on these issues and so better understand what needs to be done. It is obvious that there is lots of interest across all levels of government, across community organizations, within families, across communities that we need to work together on these issues, and we need to work together in a different way because it's one thing - this bill is just a small slice of the action and attention that needs to be taken.</p>
<p>We need to do so much more to change the cultural attitudes about sexual violence, we need to be talking about some of the root causes of these larger issues, and for the first time in my life I have seen the will, the collective will of Nova Scotians to want to make a difference now and we need to use that momentum, that keen interest to work together on this very important issue.</p>
<p>We all in this House have a responsibility as individual MLAs to be a catalyst in our own home communities, to bring groups together who have perhaps traditionally not worked together before, and to encourage governments and organizations to expand their mandate to cover some of these issues. We all need to work together in a way that we have never seen. It really begins with us, each of us.</p>
<p>I would like to suggest - and this, I have to say, is not coming out of any recent situations; it is part of a discussion that I've had with many members in this House over many years. I think it's time that this House look at the rules and procedures so that everyone feels included, everyone feels they have a role to play, and that we're able to harness the collective energy and goodwill of every member of this House. We can do a better job and I know that we will. Thank you. (Standing Ovation)</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Colchester North.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#karen.casey"><from>HON. KAREN CASEY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I'm pleased to rise again in this House to speak to the issue of bullying and cyberbullying and in particular to Bill No. 61 that is before us for third reading.</p>
<p>I want to thank the minister for her remarks and her moving third reading. I do want to say that, as the Education Critic, as an educator, and on behalf of all of the Liberal caucus, how pleased we were when this file was passed on to the Minister responsible for the Advisory Council on the Status of Women Act. We recognize the strength of her leadership and we believed that would allow us, as Members of the Legislative Assembly, to move forward to deal with an issue that is before us daily.</p>
<p>Our Leader spoke to his willingness to co-operate with the minister, to provide advice, direction, whatever was sought by the minister. I know that some of those meetings and conversations have been held and I truly believe, as I've said here in the House many times, when there is an issue and when we can collectively have input into the legislation that will address that, we do have stronger legislation.</p>
<p>The purpose of Bill No. 61 is to provide safer communities by creating administrative and court processes that can be used to address and prevent cyberbullying. We know that in this House, we have had Bill No. 30 and we have had Bill No. 102. Both of those times, those bills came before the House and the Committee on Law Amendments, and the Liberal caucus presented amendments. Again, in that spirit of trying to provide some more information and some more direction that would help strengthen the legislation, we have done that again with Bill No. 61 and when our amendments were read at the Committee on Law Amendments on Bill No. 61, it was deferred so the committee could have time to look at those amendments. I was pleased to see some of them incorporated into the amendments that came forward from government.</p>
<p>I was also encouraged to hear that what was in those amendments that did not come out as part of the bill would be addressed through regulations and policy. As a caucus and as the critic, we will be watching to see that because we believe strongly that those amendments must be addressed in some way.</p>
<p>We know that our young people are caught up in a social net. Some of them cannot get out of that. Many of the issues that are affecting and bothering and tormenting our young people are played out in our schools and in our classrooms. It's a broader issue than our public schools, the minister has acknowledged that, and so I think we have to recognize that it is a community issue. Schools, educators are one part of that community and anything we can do, any tools that we can give those people in our public schools to try to address that, is important.</p>
<p>We know, Mr. Speaker, that we're looking at changing attitudes and values and culture. Those things are not changed quickly or easily so every step that we can take towards that goal is one step that we should all be proud of. I want to thank the minister for her leadership. I'm pleased to know that the communication between the minister and our Leader has taken place and I believe that the amendments we put forward have helped to strengthen this. Thank you. (Applause)</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#jamie.baillie"><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I would like to begin by thanking the minister for her work on this important issue and her leadership and express our appreciation that the Premier turned to that particular member, that particular minister when we all needed to come together on this very important effort around bullying and cyberbullying.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, if I may - it is a possibility, to say the least, that the minister's remarks here today may be her last in this Chamber. If they are, I want to thank her for ending on a high note, which this clearly is. If this is her last action as an elected official, to have brought forward a bill of this type to the Legislature and to guide it through to passage and enactment, then she truly has finished on a high note. If this is or not, we'll find out soon enough, but in case it is, I just wanted to express our appreciation. (Applause)</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, let me just take this opportunity to say that I know we all agree that we want to continuously send the message to our young people, to those who are victims of bullying and cyberbullying, that they always have a place to turn, that there is always a place to go, always a number to call, an adult to turn to, a parent, a grandparent, a teacher, a social worker, a mental health worker.</p>
<p>Whatever your distress is as a young Nova Scotian, wherever you live in this province, when you feel that you are alone, that there is no one there to turn to, there is always someone there to turn to. When you are being harassed on-line, either anonymously or by your own friends, and you can't get away from it even at home, on your cellphone, on your laptop, on the school grounds, in what should be the safety of your own bedroom, never, ever again should a young Nova Scotian feel that they have no place to go for help.</p>
<p>This is a step in reinforcing that and making that point and making it true. That's why we support the bill and that's why we thank the minister for her work on this file, Mr. Speaker. I don't think we can reinforce enough that there's always a place for young Nova Scotians to turn when they need help, particularly from cyberbullying.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I said a moment ago, and I know we've said this as the bill has worked its way through our process, we certainly support the bill, will be voting in favour, will be encouraging the government to have it enacted into law and put into effect as soon as possible. It is definitely a big step in the right direction. As all Nova Scotians sadly know, our province became the center of national and even international attention a month ago because of a tragedy that we had in our province, in part because of cyberbullying. A very complex series of events, a very sad ending.</p>
<p>We want to make sure that we make news, nationally and beyond, in better ways in the future, particularly when it comes to bullying and cyberbullying, by making sure our province is a leader in protecting our young people, in putting in place laws that give them the tools they need to protect themselves, give law enforcement officials and schools and teachers and the community itself the tools they need to be safe and to keep young people safe.</p>
<p>Cyberbullying is a 21<sup>st</sup> Century phenomenon and it requires 21<sup>st</sup> Century laws. This bill is definitely a step in that direction, and a big one. I say that sincerely, it's a big one. It includes many items not previously in law at all, that reflect the modern technology reality that we live in.</p>
<p>I am pleased to see that the minister did take up the suggestions that we made. I know she and I met personally to go over some of our own research, as a PC caucus, and some of our own ideas on how to make the law reflect the 21<sup>st</sup> Century and they are incorporated in the bill.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I hope that Nova Scotians today see that when we do combine our ideas that good legislation can be brought forward. That truly is happening today and I'm delighted to see that and I thank the minister for her open-mindedness on that. She offered it on her first day in this new assignment and we offered it in exchange and good things happened.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, of course the work will go on. This is an ongoing effort. We can't declare victory today over bullying and cyberbullying and I know that the minister and I'm sure every member in this House agrees that we'll always be vigilant to make sure that our laws keep up with modern, 21<sup>st</sup> Century reality, all the benefits that come from new technology and the threats that come from new technology.</p>
<p>To that end, Mr. Speaker, I do just want to point out that there is more work to be done. There were PC amendments that we brought forward at Law Amendments Committee and we brought forward in Committee of the Whole House On Bills a second time that we still believe are worthy of consideration by the government in the future, to provide an even stronger framework for the protection of young Nova Scotians from cyberbullying.</p>
<p>For example, Mr. Speaker - and I won't dwell on them because this is an important milestone today - but I just want to again raise the need that we have to educate young Nova Scotians and their parents and adult Nova Scotians about the new responsibilities that we believe they now have as citizens in the digital age, that there is an educational component in our school curriculum and for adults' education, in ways to deliver to adults, the power that they now have in their hands, in their cellphones or on their laptops that can do great things in collaborating and changing ideas, to make the world a better place.</p>
<p>That is one of the great opportunities of the new technology in the digital world but it can also do great harm and that veil of anonymity that cowardly people hide behind when they want to hurt others is just too powerful in the digital age. That's why we need strong laws and that's why we need to educate our young people in school, in the curriculum, on the rights and responsibilities of a digital citizen in the 21<sup>st</sup> Century, so they know the power for good and for bad that they have in their hands.</p>
<p>The same with adults, Mr. Speaker, we need to make sure they get the information about how to monitor their kids and how to monitor their own activities, to protect each other. These are part of a series of reforms that I hope we'll look at at a future date, to make our province an even stronger leader in 21<sup>st</sup> Century laws around bullying and cyberbullying. When we do that, we will truly have made news nationally and beyond, as a leader here in Nova Scotia on this unfortunate 21<sup>st</sup> Century problem that we have, but that is for another day.</p>
<p>I sincerely want to thank the minister for her hard work and her quick turn-around on such an important file and reinforce that despite our differences, we agree on this one, and we'll be voting in favour and watching as it gets put into law and then making sure that all the resources are there to make the words of the bill truly come into play in real life and in real practice. With those few words, Mr. Speaker, I'll take my place and thank you. (Applause)</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for third reading of Bill No. 61. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that the bill do pass. Ordered that the title be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bill be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#frank.corbett">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, that concludes the government's business. I wonder if we could take a short recess while we await the arrival of the Lieutenant Governor.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is to recess until the Lieutenant Governor arrives.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <narrative>
        <p>11:14 a.m. The House recessed.</p>
      </narrative>
      <narrative>
        <p>11:40 a.m. The House reconvened.</p>
      </narrative>
      <speech by="" as="#sergeant-at-arms" status="undefined">
        <from>SERGEANT-AT-ARMS</from>
        <p>His Honour the Administrator is without.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>Let His Honour be admitted.</p>
      </speech>
      <narrative>
        <p>The Speaker and the Clerks left the Chamber.</p>
      </narrative>
      <speech by="" as="#sergeant-at-arms" status="undefined">
        <from>SERGEANT-AT-ARMS</from>
        <p>His Honour the Administrator.</p>
      </speech>
      <narrative><p>The Administrator, Chief Justice Hon. J. Michael MacDonald, preceded by his escort and by Mr. Ken Greenham, Sergeant-at-Arms, bearing the Mace, entered the House of Assembly Chamber. The Administrator then took his seat on the Throne.</p>
<p>His Honour, the Administrator, Chief Justice Michael MacDonald, entered the House of Assembly Chamber.</p>
<p>The Sergeant-at-Arms then departed and re-entered the Chamber, followed by the Speaker, the Honourable Gordie Gosse; the Chief Clerk of the House, Neil Ferguson; and the Assistant Clerk, Annette Boucher.</p>
<p>The Speaker, with the Sergeant-at-Arms on his right and the Clerk on his left, took up his position at the foot of the Speaker's Table.</p></narrative>
      <speech by="" as="#sergeant-at-arms" status="undefined">
        <from>SERGEANT-AT-ARMS</from>
        <p>It is the wish of His Honour that the ladies and gentlemen be seated.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>May it please Your Honour, the General Assembly of the Province has, at its present session, passed certain bills to which in the name and on behalf of the General Assembly, I respectfully request Your Honour's Assent.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined"><from>THE CLERK</from><p><b>Bill No. 3 - Support for Parents of Critically Ill or Abducted Children Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 32 - Solemnization of Marriage Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 36 - Provincial Court Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 37 - Innovative Transportation Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 42 - Pension Benefits Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 43 - Trustees of Onslow Cemetery Company Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 51 - Financial Measures (2013) Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 54 - Widows' Pension Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 55 - Protection of Animal Welfare and Security Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 57 - Language Schools Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 59 - Canada-Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Resources Accord Implementation (Nova Scotia) Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 61 - Cyber-safety Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 62 - Protection for Persons in Care Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 66 - Mariners' Day Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 67 - Elections Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 69 - Statute Amendments (2013) Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 70 - Medical Imaging and Radiation Therapy Professionals Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 71 - House of Assembly Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 72 - House of Assembly Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 73 - House of Assembly Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 74 - House of Assembly Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 75 - House of Assembly Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 76 - Adult Protection Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 78 - Canada-Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Resources Accord Implementation (Nova Scotia) Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 80 - Members' Retiring Allowances Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 81 - Builders' Lien Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 82 - Provincial Flag Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 83 - Halifax Regional Municipality Charter.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 84 - District of Barrington Health Professionals Assistance Act.</b></p></speech>
      <speech by="" as="#administrator" status="undefined">
        <from>THE ADMINISTRATOR</from>
        <p>In Her Majesty's name, I Assent to these Bills.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>Your Honour, having been graciously pleased to give your Assent to the Bills passed during the present session, it becomes my agreeable duty on behalf of Her Majesty's dutiful and loyal subjects, Her faithful commons of Nova Scotia to present to Your Honour a bill for the Appropriation of Supply granted in the present session for the support of the Public Service, and to request Your Honour's Assent thereto.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined">
        <from>THE CLERK</from>
        <p>An Act to Provide for Defraying Certain Charges and Expenses of the Public Service of the Province.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="" as="#administrator" status="undefined">
        <from>THE ADMINISTRATOR</from>
        <p>In Her Majesty's name, I thank her loyal subjects. I accept their benevolence and Assent to this Bill.</p>
      </speech>
      <narrative>
        <p>The Speaker and the Clerks left the Chamber.</p>
      </narrative>
      <narrative>
        <p>The Administrator left the Chamber.</p>
      </narrative>
      <speech by="" as="#sergeant-at-arms" status="undefined">
        <from>SERGEANT-AT-ARMS</from>
        <p>His Honour, the Speaker.</p>
      </speech>
      <narrative>
        <p>The Speaker took the Chair.</p>
      </narrative>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>I would ask all honourable members to please rise and join me in the singing of our national anthem.</p>
      </speech>
      <narrative>
        <p>The national anthem was sung by the members.</p>
      </narrative>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Thank you. Please be seated.</p>
<p>Before I recognize the honourable Premier I'd like to wish everybody health and happiness over the summer holidays and a safe trip home for all members. Enjoy your much needed time with your families and take care of yourselves and we'll see you again sometime.</p>
<p>The honourable Premier.</p></speech>
      <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
        <from>THE PREMIER</from>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, and members of the House of Assembly, I move that this General Assembly be adjourned, to meet again at the call of the Speaker.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>The House is adjourned until the call of the Speaker. (Applause)</p></speech>
      <narrative>
        <p>The House rose at 11:53 a.m.</p>
      </narrative>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION UNDER RULE 32(3)</heading>
        <speech by="#kelly.regan"><num title="1673">RESOLUTION NO. 1673</num><from>Ms. Kelly Regan</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas BlackBerry, formerly known as Research In Motion, has been rejuvenated with the launch of the Z10 and Q10 BlackBerrys and their new operating system; and</p>
<p>Whereas BlackBerry is expected to grow its customer base in 2013; and</p>
<p>Whereas BlackBerry is a key employer in the Bedford area;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate BlackBerry on its Z10/Q10 success, and wish the company all the best in its future endeavours.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#zach.churchill"><num title="1674">RESOLUTION NO. 1674</num><from>Mr. Zach Churchill</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Alex Gigeroff is one of Yarmouth's most prolific and renowned artists and orators; and</p>
<p>Whereas Alex's paintings, stories, and performances, have touched the hearts and minds of many in our local community and beyond; and</p>
<p>Whereas Alex's work often reflects his deep commitment to the well-being of humanity, his belief in our collective moral responsibility to one another, and his love of life and all the beauty it bestows;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly recognize Alex Gigeroff's profound contribution to the arts and his community, and thank him for being an instrument of good in the world.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#kelly.regan"><num title="1675">RESOLUTION NO. 1675</num><from>Ms. Kelly Regan</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Simone Meuse of West Pubnico fulfilled her lifelong dream of creating a book about angels just before she died, in 2012, of ovarian cancer; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ms. Meuse's book, titled <i>Angels, Angels Everywhere,</i> includes original poems and selected quotations about different kinds of angels, and is illustrated with her own delicate coloured-pencil drawings; and</p>
<p>Whereas after her death, <i>Angels, Angels Everywhere</i> was published by her husband Harold, who, to this day, continues to deliver this beautiful book to people everywhere who might be in need of comfort;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly thank both Simone and Harold Meuse for their generous gift, which is providing consolation to so many.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#diana.whalen"><num title="1676">RESOLUTION NO. 1676</num><from>Ms. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Queen Elizabeth II celebrated her accession to the throne 60 years ago with her Diamond Jubilee; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Medal was struck to commemorate this once-in-a-lifetime event, and Canadians who have made a difference or a significant contribution to our country have been presented with this medal throughout the year; and</p>
<p>Whereas Robert Patzelt, from Clayton Park, was nominated by the Canadian Maufacturers and Exporters Association and honoured with the presentation of a Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Medal for his dedication and commitment to supporting economic development and good public policy, and for his tremendous volunteer work in his community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly congratulate Robert Patzelt on his Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Medal, and acknowledge his dedication and commitment to helping our province and his community.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#stephen.mcneil"><num title="1677">RESOLUTION NO. 1677</num><from>Hon. Stephen McNeil</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Granville Ferry author Joyce Grant-Smith continues on the road to success in the writing of her latest novel, <i>Oatcakes and Courage</i>, which garnered her the prestigious honour of being named the winner of the Ken Klonsky Novella Contest; and</p>
<p>Whereas the subject of Grant-Smith's latest historical fiction novella, focusing on the voyage of the Ship Hector that set sail from Scotland in 1773, came about when she was researching the history of the Scottish settlers for her Grade 6 social studies class; and</p>
<p>Whereas this author has written three books, as well as numerous magazine articles, and in 2004, Grant-Smith was awarded the Joyce Barkhouse Writing for Children Award for her novel, "<i>The Latch: An Acadian Adventure</i>";</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly join me in congratulating Joyce on her latest recognition, and wish her continued inspiration and success in the future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#allan.gerard.macmaster"><num title="1678">RESOLUTION NO. 1678</num><from>Mr. Allan MacMaster</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Christine Campbell, of Mabou, has had two of her original songs selected as finalists in the 14<sup>th</sup> Annual Great American Song Contest; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Great American Song Contest recognizes songwriters from around the world for creative songwriting excellence; and</p>
<p>Whereas Christine has been acknowledged for her great songwriting ability internationally;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Christine Campbell on having two of her original songs chosen as finalists in the 14<sup>th</sup> Annual Great American Song Contest, and wish her continued success with her songwriting.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#stephen.mcneil"><num title="1679">RESOLUTION NO. 1679</num><from>Hon. Stephen McNeil</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas research scientist Tim Webster of the Centre of Geographic Sciences in Lawrencetown, will have the unique distinction of being the first scientist in Canada to lead the charge on a $2 million project aimed at mapping the shallow water known as "the white ribbon gap" along the coastlines of Nova Scotia; and</p>
<p>Whereas in the past equipment was too expensive and too large but now a lighter and cheaper design and the latest in imaging technology and high tech software will enable the scientific team to map seabed topography by air, revealing a wealth of data; and</p>
<p>Whereas the data collected will have practical application in predicting storm surge details, measuring coastal erosion, and assisting in determining best locations for aquaculture and the sustainable harvesting of sea plants;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly join me in recognizing research scientist Tim Webster in bringing this cutting edge technology to the province, and wish him well in his future research endeavours.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#allan.gerard.macmaster"><num title="1680">RESOLUTION NO. 1680</num><from>Mr. Allan MacMaster</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Hugh John Beaton of Port Hood has served as a custodian at Whycocomagh Education Centre for the past seven years; and</p>
<p>Whereas Hugh John has retired after 35 years in the school system; and</p>
<p>Whereas Hugh John has been a vital part of the Whycocomagh Education Centre and the other schools he has served;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly acknowledge Hugh John Beaton's retirement and wish him well in the next chapter of his life.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#diana.whalen"><num title="1681">RESOLUTION NO. 1681</num><from>Ms. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on November 1, 2012, <i>The Coast</i> publication released their annual "Best Of" edition, which named the Keshen Goodman Library one of their Gold Winners as Halifax's Best Library; and</p>
<p>Whereas this award is even more meaningful because it is the readers of <i>The Coast</i> who vote for this award; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Keshen Goodman Library is known in our area as a friendly and welcoming place full of dynamic programs and for its tremendous ability to meet the diverse needs of our community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the Nova Scotia Legislature congratulate the manager, Heather MacKenzie, and her staff at Keshen Goodman Library for being voted the Best Library in Halifax Regional Municipality by <i>The Coast's</i> readers, in recognition of its superior programs and great customer service, and wish them continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#diana.whalen"><num title="1682">RESOLUTION NO. 1682</num><from>Ms. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Rory Flynn, a Grade 9 student at Sacred Heart School of Halifax, was recognized here in the Legislature last week for her tremendous win in the Canadian debating championships at Queens University; and</p>
<p>Whereas Rory has followed up her Canadian debating achievement by finishing first at the British Under 15 National Debating Competition in Cambridge University on May 4, 2013; and</p>
<p>Whereas Rory demonstrated her outstanding debating skills and defeated 78 other students, primarily from England, Scotland and Wales, to bring home top honours from the International Competition for Young Debaters;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House congratulate Rory Flynn and her coach Brian Casey for her amazing debating success in Cambridge and for making her family, school and province proud once again.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#diana.whalen"><num title="1683">RESOLUTION NO. 1683</num><from>Ms. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Queen Elizabeth II celebrated her ascension to the Throne 60 years ago with her Diamond Jubilee; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Medal was struck to commemorate this once-in-a-lifetime event and Canadians who have made a difference or a significant contribution to our country have been presented with this medal throughout the year; and</p>
<p>Whereas Glenn Anderson from Clayton Park West was honoured with the presentation of a Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Medal at a special ceremony on August 17<sup>th</sup>, 2012, for his dedicated volunteer work within the legal profession and his community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly congratulate Glenn Anderson on his Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Medal and acknowledge with gratitude the great contribution he has made to his profession, his community and our province.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#leonard.preyra"><num title="1684">RESOLUTION NO. 1684</num><from>Hon. Leonard Preyra</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Saint Mary's University Model United Nations Society is a group of politically engaged students who strive to gain a new appreciation for the political process through participation in the annual National Model United Nations Conference; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Saint Mary's University Model United Nations Society, under the direction of faculty advisor Dr. Marc Doucet, participated in the 2013 National Model United Nations Conference in New York City from March 17 to 21, representing the Kingdom of Sweden; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Saint Mary's University Model United Nations Society earned a Distinguished Delegation award at the 2013 National Model United Nations Conference, one of only three Canadian universities to earn this recognition, with Saint Mary's students also earning awards in the categories of Outstanding Delegate and Outstanding Position Paper;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly congratulates the members of the Saint Mary's University Model United Nations Society on their exemplary performance at the 2013 National Model United Nations conference and applauds their interest and engagement in the democratic process.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#leonard.preyra"><num title="1685">RESOLUTION NO. 1685</num><from>Hon. Leonard Preyra</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Theatre Nova Scotia's 14<sup>th</sup> annual Merritt Awards was held on Monday, March 25, 2013, at Casino Nova Scotia, in Halifax; and</p>
<p>Whereas many Nova Scotian Actors, directors, producers and designers were honoured for their work in the past year including: Hugh Thomson for best actor, playing 'Auto' in Plutonium Playhouse's <i>Whale Riding Weather</i>; Ann-Marie Kerr, best actress for playing 'Jean Perkins' in <i>Funny Money,</i> for Festival Antigonish; Anthony Black and Christian Barry of 2b theatre for direction of <i>The Story of Mr. Wright</i>; Daniel MacIvor for Best New Play by a Nova Scotian for <i>Communion </i>by the KAZAN Co-op; Hugo Dann with the Mayor's Award for Achievement in Theatre; and Stephanie MacDonald with the Mayor's Award for Emerging Artist; and</p>
<p>Whereas Theatre Nova Scotia, a non-profit organization, continues to encourage and support all aspects of live theatre in Nova Scotia through programs and services and its annual award celebration;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating all the winners and nominees of the Merritt Awards for their contribution to Nova Scotia's strong and vibrant arts and culture scene, and wish them and Theatre Nova Scotia continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#leonard.preyra"><num title="1686">RESOLUTION NO. 1686</num><from>Hon. Leonard Preyra</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Shakespeare by the Sea won the Merritt Legacy Award at Theatre Nova Scotia's 14<sup>th</sup> annual Merritt Awards held in Halifax on March 25<sup>th</sup>; and</p>
<p>Whereas Shakespeare by the Sea won this award for its 20-year contribution to arts and culture in the province; and</p>
<p>Whereas this artist-driven collective and largest outdoor theatre festival east of Montreal has been committed to the ongoing development of Nova Scotian and Canadian artists, and creating original works based on classic tales;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Shakespeare by the Sea and all of the winners and nominees of Merritt Awards for their contribution to Nova Scotia's strong and vibrant arts and culture scene, and wish them and Theatre Nova Scotia continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#leonard.preyra"><num title="1687">RESOLUTION NO. 1687</num><from>Hon. Leonard Preyra</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Soccer Nova Scotia, originally called the Nova Scotia Football Association, was formed in 1913 with headquarters in the YMCA building on Barrington Street; and</p>
<p>Whereas in the 100 years since its founding, Soccer Nova Scotia has grown to become the leading sport governing body in the province with more than 27,000 players, 2,500 coaches and 700 referees, all of whom are dedicated to the promotion of soccer among all ages and levels of play, regardless of gender, race, physical anomalies or ability to pay; and</p>
<p>Whereas on May 4, 2013, Soccer Nova Scotia Chief Executive Officer George Athanasioy and President Michael Maddalena will welcome community members to a celebration of 100 years of soccer in Nova Scotia, to be held in conjunction with the Canadian Soccer Association Annual General Meeting Dinner in Halifax;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this House of Assembly congratulate Soccer Nova Scotia on this centennial milestone and recognize the role of soccer in promoting a healthy lifestyle while instilling in players a strong sense of teamwork and community spirit.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1688">RESOLUTION NO. 1688</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Destination Imagination is an educational program where student teams solve open-ended challenges and present their solutions at tournaments; and</p>
<p>Whereas Margaret's House is a local non-profit organization that provides meals twice a day for those in need; and</p>
<p>Whereas the "7 Sevens" are a team of seven Grade 7 students at Caledonia Junior High School who held a charity bingo night in aid of Margaret's House as part of their challenge to end hunger and part of their destination Imagination challenge;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly recognize the 7 Sevens team of Genevieve MacDonald, Lauren Regan, Meggie Rennie, Olivia Colaiacovo, Sara James, Megan MacDonald, Maria Sotiropoulos and team manager Kathy Colaiacovo on their outstanding efforts so far in raising almost $2,500 for Margaret's House.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1689">RESOLUTION NO. 1689</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Tatamagouche, Colchester North is hosting a train convention of model trains on May 31<sup>st</sup> and June 1<sup>st</sup> and in recognition of the event Colchester County Council has proclaimed the week of May 27 to June 2 as Train Days in the municipality; and</p>
<p>Whereas model trains will be set up in the North Shore Recreation Centre and there will also be a display of art work relating to trains by the local elementary school students; and</p>
<p>Whereas VIA Rail is sponsoring a prize for the winning entry from each class, which will entail a free train ride for the winner and an accompanying adult from Truro to Amherst;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Tatamagouche, Colchester North, for this innovative undertaking, for using this as an educational experience for the elementary students, and for giving train lovers of all ages such an educational and enjoyable experience.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1690">RESOLUTION NO. 1690</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the February 2013, Student of the Month at North Colchester High School in Tatamagouche, Colchester North, is Grade 12 student Rielle Hoeg; and</p>
<p>Whereas Rielle is an excellent academic student who has maintained an honours with distinction average from Grade 7 - 12 and placed No. 1 in Nova Scotia and in the top 1 per cent nationally in the Michael Smith Science Challenge; and</p>
<p>Whereas Rielle is involved in school and community by acting as a water safety instructor, a lifeguard, a childcare provider, a peer mentor for Big Brothers, Big Sisters, co-chair of the Prom and SafeGrad Committees, a member of STOP and the GSA and the Girl's Leadership Program;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Rielle Hoeg for her outstanding academic ability, her excellent work ethic, her many contributions to school and community, and for the honour of being named Student of the Month.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1691">RESOLUTION NO. 1691</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on May 7<sup>th</sup> the North Shore Area Community Health Board is hosting a wellness expo and grant showcase at the Tatamagouche Fire Hall in Colchester North; and</p>
<p>Whereas the event will highlight projects funded by grants received during the past couple of years to raise community awareness about how the Community Health Board contributes to wellness, how to get involved in local wellness programs, and how to access the wide range of services the district health authority offers; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteer-based groups such as the Lillian Fraser Memorial Hospital Auxiliary and the North Shore Health Services Foundation will showcase their roles in the local health care;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate the North Shore Area Community Health Board for their initiative in organizing such an informative event, and wish them a successful and productive evening.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1692">RESOLUTION NO. 1692</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Dreams Take Flight Program, started by Air Canada for students in Toronto in 1989, has branched out so hundreds of young people are given a chance to experience Disney World for the first time; and</p>
<p>Whereas the student must be between the ages of 7 and 12, have never been to Disney World, and must have the stamina to handle a more that 20-hour long day; and</p>
<p>Whereas the student will travel on an all-expense paid trip to Orlando on April 23 for a one-day, whirlwind visit to Disney World;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate 11 year old Nehalem Bigney, a Grade 5 student from North River Elementary School, Colchester North, for being chosen as the recipient of this trip of a lifetime, and wish him a very happy, rewarding experience.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1693">RESOLUTION NO. 1693</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the mission to bring images of the Pulitzer Prize winning poet Elizabeth Bishop, who spent part of her youth in Great Village, Colchester North, began with a celebration marking Bishop's 100<sup>th</sup> birthday in August 2011; and</p>
<p>Whereas colourful banners adorned utility poles during the celebration, the Elizabeth Society of Nova Scotia created the Images of My Village; A Permanent Banner Project and Online Exhibition for Youth in Colchester County; and</p>
<p>Whereas 200 entries were received and a panel of guest judges selected one entry for the permanent banner, while a postcard was made of another because of its artwork and creativity, but all entries may be viewed online as part of a Web site which was set up by two NSCC students in the IT Program;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Elizabeth Bishop Society of Nova Scotia for providing this experience for the students who participated, including the Celebration of Creativity Day being held at the Great Village School gymnasium on May 18<sup>th</sup> where free workshops, speakers and lunch are being provided for these students.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#stephen.mcneil"><num title="1694">RESOLUTION NO. 1694</num><from>Hon. Stephen McNeil</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Marilyn Coleman and 220 of her closest friends and neighbours from the community of Nictaux, Annapolis County, will start their day off right as they join together for a community breakfast celebration; and</p>
<p>Whereas Marilyn, in capturing a Kodak moment of her grandson Romeo making his first snow angel, netted the "Take the Roof Off Winter" Facebook contest grand prize in a provincial-wide contest; and</p>
<p>Whereas her photo won her the most "likes" on Facebook, she gets to share her contest grand prize of a community breakfast with her Nictaux counterparts on Saturday, May 25<sup>th</sup>;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Marilyn on her win and encourage her to keep entering photo contests with her award-wining subject and grandson, Romeo.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1695">RESOLUTION NO. 1695</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Brooke Brown is a Grade 11 student at Colchester North High School in Tatamagouche; and</p>
<p>Whereas Brooke is an eager, conscientious student whose interpersonal skills make her an excellent friend, helper, and a natural leader; and</p>
<p>Whereas Brooke is a dedicated, hardworking athlete who plays on the school soccer and basketball teams, has competed in badminton and track and field, and is also a talented singer and pianist;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Brooke Brown, a well-rounded student whose work ethic, positive attitude, participation and pleasant personality contributed to her selection as the February 2013, student of the month.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1696">RESOLUTION NO. 1696</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas The ChronicleHerald recently hosted the 5<sup>th</sup> annual Nova Scotia Spelling Bee; and</p>
<p>Whereas 54 finalists from Grade 4 to Grade 8 from across mainland Nova Scotia, and for the first time from Cape Breton schools, compete for the provincial championship and right to represent Nova Scotia at the Scripps National Spelling Bee in Washington, D.C.; and</p>
<p>Whereas these students display the best characteristics of competition and show both poise and self-assurance during very pressure-packed moments;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Katelyn Hoeg, a Grade 5 student at North River Elementary School in North River, Colchester North, for her superior spelling ability and for being selected as one of the 54 finalists in this very challenging competition.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1697">RESOLUTION NO. 1697</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas The ChronicleHerald recently hosted the 5<sup>th</sup> annual Nova Scotia Spelling Bee; and</p>
<p>Whereas 54 finalists from Grade 4 to Grade 8 from across mainland Nova Scotia and, for the first time, from Cape Breton schools, competed for the provincial championship and right to represent Nova Scotia at the Scripps National Spelling Bee in Washington, D.C.; and</p>
<p>Whereas these students display the best characteristics of competition, and show both poise and self-assurance during very pressure-packed moments;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ryan Spencer, a Grade 6 student at West Colchester Consolidated School in Bass River, Colchester North, for his superior spelling ability, and for being selected as one of the 54 finalists in this very challenging competition.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1698">RESOLUTION NO. 1698</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Medal was created to mark the 60<sup>th</sup> Anniversary of Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II's accession to the throne as Queen of Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas the medal is not only a way for Canada to honour Her Majesty for her service, but also to honour contributions and achievements by Canadians; and</p>
<p>Whereas a medal recipient must be a Canadian citizen and have made a significant contribution to a particular province, territory, region, or community within Canada, or an achievement abroad that brings credit to Canada;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Neil Morash, a World War II veteran and member of the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 72, Great Village, Colchester North, as the recipient of a Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Medal for his service to his country.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1699">RESOLUTION NO. 1699</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Medal was created to mark the 60<sup>th</sup> Anniversary of Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II's accession to the throne as Queen of Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas the medal is not only a way for Canada to honour Her Majesty for her service, but also to honour contributions and achievements by Canadians; and</p>
<p>Whereas a medal recipient must be a Canadian citizen and have made a significant contribution to a particular province, territory, region, or community within Canada, or an achievement abroad that brings credit to Canada;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Reg Myatt, a World War II veteran and member of the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 72, Great Village, Colchester North, as the recipient of a Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Medal for his service to his country.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1700">RESOLUTION NO. 1700</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Medal was created to mark the 60<sup>th</sup> Anniversary of Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II's accession to the throne as Queen of Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas the medal is not only a way for Canada to honour Her Majesty for her service, but also to honour contributions and achievements by Canadians; and</p>
<p>Whereas a medal recipient must be a Canadian citizen and have made a significant contribution to a particular province, territory, region, or community within Canada, or an achievement abroad that brings credit to Canada;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Walter Perrin, a World War II veteran and member of the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 72, Great Village, Colchester North, as the recipient of a Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Medal for his service to his country.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1701">RESOLUTION NO. 1701</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Medal was created to mark the 60<sup>th</sup> Anniversary of Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II's accession to the throne as Queen of Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas the medal is not only a way for Canada to honour Her Majesty for her service, but also to honour contributions and achievements by Canadians; and</p>
<p>Whereas a medal recipient must be a Canadian citizen and have made a significant contribution to a particular province, territory, region, or community within Canada, or an achievement abroad that brings credit to Canada;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Myles Rushton, a World War II veteran and member of the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 72, Great Village, Colchester North, as the recipient of a Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Medal for his service to his country.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1702">RESOLUTION NO. 1702</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Medal was created to mark the 60<sup>th</sup> Anniversary of Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II's accession to the throne as Queen of Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas the medal is not only a way for Canada to honour Her Majesty for her service, but also to honour contributions and achievements by Canadians; and</p>
<p>Whereas a medal recipient must be a Canadian citizen and have made a significant contribution to a particular province, territory, region, or community within Canada, or an achievement abroad that brings credit to Canada;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Colchester County Mayor Bob Taylor, a recipient of a Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Medal, as selected by the Federation of Canadian Municipalities for his contributions to the community, including his involvement with minor hockey.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><num title="1703">RESOLUTION NO. 1703</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities" as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on February 7, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Ren&#xE9;e Surette and John Malone welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ren&#xE9;e and John on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><num title="1704">RESOLUTION NO. 1704</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities" as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on January 25, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Trina and Chris Adams welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Trina and Chris on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><num title="1705">RESOLUTION NO. 1705</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities" as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 12, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Haley and Francis Landry welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Haley and Francis on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><num title="1706">RESOLUTION NO. 1706</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities" as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on December 24, 2012, a very special occasion took place when Christine and Guy Rohland welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Christine and Guy on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><num title="1707">RESOLUTION NO. 1707</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities" as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 6, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Amanda and Joseph Muise welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Amanda and Joseph on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><num title="1708">RESOLUTION NO. 1708</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities" as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on January 8, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Candace and Jacques Surette welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Candace and Jacques on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><num title="1709">RESOLUTION NO. 1709</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities" as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on February 14, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Melissa and Derek Amirault welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Melissa and Derek on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><num title="1710">RESOLUTION NO. 1710</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities" as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on January 28, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Cindy and Michel Surette welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Cindy and Michel on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><num title="1711">RESOLUTION NO. 1711</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities" as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on December 31, 2012, a very special occasion took place when Jill and Adam Aldred welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jill and Adam on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><num title="1712">RESOLUTION NO. 1712</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities" as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on February 7, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Jeanette and Joshua Thompson welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jeanette and Joshua on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><num title="1713">RESOLUTION NO. 1713</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities" as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on March 3, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Ren&#xE9;e Corporon LeBlanc and Graham Spinney welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ren&#xE9;e and Graham on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><num title="1714">RESOLUTION NO. 1714</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities" as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on February 19, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Paula and Mark Hatfield welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Paula and Mark on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><num title="1715">RESOLUTION NO. 1715</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities" as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on February 18, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Justine and Gilles d'Entremont welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Justine and Gilles on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><num title="1716">RESOLUTION NO. 1716</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities" as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on February 5, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Chrissy and Rejean Doucette welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Chrissy and Rejean on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many more happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#diana.whalen"><num title="1717">RESOLUTION NO. 1717</num><from>Ms. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community and give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas on May 8, 2013, the Halifax Mainland North Volunteer Recognition Committee held their milestone 10<sup>th</sup> Annual Community Champion Awards Dinner to recognize outstanding volunteers who consistently dedicate their time and talents to improving the lives of others; and</p>
<p>Whereas Shirley MacDonald was nominated for this award by Jenn Hill of the English as a Second Language Program at the Keshen Goodman Library in recognition of the thoughtful and kind use of her teaching background to work as a tutor for newcomers to our province, helping them to develop skills that give them increased confidence and new-found independence;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House congratulate Shirley MacDonald on receiving a 2013 Community Champion Award, recognize the importance of her work, thank her for her dedication to helping newcomers to her community and province, and wish her every success in the future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#diana.whalen"><num title="1718">RESOLUTION NO. 1718</num><from>Ms. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community and give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas on May 8, 2013, the Halifax Mainland North Volunteer Recognition Committee held their milestone 10<sup>th</sup> Annual Community Champion Awards Dinner to recognize outstanding volunteers who consistently dedicate their time and talents to improving the lives of others; and</p>
<p>Whereas Sandra Starratt has been nominated for this award by Cydney Kane, a student at Halifax West High School, in recognition of her tireless devotion to the betterment of all students who attend Halifax West High School, and her dedication to sending them into the post-secondary world well prepared and confident in pursuing their dreams;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House congratulate Sandra Starratt on receiving a 2013 Community Champion Award, thank her for her dedication to helping the youth in her community and province, and wish her every success in the future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#diana.whalen"><num title="1719">RESOLUTION NO. 1719</num><from>Ms. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community and give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas on May 8, 2013, the Halifax Mainland North Volunteer Recognition Committee held their milestone 10<sup>th</sup> Annual Community Champion Awards Dinner to recognize outstanding volunteers who consistently dedicate their time and talents to improving the lives of others; and</p>
<p>Whereas Cathy Taylor has been nominated for this award by Patricia Roberts of the Adult Literacy Program in recognition of her kind and determined work as a tutor for the Keshen Goodman Library's Adult Literacy Program, helping others develop skills that give them new-found independence and opportunities for their lives;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House congratulate Cathy Taylor on receiving a 2013 Community Champion Award, thank her for her dedication to helping others in her community and province, and wish her every success in the future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#diana.whalen"><num title="1720">RESOLUTION NO. 1720</num><from>Ms. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community and give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas on May 8, 2013, the Halifax Mainland North Volunteer Recognition Committee held their milestone 10<sup>th</sup> Annual Community Champion Awards Dinner to recognize outstanding volunteers who consistently dedicate their time and talents to improving the lives of others; and</p>
<p>Whereas Cyril Courtney was nominated by the Chair of the Centennial Rink Commission, Emily Fougere, for his more than 40 years as a volunteer with the rink where he has been instrumental in ensuring it is well run and well maintained for the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House congratulate Cyril Courtney on receiving a 2013 Community Champion Award, thank him for his years of dedicated service to Centennial Rink, and wish him every success in the future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#diana.whalen"><num title="1721">RESOLUTION NO. 1721</num><from>Ms. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community and give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas on May 8, 2013, the Halifax Mainland North Volunteer Recognition Committee held their milestone 10<sup>th</sup> Annual Community Champion Awards Dinner to recognize outstanding volunteers who consistently dedicate their time and talents to improving the lives of others; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ratnam Mohan of Clayton Park West has been nominated for this award by Merrie Mills of the Indo-Canadian Association of Nova Scotia (INCA) in recognition of her tremendous contributions to preserving and celebrating Indian culture in our province through her volunteer work with INCA and the South Indian Dance team to name just two;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House congratulate Ratnam Mohan on receiving this prestigious 2013 Community Champion Award, thank her for her dedication to our cultural diversity and her willingness to step up and help others in her community, and wish her every success in the future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#diana.whalen"><num title="1722">RESOLUTION NO. 1722</num><from>Ms. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community and give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas on May 8, 2013, the Halifax Mainland North Volunteer Recognition Committee held their milestone 10<sup>th</sup> Annual Community Champion Awards Dinner to recognize outstanding volunteers who consistently dedicate their time and talents to improving the lives of others; and</p>
<p>Whereas Tanya Verge, who is well known for her willingness to step up and has volunteered for countless fundraisers, was nominated by the Northwood Foundation in recognition of her kindness and commitment to seniors as chair of the Northwood Action Committee and co-chair of the silent auction for the Appetite for Life event, which raised $164,000;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House congratulate Tanya Verge on receiving this prestigious 2013 Community Champion Award, thank her for her dedication to helping others in her community and province, and wish her every success in the future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#diana.whalen"><num title="1723">RESOLUTION NO. 1723</num><from>Ms. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community and give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas on May 8, 2013, the Halifax Mainland North Volunteer Recognition Committee held their milestone 10<sup>th</sup> Annual Community Champion Awards Dinner to recognize outstanding volunteers who consistently dedicate their time and talents to improving the lives of others; and</p>
<p>Whereas Michael Faddoul of Clayton Park has been nominated for this award by the president of the Canadian Lebanon Society of Halifax, in recognition of his tremendous contribution to the Lebanese community in our province through his volunteer work at our Lady of Lebanon Church in Halifax and his leadership roles in the Canadian Lebanon Society, which is commemorating its 75<sup>th</sup> Anniversary this year;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House congratulate Michael Faddoul on receiving this prestigious 2013 Community Champion Award, thank him for his dedication to helping preserve and celebrate the Lebanese cultural identity in our province, and wish him every success in the future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#diana.whalen"><num title="1724">RESOLUTION NO. 1724</num><from>Ms. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community and give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas on May 8, 2013, the Halifax Mainland North Volunteer Recognition Committee held their milestone 10<sup>th</sup> Annual Community Champion Awards Dinner to recognize outstanding volunteers who consistently dedicate their time and talents to improving the lives of others; and</p>
<p>Whereas Tony Eghan of Clayton Park has been nominated for this award by the Keshen Goodman Library, in recognition of his tireless volunteer work to instill the values of team building, leadership, friendship and community through the sport of soccer, as well as being one of the founding members of the African Diaspora Association of the Maritimes;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House congratulate Tony Eghan on receiving this prestigious 2013 Community Champion Award, thank him for his dedication to our youth and for helping preserve the African cultural identity in our province, and wish him every success in the future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#diana.whalen"><num title="1725">RESOLUTION NO. 1725</num><from>Ms. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers truly are the heart of our community and give freely of their time to help organizations throughout our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas on May 8, 2013, the Halifax Mainland North Volunteer Recognition Committee held their milestone 10<sup>th</sup> Annual Community Champion Awards Dinner to recognize outstanding volunteers who consistently dedicate their time and talents to improving the lives of others; and</p>
<p>Whereas Dr. Greg Burk has been nominated for this award by Bill Taylor of the Atlantic Salmon Federation, in recognition of his contributions to the conservation of the Atlantic Salmon species, through his role as the Canadian Director for the Atlantic Salmon Federation, as well as his community volunteerism through activities such as fundraising for the IWK and leading Boy Scout groups;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House congratulate Greg Burk on receiving this prestigious 2013 Community Champion Award, thank him for his dedication to bettering our province in so many ways, and wish him every success in the future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#jim.boudreau"><num title="1726">RESOLUTION NO. 1726</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Cecily Grace Strongman of St. Mary's Academy was a 2013 recipient of the Lieutenant Governor's Medal; and</p>
<p>Whereas an awards ceremony was held May 9, 2013, at East Antigonish Education Centre/Academy where His Honour, Brigadier-General the Honourable J.J. Grant, CMM, ONS, CD Lieutenant Governor of Nova Scotia presented select Grade 11 students with the Lieutenant Governor's Medal; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Lieutenant Governor's Medal is awarded annually to students who have demonstrated qualities of leadership and service in the school and community as well as commendable performance in the courses in which they have been enrolled;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Cecily Grace Strongman on achieving this prestigious award, and wish her every success in her post-secondary education.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#jim.boudreau"><num title="1727">RESOLUTION NO. 1727</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Justin Alexander MacDonald of Guysborough Academy was a 2013 recipient of the Lieutenant Governor's Medal; and</p>
<p>Whereas an awards ceremony was held May 9, 2013, at East Antigonish Education Centre/Academy where His Honour, Brigadier-General the Honourable J.J. Grant, CMM, ONS, CD Lieutenant Governor of Nova Scotia presented select Grade 11 students with the Lieutenant Governor's Medal; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Lieutenant Governor's Medal is awarded annually to students who have demonstrated qualities of leadership and service in the school and community as well as commendable performance in the courses in which they have been enrolled;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Justin Alexander MacDonald on achieving this prestigious award, and wish him every success in his post-secondary education.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#jim.boudreau"><num title="1728">RESOLUTION NO. 1728</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Carly Victoria Avery of Guysborough Academy was a 2013 recipient of the Lieutenant Governor's Medal; and</p>
<p>Whereas an awards ceremony was held May 9, 2013, at East Antigonish Education Centre/Academy where His Honour, Brigadier-General the Honourable J.J. Grant, CMM, ONS, CD Lieutenant Governor of Nova Scotia presented select Grade 11 students with the Lieutenant Governor's Medal; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Lieutenant Governor's Medal is awarded annually to students who have demonstrated qualities of leadership and service in the school and community as well as commendable performance in the courses in which they have been enrolled;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Carly Victoria Avery on achieving this prestigious award, and wish her every success in her post-secondary education.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#jim.boudreau"><num title="1729">RESOLUTION NO. 1729</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Taylor Thomas Vincent Bezanson of St. Mary's Academy was a 2013 recipient of the Lieutenant Governor's Medal; and</p>
<p>Whereas an awards ceremony was held May 9, 2013, at East Antigonish Education Centre/Academy where His Honour, Brigadier-General the Honourable J.J. Grant, CMM, ONS, CD Lieutenant Governor of Nova Scotia presented select Grade 11 students with the Lieutenant Governor's Medal; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Lieutenant Governor's Medal is awarded annually to students who have demonstrated qualities of leadership and service in the school and community as well as commendable performance in the courses in which they have been enrolled;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Taylor Thomas Vincent Bezanson on achieving this prestigious award, and wish him every success in his post-secondary education.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#jim.boudreau"><num title="1730">RESOLUTION NO. 1730</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Stephanie Louise Delorey of Canso Academy was a 2013 recipient of the Lieutenant Governor's Medal; and</p>
<p>Whereas an awards ceremony was held May 9, 2013, at East Antigonish Education Centre/Academy where His Honour, Brigadier-General the Honourable J.J. Grant, CMM, ONS, CD Lieutenant Governor of Nova Scotia presented select Grade 11 students with the Lieutenant Governor's Medal; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Lieutenant Governor's Medal is awarded annually to students who have demonstrated qualities of leadership and service in the school and community as well as commendable performance in the courses in which they have been enrolled;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Shephanie Louise Delorey on achieving this prestigious award, and wish her every success in her post-secondary education.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#jim.boudreau"><num title="1731">RESOLUTION NO. 1731</num><from>Mr. Jim Boudreau</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Joshua David Rhynold of Canso Academy was a 2013 recipient of the Lieutenant Governor's Medal; and</p>
<p>Whereas an awards ceremony was held May 9, 2013, at East Antigonish Education Centre/Academy where His Honour, Brigadier-General the Honourable J.J. Grant, CMM, ONS, CD Lieutenant Governor of Nova Scotia presented select Grade 11 students with the Lieutenant Governor's Medal; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Lieutenant Governor's Medal is awarded annually to students who have demonstrated qualities of leadership and service in the school and community as well as commendable performance in the courses in which they have been enrolled;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Joshua David Rhynold on achieving this prestigious award, and wish him every success in his post-secondary education.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1732">RESOLUTION NO. 1732</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills and time, they often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honors;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate William Handspiker, a member of the North River and District Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his 25-year service award.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1733">RESOLUTION NO. 1733</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills and time, they often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honors;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ronald MacCallum, a member of the North River and District Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his 40-year service award.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1734">RESOLUTION NO. 1734</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills and time, they often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honours;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ralph Hamilton, a member of the North River and District Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his 40-year service award.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1735">RESOLUTION NO. 1735</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills and time, they often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honours;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Gerald Brownell, a member of the North River and District Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his 40-year service award.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1736">RESOLUTION NO. 1736</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills and time, they often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honours;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Brian Ellis, a member of the North River and District Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his 40-year service award.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1737">RESOLUTION NO. 1737</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills and time, they often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honours;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Chris Franklin, a member of the North River and District Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his 20-year service award, a year late.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1738">RESOLUTION NO. 1738</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills and time, they often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honours;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Glen Crowe, a member of the North River and District Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his 40-year service award.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1739">RESOLUTION NO. 1739</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills and time, they often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honours;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Kelsey MacRae, a member of the North River and District Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his 40-year service award.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1740">RESOLUTION NO. 1740</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills and time, they often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honours;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate LeRoy Hansen, a member of the North River and District Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving the award for the most training hours.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#karen.casey"><num title="1741">RESOLUTION NO. 1741</num><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills and time, they often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honours;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Mark Brownell, a member of the North River and District Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving the Chiefs' Choice Award as well as the Member of the Year Award.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#stephen.mcneil"><num title="1742">RESOLUTION NO. 1742</num><from>Hon. Stephen McNeil</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past eight years, the Canadian Mental Health Association in collaboration with the Mental Health Foundation of Nova Scotia have invited individuals, groups, and organizations to nominate outstanding community members to receive an Inspiring Lives Award; and</p>
<p>Whereas despite all the challenges nominees have faced in their lives, they have inspired countless others with their determination, spirit, and willingness to share their stores; and</p>
<p>Whereas Inspiring Lives winner Amanda Eve MacLeod has inspired many in her community by utilizing her gentle spirit and positivity to teach positive coping strategies and encouraging many others to build their inner peace in order to inspire hope;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this Legislature congratulate Inspiring Lives Award winner Amanda Eve MacLeod wish her many more years of inspiring others, and in the process, giving those facing mental health issues hope for their future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#stephen.mcneil"><num title="1743">RESOLUTION NO. 1743</num><from>Hon. Stephen McNeil</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past eight years, the Canadian Mental Health Association in collaboration with the Mental Health Foundation of Nova Scotia have invited individuals, groups, and organizations to nominate outstanding community members to receive an Inspiring Lives Award; and</p>
<p>Whereas despite all the challenges nominees have faced in their lives, they have inspired countless others with their determination, spirit and willingness to share their stores; and</p>
<p>Whereas Inspiring Lives winner Don Roper broke ground some 23 years ago when he began to publicly speak out about his own story of loss and recovery associated with his own mental illness and has since played a major role in the development of the health consumer movement in Nova Scotia;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this Legislature congratulate Inspiring Lives Award winner Don Roper wish him many more years of inspiring others, and in the process, giving those facing mental health issues hope for their future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#stephen.mcneil"><num title="1744">RESOLUTION NO. 1744</num><from>Hon. Stephen McNeil</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past eight years, the Canadian Mental Health Association in collaboration with the Mental Health Foundation of Nova Scotia have invited individuals, groups, and organizations to nominate outstanding community members to receive an Inspiring Lives Award; and</p>
<p>Whereas despite all the challenges nominees have faced in their lives, they have inspired countless others with their determination, spirit and willingness to share their stores; and</p>
<p>Whereas Inspiring Lives winner Joel Maxwell uses his voice and heart as a leader in the Laing House Community to create change and support others living with mental illness in the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this Legislature congratulate Inspiring Lives Award winner Joel Maxwell, wish him many more years of inspiring others, and in the process, giving those facing mental health issues hope for their future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#stephen.mcneil"><num title="1745">RESOLUTION NO. 1745</num><from>Hon. Stephen McNeil</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past eight years, the Canadian Mental Health Association in collaboration with the Mental Health Foundation of Nova Scotia have invited individuals, groups, and organizations to nominate outstanding community members to receive an Inspiring Lives Award; and</p>
<p>Whereas despite all the challenges nominees have faced in their lives, they have inspired countless others with their determination, spirit and willingness to share their stores; and</p>
<p>Whereas Inspiring Lives winner Heather McNally has channeled her passion for mental health and wellness as a Certified Life Coach, when she could no longer practice medicine due to her medical condition;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this Legislature congratulate Heather McNally on her most deserving nomination for an Inspiring Lives Award, wish her many more years of inspiring others, and in the process, giving those facing mental health issues hope for their future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#stephen.mcneil"><num title="1746">RESOLUTION NO. 1746</num><from>Hon. Stephen McNeil</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past eight years, the Canadian Mental Health Association in collaboration with the Mental Health Foundation of Nova Scotia have invited individuals, groups, and organizations to nominate outstanding community members to receive an Inspiring Lives Award; and</p>
<p>Whereas despite all the challenges nominees have faced in their lives, they have inspired countless others with their determination, spirit and willingness to share their stores; and</p>
<p>Whereas Inspiring Lives nominee Irene Skehen has risen above her own mental illness and now works as an addictions counselor in addition to volunteering her time offering educational workshops, courses and one-on-one counseling for those who need support;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this Legislature congratulate Irene on her most deserving nomination for an Inspiring Lives Award, wish her many more years of inspiring others, and in the process, giving those facing mental health issues hope for their future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#stephen.mcneil"><num title="1747">RESOLUTION NO. 1747</num><from>Hon. Stephen McNeil</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past eight years, the Canadian Mental Health Association in collaboration with the Mental Health Foundation of Nova Scotia have invited individuals, groups, and organizations to nominate outstanding community members to receive an Inspiring Lives Award; and</p>
<p>Whereas despite all the challenges nominees have faced in their lives, they have inspired countless others with their determination, spirit and willingness to share their stores; and</p>
<p>Whereas Inspiring Lives nominee Mary-Lee Chaddock has used her education degree and life experience with her own mental illness to work with and support hundreds of children faced with mental illness or that of their families;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this Legislature congratulate Mary-Lee Chaddock on her most deserving nomination for an Inspiring Lives Award, wish her many more years of inspiring others, and in the process, giving those facing mental health issues hope for their future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#stephen.mcneil"><num title="1748">RESOLUTION NO. 1748</num><from>Hon. Stephen McNeil</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past eight years, the Canadian Mental Health Association in collaboration with the Mental Health Foundation of Nova Scotia have invited individuals, groups, and organizations to nominate outstanding community members to receive an Inspiring Lives Award; and</p>
<p>Whereas despite all the challenges nominees have faced in their lives, they have inspired countless others with their determination, spirit and willingness to share their stores; and</p>
<p>Whereas Inspiring Lives nominees, the Park Bench Players, have coupled their life experience with mental illness with theatre, as a means to provide mental health education and reducing stigma;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this Legislature congratulate the Park Bench Players on their most deserving nomination for an Inspiring Lives Award, wish them many more years of inspiring others, and in the process, giving those facing mental health issues hope for their future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#stephen.mcneil"><num title="1749">RESOLUTION NO. 1749</num><from>Hon. Stephen McNeil</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past eight years, the Canadian Mental Health Association in collaboration with the Mental Health Foundation of Nova Scotia have invited individuals, groups, and organizations to nominate outstanding community members to receive an Inspiring Lives Award; and</p>
<p>Whereas despite all the challenges nominees have faced in their lives, they have inspired countless others with their determination, spirit and willingness to share their stores; and</p>
<p>Whereas Inspiring Lives nominee Wayne Schnare devotes countless hours to reducing stigma, creating awareness, and developing a greater understanding among others with mental illness;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this Legislature congratulate Wayne Schnare on his most deserving nomination for an Inspiring Lives Award, wish him many more years of inspiring others, and in the process, giving those facing mental health issues hope for their future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#stephen.mcneil"><num title="1750">RESOLUTION NO. 1750</num><from>Hon. Stephen McNeil</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past eight years, the Canadian Mental Health Association in collaboration with the Mental Health Foundation of Nova Scotia have invited individuals, groups, and organizations to nominate outstanding community members to receive an Inspiring Lives Award; and</p>
<p>Whereas despite all the challenges nominees have faced in their lives, they have inspired countless others with their determination, spirit and willingness to share their stores; and</p>
<p>Whereas despite struggling with mental health issues all of his life, Inspiring Lives Award winner Shane Brown, has overcome obstacles to work at a homeless shelter and now supports countless others through his work in the mental health field;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this Legislature congratulate Inspiring Lives Award winner Shane Brown, wish him many more years of inspiring others, and in the process, giving those facing mental health issues hope for their future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#stephen.mcneil"><num title="1751">RESOLUTION NO. 1751</num><from>Hon. Stephen McNeil</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past eight years, the Canadian Mental Health Association in collaboration with the Mental Health Foundation of Nova Scotia have invited individuals, groups, and organizations to nominate outstanding community members to receive an Inspiring Lives Award; and</p>
<p>Whereas despite all the challenges nominees have faced in their lives, they have inspired countless others with their determination, spirit and willingness to share their stores; and</p>
<p>Whereas despite his young age, Evan Hennigar has used his experience living with anxiety to produce an anti-cyberbullying video to reach out to his peers, and on a daily basis educates his friends that kindness matters and makes a difference in the lives of everyone;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this Legislature congratulate Evan Hennigar for the award he received at the Inspiring Lives luncheon, wish him many more years of inspiring others, and in the process, giving those facing mental health issues hope for their future.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1752">RESOLUTION NO. 1752</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Kristen McPhee of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1753">RESOLUTION NO. 1753</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Rachel Cartier of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1754">RESOLUTION NO. 1754</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Dana Blinkhorn of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1755">RESOLUTION NO. 1755</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Scott Gamble of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1756">RESOLUTION NO. 1756</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Aidon Drew of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1757">RESOLUTION NO. 1757</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Drew Doyle of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1758">RESOLUTION NO. 1758</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Matthew Piercey of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1759">RESOLUTION NO. 1759</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Katelyn Clarke of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1760">RESOLUTION NO. 1760</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Kate Lavers of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1761">RESOLUTION NO. 1761</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Neda Salehi of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1762">RESOLUTION NO. 1762</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Kerry Halpin of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1763">RESOLUTION NO. 1763</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Laura Moore of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1764">RESOLUTION NO. 1764</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Morgan Levangie of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1765">RESOLUTION NO. 1765</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Alec MacNeil of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1766">RESOLUTION NO. 1766</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Gillian Druhan of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1767">RESOLUTION NO. 1767</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Emily Jennings of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1768">RESOLUTION NO. 1768</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Brianna Flaim of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1769">RESOLUTION NO. 1769</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Kaitlyn McKay of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1770">RESOLUTION NO. 1770</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Abbie Shea of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1771">RESOLUTION NO. 1771</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Hannah Veinot of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1772">RESOLUTION NO. 1772</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Rachel Loughery of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1773">RESOLUTION NO. 1773</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ali Doolan of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1774">RESOLUTION NO. 1774</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Keely O'Neil of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1775">RESOLUTION NO. 1775</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Brienna O'Neil of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1776">RESOLUTION NO. 1776</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Vanna Witcher of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1777">RESOLUTION NO. 1777</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Melissa O'Neil of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1778">RESOLUTION NO. 1778</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Marley Durant of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1779">RESOLUTION NO. 1779</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jack Bowen-Maclean of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1780">RESOLUTION NO. 1780</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Andrew Betts of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1781">RESOLUTION NO. 1781</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the band category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 Band competed in the novice category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ryan Reed of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 Band, and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1782">RESOLUTION NO. 1782</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning, and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the Band Category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 band competed in the Novice Category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ben Major of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 band and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1783">RESOLUTION NO. 1783</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning, and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the Band Category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 band competed in the Novice Category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Keion Sparks of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 band and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1784">RESOLUTION NO. 1784</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning, and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the Band Category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 band competed in the Novice Category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ross Bennett of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 band and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1785">RESOLUTION NO. 1785</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning, and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the Band Category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 band competed in the Novice Category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Marcus Hughes of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 band and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1786">RESOLUTION NO. 1786</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning, and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the Band Category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 band competed in the Novice Category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Cameron Samson of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 band and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1787">RESOLUTION NO. 1787</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning, and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the Band Category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 band competed in the Novice Category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jordan Awalt of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 band and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1788">RESOLUTION NO. 1788</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning, and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the Band Category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 band competed in the Novice Category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jake Mitchell of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 band and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1789">RESOLUTION NO. 1789</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning, and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the Band Category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 band competed in the Novice Category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Alex Carreiro of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 band and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1790">RESOLUTION NO. 1790</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning, and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the Band Category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 band competed in the Novice Category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jesse Li of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 band and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1791">RESOLUTION NO. 1791</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning, and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the Band Category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 band competed in the Novice Category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Carson Craig of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 band and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1792">RESOLUTION NO. 1792</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning, and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the Band Category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 band competed in the Novice Category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Kevin Roberts of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 band and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1793">RESOLUTION NO. 1793</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning, and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the Band Category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 band competed in the Novice Category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Kaitlin Ellis-Moore of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 band and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1794">RESOLUTION NO. 1794</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning, and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the Band Category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 band competed in the Novice Category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Caito MacDonald of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 band and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1795">RESOLUTION NO. 1795</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning, and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the Band Category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 band competed in the Novice Category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jack Cumming of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 band and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#andrew.younger"><num title="1796">RESOLUTION NO. 1796</num><from>Mr. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since 1935 the Kiwanis Music Festival has supported young artists, giving them extraordinary possibilities for performing, learning, and sharing their musical talents and;</p>
<p>Whereas this year's Kiwanis Music Festival saw 25 entries in the Band Category alone; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary combined Grade 6 band competed in the Novice Category and won a gold medal for their efforts;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly congratulate Hannah Irvine of the Brookhouse/Portland Estates Elementary Grade 6 band and their equally extraordinary band teacher, Victor Fraser, on their achievement, and wish them many more years of making beautiful music.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#diana.whalen"><num title="1797">RESOLUTION NO. 1797</num><from>Ms. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Lower Deck, in Halifax, has earned an enviable reputation for offering a unique blend of food and entertainment since opening on the waterfront in 1974; and</p>
<p>Whereas in December 2012 owner Mike Condy has opened a new location of this famed establishment in Clayton Park, and has been welcomed by the community; and</p>
<p>Whereas the new Lower Deck Bar and Grill offers up to 200 seats and is earning a great reputation for providing a true "neighbourhood bar", a venue for music and entertainment;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House congratulate Mike Condy on his expansion into the Clayton Park area, and wish him the best of luck in this and all his future endeavours.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#diana.whalen"><num title="1798">RESOLUTION NO. 1798</num><from>Ms. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas artists Joseph Landry and Brian Gazeley, of Halifax, have volunteered their time and talents over the past year to recognize and honour deserving Nova Scotians with the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Awards; and</p>
<p>Whereas these awards were conceived by Brian and Joseph, along with the N.S. Division of the Duke of Edinburgh's Award in Canada, to recognize outstanding volunteer service and to commemorate both the Queen's Diamond Jubilee and the 40<sup>th</sup> Anniversary of the Duke of Edinburgh's Awards in Nova Scotia; and</p>
<p>Whereas Joseph and Brian contributed countless hours as co-chairmen on the committee, helping to review nominations, to plan the award presentations, and to create the medals and certificates for the many very deserving recipients;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House congratulate Brian Gazeley and Joseph Landry on the Diamond Jubilee Century of Service Award, which has touched the lives of so many Nova Scotians in this special year and has left a legacy of volunteer and community service across Nova Scotia.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#diana.whalen"><num title="1799">RESOLUTION NO. 1799</num><from>Ms. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Grassmarket is a Halifax-based band made up of three multi-instrumentalists who are now bridging pop-Americana style music with elements of traditional folk music; and</p>
<p>Whereas in 2007 Grassmarket released its first recording, Waiting, and was nominated for a 2008 Music Nova Scotia Award in the category of Country Bluegrass Artist/Group Recording of the Year; and</p>
<p>Whereas Grassmarket released its newest album, You are for the Ocean, in November 2012, which reflects a personal emotional struggle for the songwriters and balances themes of sadness, hopefulness, and family;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this Legislature congratulate Penelope Jackson, Dan MacCormack, and David Bradshaw of Grassmarket on their new album, and continued success.</p></speech>
      </noticesOfMotion>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
