<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="6622244d-59c2-401f-9ce8-94ac1813c111" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.stephen.mcneil" showAs="HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="53fc39ac-a3be-4439-b810-cf2a8cd8b016" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.michel.p.samson" showAs="HON. MICHEL SAMSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="c5af3c5b-9318-4bcc-a6b9-6d41edaf6180" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.lena.m.diab" showAs="HON. LENA DIAB"/>
        <TLCPerson id="39fe31af-4449-4a39-bd02-eac2eb6643e5" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.jamie.baillie" showAs="HON. JAMIE BAILLIE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="2a8a6812-dab1-49f4-b941-a875e19a943a" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.brendan.o.maguire" showAs="MR. BRENDAN MAGUIRE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="9d561239-9900-4212-aa2a-3392a94889e4" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.suzanne.lohnes.croft" showAs="MS. SUZANNE LOHNES-CROFT"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MR. SPEAKER"/>
        <TLCRole id="clerk" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.clerk" showAs="THE CLERK"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 28 November 2013</docTitle>
      <docNumber>13-02</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2013-11-28">Thursday, November 28, 2013</docDate>
      <docProponent>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docProponent>
      <legislature value="62">62nd General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="1">1st Session</session>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Please be seated.</p>
<p>The honourable Attorney General.</p></speech>
      <speech by="#c5af3c5b-9318-4bcc-a6b9-6d41edaf6180">
        <from>HON. LENA DIAB</from>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, I beg leave to introduce a bill entitled An Act Respecting Oaths of Office.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Ordered that this bill be read a second time on a future day.</p>
<p>His Honour the Lieutenant Governor has been pleased to make a Speech to the members met in General Assembly, of which Speech, for greater accuracy, I have obtained a copy which the Chief Clerk will now read.</p>
<p>of which Speech, for greater accuracy, I have obtained a copy, which the Chief Clerk will now read.</p></speech>
      <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined">
        <from>THE CLERK</from>
        <p>It is my great honour and privilege to welcome you to the First Session of the 62<sup>nd</sup> General Assembly of the Nova Scotia Legislature. For some of you it's a welcome back. For others this is &#x2026;</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>The honourable Premier.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="#6622244d-59c2-401f-9ce8-94ac1813c111">
        <from>HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL</from>
        <p>While I enjoyed it, Mr. Speaker, I move the Speech from the Throne be taken as read.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the Speech from the Throne be taken as read.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Lunenburg.</p></speech>
      <speech by="#9d561239-9900-4212-aa2a-3392a94889e4"><from>MS. SUZANNE LOHNES-CROFT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, it is an honour to rise in the 62<sup>nd</sup> Session of the House of Assembly and move the Address in Reply to the Speech from the Throne as read by His Honour Brigadier-General, the Honourable J.J. Grant.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, it is indeed a privilege to stand here in this historic House before my colleagues representing the constituency of Lunenburg, located on Nova Scotia's beautiful South Shore.</p>
<p>I would like to begin my remarks by congratulating you, Mr. Speaker, on your first official day presiding over the House of Assembly. I know you will maintain order and lead us through a productive session in the House. (Applause)</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, it is my great pleasure to say thank you to the fine people of the Lunenburg constituency for electing me to represent them in the Nova Scotia House of Assembly. I am humbled by their vote of confidence and I pledge to represent the people of Lunenburg to the best of my ability each and every day. My work experiences over the years helped me to acquire the leadership skills necessary for running for public office but I must give the greatest credit to my experiences as a volunteer.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, never underestimate the skills of a volunteer board, the enthusiasm of a sports coach, the kindness of a food bank worker, the power of a smile from a friendly visitor, or the perseverance of a home and school president. (Applause)</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I wish to acknowledge the unwavering support of my husband Ken, my sons Daniel, Samuel and Jacob, my mother Audrey, and siblings Margaret, Christine, Phillip and Andrew throughout the nomination process, my candidacy, and the writ period. They not only kept me grounded but they lifted my spirits as only a family can do.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I have another family that I wish to acknowledge today - my amazing campaign team family. This energetic and supportive group of individuals organized and implemented a most effective campaign to win the constituency with a mandate to keep the campaign clean and positive. I wish to extend my gratitude to these two families of mine for their dedication, work ethic and most importantly, the humour that sustained me throughout the campaign.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I can't begin to tell you how privileged I feel to be a member of the new Liberal Government. As His Honour mentioned in the Speech from the Throne, our new government will be focused on families, small businesses and local communities - the backbone of our province and my constituency. Our new government will be reinventing how government operates in a number of fundamental ways, always operating with the best interests of Nova Scotians as our number one priority and our guiding principle.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I wish to tell you and my fellow MLAs about the constituency of Lunenburg. Lunenburg was first settled in 1753 by foreign Protestants of French and German descent during the reign of King George II. My ancestors were among those first settlers to the area some 260 years ago. Today the people of Lunenburg constituency continue to embrace its rich and unique heritage.</p>
<p>My constituency borders those of Chester-St. Margaret's, Lunenburg West, and Annapolis. It encompasses the lands between the Martins and LaHave Rivers, extends from the rocky coastline communities of Stonehurst, Blue Rocks, and River Port, and north to the rich forest lands beyond the village of New Germany.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, what I heard loud and clear during the campaign was that the most pressing issue in Lunenburg is roads, roads, and more roads. (Applause)</p>
<p>Many of my constituents travel on roads and bridges that were never designed for high traffic volume. Many in my constituency, and I'm sure all constituencies in the province, now more than ever require travel to outside their communities, sometimes commuting hundreds of kilometres each week just to go to work, not to mention medical appointments and purchasing groceries for their families. It is vital for citizens in rural areas to have safe and reliable roads. Our transportation infrastructure is the lifeline for many communities in my constituency. The new Liberal Government will work to ensure our rural areas continue to have the best possible infrastructure in place and will work to improve these vital links wherever possible.</p>
<p>For many generations Lunenburg has been known for its abundance of natural resources, known in the past for its fisheries, boat building, forestry, agriculture, and of course Christmas tree growing. However, Mr. Speaker, this is no longer the case. The closure of the fisheries, the lower demand for our forestry products, and the challenges in the farming industry have caused our youth to go elsewhere for education, training, and work. We know there are challenges ahead relating to our economy, our population, and educational opportunities for our youth. This is exactly why the new government will be investing in education while making smart investments in our economy and communities.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, our government's plan to reduce the size of health care administration so we can focus on our valuable health resources on front-line health care services is about delivering the world class health care service that Nova Scotians deserve. I am pleased that we will be increasing access to health care professionals such as nurses and family doctors. With an aging population in my constituency we will work hard to help seniors remain in their homes longer. I am ready to work with the people of Lunenburg, to be a strong voice in this House, and have a hand in creating a better Nova Scotia for today and generations to come.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, it is now my pleasure to thank His Honour for the Throne Speech and with great pride and great confidence I move that the Address in Reply to the Speech from the Throne, as read by His Honour the Lieutenant Governor of Nova Scotia, be accepted as read. Thank you. (Applause)</p></speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>The honourable member for Halifax Atlantic.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="#2a8a6812-dab1-49f4-b941-a875e19a943a"><from>MR. BRENDAN MAGUIRE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, it is also an honour for me to rise today and express my thanks to His Honour Brigadier-General, the Honourable J.J. Grant, Lieutenant Governor of Nova Scotia, for his inspiring words.</p>
<p>I am honoured to second the Address in Reply to the Speech from the Throne. It is truly a privilege to stand before you and my colleagues from both sides of the House today in this historic Chamber. I rise today not just to second the Address in Reply to the Speech from the Throne, but also as the voice of the people of Halifax Atlantic.</p>
<p>Halifax Atlantic is a riding that is not only my home but a community that has helped save my life. I wake up every day thankful to the people of this amazing community and fully aware of the enormous responsibility they have placed on me. I am proud to be from such a unique and diverse riding, a riding that is reflective of the hard work and big hearts that Nova Scotians have become known for worldwide.</p>
<p>I am the MLA for Halifax Atlantic, a riding that is made up of unique individuals from Spryfield to Herring Cove to Portuguese Cove, Ketch Harbour, Sambro, East and West Pennant, Williamswood, Harrietsfield, and Purcells Cove. I am also husband to Rena Maguire and the proud father of Oliver Finn Maguire, who is making all the noise. I am also going to get it on record that I love both of you. (Applause)</p>
<p>I would not be here today without the help of so many people along the way, people like my foster father - let me correct that, he is actually my father - Yves Campagna, and the late Ruby Campagna; Linda Wilson, who recognized something in that hyper, mohawked child at Phoenix House over 20 years ago and became a mother and someone I can trust; Charmaine Tanner, who stood beside me, guided me, and was a rock during the toughest years of my life; Ainslie McNeil Campbell, who has been beside me since I first came to Canada in 1979; and my in-laws, Ruphina and Gerald Moir, who welcomed me into their home with open arms.</p>
<p>There are so many people who are part of this, from Kelly Gnomes to Chris Hornberger, to Donna Macready, Martha Reynolds, and Kim Dunn, who all believed in me from the start; Jennifer Langille, Alonzo McNeil, Pat Blakie, Marion Brown, Sandy Thompson, Rob Morris, Darlene Fahie, Sarah Gragg - you are a superstar - the Hubley family, Stephen Fralick, Kristian LaPierre and the LaPierre family, Maggie Fougere, David Ley, Madeline Matheson, Trevor Arsenault, Heidi Musolino, Isabelle MacPherson, and Labi Kousoulis, who was the first one to show up at my nomination meeting - he told me I had to say that, by the way - and all 75 volunteers from my campaign who worked tirelessly night and day and who put up with me, which my wife can tell you is not an easy task. There are so many more to thank, and if I missed you, I truly am sorry.</p>
<p>I stand here today the man I am because of you. I stand here today, and will every day, promising to be a strong voice for my community, no matter their gender, race, or political affiliation. Life is difficult enough, and we, as MLAs, need to put our judgments aside and really listen to the people we represent, and to appreciate how lucky we all are to be in this position and never forget who we are and who we represent. (Applause)</p>
<p>Everyone in this House has a real opportunity to show people who have grown so cynical of government on all levels that government can do great things when everybody works together with the best interests of Nova Scotians in mind. I ask all of you today, whether you are Liberal, NDP, or Progressive Conservative, to work together, to listen to each other, and to recognize that our decisions affect the people of Nova Scotia. This responsibility should not be taken lightly - like education. We can all agree that we need a strong, robust education system so that children of families such as James and Tracy Watts, Catherine and Scott Morrison, Nick and Michelle McAvoy, and Jason William and Sarah Scott's children have the resources at their fingertips to reach their full potential.</p>
<p>It is essential that we assess the quality of the curriculum that is being delivered and ensure that our students have the resources to succeed. It is time that we view our children as our most important resource and not just a budget line item. (Applause)</p>
<p>I believe a good idea is a good idea no matter which side of the House it comes from.</p>
<p>We need to be the role models that youth look up to today and tomorrow. I look forward to being part of a better Nova Scotia, and it is my honour today to second the motion that the Address in Reply to the Speech from the Throne passes as read. Thank you. (Applause)</p></speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="#39fe31af-4449-4a39-bd02-eac2eb6643e5"><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, on behalf of the Official Opposition, I would like to thank His Honour the Lieutenant Governor for his address to the House today, and for the work he's doing in service of all Nova Scotians.</p>
<p>Let me say right off the top, on behalf of those of us here in Opposition, I want to congratulate the Premier and the members of the Liberal Government on their victory in the most recent general election. I offer sincere congratulations to them for their work. (Applause)</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I heard the Premier's words outside this Chamber, that he wants to set a new and respectful tone of debate in the Legislature and I just want him to know, and everyone in his government to know, that on the Opposition side we accept that invitation and will return it in kind - it's time to set a new tone of debate in the House. (Applause)</p>
<p>We may be from different Parties - Liberal, PC, or NDP - but we are all part of the same family, the Nova Scotia family, and we ought to be guided by the way families talk and discuss issues at their own kitchen table or their own dining-room table. Although, when I think of the debates at my own family kitchen table, I'm not sure that's the right model - and I can say to the Premier that I can just imagine when he was growing up what the debates were like around his family table. (Applause)</p>
<p>If that's the model that he wishes to set, we absolutely will do that.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I want to congratulate you, sir, on your election as our Speaker. It is a moment of history in our province. (Applause) We all want to live in a province where any Nova Scotian, where every Nova Scotian, can aspire to any office in the province, whether it's the highest offices of Lieutenant Governor or Premier or Speaker, that no barrier should get in their way if their energy and their drive and their ambition can take them there - and you, Mr. Speaker, are an example of that for all Nova Scotians. (Applause)</p>
<p>I do also want to say that I quite enjoyed the maiden voyages, the maiden speeches of the mover, the member for Lunenburg, and the seconder, the member for Halifax Atlantic, of the Speech from the Throne here today. They are already showing the way for how we should conduct ourselves, speak to each other, here in the House of Assembly, and I thought that they did a fine job.</p>
<p>There are thank yous that I will start today, but time will prevent us from thanking everyone. But there are a few important thank yous that I do want to express on my own behalf and on behalf of the Official Opposition and, I am sure, of all members. As those 51 of us who sit here in the Chamber reflect on those who are there with us along the way on this journey that we're all on together, and first and foremost of course is our families - our wives, our husbands, our children - who get us to where we are. I just want to tell them that they bear a greater burden than we do here on the floor of the Legislature, and we recognize that. So let's all just take a moment, whether they are in the gallery or wherever they are, and reflect on the families that got us to where we are; they are our immediate family and part of the Nova Scotia family that I spoke of a moment ago. (Applause)</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, the Speech from the Throne listed a number of Nova Scotians who had provided great service to our province, who we lost in the past year. Some of them I knew personally, all of the stories I do know. I won't go through them all, although I just want to add from the Opposition our sincere thanks to all of them.</p>
<p>With your permission, I do want to mention one just briefly - who was a member of this Chamber, who was a personal friend of mine - and that is Jane Purves, who I miss every day in this job and I know that many members do. I think for those who did not know Jane to look back on the kind of politician she was, it is a great guiding light for all of us as we go forward. I know I am not alone, but I miss her greatly.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, outside of our families, we all should reflect today on how thankful we are to our constituents, the people who actually directly send us to the House of Assembly. In my own case, the constituency of Cumberland South took me in when they didn't really know me very well three years ago and sent me here as their representative. I am so honoured that they did that. Over the last three years, I got to know them and they got to know me better. Despite that, they re-elected me in the most recent election with over 50 per cent of the vote. I cannot thank them enough.</p>
<p>For our families who see how hard it is here or in the newspapers or whatever, what they don't always see is the magic of being an MLA in your own constituency and helping people one or two or three at a time. That's what makes this job so special and for that, I will always be grateful and will always do anything I can for the people of Cumberland South, and I am sure all members feel the same about their own constituencies.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I do want to thank all of those candidates from all Parties who put their names on the ballots in the most recent election, who ran to serve their constituency and their province. There were some 180 Nova Scotians who participated as a candidate in the most recent provincial election. They all deserve our thanks.</p>
<p>It is said, Mr. Speaker, that the important thing is to stand up for what you believe in, to go along the journey. Of course, winning is the objective but it is the trial, the tribulation, the hardship that you go through when you run for office that really is important. I hope we all take a moment to send that message to those of all Parties who ran in the last election, whether they are here or not.</p>
<p>Now I will take a moment tomorrow, Mr. Speaker, to introduce the new members of the Progressive Conservative caucus to the House of Assembly, but just let me say to them that I am awfully grateful, along with the returning members, that they chose to continue to serve the people of the province and are here today. (Applause)</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, one final group of thank yous. In addition to family and our constituency and our fellow MLAs and candidates, of course, there are thousands of Nova Scotians who volunteered to work on election campaigns of all Parties, who believed in a cause, who believed in politics as something that was worth volunteering to do - to do without pay for many hours, night and day, before and during the election. They, too, deserve thanks.</p>
<p>I will just note, with your permission, sir, that in the gallery today is the president of the PC Party, a volunteer, Janet Fryday Dorey; and our campaign chair, Tara Erskine, from Halifax. They represent for us, and I am sure for all Parties, that spirit of volunteerism that ultimately makes our democracy work in the way that it does. I do want to say a special thank you to them as well. (Applause)</p>
<p>I'll just add one more quick one, Mr. Speaker. I see that our Auditor General, Mr. Lapointe, is in the gallery today. His term of service is coming to an end; he is retiring shortly. He did a great job. I've always said there should be more chartered accountants in politics so I'm sorry to see him go. On behalf of the Opposition I certainly want to express our best wishes to Mr. Lapointe in whatever endeavour he chooses to go into next after serving for eight years as our Auditor General. (Applause)</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, let me just say very quickly about today's Speech from the Throne, "We may have a new government sitting in the government benches, but there was nothing new from this government today &#x2026;" Those are not my words; those are the words of the previous Leader of the Official Opposition and now our Premier, spoken and recorded in Hansard on Thursday, September 17, 2009, at the commencement of the NDP Government. I say that because we did just go through an election campaign and Nova Scotians voted for real change and they deserve real change.</p>
<p>The problems that this province faces - whether it's high unemployment, whether it's the high cost of living, our taxes, our energy bills, whether it's so many young workers moving away and giving up hope of a future career or life in our province - those problems did not wait while we were all off campaigning. They are there today and the old ways don't work. Nova Scotians know that and they voted for change. The message I want to send across the aisle to the Premier and the government today is we are here to first and foremost make Nova Scotia a better place and to encourage the government to actually act, to govern, to change the way that Nova Scotia is run for the better.</p>
<p>I didn't see a lot new in the Throne Speech today, Mr. Speaker. It did not read a lot differently than the Throne Speeches of previous governments which promised nothing but more studies, more consultations, more tours around the province. We have a new government and they have a chance to actually act and make a difference, and when they do we will be there to support them when they actually make real change.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, we are very mindful of the fact that we have been hired by Nova Scotians to be the Opposition and we will do our job with vigour and with energy any time that the government slips, that it flip-flops on what it said, and acts differently than it did before it was in government. When they say one thing and do another, when those things happen, or they don't keep their promises, we will do our job as the Official Opposition.</p>
<p>The Premier said that he is going to keep every one of his promises. I know he did; I was there when he said it. Well, that's a pretty high order and I sincerely hope he does, and when they do we will be there to back them up. But if there is slippage from what they told Nova Scotians when they were seeking their votes, we will do our jobs as Official Opposition and hold the government to account.</p>
<p>Let me just say in closing that it is an amazing privilege to be a member of the Nova Scotia House of Assembly. We all fought very hard to be here and we witnessed a change in government in peace because we fought with our words, with our ideas, with our TV ads, and with our competing platforms. We fought in peace; we did not fight with guns or bullets as in too many parts of the world, that's how they change governments. But not here in this country.</p>
<p>So as we conclude today's proceedings in the month of November 2013, let us remember that it is our veterans who gave us this great privilege to fight elections with ideas and words and not guns and change governments in peace.</p>
<p>With that I move that we adjourn debate for today and I will continue my remarks tomorrow when we reconvene Thank you.</p></speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is to adjourn debate. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Premier.</p></speech>
      <speech by="#6622244d-59c2-401f-9ce8-94ac1813c111">
        <from>HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL</from>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, on your behalf, at the conclusion of this session I would like to invite all members of the House and all guests in the gallery to the Red Room for a reception.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="#53fc39ac-a3be-4439-b810-cf2a8cd8b016">
        <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, that concludes the government's business for today. I move that the House do now rise to meet again tomorrow at the hour of 9:00 a.m. until 1:00 p.m.</p>
      </speech>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the House do now rise to meet again tomorrow at 9:00 a.m.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>We stand adjourned.</p></speech>
      <narrative>
        <p>The House rose at 3:20 p.m.</p>
      </narrative>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
