<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="0f46e5e4-b06b-4b91-9e3a-5bd1cd63809d" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.larry.harrison" showAs="MR. LARRY HARRISON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.diana.whalen" showAs="Hon. Diana Whalen"/>
        <TLCPerson id="b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.christopher.a.dentremont" showAs="Hon. Christopher d'Entremont"/>
        <TLCPerson id="d6c0c78d-dcf3-456a-915c-a20ecb33050f" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.john.macdonell" showAs="MR. MACDONELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="c479d7de-83a6-47c7-a045-07816407bdb3" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.lenore.zann" showAs="MS. ZANN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.leo.glavine" showAs="HON. LEO GLAVINE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="aef785d7-7697-4453-8f9c-eef26e4928c3" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.keith.colwell" showAs="HON. KEITH COLWELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.karen.casey" showAs="Hon. Karen Casey"/>
        <TLCPerson id="4f242ac5-fc82-41a3-8089-419e69284e5e" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.maurice.g.smith" showAs="HON. MAURICE SMITH"/>
        <TLCPerson id="6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.allan.gerard.macmaster" showAs="MR. ALLAN MACMASTER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="3b49aa8d-3e78-4679-b8f7-f3161f11d3a3" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.sterling.belliveau" showAs="HON. STERLING BELLIVEAU"/>
        <TLCPerson id="bc54523e-7553-4c28-b315-79d18165339b" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.john.a.lohr" showAs="MR. JOHN LOHR"/>
        <TLCPerson id="4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.jamie.baillie" showAs="Hon. Jamie Baillie"/>
        <TLCPerson id="803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.frank.corbett" showAs="HON. FRANK CORBETT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.maureen.macdonald" showAs="MS. MACDONALD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.chuck.porter" showAs="MR. PORTER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="d20d446c-118f-4445-81f4-cf995b335391" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.randy.delorey" showAs="HON. RANDY DELOREY"/>
        <TLCPerson id="d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.michel.p.samson" showAs="HON. MICHEL SAMSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="578ba1c9-5f6c-4b7b-a5cd-b915e1801c37" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.lena.m.diab" showAs="HON. LENA DIAB"/>
        <TLCPerson id="fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.stephen.mcneil" showAs="HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="d36a0432-7994-4030-ab00-b21fc858e7d2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.ross.landry" showAs="HON. ROSS LANDRY"/>
        <TLCPerson id="0c003e1d-f0de-4ef6-85c6-604c99fbd41f" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.gordon.l.wilson" showAs="MR. GORDON WILSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.keith.bain" showAs="MR. KEITH BAIN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="4fbcc786-c835-4a0e-bd05-40afb30e0683" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.charlie.parker" showAs="MR. PARKER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8834559e-ddf7-4ac7-9b30-8ada0eb9a7ca" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.zach.churchill" showAs="HON. ZACH CHURCHILL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="e23caf06-dcf3-42a5-8a00-f4435df40350" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.alfie.macleod" showAs="MR. MACLEOD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.ramona.jennex" showAs="MS. JENNEX"/>
        <TLCPerson id="2c8e1a56-2f9d-4156-a91f-77802701e3d3" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.geoff.maclellan" showAs="MR. MACLELLAN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="1e5b7bdc-363b-4df4-8258-edcf8f2bf7fb" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.andrew.younger" showAs="HON. ANDREW YOUNGER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="980981f9-4823-4d4b-8134-a47d4ecf5405" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.denise.peterson.rafuse" showAs="MS. PETERSON-RAFUSE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="32a29c39-915c-40e7-b749-7c09299ed1f7" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.david.allan.wilson" showAs="MR. DAVID WILSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.eddie.orrell" showAs="MR. ORRELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="799b989e-2c9d-4331-b5f3-5f78d3447b57" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.darrell.dexter" showAs="HON. DARRELL DEXTER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="b1bb12cd-3928-4525-bab1-d76d28109b5b" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.percy.paris" showAs="HON. PERCY PARIS"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MR. SPEAKER"/>
        <TLCRole id="#member" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.#member" showAs="AN HON. MEMBER"/>
        <TLCRole id="premier" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.premier" showAs="THE PREMIER"/>
        <TLCRole id="clerk" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.clerk" showAs="THE CLERK"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 11 April 2013</docTitle>
      <docNumber>13-11</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2013-04-11">Thursday, April 11, 2013</docDate>
      <docProponent>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docProponent>
      <legislature value="61">61st General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="5">5th Session</session>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>Order, please. We'll now begin the daily routine.</p>
      </speech>
      <petitions>
        <heading>PRESENTING AND READING PETITIONS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Order, please.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Justice.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#578ba1c9-5f6c-4b7b-a5cd-b915e1801c37"><from>HON. LENA DIAB</from><p>Mr. Speaker, as Chairman of the Committee on Law Amendments, I am directed to report that the committee has met and considered the following bill:</p>
<p><b>Bill No. 19 - Trade Union Act.</b></p>
<p>and the committee recommends this bill to the favourable consideration of the House, with certain amendments.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, it is the understanding of the three House Leaders that we will not do a late debate tonight at the moment of interruption, with the unanimous consent of the House. It's my belief that under Rule 5 we will carry that debate subject over to the next late debate, which would be Tuesday, April 16<sup>th</sup>.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The late debate, the subject matter, will be moved over to Tuesday, April 16<sup>th</sup>.</p>
<p>We will begin the daily routine.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>Ordered that this bill be referred to the Committee of the Whole House on Bills.</p>
        </speech>
      </petitions>
      <papers>
        <heading>TABLING REPORTS, REGULATIONS AND OTHER PAPERS</heading>
      </papers>
      <ministerialStatements>
        <heading>STATEMENTS BY MINISTERS</heading>
      </ministerialStatements>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Natural Resources on an introduction.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#8834559e-ddf7-4ac7-9b30-8ada0eb9a7ca">
          <from>HON. ZACH CHURCHILL</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, if I can bring everybody's attention to the east gallery, I would like to introduce the House of Assembly to two special people from the Christmas tree industry: Jonathan Veinotte from Upper Northfield, Lunenburg County; and he is joined by Richard Levy, executive director of the All Nova Scotia Green Christmas Tree Co-op. I'm happy to inform the House that these are the gentlemen responsible for our beautiful 16-foot Christmas tree that was donated to Province House. So on behalf of all of us, thank you very much and please receive the warm welcome of the House. (Applause)</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Natural Resources.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="388">RESOLUTION NO. 388</num>
          <narrative>
            <p>12:15 p.m. The House reconvened.</p>
          </narrative>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Order, please. We will now continue on with our afternoon.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <ministerialStatements>
        <heading>STATEMENTS BY MINISTERS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Premier.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#799b989e-2c9d-4331-b5f3-5f78d3447b57"><from>HON. DARRELL DEXTER</from><p>Nova Scotia is mourning the loss of Rehtaeh Parsons, a young girl who has touched the lives of people all across the province, and around the world. I wanted to reach out to the members of this House and to all Nova Scotians to assure people that I will do everything in my power to create a community that is equipped to prevent these situations, rather than a community that struggles to find a way to deal with them.</p>
<p>The issues that this situation has brought painfully forward, and into the view of the world, are ones that respect no particular departmental responsibility. They do not belong to, or within, some particular system or process. They cross all of the visible and invisible lines. That is why this government, this province, is taking a coordinated, comprehensive, and thorough approach to these difficult and disturbing issues.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I have appointed Marilyn More, the Minister responsible for the Advisory Council on the Status of Women Act, to coordinate the work of all relevant departments - Education and Early Childhood Development, Justice, Community Services, and Health and Wellness - in the days ahead. She will work with all the ministers to ensure a timely, effective, and thorough response, and a review of everything the government and our partner agencies can and should do to support Nova Scotians. She will have the full-time support of the Associate Deputy Minister of Community Services, Lynn Hartwell, to work through these complex matters. I have asked her, specifically, to assess the status of work on the supports and programs to address individuals who have, or may face sexual violence.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I want Nova Scotians, particularly our young people, to know that if they are being bullied, if they are suffering, they can and should reach out for help. They can call 811, they can call 211, the province's mental health crisis line or the Kids Help Phone. Links to all of these numbers and other supports are available on the main page of the government's Web site at novascotia.ca. And people should know that they can always visit their local hospital for help as well.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, the bottom line is however people choose to do so they can, and should, reach out for help as soon as they can. No one should feel like he or she has nowhere to turn - and no one should have to go through what the Parsons family is right now. This is a time to be kind to one another and to care for each other. We need to keep caring about these problems in the days, weeks, and months ahead. We need to channel our sorrow and frustration into positive change.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I would like to thank Nova Scotians for supporting Rehtaeh's family and respecting their privacy during this very difficult time. They are in our hearts and minds as we build a plan forward and help each other through this. Rehtaeh's mother has been very public on her daughter's death, more so than anyone could have ever expected of a grieving mother. In her comments she has a very important message for Nova Scotians - more violence is not the answer; justice is to be done in the justice system.</p>
<p>The family has asked that I, today, implore Nova Scotians not to take matters into their own hands. That is what Rehtaeh would have wanted.</p>
<p>Thank you, Mr. Speaker.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
      </ministerialStatements>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>INTRODUCTION OF BILLS</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 28 - Entitled an Act to Establish a Public Consultation Process on the Enhancement of the Canada Pension Plan. (Hon. Maureen MacDonald)</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Ordered that this bill be read a second time on a future day.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5"><from>HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I want to, first of all, associate myself with the remarks of the Premier, and extend my condolences to the Parsons family. I think all of us in this House have family and cannot begin to imagine what the Parsons family is going through. To try to imagine the experience that Rehtaeh had gone through over the last number of years is just unimaginable. It saddens me though, I must say, that in the Province of Nova Scotia, so rich in so many ways, that young people like Rehtaeh feel no support and no hope, with all that we have to offer as a society that our children get to the point where there is no one left to turn to but the tragic consequences that Rehtaeh resorted to.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, today we're talking about Rehtaeh; there are unfortunately other families who are grieving, as well, for their loved ones who have taken the same act feeling that there was no one to turn to, no public institution, no person in the community, no one in society that was there to support them. I can't tell you how saddened as a father I am to believe that young people today feel that way. We need to come to terms with - as much as things change - we need to rapidly change ourselves to deal with the change in telecommunications, to change the way young people respond to one another, and we need to do it in a very quick and forceful way.</p>
<p>I'm pleased that the Premier has appointed Minister More to head this task force. I want to say to the minister, as the Leader of this Party, I'm prepared to participate in any way I can to put in place strong consequences for the kinds of actions that have been allowed to go on for too long in the province. To put in place strong protocols so that young Nova Scotians who find themselves in the same position that Rehtaeh was in, that they know there are other options for them. I'm prepared to participate in a place that is putting in strong resources for families who find themselves at the end of the rope with no hope of trying to deal with these issues. We're here to do whatever we can to ensure that the next Nova Scotian family that finds themselves with a young person being forced into this kind of situation, that we're there to help them to the best of our ability.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I too want to echo with the Premier again today to other Nova Scotians, we have a justice system - for all of its flaws and faults - it is the appropriate place that the entire consequences around this should be dealt with. I think all members of this House should send a strong message and implore all Nova Scotians to allow the justice system to do its work, to make sure that whatever consequences can come out of this they are done in a lawful way, in a meaningful way. There is one family suffering today; the last thing we, as province, need to do is add more grief and suffering to what is already a tragic event.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, with that I want to offer again to the minister my personal support in any way that I can work with you to make sure that we have meaningful action on this file and to the Premier, I want to again offer my support in any way we can as a Party to make sure that we have meaningful results for young Nova Scotians.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Leader of the New Democratic Party.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="389">RESOLUTION NO. 389</num>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Canada Pension Plan has a decades-long track record of delivering retirement income to Canadians, with very low administrative costs; and</p>
<p>Whereas it is no secret that we face a retirement crisis in terms of income security for many people who have inadequate pensions; and</p>
<p>Whereas most provinces, pension experts, labour unions, and seniors' organizations agree that enhancing the Canada Pension Plan is the best way to avoid a crisis of income insecurity in the very near future;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this Legislature support immediate concrete action to improve Canada's retirement income so that Canadians can retire with dignity.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Let me begin by saying that on behalf of the PC Party we do reach our hands across the aisle to the government side to work together on the consequences of the tragedy that Nova Scotians all share in grieving here today. To the Premier and to the minister he has assigned, they have our full co-operation, full support as they go about doing their job in government of dealing with this horrible situation.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, Nova Scotia has gained national and international attention over the last few days as the story of Rehtaeh Parsons has echoed around the world. It's not a way that any of us in this House, regardless of our political stripe, would wish for Nova Scotia to make national and international news, but perhaps by coming together we can continue to make national news by turning the province's problem around, by truly being leaders in the country when it comes to protecting our young people, when it comes to the consequences of bullying and cyberbullying. Perhaps Nova Scotia will now take what has come our way and turn it into something that can truly be a position of leadership for our country, as we deal with the modern consequences of bullying and cyberbullying and the activities that surround this horrible tragedy.</p>
<p>I know that many if not all of us in this House, in addition to being politicians, are also moms and dads, grandfathers and grandmothers, and so we are all affected, like all other Nova Scotians are, in a very personal way. I had this very talk with my own two daughters, last night at bedtime and again this morning, as they see the front page of The ChronicleHerald and they see the evening news. This is a discussion that is going on in my house about what can be done to protect people in the future who were in the circumstances of Rehtaeh Parsons and I believe it's a discussion that's going on in every household, by every mom and dad, with their own kids.</p>
<p>In addition to being moms and dads, we are charged with the responsibility of being legislators. I hope that we now have those very same household discussions, here in this House, on behalf of the entire household of Nova Scotia, as we are responsible to do. I do want the Premier and the minister to know that as we do that, we will be working together and they will have our support. It is so sad, as we are all sad, this great Nova Scotia family, we are all sad that a young woman felt she had no place to turn. We do have a responsibility today to point out to all of the young children of Nova Scotia, teenagers and otherwise, that there is always a choice; there is always hope; there is always a place to turn, whether it's a help line, or a mental health service, or to a school official, or to your own parents.</p>
<p>Let every child in Nova Scotia know they always have someplace to go for help. Where there are holes in the system that this tragedy uncovers, let us plug those holes so we can truly say to a whole new generation of young Nova Scotians, there is always a choice and we will help you make it. We will keep you safe and we will help you back to a healthier place. That is how Nova Scotia can become a true leader and make news in a more positive way in the future.</p>
<p>I say to the minister, good luck and Godspeed in your new duties. You have our full support. We will provide you with anything that we have - ideas around earlier interventions or more of the recommendations of the task force report that we can accelerate and get into place faster. That is something that we can do, not only as parents in this House but as legislators. So, Mr. Speaker, through you and to all members of the House and to all Nova Scotians, let us tell all of our children that there is always a place to turn, there is always hope, and we will make sure that is more true in Nova Scotia than ever before - that may well be exactly what Rehtaeh Parsons wants us to do. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Fisheries and Aquaculture.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#3b49aa8d-3e78-4679-b8f7-f3161f11d3a3">
          <from>HON. STERLING BELLIVEAU</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, before I read my resolution, may I be permitted an introduction?</p>
        </speech>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>ORDERS OF THE DAY</heading>
      </debateSection>
      <questions>
        <heading>ORAL QUESTIONS PUT BY MEMBERS</heading>
        <speech by="#3b49aa8d-3e78-4679-b8f7-f3161f11d3a3">
          <from>MR. BELLIVEAU</from>
          <p>I want to direct the members of the House to the east gallery. Today joining us is Mr. Grant Jones, senior director of Ducks Unlimited Canada for Newfoundland and Labrador, and Nova Scotia. I would ask the members to give a warm welcome to Mr. Jones. (Applause)</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The time is now 10:10 a.m.; we will finish at 11:40 a.m.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>We welcome all our guests to the gallery and hope they enjoy this afternoon's proceedings.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Fisheries and Aquaculture.</p></speech>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>DEP. PREM.: HEALTH SUPERSTRUCTURE - UPDATE</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="281">RESOLUTION NO. 281</num>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, today I would like to return to where we started in this House session, just a few short weeks ago, when we were here for the first time since the election and were determined, and I believe sincerely so from all sides, to find areas of common ground where we can work together. So I do have a question for the Deputy Premier and it is in that spirit.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, we read in allnovascotia.com today that there may well be a report coming forward from the Deputy Premier, who is our Finance Minister, of a looming budget deficit and it may be reported as a sizeable one. I want to point out today that one of the areas where there is a great similarity between the Official Opposition and our position and the position of the Liberal Government is in the need to find savings in the number of district health authorities across our province - the great health super-bureaucracy that exists - to ensure that that money is available for actual health care.</p>
<p>It's a common commitment of the Liberal Party in their election platform and of the PC Party in ours, Mr. Speaker, so we are here and ready to work with the government on the savings that can be found from a proper and overdue rationalization of the health bureaucracy.</p>
<p>My question to the Deputy Premier, who is also Finance Minister, can she provide us with an update on when the government will be moving to change the health superstructure and the number of district health authorities?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#3b49aa8d-3e78-4679-b8f7-f3161f11d3a3"><from>HON. STERLING BELLIVEAU</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Ducks Unlimited Canada, a national and international organization with deep roots in this province, is celebrating its 75<sup>th</sup> Anniversary this year; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ducks Unlimited Canada's members across Nova Scotia work hard to preserve the habitat of numerous waterfowl, animals, and native plants, some of which are protected or endangered; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ducks Unlimited Canada's efforts benefit all Nova Scotians by moderating the effects of floods, droughts, climate change, and erosion, while helping to provide safe, clean sources of water;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ducks Unlimited Canada, and especially all of Nova Scotia's members, in this, their 75<sup>th</sup> year, and offer our heartfelt thanks for their selfless work to maintain wetlands and wildlife habitats across Nova Scotia and to preserve our natural heritage for future generations.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2">
            <from>HON. DIANA WHALEN</from>
            <p>Thank you very much, Mr. Speaker, I appreciate the question from the Leader of the Official Opposition. I don't have the exact timing of that process that is underway with the DHAs and I think it would be more appropriate to let the Minister of Health and Wellness speak to that. I would like to suggest that we are looking for savings as we go forward and, as Finance Minister, in that capacity I'm looking for savings in all departments. We've asked for a 1 per cent reduction.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Minister of Health and Wellness.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048">
            <from>HON. LEO GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, to the Leader of the Official Opposition, I can perhaps give a short version or I can give a very long version.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>We'll go with the short one.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048">
            <from>MR. GLAVINE</from>
            <p>We've got two more questions so I just want to say first and foremost, where this is a significant change as to how we will deliver health care in the future, it is one that needs strong consultation with medical stakeholders, with the public, with unions. That will be kicked off and a schedule coming out early in the new year, when we will visit all of the existing nine DHAs. The overarching plan is in place but we now need to put the details for Nova Scotians early in the new year.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>MR. BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I appreciate that answer. I said a moment ago that it is important that we return to the place where we started in this session and that is to find areas of common ground where we can work together. I do know that we veered - all of us, from all sides - from that intent, from time to time, even just in the last two weeks, but I do want to return to that important place where we worked together on areas where we agree and this is one.</p>
<p>In fact, I just want to offer to the Deputy Premier and the Minister of Health and Wellness, that we put together our own plan on this. It's not exactly the same as the government's, but it's close. I hope that we can work together and maybe even meet as Leaders and Health Critics and ministers on how best to go about finding those savings that all Nova Scotians know are out there in our Health and Wellness super-bureaucracy.</p>
<p>Having said that, it is actually the health care workers themselves and the service they provide that I have in mind today. As long as they wait, they wait with uncertainty about their jobs, about the service that they provide, about what the future will look like for them and their employer. I would like to ask the Deputy Premier if she can commit to moving quickly on this important issue so that health care workers can get on with whatever the new situation looks like for them?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048">
            <from>HON. LEO GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I want to convey to the Leader of the Official Opposition that this will occur within the first full year of our mandate. In early January, a plan will come out, and one of the things in the early days of the plan will be to convey to all health care workers that this will be delivered in a very strategic, thoughtful manner with little or no impact on the jobs of those who deliver the high-quality health care to the Province of Nova Scotia.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>MR. BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, again I want to thank the Deputy Premier and the Minister of Health and Wellness for their words on this area of common ground that we can work on together. I know that when we in Opposition put health authority reduction in our platform we did our homework on how best to achieve it without unduly impacting health care workers themselves. I just want to offer to share our work with the government as they put together their plan. Again, it's not exactly the same, but it's close enough that we can get to a better place by working together on this important issue. I will again say that we are more than happy to do that when we find areas of common ground like we do here.</p>
<p>Recent reports, like those in allnovascotia.com, that indicate that the province may well not have a surplus, as was previously reported, but may in fact have a deficit mean that there will be more debt and less money for actual health care service in the future, as opposed to administration. We all want to avoid that if possible, so when health care savings can be found in administration, I believe it's important that we act to find those savings. I know it is an area of agreement between the government and the Official Opposition.</p>
<p>I want to ask the Deputy Premier, who is our Minister of Finance and Treasury Board, if she will agree to provide a timeline on health authority reduction along with her upcoming fiscal update?</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 39 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 475 of the Revised Statutes of 1989. The Trade Union Act, to Protect Users of Accessible Transit Services. (Hon. Jamie Baillie)</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Ordered that these bills be read a second time on a future day.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </questions>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2">
          <from>HON. DIANA WHALEN</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, the question I thought was going to the Minister of Health and Wellness on the timeline for his changes to the DHAs. I can say that we will not have that ready to provide for you when the update is done. I'm legislated to provide an update before the end of this calendar year, so that is underway. A lot of planning is already underway for that. On the day that I give the fiscal update, that's what we'll be focusing on singularly. Thank you.</p>
        </speech>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <questions>
        <heading>ORAL QUESTIONS PUT BY MEMBERS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Leader of the New Democratic Party.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The time is now 12:33 p.m. We will finish at 1:33 p.m.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition.</p></speech>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>DEP. PREM.: GUYSBOROUGH-EAST. SHORE-TRACADIE MLA</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>- NEWSPAPER ARTICLE</heading>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question through you is to the Deputy Premier. I, like most Nova Scotians, was disappointed to read the details of past land dealings by the member for Guysborough-Eastern Shore-Tracadie in today's ChronicleHerald. This October, when similar details were disclosed by the same publication, the Premier defended the member for Guysborough-Eastern Shore-Tracadie, alleging the story contained "misrepresented, distorted facts that aren't checked, that are inaccurate being put on, being out into the media as if they're accurate." I'll table that article.</p>
<p>My question to the Deputy Premier is, does she believe the facts presented in today's ChronicleHerald are accurate, and if not, what specific details would she take issue with?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5"><from>HON. STEPHEN MCNEIL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, the Minister of Education and Early Childhood Development met with schools boards on February 14<sup>th</sup> of this year to give boards their funding targets. Five boards were told they would see funding cuts of nearly $5 million in total. This is, of course, on top of the $31 million that was cut in funding and the $34 million inflationary costs that the government has downloaded on the boards.</p>
<p>My question to the Premier is, can the Premier tell parents, students, and teachers how much money his government has cut out of public education in the last three and a half years?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The question doesn't apply to any specific ministry. We will have a brief recess.</p>
          </speech>
          <narrative>
            <p>10:19 a.m. The House recessed.</p>
          </narrative>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined"><from>THE PREMIER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, what we have done is increase the amount of per-student funding in education to its highest levels in history. We have, of course, gone through some very difficult times in this province, where there simply is not the money available to do what was done in the past, so we have sought to work with the boards in order to ensure that their funding is appropriate, to be able to deliver the services that the young people of our province need and deserve.</p>
<p>We intend to continue to do that. We asked them, and I know that the boards have worked away at taking that money out of administration so that it would not come out of the classroom. Of course, we would like to encourage them to continue to engage in that kind of appropriate budgeting.</p></speech>
          <narrative>
            <p>10:20 a.m. The House reconvened.</p>
          </narrative>
          <speech by="#fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5"><from>MR. MCNEIL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I don't know of a board in the Province of Nova Scotia that feels that the government has actually been working with them in the best interests of kids. Since taking office, the Premier has seen $76 million in cuts in public education. Over 700 teacher positions have been cut thanks to this government, and another 170 are being cut in this budget cycle alone. Schools are going without maintenance work, and young children are having to spend hours to get to and from school. On the flip side, the cost of power has gone up 30 per cent under this government, and school boards have reported power bills of $1 million - $1 million in power bills alone.</p>
<p>Will the Premier tell those parents and teachers what he expects boards to eliminate because of this direct funding cut to school boards? More teachers? Student supports? Maintenance? Buses? Which one?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>MS. MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, in October when details were revealed regarding the past transactions made by the member for Guysborough-Eastern Shore-Tracadie when he was president of the Guysborough Tourism Complex Limited. The Premier was quoted as saying that "he has been forthright and honest and up front in all my dealings with him."</p>
<p>So my question for the Deputy Premier is, can she confirm that the Premier and the government caucus had conducted a full review into the past business dealings by the member, and if we can expect that the results of that review will be provided to the public?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined"><from>THE PREMIER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I just want to correct the information from the Leader of the Official Opposition. No teachers have been cut from our system. In fact, we are adding in more teachers as a result of increased funding where they are needed. We have instituted caps on class size and hired more teachers in order to make sure that that has happened. In addition to that, we are building new schools in communities throughout the province. We are providing Nova Scotia students with the best quality of education. We are working with our partners to ensure that that takes place. We are doing that under one of the most financially-challenging periods in our province's history.</p>
<p>The good news, Mr. Speaker, as evidenced by the budget this year, is that we're turning the corner. Because of the good financial management of the province, there is now more opportunity for us to be able to extend services, and we intend to do that.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Thank you for rephrasing the question.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#fe20fa65-2371-4fef-a6ec-d2a63b72dfa5">
            <from>MR. MCNEIL</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, it's very clear that what we've seen under this government is a direct attack on public education. This government has tried to balance the books on the backs of our children. There are 700 teaching positions that have been eliminated since this government has taken power. Then, when school boards go about doing what is their responsibility when it comes to looking at their infrastructure, when they look at whether or not to close schools, when they go through the gut-wrenching experience of asking parents, teachers, and community members to come forward to make a concrete decision about what they can do, this minister interferes in that decision. But not only does the minister interfere - she interferes, but says, no new money.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be">
            <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I find it most unfortunate that this matter is being brought to the floor of the Legislature. There have been two articles on this. I believe the member from Guysborough-Eastern Shore-Tracadie has been honest and up front with this, and we're still at a loss as to exactly what allegation is being alleged in the article as there is none. This matter has clearly been dealt with and I am sure the Premier stands behind his initial comments on this matter.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined"><from>THE PREMIER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, the question - I guess it was a question - that was asked by the Leader of the Opposition contains inherent contradictions. I know that they're happy with that, but the reality is that this is a Leader who told his own annual general meeting that he was happy with the engagement that had taken place, that he thought the model worked, despite the fact that it has been community dividing and adversarial, and despite the fact that communities across the province have said that this is not the manner in which they want to handle this.</p>
<p>Further, Mr. Speaker, he talks about the idea of interfering in a process when you have a minister who is actually listening to the people of the province about the concerns that they have, and who is going to the boards to say, in the context of the decisions that you're being asked to make, would you delay these decisions so that we might work with you in order to develop a better process, who has a better process for bringing communities together, rather than dividing them? I don't see that as interference. I see that as responsibility.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9">
            <from>MS. MACDONALD</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, the Premier has stated repeatedly that trust is the yardstick by which Nova Scotians should measure this government. In the interest of trust, will the Deputy Premier request that the member from Guysborough-Eastern Shore-Tracadie make available all financial and legal documents related to the swap of land between the Guysborough Tourism Complex and the wife of the member from Guysborough-Easter Shore-Tracadie in 1995?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be">
            <from>MR. SAMSON</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, when it comes to a question of trust there is no better judge of trust than the residents of Nova Scotia, and when it comes to the member in question that the NDP have decided today to attack, I would suggest that the people have passed judgment in electing him for 25 years as a municipal councillor. He has served the people of his municipality with distinction not only as a councillor but also as a warden, and they have rewarded that most recently by electing him to this Chamber. To have the Leader of the NDP now not only question him, but question his wife is absolutely deplorable. (Applause)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Order, please. I am about to break a long-standing tradition about introductions in Question Period. I feel that it's necessary. We have a very important dignitary who has joined us here today. I will recognize the honourable Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party to do the introduction, but I will add a minute to Question Period.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>DEP. PREM.: CAPITAL DIST. HEALTH AUTH. - FAST FOOD FRANCHISES</heading>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>I'd like to return to health care, if I may - an issue of great interest to all Nova Scotians.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, in allnovascotia.com this morning it was reported that the government may well find that it's back into a deficit position, that the debts of the province continue to run up. That makes it very important that we work together to find waste and inefficiency in our system, like the number of health authorities, and ensure that that money is saved and directed to actual health care.</p>
<p>I do have a question for our Deputy Premier, who is also the Minister of Finance and Treasury Board. Last year it was discovered that Capital Health had been denied permission by the former NDP Government to end its subsidy to a Tim Hortons franchise and other private fast-food providers at its premises in the Capital District Health Authority.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, this is an area where I believe there is also common ground between the new Liberal Government and the Official Opposition, who both called the government of the day on why they would take health care dollars and spend it on fast-food franchises. In fact, the Leader of the Liberal Party, now our Premier, said at the time that it was corporate welfare of the worst kind, and I could not agree more.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I'd like to ask the Deputy Premier, now that they are in government, is that still the policy of the Liberal Party?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>We welcome all our guests to the gallery and hope that they enjoy this afternoon's proceedings.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party on his question.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>PREM. - SCH. CURRICULUM: DIGITAL CITIZENSHIP - INCLUDE</heading>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question is to the Premier. Nova Scotia is, as we discussed, making national and international news this week for very sad and tragic reasons, but together we do have a moment where we can truly make news in a more positive way by being a leader in the prevention of bullying and cyberbullying here at home, and showing the rest of the country how to do that.</p>
<p>One of the recommendations of the MacKay task force on bullying, Mr. Speaker, was to teach digital citizenship in our schools, to actually place it on the curriculum, so that all young Nova Scotians know about the rights and the responsibilities that they now have, as citizens in an on-line and digital world - that they can use those tools for the good that they are meant to be and learn not to use those tools in a destructive manner.</p>
<p>My question to the Premier is, will he agree to place digital citizenship on the school curriculum as soon as possible, as recommended by the report? I'll table that page of the report for the Premier.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2">
            <from>HON. DIANA WHALEN</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, we appreciate that question. As the honourable Leader of the Official Opposition has said, this was something that we felt was wrong, when we looked at it as we were in Opposition. I can assure the member that this is something that is being looked at in the Department of Health and Wellness.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>MR. BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I appreciate that answer from the Deputy Premier. This is an area where we can work together. Capital Health has reported that they expect to lose approximately $1.4 million on subsidies to private, fast-food providers like Tim Hortons on their premises each year and tried three times, under the previous NDP Government, to get permission to stop handing that money off to private companies like Tim Hortons, so that they could then spend it on actual health care delivery.</p>
<p>I am very pleased to hear that just like us, in the Official Opposition, the government sees the error in allowing our tax dollars to be used in such a wasteful way.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I will ask the Deputy Premier, will she take action to ensure that no health authority in Nova Scotia is allowed to prop up a private, fast-food franchise with our tax dollars?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, this recommendation was accepted by the government, and in fact it is embedded within the curriculum of the schools. It starts, as I understand it, in Primary.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>MR. BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I thank the Premier for that answer. The government has not incorporated all of the recommendations of the MacKay task force, even though it was the result of over a year of consultation and discussion with both experts and those who are involved in protecting our children. For example, the task force did provide a definition of cyberbullying that could be placed into provincial law to ensure that those who engage in bullying and cyberbullying know both what it is and the consequences of committing that offence.</p>
<p>I will ask the Premier, will he now commit to defining cyberbullying as an offence in provincial law, including spelling out the consequences for those who engage in it?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048">
            <from>HON. LEO GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I thank the Leader of the Official Opposition for the question. It's one of those areas that when you come into government, it is part of the business plan for this year. So far it is underway. We are currently working with Capital Health to see whether or not the contract is there for a period of time and how we can now deal with this. It is a question that has come back to be a current one, not just from the Opposition bringing it forward but as we look at business plans and where future changes can be made that will, in fact, put that kind of money on the front line.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined"><from>THE PREMIER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, we have looked carefully, and we have implemented those recommendations in the task force that we felt were capable of being implemented. For those that we considered needed more study, that is certainly underway.</p>
<p>The committee will have the opportunity to go back and revisit that report. We intend to move forward very, very quickly. As the Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party would know, up until this point Nova Scotia has been a leader with respect to bullying. We are the ones who had the first bullying task force, and we move forward, accepting the fact that technology is constantly changing, which means that we have a responsibility to continue to modify, continue to learn what the consequences of these technologies are and to do something about it. That is the commitment that the government has.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>MR. BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, again I thank the Premier for that answer. The need to implement all of the recommendations of the MacKay task force is now stronger than ever. I would encourage the government to not merely study the study any longer, but to get on with reviewing all of the recommendations and putting them into practice.</p>
<p>I will ask the Premier as a result - the MacKay task force included some recommendations around giving school officials and other responsible figures of authority all the tools they need for a greater early intervention when they see bullying or cyberbullying taking place, to give them the tools to actually intervene in time to stop it in its tracks - I ask the Premier, will he commit to implementing all of the recommendations of the MacKay task force, including those that specifically address early intervention tools?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined"><from>THE PREMIER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I want him to know that the recommendations that have been accepted have all been implemented, including the one that he mentioned. The fact of the matter is teachers have had in-service in order to be made aware of the supports that are available. This has been part of rolling out the programs to provide teachers with the information they need in order to be able to support students whom they may identify as having difficulty.</p>
<p>The Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party may also know that, with respect to these matters, many of those recommendations would have to involve the federal government, the areas of jurisdiction that belong wholly or partly to the federal government. I, for one, completely agree that this is something that should demand - Nova Scotia is a small jurisdiction, we are a caring jurisdiction with respect to our citizens, but there are some matters, there are some areas of work that need to be done that really extend beyond the boundaries of our province. There needs to be attention paid to this by the House of Parliament and we will work with them, not only to give them the benefit of the work that we've already done, but to assist them in any way we might to address the issues that we now find before our House.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>HEALTH &amp; WELLNESS - PARAMEDICS: BENEFITS - RETENTION</heading>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52">
            <from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, my question is to the Minister of Health and Wellness. Paramedics extracted significant concessions from the previous government through collective bargaining. They left the remaining issues to arbitration. Paramedics were always concerned that any gains made would be clawed back by the company through increasing the costs of their benefits. So my question to the minister is, what assurances can the minister give paramedics that they won't be forced to give back any hard-won gains to the company that they work for and from which they must purchase health benefits directly?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Colchester North.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>EECD: EARLY INTERVENTION PROGS. - FUNDING DETAILS</heading>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>HON. KAREN CASEY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, yesterday the Minister of Education made her Early Years announcement. Sadly, nobody was surprised when we soon realized it was more hype than substance. But keep tuned in - there will be more to come.</p>
<p>A brief issued yesterday at the announcement notes that Early Years Centres, wherever they will be, whenever they will be established will work with Early Intervention programs. My question to the minister is, can the Minister of Education and Early Childhood Development tell members of this House today how much government currently spends on Early Intervention programs?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a">
            <from>HON. RAMONA JENNEX</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, we're in transition with our new Early Years Department and the information about the early intervention is moving over from the Department of Community Services, so I won't be able to answer that because that's not over in my department at this time.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>MS. CASEY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I will tell the House - $2.9 million is currently being spent on Early Intervention, so perhaps the minister could check that out.</p>
<p>There are 900 families already getting support from 17 agencies, but those agencies are maxed out; in fact on top of supporting families and facing growing wait-lists, Early Intervention programs have to fundraise as part of their service agreements. But, children are aging out of the program while they're waiting for service because this government has not funded them properly.</p>
<p>My question to the minister is, how can the minister expect that parents will believe Early Years is a priority for her government when they can't even yet properly fund the services that are in place?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048">
            <from>MR. GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, that's a very, very important question in regard to paramedics and making their livelihood in the province while delivering first-class, really a top-class service of anywhere in North America. I will meet with the new head of EMC to discuss this issue, but I can guarantee this House I won't be a minister who interferes with negotiations.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52">
            <from>MR. D'ENTREMONT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, and no, I hope not, because we saw what it cost us on the last round. So my final question to the minister, requiring employees to purchase health benefits from the company that they work for puts a company in an unfair advantage. As you know, there's a lot of give and take here as it's a conflict of interest that EMC is actually owned by Blue Cross who gives them their insurance as well. So my final question is, will the minister look into allowing paramedics to purchase health benefits from whichever company that they choose?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a">
            <from>MS. JENNEX</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I know that parents and stakeholders across the province were very excited with the announcement yesterday of the integration of all the aspects of Early Years being under one roof. I look forward to working with the stakeholders and with our communities as we integrate our service to meet the needs of our youngest citizens.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22">
            <from>MS. CASEY</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, parents and those who were at the announcement have a right to feel concerned when this minister says that something is her priority. For example, she said a cyberbullying plan was a priority and we know what happened to that. She is putting impossible demands on school boards to choose operations over programming while she guts their funding. Her cuts to education will begin when students are continuing to wait for speech-language and school psych assessments. My question to the minister is, why should parents believe this minister is making education and early education a priority when she consistently lets children and families down?</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>FIN.: CPP ENHANCEMENT - STANCE</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Kings West.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>HEALTH &amp; WELLNESS - INSULIN PUMPS:</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>APPLICATIONS (07/31/13) - CONFIRM</heading>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>HON. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I appreciate the question from the member opposite who was the former Minister of Finance, who would know some of the discussions that are being held with other Ministers of Finance across the province. Absolutely, it is on the agenda for Finance Ministers to look at retirement security for Canadians. There is evidence that the CPP is a strong plan that has weathered the decades since it was brought in.</p>
<p>At present we are still in discussions and negotiations and following the debate federally. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048">
            <from>MR. LEO GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Over the past couple of days Nova Scotians have been flooded with a set of announcements which produced lots of photo ops but were light on details. Proof in point - the insulin pump announcement, which is a good announcement, but instead of providing specifics we got a press release which reads, "The province expects to begin taking applications by July 31." I will table that release. Mr. Speaker, that sentence doesn't instill much confidence given the press release was issued by the Premier's Office. Could the Minister of Health and Wellness please confirm whether applications will be available and accepted by July 31<sup>st</sup>, yes or no?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#32a29c39-915c-40e7-b749-7c09299ed1f7">
            <from>HON. DAVID WILSON</from>
            <p>I appreciate the member being at one of those photo ops with the Premier and me. I know he's very interested in the insulin pump program and I look forward to the member approving and supporting the budget so we can move forward to implementing this service.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>MS. MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I didn't hear a rousing support for the Canada Pension Plan from our government. Nearly one-third of our workforce will face a steep drop in their standard of living by the time they retire. Most provinces, pension experts, labour unions and seniors' organizations agree that enhancing the Canada Pension Plan is the best way to avoid a crisis of income security in the very near future.</p>
<p>My question through you to the Minister of Finance and Treasury Board is, would she please explain why her government is so indifferent to a problem which surely will not go away any time soon without acting to improve CPP?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#32a29c39-915c-40e7-b749-7c09299ed1f7">
            <from>MR. WILSON</from>
            <p>Children's health care is very important to this government, that's why we are reinstating a program cut by the Liberals under the dental care for children. That's why we're introducing an insulin pump program here in Nova Scotia. I know the young people that were in attendance at the event the other day are extremely happy, Mr. Speaker. We're going to work as quickly as we can to ensure that we pass the budget and that we implement the program as soon as we can, and I know Nova Scotians are looking forward to that program to be up and running here in the province.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>MS. WHALEN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, the question of enhancing retirement income is not one that can be answered in just a few short sentences here in Question Period. I would like to say that our government takes it very seriously that people are retiring without adequate replacement income from private pension plans or from their own savings or from the Canada Pension Plan. The member is wrong in saying that this would be - I wrote it down - she said in the very near future that this would help. An enhancement to the CPP will be a long-term position. It is not going to help in the near future. It won't help people who are already retired or about to retire. It will help young workers who are putting their money in for 30 or 40 years and then will retire.</p>
<p>The urgency of changing the CPP is not immediate. The discussions are underway. The federal minister and the provincial ministers are looking at it. It is something that needs to be in the mix with public plans, voluntary plans and so on.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Inverness.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>JUSTICE - BULLYING: EARLY INTERVENTION - TOOLS</heading>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9">
            <from>MS. MACDONALD</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, federal Finance Minister Jim Flaherty has been dragging his feet on any action that would lead to improving the Canada Pension Plan. First he said he wanted all the provinces in agreement and then he said the economic recovery following the recession had to be stronger. My question for the Minister of Finance and Treasury Board is, why are she and her government adopting the position of the Harper Government on enhancing the Canada Pension Plan?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff">
            <from>MR. ALLAN MACMASTER</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, we are mourning the death of Rehtaeh Parsons. I know in Inverness I've had many calls and e-mails from people in Inverness County who are feeling terrible about the situation. The minister said yesterday that he would consider strengthening legislation around the distribution of disturbing graphic images; this is an important step. May I also suggest we have a need for laws that allow for early intervention. My question for the Minister of Justice is, will the minister give school officials and others in position of authority the necessary tools, such as having the ability to remove cellphones, to allow for early intervention on bullying?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>MS. WHALEN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, again, I think the member opposite is wrong in suggesting that she understands what the position is of the government. We have a position of being responsible and caring for pensioners and doing our very best to look after the people of Nova Scotia as they approach retirement or are in retirement.</p>
<p>I spoke strongly against a move by the NDP Government which took away the indexing of pensioners that were under the Public Service Plan and that, I think, shows where our intentions were strong.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#d36a0432-7994-4030-ab00-b21fc858e7d2"><from>HON. ROSS LANDRY</from><p>I just want to further the Premier's statement earlier this afternoon in regard to the strategy that we are putting forth with my colleague in the House, the Minister responsible for the Advisory Council on the Status of Women Act, who will have responsibility over putting together a collaboration, a collective voice from a cross-section of all Nova Scotians, to look at how we best address this.</p>
<p>I also want to point out to my colleague that I've written to my federal colleague, the Honourable Robert Nicholson, in Ottawa, and expressed my concern to help expedite some of the work that we have been doing and have asked him if I could meet with him on an urgent basis, in regard to this matter. I'll table this letter for a matter of record.</p>
<p>I just want to point out to all Nova Scotians that the issue of bullying is something that I personally take to heart, as a commitment, and that I, as the Minister of Justice, am fully committed to this and we, as a government, are as well.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Kings North.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>GAMING: HAMMONDS PLAINS GAMING CTR.</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>- NEIGHBOURHOOD INTEGRATION</heading>
          <speech by="#bc54523e-7553-4c28-b315-79d18165339b"><from>MR. JOHN LOHR</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question is for the Minister responsible for Part II of the Gaming Control Act, VLTs. As the minister knows, a gaming centre is scheduled to open in a residential area of Hammonds Plains, and we have residents from that area in the gallery today. The residents are understandably concerned about the increased traffic and the effect a VLT centre will have on their neighbourhood.</p>
<p>What assurance can the minister give residents, such as Bruce Innes and Orrin Sangster, that the VLT centre will not change their neighbourhood?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#1e5b7bdc-363b-4df4-8258-edcf8f2bf7fb"><from>HON. ANDREW YOUNGER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, just for the information of that member, the VLTs are under Part I of the Gaming Control Act.</p>
<p>The member asked this the other day in the House and, as he is aware, the Government of Nova Scotia entered into an agreement in 2011 with all First Nations, which is a binding and legal agreement which controls gaming in the province and on First Nations Bands.</p>
<p>As the member would also be aware, the province does not approve those. There is no approval process that is given by the province. The same problem has actually happened with the municipality where, because it is reserve land that was actually permitted by the federal Conservatives to be in that community recently, that it also doesn't have to abide by the zoning of the municipality. The location of that facility is ultimately a decision of the federal government when they made the decision to award reserve lands in that community.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff"><from>MR. MACMASTER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, there is no question that bullying has been with us since the dawn of man, no doubt. Certainly it has taken on a new face. (Interruption) And the member has corrected me, and rightly so, the dawn of man and woman - my point being, in agreement with the minister, that technology has put a whole new reality around bullying.</p>
<p>I think the minister has answered my question favourably and I thank him for that, the point being that if people in schools and public places where young people are, when they are away from their parents and their homes, have the ability to use measures to remove those electronic tools when they're being used to bully others, I think that is a good thing. So, minister, I think if we are in agreement here, I'm going to avoid asking a second supplementary and allow the Speaker to carry on with Question Period. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#bc54523e-7553-4c28-b315-79d18165339b"><from>MR. LOHR</from><p>Thank you for that answer, Mr. Minister. I appreciate the correction on Part I and Part II.</p>
<p>The residents of Hammonds Plains feel helpless and don't know where to turn. The Responsible Gaming Strategy of 2011 indicated that the provincial government would work proactively with both First Nations and with residents. Will the minister commit to meet with concerned citizens of Hammonds Plains and discuss this?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Richmond.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>TIR - PAVING TENDERS: RICHMOND/INVERNESS/VICTORIA COS.</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>- CANCELLATION EXPLAIN</heading>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, earlier this year the Department of Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal issued tenders for aggregate to carry out single chip seal paving in the Counties of Richmond, Inverness, and Victoria. That work was to be carried out this summer.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, this week, on Monday, April 8<sup>th</sup>, these three tenders were abruptly cancelled by the Department of Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal. Bidders on the tenders were given no notice of the change, prior to Monday's announcement. A lot of work and effort goes into preparing these bids, and private businesses in the Counties of Richmond, Inverness, and Victoria were looking forward to some much-needed work for local truckers.</p>
<p>My question is, will the Minister of Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal advise the House as to why these three tenders were cancelled so abruptly.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#bc54523e-7553-4c28-b315-79d18165339b">
            <from>MR. LOHR</from>
            <p>Thank you, Mr. Minister, for that commitment and that is all.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Leader of the New Democratic Party.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>FIN.: CPP COVERAGE - P.E.I. PLAN</heading>
          <speech by="#4f242ac5-fc82-41a3-8089-419e69284e5e"><from>HON. MAURICE SMITH</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I thank my friend for the question. Yes, as in any process that we undertake, there is a procurement policy that we follow and tendering is the way we go. In this particular case the tenders were issued and when they were returned they were significantly higher than what our anticipation was for that project and for what the budget was we were considering would be appropriate for that project, so we cancelled those tenders and are trying to find ways of providing the aggregate needed in another fashion.</p>
<p>I can tell my friend opposite that our intent is to fully complete the work that we had indicated we were going to undertake in Cape Breton this summer, and that will happen.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>MR. SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, we're pleased to see the work is going to be carried out but the question becomes, how is the department going to get this aggregate if it's not going to a tendering process? The minister has indicated that they've respected the tendering process and that's how they operate, but now that you've cancelled the tenders, how is it that the department is going to move forward in obtaining this aggregate if the tender process has been cancelled?</p>
<p>Basically, my question to the minister is, is the minister stating today that they will be obtaining this aggregate by picking and choosing who they want rather than respecting the long-standing tendering process that has been in place?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>HON. DIANA WHALEN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, again I understand the importance of this question, but I think it's important for the House to know that this is an issue with a lot of different impacts. Certainly we want to talk with business, who'd have to pay their share of this employee benefit if it were to be increased. We have a lot of consultation to do, a lot of study to do and I'm not prepared today to give a position to the member opposite on this.</p>
<p>What I will say is that we're very well aware of the pension needs of Nova Scotians and the elements that have to be improved to get them to a proper retirement.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#4f242ac5-fc82-41a3-8089-419e69284e5e"><from>MR. SMITH</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I thank the member for the question. In this particular case, we will be, as I said - I can assure the member opposite that the appropriate measures will be taken to ensure that the work we have scheduled in Cape Breton will be going forward.</p>
<p>I actually met this week with the members from the Road Builders Association and they raised that issue with me. We explained to them what the situation was, why the tenders were cancelled at this particular time. They understood the need for us to be careful in terms of the monies we spend and to look at whatever options we can come up with in order to provide the materials necessary to get the job done and, at this stage, that's what we're doing.</p>
<p>If we can come up with a source that's going to provide us with the aggregate at a more reasonable price than the tenders provided, then that's the route we will go. Obviously, if there isn't a source that's going to provide that for us, then we will be back looking at those tenders again.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9"><from>MS. MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, Bill VanGorder, the Chair of the Canadian Association of Retired Persons, or CARP, wrote a letter to Jim Flaherty, the Premier, and the Minister of Finance on November 13<sup>th</sup>; I will table a copy of that letter. Mr. VanGorder wrote, and I quote, "The choice is now up to you to decide and declare if and when there will be a change to improve the CPP."</p>
<p>My question for the minister is, what is your response to the Canadian Association of Retired Persons?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>MR. SAMSON</from><p>Well, Mr. Speaker, I'm not sure what message this sends to all the bidders out there as to the work that they put into the tendering process if the minister can simply turn around and say the tenders are too high, we're just going to go buy it from wherever we can find it cheaper - why do we have a tendering process in the province to start off with?</p>
<p>I know that the minister is looking to find as cheap as possible, and the government has somehow painted the road builders as big, bad wolves here, but let's keep in mind that they're also local truckers, small independent businesses that were relying on this work from the larger road builders that are now out of work.</p>
<p>My question is, if the minister is going to go and cherry-pick who he's going to buy the aggregate from, will the minister indicate whether local road truckers are going to have the opportunity to be part of this work or is it all going to be carried out by whoever they buy the aggregate from that they've hand-picked?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2">
            <from>MS. WHALEN</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I think it's important to note that I've had discussions with the Minister of Finance from Prince Edward Island and I reviewed his plan that's put forward as well. But it's important to know that these decisions have been underway on the federal and provincial level since 2009, that the plans and the proposals have changed, that there are objections by certain provinces that are being - I would say objections that the Minister of Finance from P.E.I. is trying to address and make changes. It's a very fluid discussion. There's a lot of negotiating and changing going on, and it doesn't require Nova Scotia to have a position today.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#8b070bb9-483e-4dec-90fa-9496ca56f8a9">
            <from>MS. MACDONALD</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I'd like to table a paper called <i>Strengthening the Canada Pension Plan: Take it to the public</i>, in which the Caledon Institute of Social Policy correctly points out that the deliberations on reforming the CPP are happening behind closed government doors. So my final question to the minister is this: given that the matter of income security is of such importance for a growing number of Nova Scotians, shouldn't there be formal consultations with the public on enhancing the Canada Pension Plan?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>MS. WHALEN</from><p>Again, I would simply say that this is an issue that has been ongoing for years, that we will be part of that discussion, and that I have spoken to a number of the Finance Ministers from across the country, most notably P.E.I. and Ontario, who are in favour of changes. But we also have a meeting set up with the Canadian Federation of Independent Business. We need to hear from their view as well, as I'm sure everyone in the House can appreciate.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, during their time as government, when the NDP had control of government, they did not confer with the retirees of Nova Scotia before taking away their indexing.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#4f242ac5-fc82-41a3-8089-419e69284e5e">
            <from>MR. SMITH</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, again I'll tell my friend that as much as possible of course, because it's an advantage to us to use local trucking because of the distances involved in that kind of thing. As much as possible, yes, we will be using local truckers to haul the aggregate when we get it to where the site is going to be. My understanding is that there will be a number of dumps in the area where the aggregate will be placed - obviously as close as possible to the work that is going to be done - but local truckers certainly will be involved in moving it from those sites to where it needs to go.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Hants West.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>HEALTH &amp; WELLNESS: DND ORs - USAGE</heading>
          <speech by="#250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e">
            <from>MR. KEITH BAIN</from>
            <p>Yesterday the Minister of Education and Early Childhood Development avoided answering my question about her government's future plans for funding private and non-profit child care centres. I've now stood in this House and presented nine examples of the NDP saying one thing and then another on the issue. Mr. Speaker, my question once again through you is, will the minister finally tell members of this House if her department is reviewing the funding model for child care centres?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#b31db77c-006f-4f6e-ab57-0c449cb2d93a">
            <from>HON. RAMONA JENNEX</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I'm really looking forward to working with developing a provincial Early Years partnership and I'm really looking forward to working with our stakeholders in this area because there has been a lot of studies done over the last number of years and there are many issues that we need to work together on and move forward with. Thank you.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048">
            <from>HON. LEO GLAVINE</from>
            <p>I thank the Health Critic opposite for the question. To my knowledge, at this stage no negotiations or meetings have taken place in this regard.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#250f8b2e-9af9-4ca7-9778-41b96426667e"><from>MR. BAIN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, the government has changed its tune on this issue nine times in 16 months. They continue to keep parents and small business owners guessing. The government's plan will have impact on hundreds of small business owners and thousands of families.</p>
<p>People deserve to know what the NDP plans to do. Mr. Speaker, I tabled for the minister, yesterday, the Hansard from the Standing Committee on Community Services where the Deputy Minister of Community Services said there were no plans to review the funding model. Yesterday the minister told reporters there was, and I have the news article to prove that and I'll table it.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, my question through you to the minister is, what child care funding changes will the government be making?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7">
            <from>MR. PORTER</from>
            <p>As the minister knows, spending in health care is growing, and it will continue to do so as our population ages. In the past, the Auditor General has pointed out situations where the department has failed to recognize cost savings and ignored opportunities that could save millions of dollars for our health care system. This overhead at the facility at Stadacona has already long since been paid for, and there are military doctors there willing to work. Does the minister agree that this is worthy of consideration for the hundreds of Nova Scotians waiting for surgery?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048">
            <from>MR. GLAVINE</from>
            <p>As we take a look at reducing surgical wait times, in particular with orthopaedics, cataract surgery, and general surgery, all of the capacity in the province is being looked at. One of the reasons why we're changing the DHA structure is to allow for greater collaboration, for clinicians to practise in multiple facilities. This is a worthy idea that the member has brought forward.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7">
            <from>MR. PORTER</from>
            <p>I appreciate the answer from the minister, and I'll go right to my question. Given that there is an opportunity, will the minister commit to working with the representatives of the Stadacona Hospital to open their operating rooms for Nova Scotians before that eventual closure in March of 2014?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048">
            <from>MR. GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, what I can commit to is gaining an understanding of what kind of a relationship and process is needed for Nova Scotians to deliver Nova Scotian positions, to deliver services within the context of a military base, a military operation. I'm sure there are provincial-federal requirements and we can certainly have a look at that.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Queens-Shelburne.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>TIR: CROSSWALK SAFETY - AWARENESS</heading>
          <speech by="#3b49aa8d-3e78-4679-b8f7-f3161f11d3a3">
            <from>HON. STERLING BELLIVEAU</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, my question is for the Minister of Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal. Winter is a treacherous time for drivers and people walking. Dark, snowy, foggy and wet weather makes it difficult to see properly. Since the beginning of November, there have already been half a dozen different instances involving people being struck in crosswalks. My question to the minister is, what action is this government taking to increase awareness about crosswalk safety in Nova Scotia?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Richmond.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>SNSMR - STRAIT AREA TRANSIT: OPERATIONS - RESUMPTION</heading>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, Strait Area Transit provides an essential transportation system for residents in the Town of Port Hawkesbury in the Counties of Richmond and Inverness. On March 25<sup>th</sup> Strait Area Transit suspended its operations due to financial concerns.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, it has now been over two weeks that this service has not been in operation. People have had to cancel medical appointments, and miss other appointments as well, because of the suspension of the service.</p>
<p>Could the Minister of Service Nova Scotia and Municipal Relations advise the House as to the status of negotiations to resume the operations of Strait Area Transit?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#2c8e1a56-2f9d-4156-a91f-77802701e3d3"><from>MR. MACLELLAN</from><p>Thank you for the question. I met with the Road Safety Advisory Committee yesterday morning. Again, as a Nova Scotian, as an MLA and as someone who is concerned about the safety of our citizens, I wanted to understand where we help and what role we play. So, again, we've got department officials who are in constant contact with the municipal units, with private stakeholders, and there are some in particular in the HRM who have some very good ideas and have done some significant research on what ways we can improve safety for pedestrians and, of course, for drivers, as this is a shared responsibility in the sidewalks and on the roadway.</p>
<p>We are listening to any stakeholder and for me, as the minister, if there is someone who has suggestions and ideas on how we improve these things, I'm all ears. Again, it is the responsibility and the jurisdiction of the municipalities. However, we are going to work together, and specifically with this study in February, I think that creates a lot of dialogue for us to move forward and, again, where we can help, we certainly will.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#3b49aa8d-3e78-4679-b8f7-f3161f11d3a3">
            <from>MR. BELLIVEAU</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, crosswalk safety isn't a new issue but I think the Minister of Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal would agree that there are always opportunities to find new and better ways of doing things. My final question to the minister is, what new initiatives is government examining to ensure crosswalk safety is at the top of the minds of all Nova Scotians?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#d6c0c78d-dcf3-456a-915c-a20ecb33050f"><from>HON. JOHN MACDONELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I think when the member asked a question on this topic a couple of weeks back, I indicated that my staff were intending and trying to set up a meeting with stakeholders in the area, which included the representatives from the municipalities involved. That meeting happened yesterday and I haven't yet been briefed as to the outcome of that.</p>
<p>I want members to know - and the member opposite, for sure - that my staff did go with a proposal around what we could offer from the province in terms of funding. This would be short term, in the hopes that they would get to a long-term solution. The issue around people's appointments and whatever - we also fund Strait Area Transit money through a door-to-door program, which is actually the way we fund other transit associations in the province. We don't fund fixed route, but because the Strait area has a combination of the two - I think it would be up to them to try to ensure that, because we fund the door-to-door so people can get to their appointments, that would be an aspect of their program that they see to it that they maintain. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#2c8e1a56-2f9d-4156-a91f-77802701e3d3"><from>MR. MACLELLAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, basically how this works is the Transportation Association of Canada creates a set of standards that are abided by all provinces and all municipal units. We take those recommendations. The idea is to standardize them, so whether you're in Nova Scotia, you're in B.C., you're in all points in between, there's a standardized set of rules, signage and those type of things. That is the information that we have.</p>
<p>Obviously, as a provincial government, we set those regulations and those laws and it's up to the municipalities to make adjustments on how they meet those requirements and all the municipal units in this province have done a very good job to meet those requirements.</p>
<p>Again to the member's points, those stakeholders who have a role in this serious issue for Nova Scotians and have points and perspectives that they want to share - we're listening. We want to make sure we do the best things for pedestrians. Again, I do want to remind all Nova Scotians that this is a shared responsibility. We have to be very careful on the streets. Just because you have the right-of-way, don't assume that you are safe to proceed. Make sure you are looking and you are aware of both sides of the road for traffic.</p>
<p>The biggest amount of collisions and problems that we have are with sidewalks that are at intersections of lights. So just when you get that beeping hand, it doesn't mean that you can bolt across. That has been the highest number, statistically, for incidents in this province.</p>
<p>Those are the types of things we want to share. Sharing information is important, and I think that in February, some of that report will suggest we do more advertising and more marketing on the importance of road safety. If that's the recommendation from municipal units, we'll do just that. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>MR. SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I can't encourage the minister enough to look at this as an emergency situation. You've got people missing important medical appointments because of this loss of service. You have students who attend the Regional Occupational Centre in Port Hawkesbury who are being disrupted as well. People came to rely on this service, and I know the government has indicated how it sees this as an important service. I would hope that the minister would see this as an emergency situation and be prepared to put the funding necessary in place while a long-term solution is being carried out, because as we talk about this, we have riders who do not have a means of transportation, and that needs to be addressed.</p>
<p>So again, my question to the minister is, is he prepared to put in place emergency funding to get Strait Area Transit up and running as soon as possible?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#d6c0c78d-dcf3-456a-915c-a20ecb33050f">
            <from>MR. MACDONELL</from>
            <p>That was the game plan that my staff went down there with. It was the idea that we would use our envelope of funding that we have to help them in the short term until a long-term solution could happen. I think the member is aware that the province gave $120,000 last Fall and another $5,000 a couple of weeks back, and we were not informed about the impending shutdown of service. We do not fund fixed-route transit, Mr. Speaker, and it's my expectation that we will not be funding this into the long term. Thank you.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>MR. SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I'm sure that the residents of the Strait area listening to that are a bit confused about door-to-door and fixed route and funding, so let me make the answer as simple as possible, and hopefully the minister can make his answer as simple as possible.</p>
<p>How much money are the minister and his department prepared to make available to Strait Area Transit today to restore that service?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Clare-Digby.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>HEALTH &amp; WELLNESS: VILLA ACADIENNE - UPDATE</heading>
          <speech by="#d6c0c78d-dcf3-456a-915c-a20ecb33050f">
            <from>MR. MACDONELL</from>
            <p>I can probably get that number for the member before the end of the day. It will be what is in the envelope for the programs that we traditionally offer. The reason for the meeting with the stakeholders, and in particular the municipalities, is that fixed-route transit is funded through municipal units, not through the province.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#0c003e1d-f0de-4ef6-85c6-604c99fbd41f"><from>MR. GORDON WILSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, first I'd like to thank you very much for the privilege, and thank the House for the privilege, of being able to stand here and ask questions on behalf of the citizens of Clare-Digby.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, this question is for the Minister of Health and Wellness. The Villa Acadienne nursing home has been slated for replacement for some time now, and the citizens of the community of Meteghan have watched as two nursing homes adjoining them in Digby and Yarmouth have been replaced. During my campaign, the Villa Acadienne was the number one question on the minds of the people of Clare for replacement.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, can the minister provide the House with a project update on the Villa Acadienne nursing home?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Argyle.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>ERDT - SWSDA: GARIAN CONST. - PAYMENT</heading>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>It's good to stand and ask this question once again. Over the last number of sessions, I've pretty much asked this question almost every time to the Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism: the issue of the remaining creditors from the fallout of the closing of the South West Shore Development Authority.</p>
<p>As you know, a beautiful school community centre was constructed in the Village of Tusket, a great model of rural development that is well used by the Acadian community - a place to gather, and a place to celebrate and maintain our distinct culture and heritage. But a cloud still hangs over the remaining $400,000 that is owed to the local contractor Garian Construction. Will the minister review this once again and help find a solution once and for all in order to get Garian Construction paid?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048"><from>HON. LEO GLAVINE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I thank the member for the question. This announcement, I believe, was first made under the Rodney MacDonald Government. It has gone through now over four years under the NDP Government. It is identified in the top 15 replacement bed facilities that we need to be working on.</p>
<p>I want to let the member know that it will be in the first group of replacement facilities that will be initiated by this government.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#b1bb12cd-3928-4525-bab1-d76d28109b5b">
            <from>HON. PERCY PARIS</from>
            <p>First of all, I've got to say that as an entrepreneur myself - I've been in business for 23-plus years - when you're owed money, you like to be paid. I know that as an entrepreneur and as an individual, and I'm sure that there are many members of the House who have seen in our days some debts that weren't paid - money owing to us. One of the problems we have with this case, this instance, is that monies were paid out by the provincial government to take care of that debt. And certainly, I agree with the member opposite, a nice facility, a great facility down there. We did fill our obligation when we were asked by SWSDA to look after that debt, and we did that by writing the cheque.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>MR. D'ENTREMONT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I thank the minister for that answer, even though, really, when you look at it, I'm not asking that the minister go and write another cheque to try to pay for this. What I'm asking for him to do is to sit down with the local councils, maybe with some local business people, and sit down with Garian Construction, to see if there is a solution that can be found. Many times we've heard that litigation is the only way to go on this, but the difficulty we had all along with Garian Construction, the school community centre, is the fact that it is a Crown-owned property. It is attached to a school, and therefore, a lien couldn't be put on, and it would be very difficult to litigate that way.</p>
<p>So again, my question to the minister is, will the minister listen to the pleas of the local area and Garian Construction and commit to finding a solution?</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>AGRIC.: STRAWBERRY GROWERS - AID PKG.</heading>
          <speech by="#bc54523e-7553-4c28-b315-79d18165339b"><from>MR. JOHN LOHR</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question is for the Minister of Agriculture. Late last week, the Minister of Agriculture announced an aid package for strawberry growers in the amount of $2.3 million. The amount provided by the government is about half of what the industry requested.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, it is important to the province's strawberry industry that all strawberry growers eradicate the virus that damaged last year's crop. If the aid package provided by government is insufficient to do the job, will the minister provide more funding to make sure that the Nova Scotia strawberry crop is healthy and sustainable in the coming years?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Halifax Clayton Park.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>IMMIGRATION - TARGETS: FAILURE - EXPLAIN</heading>
          <speech by="#aef785d7-7697-4453-8f9c-eef26e4928c3">
            <from>MR. COLWELL</from>
            <p>I'd like to thank the honourable member again for the question. Actually, I met with the strawberry producers on Sunday. The application forms will soon be in their hands. They had an opportunity to review the information of how they would apply and have some input into that application process. We made some changes that would suit their situation better and that will be in their hands very shortly.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#bc54523e-7553-4c28-b315-79d18165339b">
            <from>MR. LOHR</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I thank the minister for the answer. If the government aid package is insufficient, the temptation will be there for some struggling farmers to do nothing and hope for the best crop possible next year. That will put nearby strawberry farms in jeopardy, since the destructive viruses will continue to spread. What is the Department of Agriculture doing to ensure that the viruses that caused the farmers to plow under millions of dollars' worth of crop don't return next year?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, au contraire. We have exceeded our targets, and to that point, we have, through the diligent work of the Premier, got it up to 700. We are working with immigrants coming into the province. We are working closely with our federal counterparts, in building our profile within the immigrant community, building that up. It is a work in progress and we are moving forward with it. Thank you.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#aef785d7-7697-4453-8f9c-eef26e4928c3">
            <from>MR. COLWELL</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, that's a very important question and it's one that has been posed by the industry itself. Unfortunately, under the present laws and the regulations we have, I do not have the ability to order those fields plowed under. There are some other processes we are looking at to see if we can make that happen, and hopefully it will happen. As the member is probably well aware, if they leave the strawberry plants in the field, the yield would be so low on it that it doesn't make any difference anyway, whether they keep them or not. But they should be plowed under, and we're going to endeavour to do everything we can to make sure those are plowed under.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>MS. WHALEN</from><p>I'm referring to the total number of immigrants. I think the minister is referring to the nominee numbers that were allowed and the 200 he speaks to are for one year only. We were given an extra 200 to increase, so that's not a permanent increase, which, again, is unfortunate to meeting any of the goals that are outlined in the Immigration Strategy. The government has cut the international graduate stream. They cut the agri-food pilot stream, and the non-dependent child stream has also been cut, all because, according to a 2012 ChronicleHerald story, the federal government was irked that these streams existed, and perhaps duplicated. I'll table that as well, Mr. Speaker, for the minister's benefit.</p>
<p>We're seeing more and more of this government ceding its own provincial responsibility to the Harper Conservatives, and no good will ever come of that. But that's not all we see cut. There has also been a cut to the immigration budget this year.</p>
<p>Could the minister please indicate whether the cut in the budget, in addition to our cuts in the provincial nominee streams, is an admission that the NDP Government has failed when it comes to immigration?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Chester-St. Margaret's.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>SENIORS: DEPT. - BUDGET CUTS</heading>
          <speech by="#980981f9-4823-4d4b-8134-a47d4ecf5405">
            <from>HON. DENISE PETERSON-RAFUSE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, my question is to the Minister of Seniors. The Liberals have promised a 1 per cent cut to almost every single government department, including the Department of Seniors. This is a small department that financially supports extremely important programs for our senior population. A $1 cut will negatively affect our Nova Scotia seniors in that department - any cuts will. My question to the minister, why is the minister cutting funding to the Department of Seniors when seniors need our support the most?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>MR. CORBETT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, one thing this government has done in a very positive way is look at our record on retention, where it's really at. We're retaining more immigrants than ever before, and indeed, the one thing that questioner came awfully close to being in agreement is that the cuts have happened, but the cuts are beside her there. It's the federal government doing the cuts, not the province.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>MS. WHALEN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, the fact of the matter is that the NDP Government has ceded parts of our Provincial Nominee Program to the Harper Conservatives, and then they're using this uploading to justify a budget cut. We all agree in this House that immigration is important, and I think we can all agree that this NDP Government has failed in their aims in immigration. It's interesting to note that this NDP Government has tied its immigration strategy to its failed jobsHere strategy, which speaks volumes.</p>
<p>Given that we need to increase the number of permanent residents by over 50 per cent in the next two years in order to meet the goals that are set out in the Immigration Strategy, would the minister please tell us how this target will ever be achieved?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#980981f9-4823-4d4b-8134-a47d4ecf5405">
            <from>MS. PETERSON-RAFUSE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, thank you very much for that answer. But when I went door to door, I know many seniors were very confused about what programs were available. They were pleased to learn that the new Seniors Navigators Program could connect people who have information about where to turn. The new Seniors Navigators Program was scheduled to begin in 2014. Will the minister commit to implementing the Seniors Navigators Program?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048">
            <from>MR. GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, again, a very, very important part of the program delivery from the Department of Seniors, and it is one that I know, in the community that I represent, is very important to a significant number. I live in a part of Nova Scotia where already there are five communities that have 25 per cent of their population that are over 65. This is an important program. It will remain in place.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Preston.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#980981f9-4823-4d4b-8134-a47d4ecf5405">
            <from>MS. PETERSON-RAFUSE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, knowing that the budget year ends in April, when will this consultation process begin?</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>SNSMR - HARP: BUDGET ALLOTMENT - EXPENDITURE</heading>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048">
            <from>MR. GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I know that we will be dealing with the Senior Citizens' Secretariat, the Department of Seniors, and I know when I do the provincial tour around the restructuring of the DHAs, it'll be broad enough that many questions regarding health care delivery, and in particular what we will be doing for seniors in the coming decades, will be very much top of mind. And so, early in the new year, that will be part of the process in the DHA tour.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#aef785d7-7697-4453-8f9c-eef26e4928c3"><from>HON. KEITH COLWELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, the Heating Assistance Rebate Program is an important program, one which many Nova Scotians rely on to assist them through the cold winter months. However, this program has been underspent for the last several years.</p>
<p>Can the Minister of Service Nova Scotia and Municipal Relations tell the House if Nova Scotians were able to access the full budget allotment for this program in this fiscal year?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Truro-Bible Hill-Millbrook-Salmon River.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>NAT. RES.: PROTECTED LANDS - MORATORIUM</heading>
          <speech by="#c479d7de-83a6-47c7-a045-07816407bdb3">
            <from>MS. LENORE ZANN</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, my question is for the Minister of Environment. Last week, the Minister of Natural Resources told this House that he has "never been a proponent of reducing protected land targets." I will table that. My question for the Minister of Environment is, has his colleague, the Minister of Natural Resources, written any correspondence to the Department of Environment within the last 12 months calling for a moratorium on protected lands?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#d6c0c78d-dcf3-456a-915c-a20ecb33050f">
            <from>HON. JOHN MACDONELL</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, yes, they were able to access it.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#d20d446c-118f-4445-81f4-cf995b335391">
            <from>HON. RANDY DELOREY</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, since the question posed actually details correspondence from my colleague, the Minister of Natural Resources, I'd like to defer to him, since he would be the source of the correspondence in question.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#aef785d7-7697-4453-8f9c-eef26e4928c3"><from>MR. COLWELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, the NDP has no problem spending millions of dollars on political advertising. Communications Nova Scotia's costs have tripled over the past few years, and yet the minister can't seem to get the word out about this important program. We are hearing from Nova Scotians who had previously accessed this program that they did not receive the automatic notifications and forms which the department promises.</p>
<p>Will the minister tell the House how many Nova Scotians were not sent notifications and forms this year, and why that didn't happen?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#8834559e-ddf7-4ac7-9b30-8ada0eb9a7ca"><from>HON. ZACH CHURCHILL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, to the member's point, I sent a letter on behalf of constituents that felt that they were ignored during the NDP consultation process regarding protected lands. They had very specific concerns about accessing their camps and recreational grounds that they have used for generations. I brought those concerns to the floor of this Legislature, as any MLA would who is representing their people. I am proud of that, I will continue to do that on behalf of my members in my riding. (Applause)</p>
<p>And again for the clarification of the House, all Parties unanimously voted in favour of that 13 per cent target. This government remains committed to it.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#d6c0c78d-dcf3-456a-915c-a20ecb33050f"><from>MR. MACDONELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I think I have answered this question once a year for three years. I would think the member opposite would be aware, because his office should have received the applications that all MLAs received to give out to their constituents. If anybody is coming in there looking for an application, they should be able to get it from him. If he has had people contacting him because they want to get on the program, what is he doing with those applications? Maybe he might just want to say, I have one here in my office.</p>
<p>We get in the range of 50,000 people who make use of the program. It could be 53,000 this year. For everyone who has used the program in the past, we mail out an application we mail out an application form to them. We send those applications to a wide variety of non-governmental organizations. They are available at our access centres, all the MLAs get them. We promoted this program through the media, Mr. Speaker.</p>
<p>There may be another program that is promoted more widely through government, I can't be sure what that would be, but certainly - his question was, who has not received it? Well there are 900,000 Nova Scotians, about 50,000 people get it - do the math.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#c479d7de-83a6-47c7-a045-07816407bdb3"><from>MS. ZANN</from><p>Yes, I've read about the meeting that was held, and in fact I believe a lot of the residents were given misinformation which was corrected by one of the members of the department at the time. The Parks and Protected Areas Plan, which the province released in August 2013, was the result of 2,000 written submissions and input from more than 1,300 people at 17 public open house sessions held across this province. But in spite of this, earlier this week the Minister of Natural Resources said that his government will make sure the views of those asking for a moratorium on protected land will be considered moving forward, and I will table that, Mr. Speaker.</p>
<p>In April 2011, the Sou'Wester reported that the goal of the petition that the minister signed was a complete moratorium on protected land identified in 40 different areas in Digby, Shelburne, and Yarmouth County. Therefore Mr. Speaker, my question for the Minister of Environment, can he please confirm whether these protected lands identified in the final Parks and Protected Areas Plan in August 2013 are now actually being reconsidered by his department, as stated by the Minister of Natural Resources?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Cape Breton West.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>NAT. RES. - MV MINER: REMOVAL - UPDATE</heading>
          <speech by="#c479d7de-83a6-47c7-a045-07816407bdb3"><from>MS. ZANN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I thank the member for his answer although I did not ask him that question - it was for the Minister of Environment.</p>
<p>However, Mr. Speaker, I do want to say that when we first became government as the NDP in this province, the people of Nova Scotia owned only 2 per cent of their own land and we brought that up to 13 per cent - and I'm extremely proud of that. In fact, our NDP Government was lauded for our protected lands and conservation movements; we went from being last in this province to second in that area.</p>
<p>My third and final question for the honourable Minister of Environment is, can the Minister of Environment - if he is listening - could the Minister of Environment &#x2026;</p></speech>
          <speech by="#e23caf06-dcf3-42a5-8a00-f4435df40350"><from>MR. ALFIE MACLEOD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question through you is for the Minister of Natural Resources.</p>
<p>As many in this House would know, we are just a few short weeks from the start of lobster season off the Cape Breton community of Main-&#xE0;-Dieu. The <i>MV Miner</i> ran aground in September 2011 on land owned and protected by the Province of Nova Scotia. At the time &#x2026;</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="##member" status="undefined">
            <from>AN HON. MEMBER</from>
            <p>And by Canada &#x2026;</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Order, please. Would the honourable member please retract that previous comment.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#e23caf06-dcf3-42a5-8a00-f4435df40350"><from>MR. MACLEOD</from><p>The land is owned and protected by the Province of Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>At the time the Premier said: "If there's an impact on those fishing grounds, that's going to hurt us." It's now 19 months later. My question to the minister is, what news does the minister have for the people of Main-&#xE0;-Dieu regarding the removal of the <i>MV Miner</i> from the protected shores of Scatarie?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#c479d7de-83a6-47c7-a045-07816407bdb3">
            <from>MS. ZANN</from>
            <p>Well, he wasn't listening, but I will retract that comment.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Will the honourable member please proceed with her question.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#4fbcc786-c835-4a0e-bd05-40afb30e0683"><from>HON. CHARLIE PARKER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, certainly we understand the concern that is in the community of Gabarus and the Cape Breton area, and we recognize that the fishery is an important component of the economy in that beautiful area. Certainly we've been working with the community over the months since this unfortunate grounding occurred. We've had communications not only with the community but also with the federal government.</p>
<p>Certainly we've made our position very clear all along - that the federal government has full responsibility under the Canada Shipping Act to remove that wreck from the shores of Cape Breton. We're going to continue our dialogue with the federal government, and with the community. We very much, as much as anybody, want to see that ship removed from the Gabarus area.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#c479d7de-83a6-47c7-a045-07816407bdb3"><from>MS. ZANN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, our NDP Government was lauded by conservation groups across Canada for adding 14 new provincial parks to the final parks and recreation areas, which means that Nova Scotians have gone from owning only 2 per cent of the province to 13 per cent.</p>
<p>My question for the Minister of Environment is, can he please confirm unequivocally that at least 13 per cent of our province's land will be protected for future generations of Nova Scotia by the year 2015, as committed by our previous NDP Government?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#e23caf06-dcf3-42a5-8a00-f4435df40350"><from>MR. MACLEOD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I want to inform the minister that it's the community of Main-&#xE0;-Dieu where this ship is, not the community of Gabarus, as he replied to me twice in this question. The people of Main-&#xE0;-Dieu have been patient. The community development association (Interruptions)</p>
<p>The fact is that the ship is off of Main-&#xE0;-Dieu, it's not off Gabarus. That's not my fault, he should know that.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, the people of Main-&#xE0;-Dieu and area have been very patient - also have the people been in Gabarus, but that's another story. The community development association worked with the Bennington Group and with the government; the fishers of the area worked with the government and the Bennington Group as well and there's still no resolution.</p>
<p>The development association in Main-&#xE0;-Dieu called a summit for January 22<sup>nd</sup> of this year - can the minister tell the residents of Main-&#xE0;-Dieu and surrounding areas, indeed all Nova Scotians, why he did not attend this meeting in the community, for which he had ample notification, and when will he meet with those people?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#d20d446c-118f-4445-81f4-cf995b335391"><from>MR. DELOREY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I'd like to thank the member for her question - finally a question that is actually directed to my attention.</p>
<p>Before answering this specific question I'd like to make a couple of clarifications. First and foremost, the 12 per cent and 13 per cent that have been referred to do not refer to lands specifically owned, or any change in the ownership specifically to the Province of Nova Scotia. What those percentages refer to in the parks and protected lands are lands that are protected by the Province of Nova Scotia - it does not refer specifically to lands owned by the Province of Nova Scotia. So let's make that clear. (Applause)</p>
<p>I would also like to clarify, as the Minister of Natural Resources stated earlier to a final point that was made in the preamble to the question, the fact that the decision to pursue an initiative to protect increased lands in the Province of Nova Scotia was not just an initiative of the former government, it was a decision that was unanimously passed by the House by all Parties in the Province of Nova Scotia. So let's get that clarified as well. (Applause)</p>
<p>Finally, Mr. Speaker, I would like to answer the actual question that the member opposite raised. In fact, yes, this government, the Departments of Environment, Natural Resources, and all members of this government and I believe this House, still stand by the decision that was previously made, unanimously, which is to continue to pursue the parks and protected lands and pursue the initiatives to continue to protect the lands that have been identified - currently we're at about 9 or 9.5 per cent that have actually been protected.</p>
<p>There have been initiatives in place over the last year or so that have increased that amount of land identified. We're in the process, and continuing the process, to make the necessary adjustments in the designations of those lands. That is moving forward and we are moving forward on that initiative and it will be taking place - any suggestions that the government is not committed to it is off ground. (Applause)</p></speech>
          <speech by="#4fbcc786-c835-4a0e-bd05-40afb30e0683"><from>MR. PARKER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I apologize for my geographical error. I know the actual ship is on the shores of Scatarie, certainly near Main-&#xE0;-Dieu for sure.</p>
<p>Again, we've worked with the community, we were prepared. My deputy minister and several other staff were available on January 22<sup>nd</sup> to attend the meeting there with the community, then it got cancelled at the last minute. Unfortunately my schedule didn't allow that to fit in that day, but we had lots of staff, including right up to the deputy minister, who were fully prepared and we continue the dialogue with the community and with the stakeholders, including Arivina Navigation, the ship's owner, who has full responsibility to remove that wreck from the shores of Scatarie, and with the tug boat owners, and certainly with the federal government. We are going to continue to work to find a workable solution here on the shores of Scatarie.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#e23caf06-dcf3-42a5-8a00-f4435df40350">
            <from>MR. MACLEOD</from>
            <p>The Community of Main-&#xE0;-Dieu has been patient and the Premier said, in October, in a Canadian Press story, and I quote &#x2026;</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>TIR - MV MINER: REMOVAL - UPDATE</heading>
          <speech by="#e23caf06-dcf3-42a5-8a00-f4435df40350"><from>MR. ALFIE MACLEOD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question through you is to the Minister of Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal. (Interruptions) He looked lonely over there.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, during the last provincial election, and shortly thereafter, the Premier of the province made a commitment to the people of Main-&#xE0;-Dieu that he would, indeed, have the <i>MV Miner </i>removed from the shores of Scatarie. As the member knows, and he was very active on the file as a member of the Opposition, that has been an issue in that community for some time. The Premier also made us aware that TIR would be the department responsible for this file. I would just like to know, could the minister share with us what he has done towards keeping the commitment of the Premier for the removal of the <i>MV Miner</i> from the shores of Scatarie?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#2c8e1a56-2f9d-4156-a91f-77802701e3d3"><from>HON. GEOFF MACLELLAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I truly do thank the member for that question. It's an important one for us on the Island and, of course, for all Nova Scotians. What we found - and I know that the member was also very active on that file - we travelled to Ottawa in November 2011 with the former Premier to discuss the <i>MV Miner</i>. At that point it was wrapped up in whose responsibility it was and, really, for two years it didn't move from that point. We made the commitment during the campaign as part of our platform. We will definitely fulfill that commitment without question.</p>
<p>What I want to tell the member is - and he is right about it - it came under TIR, we had no idea what the range of costs were for removing the <i>MV Miner</i>. What we did right off the bat was crafted up a new RFP, which will be released early in the new year, in early 2014. We'll get that tender out to the competitive sector for that type of removal. We'll get the process rolling. Then we turn to our friends in Ottawa to talk about, number one, how we possibly cost share on that endeavour and, number two, how we change the shipping laws so that this never happens again. Nova Scotians can't be on the hook for these bills. So it is moving along, and I can assure the member, we will honour our commitment.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#e23caf06-dcf3-42a5-8a00-f4435df40350"><from>MR. MACLEOD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I want to thank the minister for that answer and I know that he is committed to this file. However, it has dragged on for over two years, and even though the former NDP Premier made a similar commitment to remove the <i>MV Miner</i>, it's still there and this government now has to deal with it. As a matter of fact, in The ChronicleHerald on October 7, 2011, the Premier of the day said, "It is necessary for us to see this matter is dealt with in as expeditious a fashion as possible." I'll table that. If two years is quick, then we do understand why he's where he's at today.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, will the minister commit that this cleanup will take place regardless of federal involvement in the cleanup?</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>TIR - FITCH RD. (ANNAPOLIS): PAVING - TIME FRAME</heading>
          <speech by="#2c8e1a56-2f9d-4156-a91f-77802701e3d3"><from>MR. MACLELLAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I do thank the member for that question as well. Basically the reason this is moving at the pace it is, is because of the weather. No one can attest to this more than the member opposite; Scatarie and the area around there in the Atlantic are very tough waters. This is a massive vessel that has been shifting around. It has been two years, which is far too long. So where we're at is basically we're on a timeline that has a lot to do with (a) the weather; and (b) the fact that we are still unsure at the present day of the condition of the vessel, how we remove it, and what the options are. We hear stories of asbestos and other contaminants that are out there.</p>
<p>We have to handle this properly and do it right. That's the key and that's the importance of this RFP. We get the tender out in the new year and then we start looking at it. Knock on wood, but I can't imagine that we wouldn't get at this right away. My goal, and our goal as a government, is to make sure the <i>MV Miner</i> is gone before the 2014 fishing season around the coast of Scatarie.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#4f242ac5-fc82-41a3-8089-419e69284e5e">
            <from>HON. MAURICE SMITH</from>
            <p>If the road is not &#x2026;</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Order, please. The time allotted for the Oral Question Period has expired.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </questions>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT BUSINESS</heading>
        <speech by="#2c8e1a56-2f9d-4156-a91f-77802701e3d3"><from>MR. MACLELLAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, that is one of the elements in the equation, the upcoming fishing season. I think that if this timeline shifts into that season - I mean we're not that far from May - so if that were the case, we could maybe delay it until after that point.</p>
<p>I don't want to speculate on those things. Again, our priority and our focus right now is getting that done well before that time. Once the weather breaks and we can get out there and get at it and start removing the <i>MV Miner</i>, then that's what we'll do.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, the community group that's out there, there's a lot of committed people. They are outside of the political realm. They don't care what Party it is and what the politics are. They want this boat gone. That's why it's a commitment for us. We will consult the entire way with the Main-&#xE0;-Dieu association, who have been leaders in this endeavour. I'd be happy to meet with the group any time, either before Christmas or in the new year, to tell them what I know. I prefer to do it after the RFP is released, so we know exactly what the details for the cleanup are, but I'll meet with them at any time. Thank you.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Government Motions</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT MOTIONS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Colchester-Musquodoboit Valley.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>JUSTICE: N.S. HOME FOR COLORED CHILDREN -</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>INQUIRY TERMS OF REF.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The motion is carried.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#0f46e5e4-b06b-4b91-9e3a-5bd1cd63809d"><from>MR. LARRY HARRISON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question is for the Minister of Justice. We all know that when children go through trauma, their lives can be affected for a very long time. The Premier joined the PC caucus some time ago in calling for an inquiry into the alleged historical abuse at the Nova Scotia Home for Colored Children. The Premier said he hoped that the terms of reference for an inquiry would be set by the end of the year.</p>
<p>My question is, does the government intend to set the terms of reference for this inquiry by the end of the year?</p></speech>
          <narrative>
            <p>1:34 p.m. The House resolved itself into a CWH on Supply with Deputy Speaker Ms. Becky Kent in the Chair.</p>
          </narrative>
          <narrative>
            <p>5:53 p.m. CWH on Supply rose and the House reconvened with Deputy Speaker Ms. Becky Kent in the Chair.</p>
          </narrative>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The Chairman of the Committee of the Whole House on Supply reports:</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined"><from>THE CLERK</from><p>That the Committee of the Whole House on Supply has met, has made some progress, and begs leave to sit again.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#0f46e5e4-b06b-4b91-9e3a-5bd1cd63809d"><from>MR. HARRISON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I do appreciate that answer - was the indication, and is, that the inquiry is to happen through the Spring. The Premier pointed out at one time that there are people who want to take part in this inquiry who live away. These men and women need to know what the time frame would be, so that they can adequately prepare to come back for that inquiry or make their voice be heard.</p>
<p>I guess the question is, when will a date be set for that inquiry?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Madam Speaker, that concludes the government's business for today. I move that the House do now rise to meet tomorrow from the hours of 9:00 a.m. to 5:00 p.m. After the daily routine we'll do Committee of the Whole House on Supply.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the House do now rise to meet again tomorrow, April 12<sup>th</sup>, between the hours of 9:00 a.m. and 5:00 p.m.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>We stand adjourned.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#578ba1c9-5f6c-4b7b-a5cd-b915e1801c37">
            <from>MS. DIAB</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, as I said, this issue is an important issue, and it's one that is important for all of us here in this province. We are working on the terms of reference. Officials in my department are meeting with the lawyer for the residents, and we are in the process of having those terms established. Thank you.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#0f46e5e4-b06b-4b91-9e3a-5bd1cd63809d">
            <from>MR. HARRISON</from>
            <p>Well, I really don't have a supplementary question now. (Applause) Mr. Speaker, I'm very pleased that the inquiry will take place, and we will be awaiting future information. Thank you.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Queens-Shelburne.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>NAT. RES.: FIBRE SUPPLY/PROTECTED LANDS BALANCE</heading>
          <speech by="#3b49aa8d-3e78-4679-b8f7-f3161f11d3a3"><from>HON. STERLING BELLIVEAU</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question is for the Minister of Natural Resources. Last week when the minister was asked a direct question about how he was going to meet the fibre supply needs for those who work our forests, he gave an answer that was non-committal at best.</p>
<p>My question for the minister is, in the same vein as last week, how does he plan to balance the need for fibre to feed our economy with an adequate fibre supply while maintaining the province's protected targets?</p></speech>
          <narrative>
            <p>The House rose at 5:54 p.m.</p>
          </narrative>
          <speech by="#8834559e-ddf7-4ac7-9b30-8ada0eb9a7ca"><from>HON. ZACH CHURCHILL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I appreciate the question. Our department is working diligently to have a management plan ready for the new year, regarding the western lands. Our plan is to have allotments allocated early in the new year.</p>
<p>It is curious that this member is asking that question because previously, as a Minister of Environment, he was the lead on protecting land. One of the fibre challenges that we have in the Province of Nova Scotia, the Crown only owns about 30 per cent of the land in this province and upwards of 30 per cent of that land is now protected. I'd ask the member opposite, what is his preference - that we unprotect land to open up the fibre supply?</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION UNDER RULE 32(3)</heading>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="282">RESOLUTION NO. 282</num>
          <speech by="#3b49aa8d-3e78-4679-b8f7-f3161f11d3a3"><from>MR. BELLIVEAU</from><p>Mr. Speaker, just a point - I'm the one who asks the questions, he's the one who should answer. The member for Yarmouth isn't the only Liberal who opposes land conservation efforts. On April 11<sup>th</sup> the Liberal member for Guysborough- Eastern Shore-Tracadie called the 13 per cent land protection target a complete farce. He went on to say, "Whoever the heck the Crown is - I don't know if that's the Queen, I guess it's held by the province in trust for the Crown." I'll table that.</p>
<p>My second question to the minister is, when he has a member of his own caucus who is obviously opposed to finding a balance between protection and supply, what is his strategy for dealing with his colleagues who don't think conserving our forests should be a priority?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#8834559e-ddf7-4ac7-9b30-8ada0eb9a7ca">
            <from>MR. CHURCHILL</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I view any dialogue in this Legislature as just that, a dialogue between two parties. Regarding the protected lands question, of course there was some disagreement in the public. I know the goal of this Legislature was to accommodate, in a balanced way, all interests when it comes to those lands. I believe that the government has done its best to do that. We've settled on a 13 per cent target, that is a target that this government remains committed to, unequivocally, and if there is any debate about this issue we can talk about it further.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#3b49aa8d-3e78-4679-b8f7-f3161f11d3a3">
            <from>MR. BELLIVEAU</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, just last week the Ecology Action Centre praised our conservation efforts as a monumental achievement for natural conservation. I'll table that. My final question for the minister is, can Nova Scotians expect any changes to the current Parks and Protected Areas plan?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#8834559e-ddf7-4ac7-9b30-8ada0eb9a7ca">
            <from>MR. CHURCHILL</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, this is very interesting. I just had a meeting with the member the other day who brought forth concerns from his members about access to protected lands and use of ATV vehicles. I'd like the member to make it clear, do you want access to those lands or not?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Northside-Westmount.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>HEALTH &amp; WELLNESS: HOMECARE SERVICES - EXPENSES</heading>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="283">RESOLUTION NO. 283</num>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2">
            <from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, my question is to the Minister of Health and Wellness. If we want to ensure more seniors are able to stay in their homes, then the government needs to make that possible for struggling seniors. A constituent of mine, Ada Greene, receives home care twice a day and her husband, Cecil, struggles to keep the maintenance of their home on a fixed income. He cannot afford to pay to have his driveway shovelled but if it's not cleared, home care will not come to provide the services his wife needs. My question to the minister is, does the minister agree that this defeats the purpose of allowing the family to stay in their own homes?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas 81-year-old Joe Rector from Onslow, Colchester North, was a security guard at the Colchester Legion Stadium for 46 years; and</p>
<p>Whereas Joe used a common-sense approach and his ability to reason with people in a calm manner to diffuse most volatile situations without incident; and</p>
<p>Whereas Joe officially retired following the final game of the Truro Junior A Bearcats at the Colchester Legion Stadium before they moved to the new Rath EastLink Community Centre on March 2<sup>nd</sup>;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Joe Rector for his many years of service to the sport teams and all the members of the public who have used the stadium or have attended a sporting or other event there.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048">
            <from>HON. LEO GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I thank the member opposite for the question. I know it is through individual issues and concerns that we are able to give more support to the home care program. This year the budget had a significant increase in home care and it obviously has not expanded to look after those kinds of needs at the moment. I will certainly take the member's letter and concern of his constituent under my concern.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2">
            <from>MR. ORRELL</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, our seniors have worked hard and contributed all their lives. They deserve better than this. Mr. Greene struggles to keep his family's head above water. Once a month he's forced to visit the local food bank to ensure there is food on the table for him and his wife. The reality is this is not a situation unique to my constituency; seniors all over the province are struggling. Many who wish to remain in their homes find it unaffordable and the system is unresponsive. My question to the minister is, what choice is the minister giving the seniors? Does he really expect to keep seniors in their homes when they are already struggling to afford it?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048">
            <from>MR. GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, it is an important question because we do have to keep more seniors in their homes and it is an expanded program that looks after what may seem to us as small needs that in fact are very significant and large needs when it comes to getting in the wood, cutting the lawn and, as the member opposite has brought up today, shovelling the snow to allow the caregivers to get to the house of a senior. It's one that I will take very seriously. At the moment we're reviewing the Continuing Care Program and all that that entails - and it does have a major emphasis and component around keeping seniors in their home.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#e14ef5f0-e76a-4413-842d-24e0bfcba8d2"><from>MR. ORRELL</from><p>Mr. Minister, as we wait for a review of the Continuing Care Strategy, more families will be faced with impossible challenges. As winter approaches, more families like the Greenes will struggle to clear their driveways so their loved ones can receive proper home care.</p>
<p>My question to the minister is, is there anything we can do now to protect those families before the winter season pushes them into further hardship?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048">
            <from>MR. GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, sometimes I know in my riding I've been able to partner with a service club that had a list of individuals who were prepared to help seniors. I know we want to expand the program. At the present time we're living with a budget that's already in place and one that is very difficult to make adaptations to at this point in the year, but I will certainly take this case and what it means in the larger picture of providing a full array of services to help seniors stay in their home.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Inverness.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="284">RESOLUTION NO. 284</num>
          <speech by="#72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7"><from>Mr. Chuck Porter</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Ashley Thompson is a talented reporter with the Hants Journal weekly newspaper in Windsor and her work is being recognized at the Newspapers Atlantic 2013 Better Newspapers Competition 41<sup>st</sup> Annual Conference in Halifax, May 13<sup>th</sup>; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ashley is a standing finalist in the three categories of outstanding journalist, best feature story, and best investigative story; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ashley was nominated for Best Feature Story for her touching story about Curry's Corner resident Charbel Rouhana and his fight to regain strength and independence following a horrible highway crash, and her investigative reporting is being recognized for her stories on the continuing debate and cost of fire services between the Windsor Fire Department and the Municipality of West Hants and the Town of Windsor;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize the journalistic integrity and accomplishments of one Ashley Thompson, and wish her every success on May 13<sup>th</sup>.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff"><from>MR. ALLAN MACMASTER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question is for the honourable Minister of Energy.</p>
<p>Nova Scotia Power has started a request for proposals to replace approximately 250 employees. This includes thermal plant maintenance for power plants like Point Tupper, and line work along the South Shore and in the Valley. They plan to have discussions with companies that would do this work in the first quarter of 2014.</p>
<p>My question is, does the minister agree with Nova Scotia Power that skilled labour can be found, at a lower price, to replace these workers?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#1e5b7bdc-363b-4df4-8258-edcf8f2bf7fb"><from>HON. ANDREW YOUNGER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I appreciate the question from the member. I have already spoken with the IBEW and Nova Scotia Power about this issue. Quite frankly, I will not accept anything that reduces the service for Nova Scotians or the reliability for Nova Scotians in power generation, distribution, or safety in this province. I have made that absolutely clear to Nova Scotia Power - I will not let that happen.</p>
<p>I have had ongoing discussions; in fact, either myself or the deputy minister in my department has had pretty well weekly discussions with the IBEW on this matter and we're keeping in constant communication.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff"><from>MR. MACMASTER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, on the Big Harbour Island Road along the shores of the Bras d'Or Lakes, residents went without power for 67 hours last week - that was from Tuesday night at about 10:30 p.m. until Friday at a little bit after 5:00 p.m. This is a line service that could benefit from a more responsive outlay of resources by the company, but it is a service delivered by Nova Scotians who live in our communities - these are people who have made a commitment to living here and raising families and presumably have their neighbours' best interests at heart.</p>
<p>What specific assurances can the minister provide for people on the Big Harbour Island Road that they will receive better service if future line workers are brought in from out of province to respond to power outages?</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="285">RESOLUTION NO. 285</num>
          <speech by="#72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7"><from>Mr. Chuck Porter</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Queen's Diamond Jubilee Medal is a commemorative honour presented in 2012 to 60,000 deserving Canadians for their significant contributions and achievements in their respective communities, and is recognized as a national honour by the Canadian Governor General's Office; and</p>
<p>Whereas when it comes to community contributions, Sheila Roberts has led many groups and activities, including volunteering at the Poplar Grove Community Hall, Women's Institutes, 4-H, the food bank, the Terry Fox Run, the Avondale United Church, and the Newport Jolly Seniors Group; and</p>
<p>Whereas Sheila's significant contributions to her community were recognized when she received the Queen's Diamond Jubilee Medal;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly pay tribute to the outstanding contributions of Sheila Roberts for being a recipient of the Queen's Diamond Jubilee Medal, and wish her continued success with all of her future endeavours.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#6918f31d-8900-4400-a42c-b0374b14b8ff">
            <from>MR. MACMASTER</from>
            <p>Well, Mr. Speaker, word on the street is that a B.C. company called Valard Power is interested in picking up this contract. Now Nova Scotia Power's actions may be retaliation to the government's commitment to charge the efficiency tax to Nova Scotia Power. If labour costs form a smaller percentage of overall power rate costs and these changes will not lead to lower power bills, what is the government doing to address this matter for those workers who are living with uncertainty as we head into the Christmas season?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#1e5b7bdc-363b-4df4-8258-edcf8f2bf7fb"><from>MR. YOUNGER</from><p>As I already told the member - and maybe he wrote his supplementary before he actually listened to the answer - the reality is we've been having weekly discussions with the union about this, and they've indicated they're actually very happy with the discussions they've been having with me and my department.</p>
<p>Moreover, Mr. Speaker, the fact that this member thinks that it is a retaliatory thing against this government's decision to remove a tax - that this Party decides to defend - on Nova Scotians is a bit funny since it shows how little they are paying attention to the actions of Nova Scotia Power, because this work actually began about - and the layoffs at Nova Scotia Power - actually began about nine months before we were even in power and the knowledge of the RFPs (Interruptions)</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Order, please. The honourable Minister of Energy has the floor.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="286">RESOLUTION NO. 286</num>
          <speech by="#72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7"><from>Mr. Chuck Porter</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Avery's Valley Wild Midget AA girls hockey team won the Nova Scotia Provincial Championship for 2012-13 when they defeated Antigonish 3-1 in the championship game on March 24<sup>th</sup> in Kentville; and</p>
<p>Whereas Avery's Wild finished the round-robin portion of their schedule with two wins and two ties before their championship win over Antigonish, in a tournament that featured a total of five teams including Pictou, Halifax, and Tasa-Chebucto; and</p>
<p>Whereas West Hants was proudly represented on the Valley team with Natalie Rippey of Curry's Corner, Sam Lake from Chester Road, Lillie Ryan and Olivia Lynch of Garland's Crossing, and associate player Maddie Phillips, all playing an integral role in their team's championship win;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Avery's Valley Wild Midget AA girls hockey team for capturing the provincial championship this year.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>HEALTH &amp; WELLNESS: CECs - CONTINUATION</heading>
          <speech by="#32a29c39-915c-40e7-b749-7c09299ed1f7"><from>HON. DAVID WILSON</from><p>My question is for the Minister of Health and Wellness this afternoon.</p>
<p>According to the province's emergency care adviser, Dr. John Ross, Collaborative Emergency Centres, or CECs, are community-based and locally-managed solutions to the basic health care needs of Nova Scotians while maintaining ready access to 24-hour emergency care. Ross acknowledges the innovative core team of paramedics, nurses, and physicians, with the support from many others, makes best use of the available resources in communities across Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>So my question for the Minister of Health and Wellness is, will he commit today to continuing this innovative model of care here in Nova Scotia?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048">
            <from>HON. LEO GLAVINE</from>
            <p>I thank the former Health and Wellness Minister for the question. CECs are proving to be valuable primary care extensions in our communities. There are very few that are providing urgent or emergency care. They are an important part of supplementing communities, especially ones that have shortages of physicians or nurse practitioners and our commitment, while a review will be going on, is to continue to support CECs.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#32a29c39-915c-40e7-b749-7c09299ed1f7"><from>MR. DAVID WILSON</from><p>I think for us in our Party, and on this side, and I think Nova Scotians are cautious when they hear "review." We've heard many from the current government within health care and education that reviews will take place, and really reviews, Mr. Speaker, means a delay and that's why I find it extremely important that the Minister of Health and Wellness recognize the contributions of the change of model of care with Collaborative Emergency Centres. We have communities like Parrsboro, Springhill, Tatamagouche, Pugwash, Annapolis Royal, who currently now have available to their residents same-day or next-day appointments, which is extremely important.</p>
<p>So I hope that the seven more communities where it was recently announced that they would receive a CEC would not be caught up in what a review is from the current government, and I hope the minister will commit to that today.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7"><from>Mr. Chuck Porter</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Carlos De Rosa is an accomplished painter in Falmouth; and</p>
<p>Whereas as a source of inspirations for his paintings Carlos enjoys the scenic beauty of Nova Scotia and places such as the powerful tides of the Minas Basin and the red cliffs of Blomidon; and</p>
<p>Whereas Carlos also draws inspiration from his travels to Italy and other European countries;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly applaud the talent of Carlos De Rosa of Falmouth, and wish him continued success in his artistic endeavours.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#15a1cda3-8762-45c9-b3f6-609ff9fc7048">
            <from>MR. GLAVINE</from>
            <p>The CECs are proven to be valuable extensions of primary health care. Each community has unique requests; we are looking at those requests and I think there will be some news in the not-too-distant future about CECs and communities that desire to have this particular model and extension of primary care.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#32a29c39-915c-40e7-b749-7c09299ed1f7"><from>MR. DAVID WILSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, thank you to the minister opposite. I'm glad to hear him using the term "valuable" and that CECs are valuable to Nova Scotians because I would agree with that, and I will support the minister and this government as long as they continue to recognize the value in ensuring that Nova Scotians have access to the care they need, especially in CECs.</p>
<p>We know over the past number of years, the current Premier criticized Collaborative Emergency Centres. So I'm glad to see that the Minister of Health and Wellness maybe doesn't hold that opinion of Collaborative Emergency Centres and I look forward &#x2026;</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Order, please. The time allotted for the Oral Question Period has expired.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>OPPOSITION MEMBERS' BUSINESS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable House Leader for the New Democratic Party.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#803ea908-016e-4462-b4b5-e2a418f97f23">
          <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, as I stated yesterday, the New Democratic Party will not be calling business today because of a very important meeting that you're holding in the Red Chamber beginning at 2:00 p.m. So it would be our position that we'll turn it over now to the Government House Leader to announce the time and business for tomorrow.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#d2209e4d-eae1-410c-8dfa-b4444f1e67be"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, again I extend my thanks to the House Leader for the NDP for the co-operation that was shown for the hours today. For tomorrow's business, the House will meet from 12:00 noon until 10:00 p.m. During that time government business will include Committee of the Whole House on Bills, Bill Nos. 12, 14, 15, 19 and 20. As well, there will be Committee of the Whole House on Bills for Bill No. 13 - Ladies of the Sacred Heart at Halifax Act. Then we will proceed to Third Reading of Bill Nos. 1, 5, 7, 9, 10 and 17. And with the consent of the House, the bills that will be dealt with in Committee of the Whole House will possibly be dealt with for Third Reading as well tomorrow, and if time permits, we will conclude with Address in Reply to the Speech from the Throne.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, with that I move that the House do now rise to meet again on Thursday from the hours of 12:00 noon until 10:00 p.m.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the House now rise to meet again on Thursday, December 12<sup>th</sup> between the hours of 12:00 noon and 10:00 p.m.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>We stand adjourned until 12:00 noon tomorrow.</p></speech>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="289">RESOLUTION NO. 289</num>
          <speech by="#72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7"><from>Mr. Chuck Porter</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Kings-Edgehill girls hockey team captured their first Nova Scotia Schools Athletic Federation Girls Hockey Championship last week by defeating Northumberland 4-2 in the championship game, while being paced in the tournament by Erica Kelly who scored 11 points in five games; and</p>
<p>Whereas the girls hockey team is coached by Laura Shearer of Falmouth, a former captain of the Dalhousie women's hockey team, who also had her younger sister, Abby, as a member of the championship team; and</p>
<p>Whereas Kings-Edgehill was a dominant force on the ice all winter, going 16-0-0 in the Valley High School Girls Hockey League and scoring 161 goals and allowing only eight against;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Head Coach Laura Shearer and the Kings-Edgehill girls hockey team on a very successful 2012-13 championship hockey season, and wish them continued success.</p></speech>
          <narrative>
            <p>The House rose at 11:43 a.m.</p>
          </narrative>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="290">RESOLUTION NO. 290</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of the individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills, and time but often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, and most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honours;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Tim Colburn, a member of the Tatamagouche Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his 25-year medal and service pin.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#4caa514a-7759-421a-8574-ba7d1932db92"><from>Hon. Jamie Baillie</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Order of Nova Scotia is the highest honour of the Province of Nova Scotia that recognizes outstanding contributions or achievements by members of our community; and</p>
<p>Whereas through his frequent lectures to university business students and his great business success, Mr. Fred George has inspired future generations of Nova Scotians to dream big and work hard to achieve their goals; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. George has supported many causes, given generously of his time and knowledge, and has also been a long-time supporter of our veterans, members of the Canadian Forces and their families;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Mr. Fred George on receiving the Order of Nova Scotia and thank him for making our province a more caring place through his generous sharing of time and talents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="291">RESOLUTION NO. 291</num>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="391">RESOLUTION NO. 391</num>
          <speech by="#72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7"><from>Mr. Chuck Porter</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Colan McCulloch of Kennetcook busily prepared all summer to play for Team Nova Scotia's baseball contingent at the Canada Summer Games in Sherbrooke, Quebec; and</p>
<p>Whereas Colan is the grandson of Windsor resident Helen Romans who showed up at every game possible to cheer her grandson on; and</p>
<p>Whereas Colan is 16 years old and has played both shortstop and second base, positions he described as challenging but a lot of fun;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Colan and his teammates for a superior effort in the 2013 Canada Summer Games and congratulate his grandmother Helen Romans for her loyal support of Colan's baseball accomplishments.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="392">RESOLUTION NO. 392</num>
          <speech by="#72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7"><from>Mr. Chuck Porter</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Alvin Harvey recently retired and was recognized by the Town of Windsor for his 22 years of service as a Public Works employee; and</p>
<p>Whereas the job of a Public Works employee requires someone who has many skills, including being able to brave the bitter cold and wind and snow to ensure sidewalks and streets are safe for the general public each winter; and</p>
<p>Whereas Alvin, a resident of Ardoise, was described at his retirement ceremony by Mayor Paul Beazley as a dedicated and hard worker and someone who could be counted on for keeping "Big Bertha", better known as the town's large snow blower, on the road well beyond its life expectancy;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly wish Alvin Harvey the very best with his retirement and thank him for his many years of dedicated service to the Town of Windsor's Public Works Division.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="293">RESOLUTION NO. 293</num>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="393">RESOLUTION NO. 393</num>
          <speech by="#72906878-3b4e-496f-adc4-15b4975f3aa7"><from>Mr. Chuck Porter</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas 16-year-old Avonview High School student Andrew Maynard of Windsor is turning a number of heads with his musical talent and for his vast collection of guitars; and</p>
<p>Whereas Maynard is especially adept at playing the banjo, but has no difficulty playing other instruments such as guitar, bass, mandolin, trumpet and stand-up bass; and</p>
<p>Whereas Andrew presently has a collection of some 40 instruments, including 26 guitars, and he thoroughly enjoyed playing at the Eastern Canadian Bluegrass Music Awards Show in Truro in October;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly commend Andrew Maynard for his musical talents and love of music and wish him every future success with whatever instrument he picks up and continues to play.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="394">RESOLUTION NO. 394</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of the individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills, and time but often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, and most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honours;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Mike Forbes, a member of the Tatamagouche Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his 10-year service pin.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>Monsieur le Pr&#xE9;sident, &#xE0; une date ult&#xE9;rieure, je demanderai l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu que Vernon d'Eon, un homme d'affaires et entrepreneur de Pubnico-Ouest-le-centre, &#xE9;tait le destinataire d'un dipl&#xF4;me honorifique de l'Universit&#xE9; Sainte-Anne, le 19 juin, 2013; et</p>
<p>Attendu que Vernon d'Eon a commenc&#xE9; sa carri&#xE8;re &#xE0; un jeune &#xE2;ge comme p&#xEA;cheur de homard mais avec la diminution des prises, il a tourn&#xE9; son attention vers la fabrication des piquets de homard et en 1975 a form&#xE9; son entreprise Vernon d'Eon Lobster Plugs Limited; et</p>
<p>Attendu que Vernon d'Eon Lobster Plugs a depuis &#xE9;largi pour inclure sept magasins dans toute la Nouvelle-&#xC9;cosse, et &#xE0; l'&#xFFFD;le-du-Prince-&#xC9;douard avec la vente d'une grande vari&#xE9;t&#xE9; de produits de la p&#xEA;che et de v&#xEA;tements ainsi que le restaurant Dennis Point Caf&#xE9; &#xE0; Pubnico-Ouest-le-bas, avec 65 employ&#xE9;s &#xE0; temps plein;</p>
<p>Par cons&#xE9;quent, qu'il soit r&#xE9;solu que tous les membres de cette Assembl&#xE9;e f&#xE9;licite Vernon d'Eon en recevant son dipl&#xF4;me honorifique, le remercier pour son leadership et vision tout au long de sa carri&#xE8;re et lui souhaitons beaucoup de succ&#xE8;s dans l'avenir.</p>
<p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Vernon d'Eon, a well-known businessman and entrepreneur from Middle West Pubnico was the recipient of an honorary degree from Universit&#xE9; Sainte-Anne on June 19, 2013; and</p>
<p>Whereas Vernon d'Eon began his career at a young age as a lobster fisherman, but with declining catches turned his attention to fabricating lobster pegs and in 1975 formed his company Vernon d'Eon Lobster Plugs Ltd.; and</p>
<p>Whereas Vernon d'Eon Lobster Plugs has since expanded to seven stores throughout Nova Scotia and one in P.E.I., selling a large variety of fishing supplies and clothing, as well as a restaurant, Dennis Point Caf&#xE9; in Lower West Pubnico, employing 65 full-time employees;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Vernon d'Eon on receiving his honorary degree, thank him for his leadership and vision throughout his career and wish him continued success in the future.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="295">RESOLUTION NO. 295</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of the individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills, and time but often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, and most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honours;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Mark Langille, a member of the Tatamagouche Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his 15-year service pin.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="395">RESOLUTION NO. 395</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas birthdays are an occasion for family and friends to gather together to celebrate the life of an individual; and</p>
<p>Whereas on October 25, 2013, Julie Surette of Tusket, formerly of Surette's Island, celebrated her 85<sup>th</sup> birthday; and</p>
<p>Whereas to have reached 85 years of age and continue to be active and share all the memories gathered over your lifetime with your loved ones is a wonderful reason to celebrate;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Julie Surette on reaching this milestone in her life and wish her many more happy birthdays and continued good health.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="296">RESOLUTION NO. 296</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of the individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills, and time but often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, and most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honours;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Kent MacDonald, a member of the Tatamagouche Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his 20-year medal and service pin.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="396">RESOLUTION NO. 396</num>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="297">RESOLUTION NO. 297</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills, and time but often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, and most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honours;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Kenny Newcomb, a member of the Tatamagouche Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his 10-year service pin.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="397">RESOLUTION NO. 397</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas birthdays are an occasion for family and friends to gather together to celebrate the life of an individual; and</p>
<p>Whereas on August 25, 2013, Regina Doucette, resident of Villa St. Joseph du Lac, Yarmouth, and formerly of Hubbard's Point, celebrated her 104<sup>th</sup> birthday; and</p>
<p>Whereas to have reached 104 years of age and continue to be active and share all the memories gathered over your lifetime with your loved ones is a wonderful reason to celebrate;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Regina Doucette on reaching this milestone in her life and wish her many more happy birthdays and continued good health.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="298">RESOLUTION NO. 298</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills, and time but often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, and most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honours;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Kenny Anderson, a member of the Tatamagouche Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his 10-year service pin.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="398">RESOLUTION NO. 398</num>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="299">RESOLUTION NO. 299</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas birthdays are an occasion for family and friends to gather together to celebrate the life of an individual; and</p>
<p>Whereas on October 17, 2013, Th&#xE9;r&#xE8;se Bourque of Wedgeport celebrated her 100<sup>th</sup> birthday; and</p>
<p>Whereas to have reached 100 years of age and continue to be active and share all the memories gathered over your lifetime with your loved ones is a wonderful reason to celebrate;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Th&#xE9;r&#xE8;se Bourque on reaching this milestone in her life and wish her many more happy birthdays and continued good health.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="399">RESOLUTION NO. 399</num>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="300">RESOLUTION NO. 300</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills, and time but often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, and most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honours;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jeremy Russell, a member of the Tatamagouche Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for being named Firefighter of the Year.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="400">RESOLUTION NO. 400</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills, and time but often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, and most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honours;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jeffery Friesen, a member of the Tatamagouche Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for being named Firefighter Most Interested in Training.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas anniversaries are an occasion for family and friends to gather together to celebrate the life of two individuals united as one; and</p>
<p>Whereas it was once said that a marriage anniversary is the celebration of love, trust, partnership, tolerance and tenacity but the order varies for any given year; and</p>
<p>Whereas on November 16, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Margaret and Sheldon d'Entremont of West Pubnico celebrated their 50<sup>th</sup> Wedding Anniversary;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Margaret and Sheldon d'Entremont on this remarkable milestone in their life together and wish them many more happy years.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="401">RESOLUTION NO. 401</num>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="302">RESOLUTION NO. 302</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills, and time but often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, and most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honours;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ian MacDonald, newly-elected chief of the Tatamagouche Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his 25-year medal and service pin and being named Fire Person of the Year.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="402">RESOLUTION NO. 402</num>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="303">RESOLUTION NO. 303</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas anniversaries are an occasion for family and friends to gather together to celebrate the life of two individuals united as one; and</p>
<p>Whereas it was once said that a marriage anniversary is the celebration of love, trust, partnership, tolerance and tenacity but the order varies for any given year; and</p>
<p>Whereas on August 7, 2013 a very special occasion took place when Marilyn and Patrick LeBlanc of Wedgeport celebrated their 50<sup>th</sup> Wedding Anniversary;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Marilyn and Patrick LeBlanc on this remarkable milestone in their life together and wish them many more happy years.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="403">RESOLUTION NO. 403</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas anniversaries are an occasion for family and friends to gather together to celebrate the life of two individuals united as one; and</p>
<p>Whereas it was once said that a marriage anniversary is the celebration of love, trust, partnership, tolerance and tenacity but the order varies for any given year; and</p>
<p>Whereas on September 27, 2013 a very special occasion took place when Muriel and Ernest Doucette of Amirault's Hill celebrated their 65<sup>th</sup> Wedding Anniversary;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Muriel and Ernest Doucette on this remarkable milestone in their life together and wish them many more happy years.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="304">RESOLUTION NO. 304</num>
          <speech by="#13787640-1a96-4b80-8d04-ce79410f4a22"><from>Hon. Karen Casey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's fire departments are made up of individuals who are dedicated to serving others; and</p>
<p>Whereas these firefighters and first responders not only contribute hard work, skills, and time but often risk their lives and must deal with incidents of great emotional stress; and</p>
<p>Whereas firefighters seldom receive the accolades which they deserve, and most fire brigades hold a banquet and awards ceremony to thank all members and to present special honours;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Colin Cunningham, a member of the Tatamagouche Fire Brigade, Colchester North, for receiving his 35-year service pin.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="404">RESOLUTION NO. 404</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas anniversaries are an occasion for family and friends to gather together to celebrate the life of two individuals united as one; and</p>
<p>Whereas it was once said that a marriage anniversary is the celebration of love, trust, partnership, tolerance and tenacity but the order varies for any given year; and</p>
<p>Whereas on November 4, 2013 a very special occasion took place when Carol and Franklyn Moulaison of Amirault's Hill celebrated their 50<sup>th</sup> Wedding Anniversary;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Carol and Franklyn Moulaison on this remarkable milestone in their life together and wish them many more happy years.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="405">RESOLUTION NO. 405</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas anniversaries are an occasion for family and friends to gather together to celebrate the life of two individuals united as one; and</p>
<p>Whereas it was once said that a marriage anniversary is the celebration of love, trust, partnership, tolerance and tenacity but the order varies for any given year; and</p>
<p>Whereas on August 19, 2013 a very special occasion took place when Hayden and Pauline Landry of Hubbard's Point celebrated their 50<sup>th</sup> Wedding Anniversary;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Hayden and Pauline Landry on this remarkable milestone in their life together and wish them many more happy years.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="406">RESOLUTION NO. 406</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas anniversaries are an occasion for family and friends to gather together to celebrate the life of two individuals united as one; and</p>
<p>Whereas it was once said that a marriage anniversary is the celebration of love, trust, partnership, tolerance and tenacity but the order varies for any given year; and</p>
<p>Whereas on October 12, 2013 a very special occasion took place when Isabelle and Chester Doucette of Quinan celebrated their 50<sup>th</sup> Wedding Anniversary;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Isabelle and Chester Doucette on this remarkable milestone in their life together and wish them many more happy years.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="407">RESOLUTION NO. 407</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on July 14, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Tiffany and Devin Conrad welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Tiffany and Devin Conrad on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="408">RESOLUTION NO. 408</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on July 19, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Renee Penney and Chad Hallett welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Renee and Chad on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="409">RESOLUTION NO. 409</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on June 28, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Maggie Watt and Darren Stuart welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Maggie and Darren on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="410">RESOLUTION NO. 410</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on August 3, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Lisa d'Entremont and Kevin d'Eon welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Lisa and Kevin on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="411">RESOLUTION NO. 411</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on June 21, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Leah and Tom Muise welcomed their son Spencer into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Leah and Tom on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="412">RESOLUTION NO. 412</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on August 17, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Laura Doucet and John Fall welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Laura and John on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="413">RESOLUTION NO. 413</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on June 13, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Jessica Harris and Ivan Nickerson welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jessica and Ivan on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="414">RESOLUTION NO. 414</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on August 21, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Heidi Jenkins and Cliff d'Eon welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Heidi and Cliff on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="415">RESOLUTION NO. 415</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on September 1, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Heidi and Chris Ross welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Heidi and Chris on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="416">RESOLUTION NO. 416</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on September 6, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Darlene Surette and David Vaux welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Darlene and David on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="417">RESOLUTION NO. 417</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on October 30, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Danielle Francis and Tyson Blades welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Danielle and Tyson on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="418">RESOLUTION NO. 418</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on August 31, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Brandi-Lee and Nicholas Penney welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Brandi-Lee and Nicholas on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="419">RESOLUTION NO. 419</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on August 9, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Bobbi Ann and Scott Markle welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Bobbi Ann and Scott on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="420">RESOLUTION NO. 420</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on September 1, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Katlyn Miller and Joshua Goodwin welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Katlyn and Joshua on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="421">RESOLUTION NO. 421</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on June 3, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Heidi Nickerson and Dwayne MacKay welcomed their son into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Heidi and Dwayne&#xFFFD; on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="422">RESOLUTION NO. 422</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on August 26, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Shannon Jones and Trevor Malone welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate&#xFFFD; Shannon and Trevor on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="423">RESOLUTION NO. 423</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on September 2, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Shana Newell and Steve Quinlan welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Shana and Steve&#xFFFD; on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="424">RESOLUTION NO. 424</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on October 9, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Sarah d'Entremont and Jordan Smith welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Sarah and Jordan&#xFFFD; on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="425">RESOLUTION NO. 425</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on July 18, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Samantha and Robert Nickerson welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Samantha and Robert on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="426">RESOLUTION NO. 426</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on October 9, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Michele and Mark Bain welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Michele and Mark on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="427">RESOLUTION NO. 427</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on July 26, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Lyndsey and Adam Kenney welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Lyndsey and Adam on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="428">RESOLUTION NO. 428</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on October 24, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Larissa Newell and Elijah Lee welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Larissa and Elijah on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="429">RESOLUTION NO. 429</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on October 1, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Kelli and Grant Conrad welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Kelli and Grant on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="430">RESOLUTION NO. 430</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on October 4, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Hailey Williams and Jesse Hopkins welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Hailey and Jesse on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="431">RESOLUTION NO. 431</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on October 30, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Gloria Marginson and Jamie Doucette welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Gloria and Jamie on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="432">RESOLUTION NO. 432</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on September 6, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Della and Dwayne Nickerson welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Della and Dwayne on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="433">RESOLUTION NO. 433</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on August 12, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Colette and Allan Doucette welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Colette and Allan on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="434">RESOLUTION NO. 434</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on August 19, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Cassandra and Martial d'Entremont welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Cassandra and Martial on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="435">RESOLUTION NO. 435</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on June 14, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Charlene and Stuart Nickerson welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Charlene and Stuart on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="436">RESOLUTION NO. 436</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on July 15, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Ashley Doucette and Justin Hubbard welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ashley and Justin on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="437">RESOLUTION NO. 437</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on August 15, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Ashley Hill and Tom Ross welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ashley and Tom on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="438">RESOLUTION NO. 438</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on October 18, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Amelia Smith and Graham Nickerson welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Amelia and Graham on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="439">RESOLUTION NO. 439</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on August 16, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Amanda Nickerson and Billy Joe Sears welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Amanda and Billy Joe on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="440">RESOLUTION NO. 440</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on July 17, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Amanda MacDonald and Lorne Pace welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Amanda and Lorne on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="441">RESOLUTION NO. 441</num>
          <speech by="#b67194ee-eead-4e8d-9cdb-2d1935c5be52"><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the birth of a child is a momentous event and marks the beginning of a very satisfying journey down a long road, where the rewards far outnumber the challenges; and</p>
<p>Whereas "A new baby is like the beginning of all things - wonder, hope, a dream of possibilities," as quoted by author Eda J. LeShan; and</p>
<p>Whereas on November 15, 2013, a very special occasion took place when Jessica Trenholm and Michael Cameron welcomed their daughter into the world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jessica and Michael on this miraculous event in their lives, and wish them many happy years as parents.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="442">RESOLUTION NO. 442</num>
          <speech by="#1e5b7bdc-363b-4df4-8258-edcf8f2bf7fb"><from>Hon. Andrew Younger</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Darren Fisher was elected Halifax Regional Councillor for District 6, East Dartmouth - The Lakes in September 2009; and</p>
<p>Whereas Councillor Fisher was re-elected in October 2012 as councillor for the newly re-named District 6, Harbourview-Burnside-Dartmouth East; and</p>
<p>Whereas on November 9, 2013 Councillor Fisher was elected by Halifax Regional Council as Deputy Mayor for a one-year term;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Deputy Mayor Darren Fisher on his new role and wish him all the best for the coming year.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="443">RESOLUTION NO. 443</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>Hon. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas local literature is an essential element of what makes up the rich and dynamic culture of Nova Scotia; and</p>
<p>Whereas Colleen Anthony of Clayton Park West has caught the attention and touched the hearts of many with her widely-known, award-winning blog, <i>Curtains are Open</i>, through which she shares reflections on her personal experiences and life lessons; and</p>
<p>Whereas Colleen Anthony has achieved a wonderful accomplishment in the publication of her first book, <i>Full Speed Ahead</i>, a compilation of 82 excerpts from her ever-popular blog;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Colleen Anthony on the publication of her first literary work and wish her every success in all her future endeavours.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="444">RESOLUTION NO. 444</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>Hon. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas in June 2013, Amanda Dean's professionalism and talent were recognized with her appointment as Atlantic Vice-President of the Insurance Bureau of Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ms. Dean's distinguished background in communications and public relations made her a leader in both the public and private sectors and took her to the Insurance Bureau in 2006, where she served in several different roles leading to her recent promotion; and</p>
<p>Whereas in her position as vice-president, Ms. Dean oversees all government relations in Atlantic Canada, specifically representing the positions of the property and casualty insurance industry to government officials;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this Nova Scotia Legislature congratulate Amanda Dean on her appointment and join me in extending our appreciation for the tremendous work she does on behalf of her clients and in partnership with government.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="445">RESOLUTION NO. 445</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>Hon. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on November 6, 2013, the Canadian Progress Club of Halifax Cornwallis held its 23<sup>rd</sup> Annual Progress Women of Excellence Awards Dinner at the World Trade and Convention Centre; and</p>
<p>Whereas 19 inspirational women were honoured for their exceptional contributions to their professions and their ability to influence, motivate, and inspire others; and</p>
<p>Whereas Dr. Ramona Lumpkin was recognized at the event in the Research and Education category for the impact she has made as president of Mount Saint Vincent University and her contribution to the university community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly recognize the great contribution that Dr. Ramona Lumpkin has made to our province, congratulate her on receiving this prestigious award, and wish her continued success in all her future endeavours.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="446">RESOLUTION NO. 446</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>Hon. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Janet McKeough has served the homebuyers of the Halifax area as a mortgage broker for 19 years and has earned the trust and respect of her clients through superior customer service and her understanding of the many needs of homebuyers; and</p>
<p>Whereas Janet further contributes to the profession in her role as president of the Mortgage Brokers Association of Atlantic Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas Janet was rightfully distinguished Canada-wide in a recent article in the <i>Canadian Mortgage Professionals</i> magazine, entitled "10 Most Influential Women";</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly thank Janet McKeough for her enormous contribution to her field in Nova Scotia and wish her the best of luck as she continues to set the bar for mortgage brokers across the province.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="447">RESOLUTION NO. 447</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>Hon. Diane Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the promotion of positive aging is essential to maintaining the happiness and fulfillment of Nova Scotians as they grow older; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Mother Pluckers Music and Hockey Society are leaders in positive aging through staying active and sharing their musical talent with seniors as well as young people; and</p>
<p>Whereas Corinne Boudreau, a resident of Clayton Park West, was the distinguished recipient of a Haliward as a salute to her work with this exciting and dynamic society;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly applaud Corinne Boudreau for her tremendous work with the Mother Pluckers, congratulate her on receiving a prestigious Haliward, and offer best wishes to the Mother Pluckers as they continue to bring joy to many and be leaders in the community.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="448">RESOLUTION NO. 448</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>Hon. Diane Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia takes great pride in the successes of its young professionals; and</p>
<p>Whereas Scott Noddin of Halifax has had tremendous success as a chartered accountant for Collins Barrows and received his letters in the shortest period possible because of his tremendous dedication and knowledge; and</p>
<p>Whereas Saint Mary's University recognized his exceptional talent in rewarding him the distinguished Young Alumni Award for 2013 for his professionalism and volunteerism;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Scott Noddin on his award and wish him the very best as one of Nova Scotia's most promising accounting professionals.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="449">RESOLUTION NO. 449</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>Hon. Diane Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Ted Doane, executive director of Internal Audit for the Province of Nova Scotia, is one of five chartered accountants in our province who were honoured with the prestigious FCA designation; and</p>
<p>Whereas this designation is the Institute of Chartered Accountant's highest honour and is requiring CAs to serve a minimum of 15 years in the profession while remaining in good standing and making exemplary contributions to the field or their community; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Doane received his CA in 1991, and in addition to his work for the province, he has actively supported many professional associations, most notably serving as president for the Institute of Chartered Accountants in Nova Scotia and recently sitting on the steering committee for merging the accounting professions;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the Nova Scotia Legislature congratulate Ted Doane on receiving this well-deserved honour and join me in extending our most sincere appreciation for his professional commitment and contribution to the Province of Nova Scotia.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="450">RESOLUTION NO. 450</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>Hon. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on December 6, 2013, the student government of Park West School in Clayton Park showed tremendous creativity in organizing a Christmas gift sale to raise funds for the community; and</p>
<p>Whereas the determination of the organizers and the warm hearts of the Park West School community made the event an outstanding success, raising a one-day total of over $725; and</p>
<p>Whereas the majority of the money will go towards buying gifts and turkeys for the less fortunate, with the rest being reinvested into Park West School and the community of Clayton Park;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House thank the student government team and the Park West School community for bringing joy and comfort to many and join with me in wishing everyone in Clayton Park a Merry Christmas and Happy Holidays.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="451">RESOLUTION NO. 451</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>Hon. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Duke of Edinburgh's Award, founded by His Royal Highness Prince Philip, the Duke of Edinburgh, was introduced to Canada in 1963 and is currently present in more than 120 countries; and</p>
<p>Whereas the award encourages young people to become active in their communities and challenges them to hone a skill and embark on an adventurous journey; and</p>
<p>Whereas Amira Kadray, a student at Halifax West High School, successfully completed the rigorous requirements and was awarded the bronze Duke of Edinburgh's Award at a ceremony on November 25, 2013, at Halifax West High School;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Amira Kadray on receiving this prestigious award, and offer best wishes for continued success as a leader in the community.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="452">RESOLUTION NO. 452</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>Hon. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Duke of Edinburgh's Award, founded by His Royal Highness Prince Philip, the Duke of Edinburgh, was introduced to Canada in 1963 and is currently present in more than 120 countries; and</p>
<p>Whereas the award encourages young people to become active in their communities and challenges them to hone a skill and embark on an adventurous journey; and</p>
<p>Whereas Austeja Galinyte, a student at Halifax West High School, successfully completed the rigorous requirements and was awarded the bronze Duke of Edinburgh's Award at a ceremony on November 25, 2013, at Halifax West High School;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Austeja Galinyte on receiving this prestigious award, and offer best wishes for continued success as a leader in the community.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="453">RESOLUTION NO. 453</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>Hon. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Duke of Edinburgh's Award, founded by His Royal Highness Prince Philip, the Duke of Edinburgh, was introduced to Canada in 1963 and is currently present in more than 120 countries; and</p>
<p>Whereas the award encourages young people to become active in their communities and challenges them to hone a skill and embark on an adventurous journey; and</p>
<p>Whereas Liam Rappoldt, a student at Halifax West High School, successfully completed the rigorous requirements and was awarded the bronze Duke of Edinburgh's Award at a ceremony on November 25, 2013, at Halifax West High School;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Liam Rappoldt on receiving this prestigious award, and offer best wishes for continued success as a leader in the community.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="454">RESOLUTION NO. 454</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>Hon. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Duke of Edinburgh's Award, founded by His Royal Highness Prince Philip, the Duke of Edinburgh, was introduced to Canada in 1963 and is currently present in more than 120 countries; and</p>
<p>Whereas the award encourages young people to become active in their communities and challenges them to hone a skill and embark on an adventurous journey; and</p>
<p>Whereas Seokho Lim, a student at Halifax West High School, successfully completed the rigorous requirements and was awarded the bronze Duke of Edinburgh's Award at a ceremony on November 25, 2013, at Halifax West High School;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Seokho Lim on receiving this prestigious award, and offer best wishes for continued success as a leader in the community.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="455">RESOLUTION NO. 455</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>Hon. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Duke of Edinburgh's Award, founded by His Royal Highness Prince Philip, the Duke of Edinburgh, was introduced to Canada in 1963 and is currently present in more than 120 countries; and</p>
<p>Whereas the award encourages young people to become active in their communities and challenges them to hone a skill and embark on an adventurous journey; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mohini Bhade, a student at Halifax West High School, successfully completed the rigorous requirements and was awarded the bronze Duke of Edinburgh's Award at a ceremony on November 25, 2013, at Halifax West High School;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Mohini Bhade on receiving this prestigious award, and offer best wishes for continued success as a leader in the community.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="456">RESOLUTION NO. 456</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>Hon. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Duke of Edinburgh's Award, founded by His Royal Highness Prince Philip, the Duke of Edinburgh, was introduced to Canada in 1963 and is currently present in more than 120 countries; and</p>
<p>Whereas the award encourages young people to become active in their communities and challenges them to hone a skill and embark on an adventurous journey; and</p>
<p>Whereas Brianna O'Malley, a student at Halifax West High School, successfully completed the rigorous requirements and was awarded the bronze Duke of Edinburgh's Award at a ceremony on November 25, 2013, at Halifax West High School;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Brianna O'Malley on receiving this prestigious award, and offer best wishes for continued success as a leader in the community.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <num title="457">RESOLUTION NO. 457</num>
          <speech by="#08ecdd96-bc51-4f9f-bb87-7a7b5060d8c2"><from>Hon. Diana Whalen</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Duke of Edinburgh's Award, founded by His Royal Highness Prince Philip, the Duke of Edinburgh, was introduced to Canada in 1963 and is currently present in more than 120 countries; and</p>
<p>Whereas the award encourages young people to become active in their communities and challenges them to hone a skill and embark on an adventurous journey; and</p>
<p>Whereas Keelan O'Malley, a student at Halifax West High School, successfully completed the rigorous requirements and was awarded the bronze Duke of Edinburgh's Award at a ceremony on November 25, 2013, at Halifax West High School;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Keelan O'Malley on receiving this prestigious award, and offer best wishes for continued success as a leader in the community.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
