<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="david.allan.wilson" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.david.allan.wilson" showAs="HON. DAVID WILSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="jamie.baillie" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.jamie.baillie" showAs="HON. JAMIE BAILLIE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="maureen.macdonald" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.maureen.macdonald" showAs="HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="eddie.orrell" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.eddie.orrell" showAs="MR. EDDIE ORRELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="allan.gerard.macmaster" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.allan.gerard.macmaster" showAs="MR. ALLAN MACMASTER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="sterling.belliveau" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.sterling.belliveau" showAs="HON. STERLING BELLIVEAU"/>
        <TLCPerson id="tim.houston" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.tim.houston" showAs="MR. TIM HOUSTON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="lenore.zann" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.lenore.zann" showAs="MS. LENORE ZANN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="john.a.lohr" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.john.a.lohr" showAs="MR. JOHN LOHR"/>
        <TLCPerson id="michel.p.samson" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.michel.p.samson" showAs="HON. MICHEL SAMSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="christopher.a.dentremont" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.christopher.a.dentremont" showAs="Hon. Christopher d'Entremont"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MR. SPEAKER"/>
        <TLCRole id="clerk" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.clerk" showAs="THE CLERK"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 29 September 2014</docTitle>
      <docNumber>14-03</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2014-09-29">Monday, September 29, 2014</docDate>
      <docAuthority>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docAuthority>
      <legislature value="62">62nd General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="2">2nd Session</session>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://nslegislature.ca/index.php/proceedings/hansard/C96/house_14sep29/"/>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>Order, please. We'll now begin with the daily routine.</p>
      </speech>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>INTRODUCTION OF BILLS</heading>
        <other>
          <p>
            <b> Bill No. 1 - Entitled an Act to Provide for Health Authorities and Community Health Boards. (Hon. Leo Glavine)</b>
          </p>
        </other>
        <other>
          <p>
            <b> Bill No. 2 - Entitled an Act Respecting Clean Air. (Ms. Karla MacFarlane)</b>
          </p>
        </other>
        <other>
          <p>
            <b> Bill No. 3 - Entitled an Act to Reduce the Regulatory Burden in Nova Scotia. (Mr. Tim Houston)</b>
          </p>
        </other>
        <other>
          <p>
            <b> Bill No. 4 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 217 of the Revised Statutes of 1989. The Income Tax Act. (Ms. Karla MacFarlane)</b>
          </p>
        </other>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>Ordered that these bills be read a second time on a future day.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Sackville-Cobequid.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#david.allan.wilson"><num title="12">RESOLUTION NO. 12</num><from>HON. DAVID WILSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas paramedics in Nova Scotia are comprised of highly-trained, dedicated men and women who are always ready to respond to any emergency; and</p>
<p>Whereas 11 years ago, paramedic John Rossiter made the ultimate sacrifice when he died in the line of duty during Hurricane Juan; and</p>
<p>Whereas John was well-respected as a dedicated paramedic by both his fellow colleagues and the thousands of patients who were fortunate to have been treated by him;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this Nova Scotia Legislature remember John Rossiter, who died in the line of duty during Hurricane Juan on September 29, 2003, and thank our current paramedics for their ongoing dedication and contribution to the paramedicine profession in Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition</p></speech>
        <speech by="#jamie.baillie"><num title="13">RESOLUTION NO. 13</num><from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas in Canada, the last Sunday of September each year is designated as Police and Peace Officers' National Memorial Day; and</p>
<p>Whereas yesterday on Parliament Hill five police officers killed in the line of duty, including the three RCMP officers in Moncton, were honoured; and</p>
<p>Whereas police officers in Nova Scotia and across Canada risk their lives each day to protect citizens against those who threaten the safety of individuals and communities;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House salute Nova Scotia's dedicated police officers and remember the officers across Canada who paid the ultimate price to protect us.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Interim Leader of the New Democratic Party.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#maureen.macdonald"><num title="14">RESOLUTION NO. 14</num><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas this year marks the 250<sup>th</sup> Anniversary of Gottingen Street, which has been the heart of the North End Halifax community for centuries; and</p>
<p>Whereas many community groups came together to hold the Gottingen 250 Festival on September 13<sup>th </sup>to September 14<sup>th</sup> to commemorate this milestone; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers and staff spent many hours planning and coordinating entertainment, community art, and historic recognition projects so that the Gottingen community could come together and celebrate;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the Nova Scotia House of Assembly congratulate the organizers and volunteers of the Gottingen 250 Festival and express its appreciation for their hard work and commitment to Halifax and its history.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Northside-Westmount.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#eddie.orrell"><num title="15">RESOLUTION NO. 15</num><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Cape Breton Regional Police Chief Peter McIsaac was officially inducted into the Order of Merit of the Police Forces during a ceremony at Rideau Hall this month; and</p>
<p>Whereas Chief McIsaac was among 31 members the honour was bestowed upon by Governor General David Johnston; and</p>
<p>Whereas this award was created in 2000 to recognize outstanding merit and exceptional service by members and employees of Canadian police forces whose contributions extend beyond protection of community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly salute Chief McIsaac for his stellar service and commitment to our community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Inverness.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#allan.gerard.macmaster">
          <from>MR. ALLAN MACMASTER</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, I beg leave to make an introduction.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>Permission granted.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#allan.gerard.macmaster"><from>MR. MACMASTER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I had intended to deliver a speech this evening and I understand I can't do that now. But there is somebody here who is very special because he stood up, a victim of sexual abuse. His name is Bob Martin. I would like to direct everybody's attention to the Speaker's Gallery, and Bob, please stand and receive the welcome of the House. (Applause)</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, if I may - and I'm not going to make a speech - but I just wanted to acknowledge Bob for what he's gone through, for showing his bravery in coming here tonight and perhaps at a future date, I'll be able to deliver some remarks that are a fitting tribute to what he's gone through and what others have gone through. Thank you.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Queens-Shelburne.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#sterling.belliveau"><num title="16">RESOLUTION NO. 16</num><from>HON. STERLING BELLIVEAU</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Mersey Tobeatic Research Institute has recently released a video about local volunteer Jeff Craft from Bangs Falls, Queens County; and</p>
<p>Whereas Jeff Craft has provided more than 250 volunteer hours with the Mersey Tobeatic Research Institute; and</p>
<p>Whereas during his five years volunteering with the Mersey Tobeatic Research Institute, Jeff Craft has contributed to projects including old growth forests, flying squirrels and common loons, to name a few;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly recognize the work of Jeff Craft and volunteers like him who provide valuable work in furthering our knowledge and understanding of wildlife and wild places in Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Pictou East.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#tim.houston"><num title="17">RESOLUTION NO. 17</num><from>MR. TIM HOUSTON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Pictou County Sno-Riders Club is supporting Pictou County Crime Stoppers by displaying Nova Scotia Crime Stoppers signs on their trails and their hut; and</p>
<p>Whereas the signs raise awareness that the property is protected and it also sends the message that you can use the tip line to report information about a crime and remain anonymous; and</p>
<p>Whereas this partnership is a win-win in making our county and our province safer for all;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly thank the Pictou County Sno-Riders for supporting Pictou County Crime Stoppers and helping to make our community safer.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Truro-Bible Hill-Millbrook-Salmon River.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#lenore.zann"><num title="18">RESOLUTION NO. 18</num><from>MS. LENORE ZANN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on August 17, 2014, Truro native 14-year-old Cali Bruce swam across the Northumberland Strait; and</p>
<p>Whereas Cali was part of The Big Swim, a fundraiser for Brigadoon Village in the Annapolis Valley, where she personally raised $11,000; and</p>
<p>Whereas Cali broke a 50-year-old record as she is now the youngest swimmer to make the crossing;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the Nova Scotia Legislature congratulate Cali Bruce for her courage and dedication and wish her every success in her future competitive swimming career.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Kings North.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#john.a.lohr"><num title="19">RESOLUTION NO. 19</num><from>MR. JOHN LOHR</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Alaina Poirier of Kentville was a member of the Nova Scotia Under-15 Girls Basketball team, which played in the national championships in Edmonton in July; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Under-15 Nova Scotia Girls team defeated New Brunswick 73-65 to clinch fifth place in the tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas Alaina contributed to Nova Scotia's round-robin play, where the team finished with three wins and three losses;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Alaina Poirier from Kentville on her outstanding basketball talent and wish her every success in the sport and with her school studies this year.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT BUSINESS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Thank you, Mr. Speaker. That concludes the government's business for this evening. Tomorrow, the hours of the House will be from 7:00 a.m. until 11:59 p.m. Following the daily routine and Question Period will be second reading of Bill No. 1.</p>
<p>With that, Mr. Speaker, I move that the House do now rise to meet again at 7:00 a.m. on Tuesday, September 30<sup>th</sup>.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that House rise to meet again on Tuesday, September 30<sup>th</sup> between the hours of 7:00 a.m. and 11:59 p.m.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>There has been a call for a recorded vote. We will ring the bells for one hour while we set up for the recorded vote.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>The Division bells were rung.</p>
        </narrative>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>Are the Whips satisfied?</p>
        </speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>The Clerk calls the roll.</p>
        </narrative>
        <other><table>
<tr>
<th>YEAS</th>
<th>NAYS</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. Colwell&#xA0;</td>
<td>Mr.  MacMaster&#xA0;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. Churchill&#xA0;</td>
<td>Mr.  Dunn&#xA0;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ms. Regan&#xA0;</td>
<td>Mr.  Baillie&#xA0;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. Samson&#xA0;</td>
<td>Mr.  d'Entremont&#xA0;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. McNeil&#xA0;</td>
<td>Mr.  Corbett&#xA0;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ms. Whelan&#xA0;</td>
<td>Ms.  MacDonald&#xA0;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. Glavine&#xA0;</td>
<td>Mr.  David Wilson&#xA0;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ms. Casey&#xA0;</td>
<td>Mr.  Gosse&#xA0;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. MacLellan&#xA0;</td>
<td>Ms. Zann&#xA0;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ms. Diab&#xA0;</td>
<td>Ms.  Peterson-Rafuse&#xA0;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. Horne&#xA0;</td>
<td>Mr.  Belliveau&#xA0;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. Hines&#xA0;</td>
<td>Mr.  Orrell&#xA0;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. Stroink&#xA0;</td>
<td>Ms.  MacFarlane&#xA0;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ms. Arab&#xA0;</td>
<td>Mr.  Houston&#xA0;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. Delorey&#xA0;</td>
<td>Mr.  Porter&#xA0;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. Kousoulis&#xA0;</td>
<td>Mr.  Harrison&#xA0;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. Furey&#xA0;</td>
<td>Mr.  Lohr&#xA0;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. Farrell&#xA0;</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. Gordon Wilson&#xA0;</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. Rankin&#xA0;</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ms. Miller&#xA0;</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. Rowe&#xA0;</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. Maguire&#xA0;</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ms. Eyking&#xA0;</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ms. Lohnes-Croft&#xA0;</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ms. Treen&#xA0;</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. Gough&#xA0;</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. Jessome&#xA0;</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mr. Irving&#xA0;</td>
<td/>
</tr>
</table>
</other>
        <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined">
          <from>THE CLERK</from>
          <p>For, 29. Against,17.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The House will now adjourn until 7:00 a.m. tomorrow morning.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>The House rose at 8:24 p.m.</p>
        </narrative>
      </debateSection>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION UNDER RULE 32(3)</heading>
        <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><num title="20">RESOLUTION NO. 20</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Monday, May 26<sup>th</sup>, the Municipality of Argyle held a networking session for local business owners and to introduce their newly-hired Tourism Ambassador; and</p>
<p>Whereas Marilyn d'Entremont from West Pubnico has been appointed to the position to provide visitors with information on what to see and do in the region; and</p>
<p>Whereas Marilyn d'Entremont will be responsible for the distribution of brochures and marketing materials, as well as visiting set locations at festivals and events and any other opportunities that may arise;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Marilyn d'Entremont on her appointment and wish her much success in her endeavours.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#allan.gerard.macmaster"><num title="21">RESOLUTION NO. 21</num><from>Mr. Allan MacMaster</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas today marks the second annual Medic Monday, recognizing the work of over 1,400 paramedics in Nova Scotia; and</p>
<p>Whereas paramedics are unsung heroes who work tirelessly day and night, providing emergency care for Nova Scotians; and</p>
<p>Whereas their professionalism, care, and compassion are integral components of our health care system;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly show their appreciation for Nova Scotia's paramedics on the second annual Medic Monday.</p></speech>
      </noticesOfMotion>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
