<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="michel.p.samson" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.michel.p.samson" showAs="HON. MICHEL SAMSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="kelly.regan" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.kelly.regan" showAs="HON. KELLY REGAN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="patrick.dunn" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.patrick.dunn" showAs="HON. PAT DUNN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="maureen.macdonald" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.maureen.macdonald" showAs="HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="jamie.baillie" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.jamie.baillie" showAs="HON JAMIE BAILLIE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="eddie.orrell" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.eddie.orrell" showAs="MR. EDDIE ORRELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="sterling.belliveau" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.sterling.belliveau" showAs="HON. STERLING BELLIVEAU"/>
        <TLCPerson id="joyce.treen" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.joyce.treen" showAs="MS. JOYCE TREEN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="allan.gerard.macmaster" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.allan.gerard.macmaster" showAs="MR. ALLAN MACMASTER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="denise.peterson.rafuse" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.denise.peterson.rafuse" showAs="HON. DENISE PETERSON-RAFUSE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="tony.ince" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.tony.ince" showAs="HON. TONY INCE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="alfie.macleod" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.alfie.macleod" showAs="MR. ALFIE MACLEOD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="lenore.zann" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.lenore.zann" showAs="MS. LENORE ZANN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="keith.irving" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.keith.irving" showAs="MR. KEITH IRVING"/>
        <TLCPerson id="suzanne.lohnes.croft" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.suzanne.lohnes.croft" showAs="MS. SUZANNE LOHNES-CROFT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="allan.rowe" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.allan.rowe" showAs="MR. ALLAN ROWE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="margaret.miller" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.margaret.miller" showAs="MS. MARGARET MILLER"/>
        <TLCPerson id="lloyd.hines" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.lloyd.hines" showAs="MR. LLOYD HINES"/>
        <TLCPerson id="brendan.o.maguire" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.brendan.o.maguire" showAs="MR. BRENDAN MAGUIRE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="iain.rankin" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.iain.rankin" showAs="MR. IAIN RANKIN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="gordon.l.wilson" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.gordon.l.wilson" showAs="MR. GORDON WILSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="mark.furey" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.mark.furey" showAs="HON. MARK FUREY"/>
        <TLCPerson id="patricia.arab" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.patricia.arab" showAs="MS. PATRICIA ARAB"/>
        <TLCPerson id="terry.farrell" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.terry.farrell" showAs="MR. TERRY FARRELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="karla.macfarlane" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.karla.macfarlane" showAs="MS. KARLA MACFARLANE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="labi.kousoulis" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.labi.kousoulis" showAs="HON. LABI KOUSOULIS"/>
        <TLCPerson id="christopher.a.dentremont" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.christopher.a.dentremont" showAs="HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="zach.churchill" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.zach.churchill" showAs="HON. ZACH CHURCHILL"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MR. SPEAKER"/>
        <TLCRole id="clerk" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.clerk" showAs="THE CLERK"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 28 April 2014</docTitle>
      <docNumber>14-35</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2014-04-28">Monday, April 28, 2014</docDate>
      <docAuthority>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docAuthority>
      <legislature value="62">62nd General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="1">1st Session</session>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://nslegislature.ca/index.php/proceedings/hansard/C94/house_14apr28/"/>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>Order, please. We'll now proceed with the daily routine.</p>
      </speech>
      <papers>
        <heading>TABLING REPORTS, REGULATIONS AND OTHER PAPERS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, j'ai le plaisir de pr&#xE9;senter le Rapport d'&#xE9;tape 2013 sur les Services en fran&#xE7;ais offerts par le gouvernement de la Nouvelle-&#xC9;cosse.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I'm pleased to table the 2013 Progress Report on French-language services provided by the Government of Nova Scotia.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The report is tabled.</p>
        </speech>
      </papers>
      <ministerialStatements>
        <heading>STATEMENTS BY MINISTERS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Labour and Advanced Education.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#kelly.regan"><from>HON. KELLY REGAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I rise today to recognize April 28<sup>th</sup> as the National Day of Mourning. Every year we join together on this day to pay tribute to the workers who have been killed, injured, or suffered illness because of workplace hazards or incidents.</p>
<p>Thirty-four people lost their lives on the job in Nova Scotia last year. They were precious lives that were taken away far too soon. Each of these deaths was preventable, each one unnecessary, and each one left a wake of heartbreak for families and loved ones. Those 34 workers were mothers, fathers, brothers, sisters, daughters, and sons, and those they left behind will carry their loss with them every day.</p>
<p>Nova Scotians have the right to return home each day safe and healthy. Death, injury, work-related illness, and risk to life and limb should not be part of the job. Unfortunately, this isn't always the case, and that must change. Today is a day to remember, reflect, and pay tribute. It is also a day to reaffirm our shared commitment, not just to reduce workplace fatalities, but to eliminate them. It's a day to reaffirm our commitment to the families and loved ones who have suffered unimaginable loss. These families have asked us for change, and on this important day, I want to assure them and everyone here that we are listening.</p>
<p>In this Legislature we may not always agree on everything. In fact, I'm pretty sure we don't always agree on everything, but I think I can safely say that we all stand united when it comes to improving workplace safety and eliminating illness, injury, and death on the job. Families have told us, and we wholeheartedly agree, that workplace safety must be top of mind at all times, for every worker in every workplace.</p>
<p>We've taken some important steps over the past few months in order to get us there. Last Fall we launched the What Matters Most campaign. This campaign reminds us of the important reasons we need to be safe at work: so we can come home to our families at the end of the day, safe and sound.</p>
<p>This campaign sends a powerful message and it has people talking - in office lunchrooms, around the supper table, and across social media networks like Facebook. These ads call for a shift in our thinking. We know this won't happen overnight, Mr. Speaker, but with the support this campaign has already received from workers, businesses, and everyday Nova Scotians, it's fair to say the shift is already on.</p>
<p>We also recently announced an expansion of the province's Occupational Health and Safety team. A new outreach unit with 12 new positions is being created to focus on education, enforcement, and compliance. This is in addition to the five new safety inspectors the province is hiring to focus on targeted inspections and improved compliance of high-risk workplaces, and we are partnering with the Public Prosecution Service to add an additional prosecutor to focus on occupational health and safety offences. This will ensure that workplace accidents resulting in death or serious injury will be thoroughly investigated, and prosecuted where warranted.</p>
<p>These changes have come about because families asked for them, and because they are needed. This province is rich in people who are dedicated and passionate about making workplaces safer. The WCB, the Federation of Labour, and our many partners have been working with us on these and many changes. They are hard at work every day, making safety a priority in workplaces across the province. Thanks to their efforts and the efforts of workers, families, and loved ones, change is happening - change that will mean a safer Nova Scotia for all.</p>
<p>While today we remember those who are no longer with us, let us pledge to make workplace deaths and injuries a thing of the past. Thank you, Mr. Speaker.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Pictou Centre.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#patrick.dunn"><from>HON. PAT DUNN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I want to thank the minister for providing a copy of her remarks earlier today.</p>
<p>April 28<sup>th</sup>, the National Day of Mourning, is a solemn occasion - a day to commemorate workers who have been killed or injured or suffered illness due to workplace accidents. Today our thoughts are not only with the 34 Nova Scotians who lost their lives on the job last year, but with their families and communities. For them, every day is a day of mourning, because they know their son or daughter, mother or father, sister or brother will never come home from their workplace.</p>
<p>On behalf of the Progressive Conservative caucus, I extend my sincere condolences. Even one workplace death is too many.</p>
<p>The Day of Mourning brings much-needed awareness and attention to this very serious issue, and we thank everyone who has worked tirelessly on this campaign and everyone who works to prevent workplace accidents.</p>
<p>Workplace safety is a partnership between employer and employee, and like any great partnership, you need to have open and constant communication. Employers need to be accountable for providing a safe environment for their employees to perform and succeed in, and employees need to make sure that, if they see a potential harm or threat, it gets reported immediately.</p>
<p>I want to thank the men and women, both employee and employer, who have noticed something unsafe in their work area and who quickly took action to prevent a workplace accident from happening. Our province has an amazingly skilled workforce filled with talented and dependable workers. It is an absolute must that we keep them safe.</p>
<p>Together we can all make Nova Scotia a safer place to work, so that each year the number of workplace tragedies gets closer and closer to zero. I appreciate the opportunity today to honour those who have lost their lives, and to offer our commitment to eliminating workplace accidents and tragedies in our province. Thank you.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Leader of the New Democratic Party.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#maureen.macdonald"><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I want to, first, thank the minister for providing a copy of her remarks in advance. Today, as we all know, is the National Day of Mourning, a day to remember those who have gone to work in the morning and not come home at night. Sadly, in our province there were 34 workplace fatalities since this time last year.</p>
<p>First and foremost, I, on behalf of the NDP caucus want to extend our sincere condolences to those people, their families, and their friends who have been affected by workplace injuries and deaths. One is one too many, Mr. Speaker, and many of these fatalities we know are preventable. It's a very sad reality that every day, dozens of Nova Scotians leave for work and they return home with injuries, and some may not return at all.</p>
<p>This is a reality that does have to change, and I fully agree with the minister, and I know my colleagues to my right agree as well - this is an issue that transcends partisan politics. It is something that we all feel very deeply and we believe fervently that needs to change.</p>
<p>Workplace injuries and deaths in almost all cases are preventable, and while there will always be occupations that put Nova Scotians at a higher risk for injury, this is no excuse for accepting the status quo or the idea that workplace injuries and deaths will happen no matter what we do. Workplace deaths and injuries are a direct result of our individual and collective actions, and we need to step up our efforts to educate Nova Scotians about workplace safety because Nova Scotians have a right to know what a safe workplace looks like.</p>
<p>I know we're all particularly concerned about young workers who tragically seem sometimes to be at higher risk in our workplaces, and that's why our government, a few years ago, established the Grade 9 curriculum program to connect with the next generation of workers. By expanding the Workplace Health and Safety modules from its pilot project to all schools across the province, all Grade 9 students now have an opportunity to learn how to respect their work environment and the tools to help prevent workplace accidents.</p>
<p>Nova Scotians must understand that they have both a right and a duty to raise safety concerns with their employers and, conversely, employers have a responsibility to provide safe working environments. Employers who fail to do this must be held to account - that is why the NDP introduced legislation, regulations, that provide for administrative penalties when violations are found at work sites. Also, about a year ago the NDP and the Workers' Compensation Board launched a new five-year workplace safety strategy that aims to make Nova Scotia the safest province in the country for our workforce.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I said this morning at the Day of Mourning ceremony here at Province House that as MLAs we are privileged to experience great joy in our work when we attend celebrations in our community where people are having a 100<sup>th</sup> Birthday, or where young people are graduating from a program that they have had great success in, or a new community project that has been worked on for decades comes into reality, but a day like today is a day of sorrow for MLAs in our House. We all know families, we all know communities that have felt the tragedy, the sorrow, the human cost of having someone from our province lose their life on the job. Collectively I know we are determined to turn these statistics around so that sorrow will be absent in our lives and in the lives of our communities. Thank you.</p></speech>
      </ministerialStatements>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="1389">RESOLUTION NO. 1389</num><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, with this resolution, I will read it and then ask the Leader of the Official Opposition and the Leader of the New Democratic Party to read a resolution as well. Rather than asking for waiver for each one of them, maybe we can ask for waiver following the resolution by the Leader of the New Democratic Party and then we will have a moment of silence following all three resolutions.</p>
<p>On behalf of the Premier, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas this year, Yom HaShoah, Holocaust Memorial Day, is April 28<sup>th</sup>; and</p>
<p>Whereas Yom HaShoah is a day committed to remember the six million Jews who were murdered during the Holocaust; and</p>
<p>Whereas organizations like the Atlantic Jewish Council have organized remembrance ceremonies, which include lighting of memorial candles and the reading of names of those lost during the Holocaust;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this Legislature acknowledge today, April 28<sup>th</sup>, as Holocaust Memorial Day and be ever mindful of the atrocities that exceeded all bounds of human dignity, and ensure these events are neither forgotten nor repeated.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#jamie.baillie"><num title="1390">RESOLUTION NO. 1390</num><from>HON JAMIE BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I have a resolution after which I think we will have a joint moment of silence, with your permission, when we've concluded the three of them.</p>
<p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Yom HaShoah, or Holocaust Remembrance Day, began yesterday evening; and</p>
<p>Whereas this day serves as a reminder of the lives lost and the heroism of the more than six million Jewish people who died at the hands of the Nazis during the Holocaust; and</p>
<p>Whereas Jewish communities across Nova Scotia will pay tribute to the innocent lives lost and raise awareness of the atrocities that occurred;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House recognize Yom HaShoah and let today serve as a reminder of the horrors that intolerance and hatred can produce, and to resolve never to let these crimes be forgotten or repeated.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Would everyone please rise for a moment of silence in honour of those who fell during the Holocaust.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>A moment of silence was observed.</p>
        </narrative>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Pictou Centre.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#patrick.dunn"><num title="1391">RESOLUTION NO. 1391</num><from>HON. PAT DUNN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Trenton Trojans Mini Boys basketball team captured the provincial championship with a 39-26 victory over Dartmouth; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Trenton squad played strong defence, showing that good balance is the key to a great defensive stance and guarding the ball; and</p>
<p>Whereas Nick MacInnis was selected MVP of the tournament and Brandon Campbell was named to the all-star team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate coach Shannon MacInnis and his group of mini stars for their recent stellar performance as Nova Scotia's Provincial Mini Boys basketball champions.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the New Democratic Party.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#maureen.macdonald"><num title="1392">RESOLUTION NO. 1392</num><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas April 28<sup>th</sup> is officially recognized as the Day of Mourning in Canada and observed by over 80 countries worldwide; and</p>
<p>Whereas today we acknowledge the men and women who have lost their lives or who have been hurt or became ill in the workplace; and</p>
<p>Whereas today we are reminded that employees and employers must be vigilant, we must educate ourselves and others, and commit to workplace safety;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly honour the memory of those who have lost their lives by committing to improve health and safety in the workplace.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson">
          <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
          <p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, je pr&#xE9;sente cette r&#xE9;solution au nom de l'honorable d&#xE9;put&#xE9; de Eastern Shore.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><num title="1393">RESOLUTION NO. 1393</num><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, &#xE0; une date ult&#xE9;rieure, je demanderai l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu que Beverly Hugli est une &#xE9;ducatrice retrait&#xE9;e apr&#xE8;s nombreuses ann&#xE9;es de service dans la r&#xE9;gion de la C&#xF4;te Est; et</p>
<p>Attendu que Beverly est pr&#xE9;sentement pr&#xE9;sidente du conseil d'administration du Groupe d'int&#xE9;r&#xEA;ts de la communaut&#xE9; de West Chezzetcook et Grand D&#xE9;sert, le groupe qui g&#xE8;re le Mus&#xE9;e de la Maison acadienne &#xE0; West Chezzetcook; et</p>
<p>Attendu que gr&#xE2;ce aux efforts soutenus de Beverly, la communaut&#xE9; de Grand D&#xE9;sert a pu sauvegarder sa culture acadienne;</p>
<p>Par cons&#xE9;quent, qu'il soit r&#xE9;solu que les membres de la Chambre d'assembl&#xE9;e se joignent &#xE0; moi pour remercier Beverly Hugli de sa passion et de sa conviction continue pour la pr&#xE9;servation de la culture acadienne de la r&#xE9;gion de la C&#xF4;te Est.</p>
<p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, je demande l'adoption de cette r&#xE9;solution sans pr&#xE9;avis et sans d&#xE9;bat.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, on behalf of the honourable member for Eastern Shore, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Beverly Hugli is a retired educator who taught on the Eastern Shore for many years; and</p>
<p>Whereas Beverly is currently President of the West Chezzetcook and Grand Desert Interest Group, which operates the Acadian House Museum in West Chezzetcook; and</p>
<p>Whereas Beverley's efforts have contributed greatly to maintaining the strong Acadian heritage and culture in Grand Desert;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly join me in thanking Beverly Hugli for giving of her time and talents for the preservation of the Acadian culture on the Eastern Shore.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Northside-Westmount.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#eddie.orrell"><num title="1394">RESOLUTION NO. 1394</num><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas contributions both big and small were recognized during the unveiling of the Donor Wall of Caring at the Northside Community Guest Home; and</p>
<p>Whereas the guest speaker was Cape Breton University Chancellor Annette Verschuren, whose mother Annie volunteered for many years at the home; and</p>
<p>Whereas she thanked the many volunteers and contributors who have made the Northside Community Guest Home one of the best in the province;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate those recognized on the Donor Wall for their generosity, making this facility second to none.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Queens-Shelburne.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#sterling.belliveau"><num title="1395">RESOLUTION NO. 1395</num><from>HON. STERLING BELLIVEAU</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas in this week's edition of the Shelburne Coast Guard, residents expressed concern over the condition of the Ferry West Road and the Lockes Island Road; and</p>
<p>Whereas much of the uncertainty over rural roads would be eliminated with the creation of a multi-year rural road plan; and</p>
<p>Whereas local residents would like the Minister of Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal to evaluate the condition of Ferry West Road and the Lockes Island Road and provide them with a timetable of when needed repairs will be completed;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly support the creation of a public, multi-year, rural road plan so that Nova Scotians, such as those living along Lockes Island Road and the Ferry West Road, would be given more information and clarity of when they can expect their roads to be repaired or repaved.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cole Harbour-Eastern Passage.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#joyce.treen"><num title="1396">RESOLUTION NO. 1396</num><from>MS. JOYCE TREEN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Eastern Passage/Cow Bay Lions Club supports numerous community groups and families in need; and</p>
<p>Whereas they hold monthly bingos for the seniors at the Ocean View Continuing Care Centre and held a dinner at no cost for World Service Day; and</p>
<p>Whereas they also provide a location for many community fundraisers and help organize the Christmas food boxes for needy families within our community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly join me in thanking the Eastern Passage/Cow Bay Lions Club for their unwavering support to our community and wish them continued success in the future.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Inverness.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#allan.gerard.macmaster"><num title="1397">RESOLUTION NO. 1397</num><from>MR. ALLAN MACMASTER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Wayne Aucoin, owner of Wayne's Beauty Salon, provides quality hair care for locals and visitors to Cheticamp; and</p>
<p>Whereas Wayne's dedication and friendship with clients has kept him going for 37 years; and</p>
<p>Whereas Wayne has always wanted to work with hair, beginning with his mom's, as a young boy;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly acknowledge Wayne for following his heart and providing confidence and positive reinforcement for all of his lifelong clients.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Chester-St. Margaret's.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#denise.peterson.rafuse"><num title="1398">RESOLUTION NO. 1398</num><from>HON. DENISE PETERSON-RAFUSE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas since the first Women's World Championship in 1990, the sport of women's hockey has taken its place as an exciting and interesting national sport; and</p>
<p>Whereas the TASA Ducks Hockey Association has joined in developing a strong and successful female hockey program, as shown by the TASA Female Bantam AA, who posted 38 wins, 4 losses and 13 ties, winning tournaments at home and around Atlantic Canada; and</p>
<p>Whereas the TASA Female Bantam AA team's success is a big team effort and includes the parents and the TASA association, along with the coaches and talented players;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House congratulate the TASA Female Bantam AA players, coaches, and parents on such a successful year and recognize the contributions that TASA association is making to this generation's players and fans of women's hockey.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Communities, Culture and Heritage.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#tony.ince"><num title="1399">RESOLUTION NO. 1399</num><from>HON. TONY INCE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas over the years, Melinda Daye has served in many capacities in her community as a school principal, president of the Black Educators Association, a member of the Halifax Regional School Board, and director with the Nova Scotia School Boards Association; and</p>
<p>Whereas Melinda Daye continues to make a significant contribution to the community by encouraging and empowering students to become active participants and leaders in their schools and communities; and</p>
<p>Whereas in recognition of Melinda Daye's work as an advisor on race, colour, and ethnic affairs with Halifax Regional School Board and Nova Scotia School Boards, Ms. Daye was named the 2014 Education Week Partners Award winner at the annual Educational Week celebration;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly congratulate Melinda Daye on receiving this distinguished award, and commend her for her tireless work to promote education and community involvement across the province.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Sydney River-Mira-Louisbourg.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#alfie.macleod"><num title="1400">RESOLUTION NO. 1400</num><from>MR. ALFIE MACLEOD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Natasha Burke-Morash, of Little Lorraine, was recently nominated for the prestigious NSTU's Teachers Make a Difference campaign; and</p>
<p>Whereas Natasha Burke-Morash teaches junior high at George D. Lewis School in Louisbourg; and</p>
<p>Whereas Natasha Burke-Morash is a teacher who never stops helping out in all her capacities at her school and in her community, which means volunteering her time continuously in extracurricular activities;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate Natasha Burke-Morash on her nomination, and thank her for all she does for her students.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Truro-Bible Hill-Millbrook-Salmon River</p></speech>
        <speech by="#lenore.zann"><num title="1401">RESOLUTION NO. 1401</num><from>MS. LENORE ZANN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Doug MacInnes, a Big Brothers Big Sisters organization supporter, participated in the Bowl for Kids fundraiser in Bible Hill, Nova Scotia, recently; and</p>
<p>Whereas the fundraiser is now in its 36<sup>th</sup> year and has raised approximately $32,000; and</p>
<p>Whereas all money collected for the Big Brothers Big Sisters organization at the Bowl for Kids fundraiser goes towards programs for children in our local area;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the Nova Scotia Legislature congratulate Doug MacInnes and other participants for helping raise funds for the Big Brothers Big Sisters organization.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Kings South.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#keith.irving"><num title="1402">RESOLUTION NO. 1402</num><from>MR. KEITH IRVING</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Adam Melanson is a native of North Alton, Kings County, and plays football for Acadia University in Wolfville, as did generations of Melansons before him; and</p>
<p>Whereas Adam has distinguished himself as a starter on the defensive line in his first year; and</p>
<p>Whereas Adam Melanson has recently been declared the Outstanding First Year Male Athlete of the Year by Acadia Athletics;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the House of Assembly congratulate Adam on his achievements, and wish him continued success in his sport. Go Acadia Go.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Northside-Westmount on an introduction.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#eddie.orrell">
          <from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, in the gallery opposite this evening is a gentleman who is a first-timer to Nova Scotia, Mr. Lance Bright lives in Vancouver, but works on the Maritime Aerial Surveillance Team for the Department of Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal. I'd like for the House of Assembly to give him a warm welcome to the province. (Applause)</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Northside-Westmount.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#eddie.orrell"><num title="1403">RESOLUTION NO. 1403</num><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for more than 20 years students from Robin Foote Elementary School have entertained the veterans of Harbourview Hospital with a variety of concerts, handcrafted Valentines, and other treats to celebrate Valentine's Day; and</p>
<p>Whereas the two-hour performance is strictly for the entertainment of the veterans, but it also helps the students build their confidence; and</p>
<p>Whereas it is hard to determine who gets the most out of this event, the veterans or the students;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly thank the students and staff of Robin Foote Elementary School and the local Legions to make this yearly event a possibility for our veterans.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Lunenburg.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#suzanne.lohnes.croft"><num title="1404">RESOLUTION NO. 1404</num><from>MS. SUZANNE LOHNES-CROFT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Grand Banker Seafood Bar and Grill has long been one of Lunenburg's most frequented and respected restaurants; and</p>
<p>Whereas Adam Bower started working in the restaurant as a busboy in 1998; and</p>
<p>Whereas Adam has returned to where his working life began, this time as the new owner of the iconic establishment;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Adam and his wife Christina on their hard work in making this dream come true.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Dartmouth South.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#allan.rowe"><num title="1405">RESOLUTION NO. 1405</num><from>MR. ALLAN ROWE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, on behalf of the member for Eastern Shore, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Fran Bellefontaine-Kelly is a long-time resident of the Eastern Shore and an accomplished businesswoman; and</p>
<p>Whereas Fran Bellefontaine-Kelly is an entrepreneur with a love of all children, and has operated Busy Bee Daycare Centres in five locations along the Eastern Shore; and</p>
<p>Whereas Fran will join with her family and extended family of hundreds of "Bees" alumni on June 21, 2014, to celebrate the 40<sup>th</sup> Anniversary of Busy Bee Daycare Centres;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Fran Bellefontaine-Kelly on celebrating 40 years in business at Busy Bee Daycare Centres.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Hants East.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#margaret.miller"><num title="1406">RESOLUTION NO. 1406</num><from>MS. MARGARET MILLER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas 12-year-old Makayla Lynn of Belnan has undeniable musical talents as a songwriter, musician, and singer; and</p>
<p>Whereas Makayla Lynn has realized a dream of recording her first studio-produced, radio mastered-quality album in Nashville, Tennessee; and</p>
<p>Whereas Makayla Lynn continues to grow, reach new heights, and share her incredible gift with audiences;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Makayla Lynn on the production of this album and wish her continued success in all of her musical pursuits.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Guysborough-Eastern Shore-Tracadie.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#lloyd.hines"><num title="1407">RESOLUTION NO. 1407</num><from>MR. LLOYD HINES</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Eastern Shore-Musquodoboit Valley Literacy Network has been offering literacy and essential skills development programs since 1996; and</p>
<p>Whereas they assist approximately 75 adult learners annually through their day and evening classes for levels 1 and 2 of the Nova Scotia School for Adult Learning's Adult Learning Program, GED preparation classes, computer literacy classes, and individualized training; and</p>
<p>Whereas all of their programs incorporate the essential skills necessary for adults to prepare to enter or re-enter the workforce;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly express our support for the importance of adult learning and the difference it can make in people's lives.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Halifax Atlantic.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#brendan.o.maguire"><num title="1408">RESOLUTION NO. 1408</num><from>MR. BRENDAN MAGUIRE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Rob Romans and his wife Jan Drisdelle both grew up in Halifax Atlantic and now raise their family in Spryfield; and</p>
<p>Whereas both Rob and Jan embarked on a new endeavour on January 6, 2014, opening their family business, Kool T's &amp; More, on Isleville Street; and</p>
<p>Whereas Kool T's offers one-stop, custom printing and with state-of-the-art equipment, they are able to provide high-quality, durable products such as signs, banners, T-shirts and much more;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of the House of Assembly congratulate Rob and Jan on their entrepreneurial spirit, and wish their new business success and prosperity.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Timberlea-Prospect.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#iain.rankin"><num title="1409">RESOLUTION NO. 1409</num><from>MR. IAIN RANKIN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Kevin Cox started a softball program in Timberlea 25 years ago, and it still remains active to this day; and</p>
<p>Whereas Kevin worked hard to get improvements such as the lights at the ball field; and</p>
<p>Whereas Kevin has given generously of his time and talents, volunteering now with three separate leagues;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly congratulate Kevin Cox for all of his efforts to give children the opportunity to have early success in sports and to lead active, healthy lifestyles.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Clare-Digby.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#gordon.l.wilson"><num title="1410">RESOLUTION NO. 1410</num><from>MR. GORDON WILSON</from><p>M. le Pr&#xE9;sident, par la pr&#xE9;sente, j'avise que je proposerai &#xE0; une date ult&#xE9;rieure l'adoption de la r&#xE9;solution suivante:</p>
<p>Attendu que Patrice Boulianne, pendant 20 ann&#xE9;es, par son talent de musicien, a promu la culture et la langue acadiennes sur les plans national et international; et</p>
<p>Attendu que Patrice Boulianne vient de lancer un album pour le groupe Blou, un groupe musical hautement reconnu; et</p>
<p>Attendu que Patrice Boulianne a m&#xE9;rit&#xE9; plusieurs prix et distinctions;</p>
<p>Par cons&#xE9;quent, qu'il soit r&#xE9;solu que les membres de cette Assembl&#xE9;e f&#xE9;licitent Patrice Boulianne et Blou &#xE0; l'occasion du lancement de son r&#xE9;cent album et lui souhaitent un succ&#xE8;s continu.</p>
<p>Monsieur le Pr&#xE9;sident, je propose l'adoption de cette r&#xE9;solution sans pr&#xE9;avis et sans d&#xE9;bat.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Patrice Boulianne has promoted the Acadian language and culture for 20 years as a musician, nationally and internationally; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Patrice Boulianne has recently launched a musical album under his group name Blou, a well-known musical group; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mr. Patrice Boulianne has been awarded prizes and awards over the years;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this Assembly congratulate Patrice Boulianne and Blou for launching his recent album and wish him continued success.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Municipal Affairs.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#mark.furey"><num title="1411">RESOLUTION NO. 1411</num><from>HON. MARK FUREY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Bridgewater Music Festival has been held annually since 1973; and</p>
<p>Whereas with the leadership of festival president Catherine Isaac-Jamieson, this years' festival was held from April 5<sup>th</sup> to 16<sup>th</sup>; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Bridgewater Music Festival showcases choir, concert bands, musical theatre, and piano, to name a few, providing a venue for our young musicians and vocalists to show their talents to family, friends and community members;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate all participants of the Bridgewater Music Festival for their performances and thank the festival organizers for their hard work and dedication to making the Bridgewater Music Festival a success.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Fairview-Clayton Park.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#patricia.arab"><num title="1412">RESOLUTION NO. 1412</num><from>MS. PATRICIA ARAB</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Edith Brumby has been a dedicated volunteer at the IWK Hospital for many years, also spending hours of her time knitting stuffed toy animals for children undergoing surgery and other procedures; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ms. Brumby donates so much of her time to promote the happiness of others and is a truly generous person; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ms. Brumby was honoured at the 11<sup>th</sup> annual Mainland North Community Services Volunteer Awards and is the recipient of the Community Service Volunteer Award;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate Edith Brumby and thank her for all her years of volunteer service in our community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Guysborough-Eastern Shore-Tracadie.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#lloyd.hines">
          <from>MR. LLOYD HINES</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, on behalf of the member for Eastern Shore . .</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Order, please. There has already been two resolutions read on behalf of that particular member so we'll save that one for tomorrow.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Labour and Advanced Education.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#kelly.regan"><num title="1413">RESOLUTION NO. 1413</num><from>HON. KELLY REGAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Bedford resident Elaine Loney is a quintessential volunteer who has served on the Advisory Council at C.P. Allen High School for the past seven years and has also worked for the Consult Program, at the Palliative Care Unit at the QE II, as well as for the Bedford Watershed Advisory Committee, and Bedford United Church; and</p>
<p>Whereas Elaine's skill set is vast and she is a fair-minded, community-centered, dynamic thinker, unwavering in her commitment to her role and the stakeholders she is representing, always ensuring that she is well informed on the issues, is tenacious, conscientious and a persevering problem solver; and</p>
<p>Whereas having served for several years as Chair of the Advisory Council and on the Site Selection and School Steering Committees, Elaine Loney was nominated by C.P. Allen High School for the 2014 Bedford Volunteer Awards;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House congratulate Elaine Loney for being named one of two Adult Bedford Volunteers of the Year at the ceremony yesterday in Bedford and commend her outstanding service to her community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Labour and Advanced Education.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#kelly.regan"><num title="1414">RESOLUTION NO. 1414</num><from>HON. KELLY REGAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for 17 years, Veronica Parker has been a dedicated, active, reliable, capable and joyful volunteer with the Fort Sackville Foundation, assisting in the tea room for 15 years and in numerous other projects, thereby becoming a director and lifetime member of the foundation; and</p>
<p>Whereas Veronica Parker was a founding member of the Bedford Basin Art Group, the 14<sup>th</sup> Palette Art Group, founded the 1<sup>st</sup> Sackville Cub Pack and the 2<sup>nd</sup> Sackville Girl Guide Company, was a member of the Sackville Rivers Association, the Federation of Scottish Clans, Clan Lamont, Dartmouth Heritage Society, Red Cross Society and Anchor Industries Society, while also support Saint Ignatius Parish, Bedford United Church's Fish Line, Hope Cottage and Meals on Wheels; and</p>
<p>Whereas she was nominated by the Fort Sackville Foundation for the 2014 Bedford Volunteer Awards;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved the members of this House congratulate Veronica Parker for being names one of the two Adult Bedford Volunteers of the Year at the ceremony yesterday in Bedford and commend her outstanding service to her community.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#terry.farrell">
          <from>MR. TERRY FARRELL</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, I would ask that you call a five minute recess prior to the commencement of Government Business.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>On the request of the Deputy Government House Leader we will have a five minute recess before we commence with Government Business.</p>
        </speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>4:54 p.m. The House recessed.</p>
        </narrative>
        <narrative>
          <p>4:57 p.m. The House reconvened.</p>
        </narrative>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>Order, please. We'll now resume with Orders of the Day.</p>
        </speech>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT BUSINESS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson">
          <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Public Bills for Second Reading.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PUBLIC BILLS FOR SECOND READING</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson">
          <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 67.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 67 - Invest Nova Scotia Board Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I move that Bill No. 67, the Invest Nova Scotia Board Act be now read a second time. This legislation is part of this government's commitment to change the way we do economic development in this province. It's a significant step towards a new direction that allows the private sector to drive our economy forward.</p>
<p>The new Invest Nova Scotia Board will help set the winning conditions for more Nova Scotia businesses to thrive. The board will support projects that have broad-based benefits across sectors and in regions across the province. Mr. Speaker, under this legislation economic development will be done in a responsible way, in a way that will make Nova Scotians proud.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, Nova Scotians told us they wanted government to be more accountable and transparent in how public funds are spent. Last Fall we brought forward the Accountability in Economic Development Assistance Act and launched a new website that provides more information than ever before about the financial assistance government provides to business. That website has been live since April 1<sup>st</sup>. We're setting the bar higher for the rest of the country.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, with the passage of this bill, I am pleased to announced that the Nova Scotia's Jobs Fund will close. Rather than Cabinet deciding which corporations get financing, an independent and arm's-length board will have the final say. I am pleased to say that government is no longer in the business of picking winners and losers. The knowledgeable men and women who will lead this board will have the freedom to make the best choices for Nova Scotia. This is a significant change; it's the kind of change that Ray Ivany is promoting.</p>
<p>The Invest Nova Scotia Board could choose to invest in sector development or economic diversification, or they might support workforce development, research, or regional development in high unemployment areas. They may find worthy projects in all of these areas.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, the one thing the Invest Nova Scotia Board will not need do is go to Cabinet to get approval. Cabinet will have no role in the Invest Nova Scotia Fund. We will create the legislative framework, set clear economic development objectives for the new board to put into action, and ensure they have some funds to work with.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, government isn't here to be a banker or even to lead when it comes to commercial projects. Government is here to be a supportive and enthusiastic partner with the private sector because it is the private sector that creates jobs; it is government's job to set the conditions so companies can grow. Our government will be a champion for the kind of change that will get this province to be known as one of the best places to live, work, and do business.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, as Ray Ivany told us, we must believe in the potential of Nova Scotia, in our people, in our communities, and in our natural assets. We have an opportunity to turn things around for our future. We'll partner with sector associations, research institutions, co-operatives, and businesses that are identifying the next opportunity for growth that needs our help. That means supporting entrepreneurship in a start-up economy, investing in and retaining our youth, and making sure businesses have better access to capital. Our government will be doing all these things.</p>
<p>In March we received some very good advice from Dr. Tom Traves on how to move forward with our economic development tools. While we still have a lot of work to do to streamline and strengthen our programs, this bill is one of the most significant responses to Dr. Traves' report. The Invest Nova Scotia Board will have an important role in providing the kind of economic development support our province needs to advance. They will have the flexibility they need to respond to great opportunities that have lasting and positive effects on our economy, and they will be accountable to the government and to all Nova Scotians.</p>
<p>Over the next few weeks and months we'll be looking for qualified board members, and my department will be working on the regulations to ensure the Invest Nova Scotia Board has what it needs to get started and do its work on behalf of the people of Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I look forward to the comments from my colleagues and any recommendations they have regarding Bill No. 67. Merci beaucoup.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Pictou West.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#karla.macfarlane"><from>MS. KARLA MACFARLANE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I am pleased to stand in my place this evening and speak to Bill No. 67.</p>
<p>It is disappointing to see that the Liberal Government has broken yet another promise in six short months. Before forming government they were adamant that Cabinet-controlled slush funds were not in the best interest of Nova Scotians. Once they formed government they quickly changed their tune upon realizing it could be finally their Cabinet in control.</p>
<p>After so many decades of government spending taxpayers' money irresponsibly, it is time we take the necessary steps to assure Nova Scotians that era is behind us - this bill does not do that.</p>
<p>People are tired of seeing news stories about government secrecy in funding programs - they work hard for their money and, as elected officials, it is our job to defend them. We want to see the politics taken out of investments, but we don't see that in this bill. This does not measure up to the promise made by the Liberals before the election. Once again, Nova Scotians didn't get the full story with Liberal campaign promises. Before the election the Liberals did not believe in having Cabinet-controlled investment decisions for Nova Scotia; now they've created two funds. This is no different than what the NDP did with the creation of the Jobs Fund. It has a new name and a fancy new co-signer.</p>
<p>This is not a step forward; it is a step backward. Nova Scotians were hoping this government would deliver on its promise and finally show accountability to taxpayers; instead they are redirecting power back to the Treasury Board. There is no room for political games when it comes to growing our economy. As the Ivany report points out, we are at a crossroads, the government should have heeded the advice of the experts and left politically motivated investments behind.</p>
<p>When the Industrial Expansion Fund was rebranded as the Jobs Fund, the Premier, while in Opposition, said, "This is nothing more than a sham. Government should be embarrassed to stand up and suggest that this is rebranding &#x2026; This is nothing more than keeping the old fund available to this Cabinet. If they really wanted to try something different, maybe they would have moved the investment arm out of government &#x2026;" - and I will table those statements for the benefit of the House.</p>
<p>Once we saw the restructuring the government introduced last week, we realized that it is nothing more than the same old political games of the past. The Premier should have stayed true to his word but he did not. Nova Scotians aren't comforted by this change nor are they comforted by the fact that Cabinet will design the guidelines that the Invest Nova Scotia Board will follow. Until we see regulations, it is impossible to say what this will mean for Nova Scotians. We are saddened to see the new government simply exchange the NDP chequebook for the Liberal chequebook.</p>
<p>We look forward to hearing from Nova Scotians about Bill No. 67 in the Law Amendments Committee.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Chester-St. Margaret's.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#denise.peterson.rafuse"><from>HON. DENISE PETERSON-RAFUSE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, it's my pleasure to speak on Bill No. 67. I know that my colleagues beside us call it a shell game; we call it the "Michel game". That's what it is; it is a game. I want to bring forward several facts. There's information that people can find out.</p>
<p>When the NDP became government, one thing that we made sure we did, in terms of looking at corporations or any type of medium-size business coming to Cabinet, was the fact that in the past there weren't any kind of rules behind why that cheque or funding would be given to a corporation. What we looked at is the fact that it needed to be tied into job creation. There are enough documents to show that when an analysis on whether or not funding should be in place for a business, we did the statistical and economic analysis to see if X number of jobs are created - and we do know that when jobs are created, it actually brings back more money for dollar-for-dollar investment.</p>
<p>That didn't happen in the past. We made sure it was related to those job numbers. There is a lot of proof around that because I know that the minister himself has said in the House that the Jobs Fund itself is going to be continued because there were commitments made into the future. That's proof to show those commitments are tied into job creation.</p>
<p>The other aspect is, when they were in Opposition, the now Liberal Government were very adamant against the Irving investment. We don't hear very much about that now. The full amount they were throwing out that we were investing has not been totally given to the Irvings because of the fact they're tied into job creation. This government now in power can do exactly what they said, when they were over on this side, they could cut that funding stream if they chose. They were totally against it; they are the government of the day. There are many contracts that are out there that this government has reneged on and so there's no difference here because those were tied into jobs.</p>
<p>I don't want to see that happen because I believe, and we believe, that the investment into the Irving Shipbuilding contract will bring thousands of jobs to this province and billions of dollars to the economy. I think that it's also important to note that we're very proud, in the NDP, of the Ivany report and that is a report that was initiated under our government because we did know there were issues in rural Nova Scotia and we're pleased that the Liberal Party is able to adopt that report that the NDP initiated and that they're using it as part of their strategy.</p>
<p>I think the public needs to know one thing about Invest Nova Scotia. This is just moving around the players; it is not getting rid of the players. Number one, the board that will be created is under the jurisdiction and auspices of the minister to create. He can choose who sits or does not sit on that board. Also, I think this is the key factor that Nova Scotians need to know, and will know, and will see, because they are very smart about these political games, that those who are sitting, it goes through from the new board that is created to the Treasury Board in the province. Now who sits on our Treasury Board but Cabinet Ministers - if anyone thinks there is not going to be control from the Cabinet, I'm sorry, they are wrong because there will be.</p>
<p>Now there are options for the minister and the government - they could give their new board, if they're saying that board is going to be balanced and fair in terms of their decision making and their politics, well then give them a budget. When they come to a point that they're having issue, it's no different than other operations that go on in the government, it's the same as Community Services with their disability strategy, they're saying that as they move that strategy along when they need money they will go to the Treasury Board and there's a certain amount of money put aside for them. No difference here, this is the makeup that could take place in how they structure this particular new Invest Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>The government could very well leave the board be independent with a budget, allow them to make their decisions and if they come to a circumstance where a major corporation may be closing its door or needs a very large investment, then the new board could present that to the Treasury Board for a decision if those funds are available in the government's coffers to be able to provide. So there is a real way that our government could show to Nova Scotians that what they are doing is actually being transparent. I know the minister often says we're being transparent because we put it on the Internet. Well, who is putting it on the Internet? They can pick and choose what goes there also.</p>
<p>I think the key out of everything that I have said here today is the actual structure and the lines of decision making that is in the present legislation, which certainly does not remove it from any interference or discussion from a Cabinet level - and Nova Scotians know that, it is not something you're going to fool Nova Scotians on. As time goes by they will learn more, they will see that, so I suggest to the minister and government if they truly want to be transparent let this board be independent with their own budget. If they run into the circumstances that they need more financial assistance, then the Treasury Board comes into play to make a decision in that particular case. Thank you very much, Mr. Speaker.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>I do want to thank the honourable member for Chester-St. Margaret's for her comments, but I do want to draw to the honourable member's attention that it is unparliamentary to refer to another member using their name, in terms of the "Michel shell game," the risk of repeating that and also, according to Page 147 of Beauchesne's Parliamentary Rules &amp; Forms, the member had referred to the "reneged contracts of the government" and that is also unparliamentary. I would ask the honourable member to apologize.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#denise.peterson.rafuse">
            <from>HON. DENISE PETERSON-RAFUSE</from>
            <p>Thank you very much, Mr. Speaker.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>If I recognize the minister it will be to close the debate.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I listened with great attention to the comments made by the critics on the opposite side. I guess the tactic of the Official Opposition and their critic is that if you say something often enough someone might believe you, but to suggest that our government has been secret in its financing decisions in this province is quite a stretch to say the least.</p>
<p>The fact is we have put in our Accountability in Economic Development Assistance Act; decisions being made using taxpayers' money as investments are being put online for all Nova Scotians to see regardless of where they live. Only the Official Opposition could turn that to secrecy. We are the first Canadian province to have done so and I'm certainly proud to be part of a government which has done so, and I'm certainly proud to be part of a government which has done so.</p>
<p>There may be some confusion on the part of the member for Pictou West when it comes to the issue of the Jobs Fund, so let me make it as clear as I can. Under the Jobs Fund, there were a number of deals negotiated by the previous government which are over a period of time. That fund is being kept to allow those deals to continue to proceed.</p>
<p>Let me say it one more time here in the House: we will not be spending additional monies under the Jobs Fund during the term of our government, or if we are lucky enough to be re-elected in the future, you will not see more monies being spent under the Jobs Fund than the deals previously negotiated by the previous government.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, actions speak louder than words, and I urge the member for Pictou West to keep an eye on exactly what is happening there. I would hope that the day may come where she will withdraw her accusation that we have set up a slush fund, or that we will continue to be using that fund. The fact is that the Irving deal, for example, is a 30-year deal, so that fund has to remain there in order to allow those funds to be able to continue.</p>
<p>Now, Mr. Speaker, I will get to the member for Chester-St. Margaret's in a minute, but I would ask her to be patient, and I would ask her to be attentive to my remarks, which is something I would say she has not done during this session very often.</p>
<p>The Invest Nova Scotia Fund - again, actions speak louder than words, and I would hope that the Opposition will watch carefully to see who the initial board members on this fund will be. I believe that will send a clear message of how serious our government is when it talks about wanting to allow the private sector to make these decisions and to allow this board to be independent. I will certainly be more than happy to have the Opposition judge us once they see exactly who will be sitting on the initial board.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I guess this addresses a concern raised by both Critics. I'm not sure if they had the opportunity to read Dr. Tom Traves' report, but the Invest Nova Scotia Board is exactly what he recommended. Now, I know that the Leader of the Official Opposition keeps saying that it should all go to NSBI. He is entitled to his opinion, but after Dr. Traves reviewed what was being done in jurisdictions around the world, in the United States and throughout Canada, he recommended not sending this work to NSBI. His comments were that what Nova Scotia Business Incorporated is doing is working. It is working as a brand, it is bringing success in its work to the Province of Nova Scotia, and it is helping to grow the economy. To further water down the work they are doing by adding to it, he felt, was not prudent.</p>
<p>At the end of the day, again, the Leader of the Official Opposition is entitled to his opinion, but it doesn't necessarily mean that Nova Scotians or Dr. Traves share his opinion. We listened to that independent report that was made and that clearly said this work has to be done outside of Nova Scotia Business Incorporated, which is what we have set up in this report.</p>
<p>I want to make this very clear, and unfortunately, I guess there appears to be some confusion here. The fund itself, which will have to be used for Invest Nova Scotia to be able to make decisions - as we are developing this, it's a question right now of how it's going to operate, or, I should say, how much funding it will need. Let me make it very clear: they will have a budget. They will have a pot of money to start off with.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, as has been pointed out - as was done under the Jobs Fund at times, as has been done before - when you try to set up a budget, you cannot necessarily predict how much money will be required, and there will be circumstances where it will come forward. The only time Treasury Board will have any involvement with the Invest Nova Scotia board will be if they need additional funds and they are requesting that. The only consideration there would be for Treasury Board is if there is enough money in the fiscal year to accommodate the request. It will not be to pass judgment.</p>
<p>We have already said that decisions made by Invest Nova Scotia, approved by their board, will be put up on the website for every Nova Scotian to see. That is a fundamental change from what the previous government did with the Jobs Fund. Under the Jobs Fund, they had an advisory board and they did not share with Nova Scotians what advice they received from that advisory board. What we now know is on several projects approved by the previous administration, their own advisory board told them no. Yet they went ahead and made the decision to approve it.</p>
<p>Now Cabinet has every right to do so, but accountability would have meant that the previous administration should have told Nova Scotians our advisory board said no and here are the reasons why, but we as an executive and as a government disagree, and here are the reasons why. That's accountability, that's transparency, and that's making sure that Nova Scotians know how their monies are being spent.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I listened to the comments being made by the member for Chester-St. Margaret's, and I know she is paying very close attention to what I say. What I can tell you is that I've spent 16 years in the House and I've had my share of disagreements with the governments of the day, and either of the Opposition Parties, but what I can say is this, when I had something critical to say about another member of this House, another party, another caucus - after I was done I sat down and I listened to what they had to say in return. I didn't run away. (Applause)</p></speech>
          <speech by="#sterling.belliveau">
            <from>HON. STERLING BELLIVEAU</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, on a point of order, the member opposite should know full well that he is not allowed to point out who is in this Chamber at any time. Thank you for your attention. (Interruption)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Point taken. Order, please.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><from>MR. SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, let me clarify. I believe I said that during my time in the House and when I spoke, I never ran away. Whether it's in this Chamber, whether it's in the Red Room during estimates, Law Amendments, or any other procedures, when I had something to say, when it was time for people to respond, I stayed in my place and I listened to what they had to say. But I do want to thank the member for Queens-Shelburne for helping us out for anyone watching who may not have been absolutely positive as to what I was referring to. I do appreciate his assistance in making it abundantly clear.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, obviously the previous administration failed to read the Auditor General's Report on the Jobs Fund. Someone asked me when the report was given, why was it given at this time? My response was that had that report been released prior to the October 8<sup>th</sup> election, there would be no members of the New Democratic Party in this House today.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, after the Auditor General's Report &#x2026;</p></speech>
          <speech by="#denise.peterson.rafuse">
            <from>HON. DENISE PETERSON-RAFUSE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, on a point of order. I am in this House and I have heard what the minster has said and I have a right, if I need to make a phone call or step out for a couple of minutes, I don't need to be criticized by the member and he knows that. I've been in this House for (Interruptions)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Order, please. Order, please.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Chester-St. Margaret's.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#denise.peterson.rafuse">
            <from>MS. PETERSON-RAFUSE</from>
            <p>The point of order is the fact that he is balancing on a very fine line, implying what he is implying in terms of whether I am in this House or not, and that is not allowed in the rules. That's a very fine line.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Thank you. Order, please.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Economic and Rural Development and Tourism.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><from>MR. SAMSON</from><p>You know, Mr. Speaker, that's kind of rich coming from the same member who you just corrected for being unparliamentary in mentioning someone's name here in the House, so now that member is correcting other members in the House, I do have to say it is a bit rich.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, when you look at the Auditor General's Report, a more scathing report you would not find. As far as accountability, as far as transparency, as far as basic principles of good governance, we're out the door. This is the Auditor General stating this - not the Liberal Party, not the Liberal Government, but the Auditor General. Yet when their interim Leader a few weeks ago got up at their convention and said to Nova Scotians "we get it", well today is further proof that the NDP still does not get it, they still did not get the message Nova Scotians sent on October 8<sup>th</sup>.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, we have listened to what Nova Scotians have had to say which is why, as I said earlier, we started with the Accountability in Economic Development Assistance&#xFFFD; Act which puts more transparency and allows Nova Scotians, wherever they live in the province, to see exactly how their tax dollars have been invested. The decisions made by the Invest Nova Scotia Board will be under that same test. Nova Scotians themselves will see exactly what is being done.</p>
<p>There is no Cabinet control; there is no Treasury Board control. The only issue that Treasury Board would ever be asked is, is there enough money in the fiscal year to be able to do any of the agreements that have been reached by the board if it surpasses the budget they have been provided with? It can't be simpler than that. In fact, Mr. Speaker, that's exactly what Dr. Traves recommended in his report to ensure accountability to Nova Scotians on that very issue.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, we are going to do everything to move this as quickly as possible, so it can be set up and we can have a board that is going to be appointed - as was indicated, the appointment process for the board moving forward after the initial board is that it will self-appoint, the same as Nova Scotia Business Incorporated has been doing since it was created by the Progressive Conservatives many years ago. So there is no surprise there.</p>
<p><i>&#xFFFD;</i>I know that the Leader of the NDP tried to say that somehow this was still going to be under the control of Cabinet and that this was something different than what was being done on other boards and agencies. Absolutely false - it is the same model that Nova Scotia Business Incorporated has been dealing with and I have to tell you that I have not heard before in this House where the New Democratic Party had an issue with that process. They spent four years in government, not once did I hear them have an issue - and I should point out that not once did they try to change that appointment process.</p>
<p>I will assume from that that it was something they agreed with, but then again I could be wrong because we're now seeing that all sorts of things that could have been done during their four years in government they didn't do but now they are all ideas that should have been done and they criticize the government of the day for not doing what they had every opportunity to do in four years.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, whether it's having a paving plan for rural roads being made available or whether it's saving Oak Island, those are all issues that could have been done under four years of NDP rule in this province, but somehow it was not a priority. Yet today it suddenly is.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#denise.peterson.rafuse">
            <from>HON. DENISE PETERSON-RAFUSE</from>
            <p>Oh, you are full of so much.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>I would ask the honourable member for Chester-St. Margaret's to apologize for that remark.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#denise.peterson.rafuse">
            <from>MS. DENISE PETERSON-RAFUSE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I will apologize, but can I make one little point?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>No.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><from>MR. SAMSON</from><p>Well, Mr. Speaker, that is twice you've corrected her. If I keep going, maybe we'll hit for the cycle today and get one more.</p>
<p>You know at the end of the day the fact is that Bill No. 67 addresses the message that Nova Scotians sent to us on October 8<sup>th</sup>. I do ask for the patience of the Opposition in judging us by our actions. To date, I believe that we have been very responsible on this issue, and Nova Scotians are telling us that exact message.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I am pleased that Bill No. 67 is moving forward. I do look forward to any comments that there will be at the Law Amendments stage, and seeing this bill passed through the House so that we can have the Invest Nova Scotia Board set up as quickly as possible, to start making investments and start making decisions by an independent private sector-led board that is going to represent cross-sections of Nova Scotian society from one end of the province to the next, with various amount of experience, whose mandate will be the same mandate of our administration - to grow our province, grow our economy, and make Nova Scotia a good place to work, a good place to live, and a good place to want to raise your children. Merci.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for second reading of Bill No. 67. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill be referred to the Committee on Law Amendments.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#michel.p.samson">
            <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 69.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 69 - House of Assembly Management Commission Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Minister of Internal Services.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#labi.kousoulis">
            <from>HON. LABI KOUSOULIS</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I move this bill for second reading.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Argyle-Barrington.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, just to speak to this one quickly. As members of the Management Committee, or the Audit Committee of the HAMC, the House of Assembly Management Commission, these were requested by the Auditor General's office and run through the audit committee.</p>
<p>Basically it is that the Auditor General has made a request that the third-party audit is no longer required for the books of the Speaker's Office. One that was duplication of services and was costing taxpayers some extra money on this one - again, it's just simple housekeeping items, and one that we can support. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>If I recognize the minister it will be to close the debate.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Internal Services.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#labi.kousoulis">
            <from>HON. LABI KOUSOULIS</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I move second reading of Bill No. 69.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for second reading of Bill No. 69. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill be referred to the Committee on Law Amendments.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#michel.p.samson">
            <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I move that you do now leave the Chair and the House resolve itself into a Committee of the Whole House on Bills.</p>
          </speech>
          <narrative>
            <p>5:32 p.m. The House resolved into a Committee of the Whole House on Bills with Deputy Speaker Ms. Margaret Miller in the Chair.</p>
          </narrative>
          <narrative>
            <p>5:51 p.m. Committee of the Whole House on Bills rose and the House reconvened. Mr. Speaker, Hon. Kevin Murphy, resumed the Chair.</p>
          </narrative>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The Chairman of the Committee of the Whole House on Bills reports:</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined"><from>THE CLERK</from><p>That the Committee of the Whole House on Bills has met and considered the following bills:</p>
<p><b>Bill No. 35 - Property Valuation Services Corporation Act.</b></p>
<p>and the chairman has been instructed to recommend these bills to the favourable consideration of the House without amendments.&#xFFFD;</p>
<p><b>Bill No. 43 - Direct Sellers' Regulation Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 45 - Apprenticeship and Trades Qualifications System Reform (2014) Act.</b></p>
<p>which was reported with certain amendments by the Committee on Law Amendments to the Committee of the Whole House, without further amendments, and the chairman has been instructed to recommend these bills to the favourable consideration of the House.</p>
<p><b>Bill No. 51 - Municipal Government Act.</b></p>
<p>which was reported without amendments by the Committee on Law Amendments but was a subject of certain further amendments in the Committee of the Whole House on Bills, and the chairman has been instructed to recommend this bill to the favourable consideration of the House.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Ordered that these bills be read a third time on a future day.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#michel.p.samson">
            <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Public Bills for Third Reading.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>PUBLIC BILLS FOR THIRD READING</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson">
          <from>HON. MICHAEL SAMSON</from>
          <p>I would ask you to please call Bill No. 32.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 32 - Forestry Agreement Statutes Repeal (2014) Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Minister of Natural Resources.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#zach.churchill"><from>HON. ZACH CHURCHILL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I move that Bill No. 32, the Forestry Agreement Statutes Repeal (2014) Act, be now read a third time and do pass. This bill is necessary because there is outdated legislation currently in the Province of Nova Scotia that relates to the forestry sector, and at a time with that sector going through such a period of transition, we need to make sure that our legislation is up to speed and reflective of best management practices and sustainability practices as well.</p>
<p>Under this bill there are four pieces of legislation that will be repealed: the Bowaters Mersey Agreement Act, which was brought in place in 1962; the Halifax Power and Pulp Company Limited Agreement Act, 1962; the Oxford Lease Purchase Act, 1960; and the Scott Maritimes Limited Agreement (1965) Act. Thank you very much.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for third reading of Bill No. 32. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill do pass. Ordered that the title be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bill be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#michel.p.samson">
            <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 33.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 33 - Fair Registration Practices Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Minister of Labour and Advanced Education.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#kelly.regan"><from>HON. KELLY REGAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I move that Bill No. 33, an Act to Amend Chapter 38 of the Acts of 2008, the Fair Registration Practices Act, be now read a third time and do pass. The Fair Registration Practices Act ensures that people who have trained outside the province receive a fair review of their qualifications. It's about giving trained professionals timely, clear, and understandable information about registration and licensing requirements and processes to help them find a job in their chosen profession.</p>
<p>Under the Act, regulatory - for some reason, I had trouble with the "tory" part, I don't know (Laughter) - regulatory authorities are responsible for setting the standards or certification for an occupation, assessing the qualifications of workers against this criterion and formally recognizing if a candidate meets the standards or requirements to work at that occupation.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, changes to the Act will make it clear that all regulatory bodies that oversee professions are subject to the Act and are required to do regular reporting. They will make sure that people who have trained outside the province continue to receive a fair review of their qualifications.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, these changes will also streamline the process, allowing more occupations to become recognized more quickly. The changes will help professionals who offer in-demand skills to be ready to work in Nova Scotia, and that benefits our communities, our businesses and our workforce. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for third reading of Bill No. 33. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill do pass. Ordered that the title be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bill be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#michel.p.samson">
            <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 55.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 55 - Halifax Regional Municipality Charter.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Minister of Municipal Affairs.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#mark.furey"><from>HON. MARK FUREY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I rise to call third reading on Bill No. 55, the Halifax Regional Municipality Charter. The bill itself contains five amendments to the Halifax Charter that deal specifically with administrative matters and the opportunity for Halifax Regional Municipality to advance development within HRM.</p>
<p>I move third reading of Bill No. 55.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for third reading of Bill No. 55. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill do pass. Ordered that the title be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bill be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#michel.p.samson">
            <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 57.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 57 - Cemetery and Funeral Services Act and the Embalmers and Funeral Directors Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Minister of Municipal Affairs.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#mark.furey"><from>HON. MARK FUREY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I move that Bill No. 57 be now read a third time. It captures a number of amendments that enhance consumer protection in the area of direct sellers.</p>
<p>I move third reading of Bill No. 57.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for third reading of Bill No. 57. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill do pass. Ordered that the title be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bill be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#michel.p.samson">
            <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Bill No. 58.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>Bill No. 58 - Oil Refineries and L.N.G. Plants Municipal Taxation Act.</heading>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Minister of Municipal Affairs.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#mark.furey"><from>HON. MARK FUREY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I move that Bill No. 58, the Oil Refineries and L.N.G. Plants Municipal Taxation Act be now read a third time. This bill deals specifically with the revert of the facility from a refinery to a storage facility for purposes of fair taxation.</p>
<p>I now move third reading of Bill No. 58.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for third reading of Bill No. 58. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>Ordered that this bill do pass. Ordered that the title be as read by the Clerk. Ordered that the bill be engrossed.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, that concludes the government's business for tonight. I want to thank all members of the House for their co-operation and debate. Tomorrow the House will sit from the hours of 2:00 p.m. until 8:00 p.m. Following the daily routine and Question Period, the government will be calling Committee of the Whole House on Bills and continuing with third reading of public bills and third reading of private and local bills.</p>
<p>With that, I move the House do now rise.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the House do now rise, to meet again tomorrow at 2:00 p.m.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
          <narrative>
            <p>The House rose at 6:01 p.m.</p>
          </narrative>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
