<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.lena.m.diab" showAs="Hon. Lena Diab"/>
        <TLCPerson id="5d38d43f-02b4-43b7-a6e7-e2ae6a93c4cf" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.brendan.o.maguire" showAs="MR. BRENDAN MAGUIRE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="181841b4-2d84-4daa-a250-fab4f2a44d08" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.lenore.zann" showAs="MS. LENORE ZANN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="c13007bc-6c67-4dc5-99ef-3dbf0e256bab" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.allan.rowe" showAs="MR. ALLAN ROWE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="e385351d-7663-4216-aafb-465399915774" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.patricia.arab" showAs="MS. PATRICIA ARAB"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8d336b40-1bad-4176-b6cc-e7e3d25ec01d" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.stephen.gough" showAs="MR. STEPHEN GOUGH"/>
        <TLCPerson id="64079cb8-9198-4f19-818a-597f1468ed7d" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.christopher.a.dentremont" showAs="Hon. Christopher D'Entremont"/>
        <TLCPerson id="bca364ea-bc08-403f-b7ec-38e16094c7f4" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.terry.farrell" showAs="MR. TERRY FARRELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="e6d39654-bcf3-4494-b7df-bbb286f0eeef" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.kelly.regan" showAs="Hon. Kelly Regan"/>
        <TLCPerson id="abb112ca-5557-436b-b603-9754cce09178" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.karla.macfarlane" showAs="Ms. Karla MacFarlane"/>
        <TLCPerson id="e2d2e894-19b6-444f-8f0d-28d6c40392db" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.denise.peterson.rafuse" showAs="HON. DENISE PETERSON-RAFUSE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8be1bf8c-0364-464e-b913-1a24edaca18e" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.joyce.treen" showAs="MS. JOYCE TREEN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="2ff2ba98-5c95-466a-adbc-991700eba459" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.gordon.l.wilson" showAs="MR. GORDON WILSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="6c29e100-c183-4cae-a6e0-92692d6dc9ee" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.randy.delorey" showAs="Hon. Randy Delorey"/>
        <TLCPerson id="a5abc84f-b08b-4dbd-83c9-7ec773c5bf25" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.mark.furey" showAs="HON. MARK FUREY"/>
        <TLCPerson id="d40ad9c0-f916-4a57-89ac-afb555ab1b1b" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.david.allan.wilson" showAs="Hon. David Wilson"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8df62f83-83e7-422c-b746-9d29a23dddb0" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.patrick.dunn" showAs="HON. PAT DUNN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="a6511e6d-7220-4ede-a4f2-3fe849660042" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.tim.houston" showAs="Mr. Tim Houston"/>
        <TLCPerson id="2962659a-3097-48db-83a4-9e643024b240" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.suzanne.lohnes.croft" showAs="MS. SUZANNE LOHNES-CROFT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="9aa9bcf8-0fe1-43ec-beba-6751551d5a29" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.john.a.lohr" showAs="MR. JOHN LOHR"/>
        <TLCPerson id="7c573d74-e55d-4dee-8ada-9979da97e50c" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.lloyd.hines" showAs="MR. LLOYD HINES"/>
        <TLCPerson id="3272398f-58c4-4a1b-9770-bcb2505bea5e" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.larry.harrison" showAs="MR. LARRY HARRISON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="8139ac33-7e56-4d7a-8bf1-c1574c3b47c4" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.joanne.bernard" showAs="HON. JOANNE BERNARD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="9083e65a-2973-487c-826c-5dbe3168699c" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.karen.casey" showAs="HON. KAREN CASEY"/>
        <TLCPerson id="83d0afae-ac80-4ef9-8fd5-7098acd3a137" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.bill.horne" showAs="MR. BILL HORNE"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MR. SPEAKER"/>
        <TLCRole id="clerk" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.clerk" showAs="THE CLERK"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 14 April 2014</docTitle>
      <docNumber>14-27</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2014-04-14">Monday, April 14, 2014</docDate>
      <docProponent>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docProponent>
      <legislature value="62">62nd General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="1">1st Session</session>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>Order, please. We'll begin the daily routine.</p>
      </speech>
      <papers>
        <heading>PRESENTING REPORTS OF COMMITTEES</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Justice.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91"><from>HON. LENA DIAB</from><p>Mr. Speaker, as Chairman of the Committee on Law Amendments, I am directed to report that the committee has met and considered the following bills:</p>
<p><b>Bill No. 32 - Forestry Agreement Statutes Repeal (2014) Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 33 - Fair Registration Practices Act.</b></p>
<p><b>Bill No. 34 - Notaries and Commissioners Act.</b></p>
<p>and the committee recommends all three bills to the favourable consideration of the House, each without amendment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>Ordered that these bills be referred to the Committee of the Whole House on Bills.</p>
        </speech>
      </papers>
      <papers>
        <heading>TABLING REPORTS, REGULATIONS AND OTHER PAPERS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Justice.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91">
          <from>HON. LENA DIAB</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, I have two to table this afternoon. First, amendments to the Nova Scotia Civil Procedure Rules from the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Nova Scotia, and second, amendments to the Nova Scotia Court of Appeal Rules.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The reports are tabled.</p>
        </speech>
      </papers>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Municipal Affairs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#a5abc84f-b08b-4dbd-83c9-7ec773c5bf25"><num title="1059">RESOLUTION NO. 1059</num><from>HON. MARK FUREY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas 911 call takers play a critical role in protecting the health, safety, and property of Nova Scotians; and</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotia's well-trained 911 call takers handle more than 240,000 calls per year; and</p>
<p>Whereas April 13<sup>th</sup> to April 19<sup>th</sup> is National Public Safety Telecommunications Week;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House offer a well-deserved thank you to the hundreds of 911 call takers who work tirelessly to preserve the health and safety of Nova Scotians.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Community Services.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#8139ac33-7e56-4d7a-8bf1-c1574c3b47c4"><num title="1060">RESOLUTION NO. 1060</num><from>HON. JOANNE BERNARD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas sexual assault is a heartbreaking, violent crime that affects many individuals and families; and</p>
<p>Whereas Irene Smith and the team at Avalon Sexual Assault Centre have been working for 19 years to help survivors and their families and to increase awareness, education, and prevention of sexual violence; and</p>
<p>Whereas no one can eliminate sexual violence on their own, yet with leadership and commitment we can work together to respond to sexual violence and improve our response to the needs of survivors;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly do hereby recognize Irene Smith on her retirement, and acknowledge the work of Avalon and all the community-based organizations and caring professionals who have tirelessly and passionately worked to address this issue - for their strength, courage, and commitment to creating a world where we can all live safely from sexual violence.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>INTRODUCTION OF BILLS</heading>
        <other>
          <p>
            <b> Bill No. 51 - Entitled an Act to Amend Chapter 18 of the Acts of 1998. The Municipal Government Act. (Hon. Mark Furey)</b>
          </p>
        </other>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>Ordered that this bill be read a second time on a future day.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Pictou Centre.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#8df62f83-83e7-422c-b746-9d29a23dddb0"><num title="1061">RESOLUTION NO. 1061</num><from>HON. PAT DUNN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on March 25, 2014, two New Glasgow residents, Seth Rozee and Jeff Davis, flew to Toronto to tape their business pitch for season nine of the CBC program Dragon's Den; and</p>
<p>Whereas a third partner, Jonah Brotman of Toronto, joined them as they faced and presented their business plan to a panel of venture capitalists known as the dragons; and</p>
<p>Whereas the three entrepreneurs remained cool under pressure and proceeded to deliver a stellar performance;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Seth, Jeff, and Jonah for their excellent business pitch, seeking a large investment for their business, StashBelt, which produces a unique travel security accessory while also creating sustainable jobs in Kenya.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Dartmouth South.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#c13007bc-6c67-4dc5-99ef-3dbf0e256bab"><num title="1062">RESOLUTION NO. 1062</num><from>MR. ALLAN ROWE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas in 1965 the first Dartmouth Boys Pipe Band was formed by Gordon Sutherland and has since grown into the Dartmouth &amp; District Pipe Band and school; and</p>
<p>Whereas since its inception the Dartmouth &amp; District Pipe Band school has trained hundreds of bagpipers and drummers, some of whom continue to perform and compete locally and others across the world, promoting Celtic traditions, music, and culture; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Dartmouth &amp; District Pipe Band practises throughout the warmer months of the year in outdoor spaces like the Dartmouth Common, where the band participated in Clean Nova Scotia's Great Nova Scotia Pick-Me-Up event this past Saturday, April 12<sup>th</sup>, to honour April as Earth Month;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly recognize the valuable and far-reaching community contributions of the Dartmouth &amp; District Pipe Band and their commitment to promoting Celtic heritage in Nova Scotia and abroad.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Colchester-Musquodoboit Valley.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#3272398f-58c4-4a1b-9770-bcb2505bea5e"><num title="1063">RESOLUTION NO. 1063</num><from>MR. LARRY HARRISON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Colchester Historical Society's mandate is to preserve and exhibit the social, cultural, and natural history of our county for present and future generations; and</p>
<p>Whereas the society is working to raise $800,000 to acquire specialized equipment required to display their new Life in the Heart of Nova Scotia exhibition at the Colchester Historeum, which will tell the complete story of our Colchester history; and</p>
<p>Whereas thanks to the contribution of many generous residents, along with the $50,000 donation from the federal government, presented by Member of Parliament Scott Armstrong, the Colchester Historical Society is approximately halfway to their fundraising target and hopes to complete their monumental task within the next 12 months;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly wish the Colchester Historical Society the best of luck with their continuing fundraising efforts and in building the Life in the Heart of Nova Scotia.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Chester-St. Margaret's.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#e2d2e894-19b6-444f-8f0d-28d6c40392db"><num title="1064">RESOLUTION NO. 1064</num><from>HON. DENISE PETERSON-RAFUSE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Girls Under-18 Curling team out of Chester, Nova Scotia, are this year's provincial champions and represented Nova Scotia at the Atlantic championships in Oromocto, New Brunswick, on April 3<sup>rd</sup> of this year; and</p>
<p>Whereas these girls are not only competing for the Atlantic championships but are also hoping for a spot on the Canada Winter Games team; and</p>
<p>Whereas the team members are Taylour Stevens, Rachel Crouse, Megan Brown, and Cassie Cocks, and have many significant accomplishments together over the past three years of being together as a team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the Nova Scotia Legislature congratulate the Chester Girls Under-18 Curling team for their significant accomplishments, and wish them the best of luck in their upcoming tournaments.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Halifax Atlantic.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#5d38d43f-02b4-43b7-a6e7-e2ae6a93c4cf"><num title="1065">RESOLUTION NO. 1065</num><from>MR. BRENDAN MAGUIRE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the CBC is part of what makes us Canadian, reaching us from coast to coast to coast and promoting our country's values, history, and heritage; and</p>
<p>Whereas our Prime Minister has decided to gut the CBC with massive cuts and put over 600 of our fellow Canadians, friends, and family members out on the street without the means to support themselves; and</p>
<p>Whereas each and every member of this House should recognize the hard work of all those CBC employees and the service they provide to our amazing country;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House acknowledge the importance of this issue and encourage their constituents to express their outrage at the federal government's attack on our culture and heritage by getting out during the next federal election and expressing their democratic given right to vote.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The notice is tabled.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Pictou West.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#abb112ca-5557-436b-b603-9754cce09178"><num title="1066">RESOLUTION NO. 1066</num><from>MS. KARLA MACFARLANE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Mrs. Elsie MacDonald, of Pictou, Nova Scotia, upon retirement from her paid job, decided to fill her days with volunteer work; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mrs. MacDonald has continued to faithfully serve the Pictou Food Bank for over 23 years, recently stepping down as coordinator but remaining as treasurer; and</p>
<p>Whereas Mrs. MacDonald and the Pictou Food Bank provide an invaluable service to families from all of Pictou West, three days per week, all year long;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate and thank Mrs. Elsie MacDonald for her many years of volunteering with the Pictou Food Bank, and wish her continued good health and happiness.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Truro-Bible Hill-Millbrook-Salmon River.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#181841b4-2d84-4daa-a250-fab4f2a44d08"><num title="1067">RESOLUTION NO. 1067</num><from>MS. LENORE ZANN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Millbrook's Legends Gaming Centre in Truro has successfully raised $28,537 for local charities in the past year; and</p>
<p>Whereas charity recipients are chosen by application and all money is being donated back to the local communities through Legends' 50/50 draw; and</p>
<p>Whereas Legends Gaming Centre will continue to donate money back into local communities which benefit local organizations;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the Nova Scotia Legislature congratulate Millbrook's Legends Gaming Centre on their strong community support and wish it continued success.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Lunenburg.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#2962659a-3097-48db-83a4-9e643024b240"><num title="1068">RESOLUTION NO. 1068</num><from>MS. SUZANNE LOHNES-CROFT</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Bayview Community School, my school, has a reputation as a school that fosters extracurricular activities; and</p>
<p>Whereas the school's basketball teams, through hard work by the players and coaches with the support of parents, have long been among the most competitive in Lunenburg County; and</p>
<p>Whereas both the junior high boys and girls teams won their regional and district championships;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Bayview Bobcats junior high basketball teams on their hard work and tremendous achievements in representing the school and the county.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Kings North.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#9aa9bcf8-0fe1-43ec-beba-6751551d5a29"><num title="1069">RESOLUTION NO. 1069</num><from>MR. JOHN LOHR</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on February 18<sup>th</sup>, the Annapolis Valley Chamber of Commerce handed out the 2014 Valley's Best awards; and</p>
<p>Whereas Kings County Home Hardware in Kentville was named Best Hardware Store; and</p>
<p>Whereas Kings County Home Hardware is well known for its old-fashioned customer service;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Kings County Home Hardware for being awarded Annapolis Valley Chamber of Commerce Valley's Best Hardware Store for 2014.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Cole Harbour-Eastern Passage</p></speech>
        <speech by="#8be1bf8c-0364-464e-b913-1a24edaca18e"><num title="1070">RESOLUTION NO. 1070</num><from>MS. JOYCE TREEN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Seaside Elementary School in Eastern Passage conducts annual musicals for their community, with this year's performance being <i>Anne of Green Gables</i>; and</p>
<p>Whereas these musicals run over a two-day period and are attended by hundreds of people within the community; and</p>
<p>Whereas there are numerous dedicated volunteers who contribute countless hours to ensure these musicals are a great success;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Seaside Elementary School for their past successful musicals, and wish them the very best with <i>Anne of Green Gables</i>.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Pictou Centre.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#8df62f83-83e7-422c-b746-9d29a23dddb0"><num title="1071">RESOLUTION NO. 1071</num><from>HON. PAT DUNN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas New Glasgow native Dr. Kent MacDonald was recently appointed by the St. F.X. Board of Governors as the university's 18<sup>th</sup> president and vice-chancellor; and</p>
<p>Whereas Dr. Kent MacDonald is an alumnus of St. F.X., where he received a Master's Degree in Education, a Bachelor of Science, and went on to complete his doctorate at the University of Pennsylvania, as well as an MBA from the University of Ottawa; and</p>
<p>Whereas with his passion for higher education and for his alma mater, as well as extensive experience and credentials, Dr. MacDonald is certainly the person to lead St. F.X. into the future;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate Dr. Kent MacDonald on the occasion of the great honour of being named the 18<sup>th</sup> president and vice-chancellor of St. Francis Xavier University, and wish him well as he takes on this new challenge.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Sackville-Beaver Bank.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#8d336b40-1bad-4176-b6cc-e7e3d25ec01d"><num title="1072">RESOLUTION NO. 1072</num><from>MR. STEPHEN GOUGH</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past four years Sackville Heights Elementary School, in Middle Sackville, has been offering the breakfast program, and the greatest challenge has been to secure dedicated volunteers to give 45 minutes of their time; and</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers Frances Hammond, Wendy Spears, Margaret Salter, Valerie Gillis, Mary Banks, Ferne Joudrey, Avila Cox, Pat Monahan, Jason Arnold, Tom Miller, Cindy Hunter, and Krista Beaver, give of their time to make sure the breakfast food items, such as bagels, toast, cereal, milk, juice, fresh fruit, and yogurt, in different combinations, are ready for the 7:45 a.m. rush on Mondays, Wednesdays, and Fridays and with an average of 50 students served each day of the program, preparation, serving, and cleanup can be challenging; and</p>
<p>Whereas a nutritious breakfast is key to a successful day, academically and socially, without the dedication of these individuals the breakfast program at Sackville Heights Elementary could not be offered;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly recognize these volunteers for their dedication and support to the Sackville Heights Elementary School Breakfast Program.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Colchester-Musquodoboit Valley.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#3272398f-58c4-4a1b-9770-bcb2505bea5e"><num title="1073">RESOLUTION NO. 1073</num><from>MR. LARRY HARRISON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Truro Harness Horse Owners Association honoured the 2013 harness racing achievement at their annual banquet and awards ceremony held on March 29<sup>th</sup> at the Truro Horsemen's Club; and</p>
<p>Whereas with a record of 45 wins in 160 races in 2013, Ryan Ellis of Brookfield was named the Driver of the Year with more than 100 starts, for the third consecutive year; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ryan is a relative newcomer to harness racing, having received his licence in 2007, his reputation as a strong competitor is further demonstrated by the fact that he wins more than anyone else, despite the fact that he often misses races while working as a pilot for Air Canada Jazz;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ryan Ellis for being named Driver of the Year by the Truro Harness Horse Owners Association for three straight years, and wish him the best of luck in the future.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Clare-Digby.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#2ff2ba98-5c95-466a-adbc-991700eba459"><num title="1074">RESOLUTION NO. 1074</num><from>MR. GORDON WILSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the <i>Nova Star</i> ferry, Nova Scotia's newest transportation link between this province and the United States, will make its first North American port of call to Yarmouth tomorrow; and</p>
<p>Whereas a month from now, on May 15<sup>th</sup>, the <i>Nova Star</i>, equipped with its multiple dining options, onboard casino, live entertainment and more, will begin accepting passengers, beginning a new era of ferry transportation between New England and Nova Scotia; and</p>
<p>Whereas the return of the ferry service to southern Nova Scotia is a great economic boost and benefit to not just the surrounding area but the Province of Nova Scotia as a whole, one that this government campaigned hard for and has delivered on;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly welcome and celebrate the arrival of the <i>Nova Star</i> ferry along with the great benefits it brings to this province.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Kings North.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#9aa9bcf8-0fe1-43ec-beba-6751551d5a29"><num title="1075">RESOLUTION NO. 1075</num><from>MR. JOHN LOHR</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on February 18<sup>th</sup> the Annapolis Valley Chamber of Commerce handed out the 2014 Valley's Best awards; and</p>
<p>Whereas Foote's Farm Market was awarded as Best Farm Market; and</p>
<p>Whereas Foote's Farm Market has long been known for its good quality and great prices for fish, fruit, vegetables and much more;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Foote's Farm Market for being awarded Annapolis Valley Chamber of Commerce Valley's Best Farm Market for 2014.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Waverley-Fall River-Beaver Bank.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#83d0afae-ac80-4ef9-8fd5-7098acd3a137"><num title="1076">RESOLUTION NO. 1076</num><from>MR. BILL HORNE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Acadia University hosts the Acadia Global Brigades, a chapter of the world's largest student-led global health and sustainable development organization; and</p>
<p>Whereas upon hearing of this program, Danielle Wisen, a 2013 graduate of Lockview High School in Fall River in her first year of studies at Acadia, knew she wanted to be part of this program, now says she expects to learn much more than she will be able to give - the brigade will be contributing to sustainable change by helping construct eco stoves, lanterns, water storage units, showers, concrete floors as well as helping set up local clinics to diagnose and treat the patients; and</p>
<p>Whereas Danielle has always been involved in a variety of volunteer activities and finds that she learns a great deal from volunteerism;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly thank Danielle for her past and continuing volunteer efforts, and appreciate the contributions of our youth volunteers.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Guysborough-Eastern Shore-Tracadie.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#7c573d74-e55d-4dee-8ada-9979da97e50c"><num title="1077">RESOLUTION NO. 1077</num><from>MR. LLOYD HINES</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Blair Borden of Sunnyville completed a new Opportunities to Work program at Guysborough County Adult Learning Association; and</p>
<p>Whereas all participants completed in-depth assessments under a current skill level and a plan was developed for each individual, they were able to work at their own pace and covered material that contributed to advancement of their individual learning and a return to work plan; and</p>
<p>Whereas through hard work and commitment, Blair was able to improve his employability skills while gaining work experience through volunteer placements throughout the community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly recognize and congratulate Blair on successfully completing the NOW Program, and express our support for the importance of adult learning and the differences it can make in people's lives.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Fairview-Clayton Park.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#e385351d-7663-4216-aafb-465399915774"><num title="1078">RESOLUTION NO. 1078</num><from>MS. PATRICIA ARAB</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Dunbrack Soccer Club was first established in 1993 to serve primarily the residents of Fairview, Clayton Park, Rockingham, and other west-side areas of Halifax; and</p>
<p>Whereas Dunbrack Soccer Club has started a new initiative, entitled Everyone Plays; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Everyone Plays initiative is designed to allow all children the chance to play soccer, regardless of economic status or ability;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Dunbrack Soccer Club for their inclusive program, and commend the club on promoting equality and community unity.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Community Services.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#8139ac33-7e56-4d7a-8bf1-c1574c3b47c4"><num title="1079">RESOLUTION NO. 1079</num><from>HON. JOANNE BERNARD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas 23 members of the Human Rights Interact Club from Dartmouth High School travelled to the Dominican Republic during their recent March break; and</p>
<p>Whereas during their visit the students assisted with outreach activities and supplied school supplies, children's clothing, and medical supplies for residents of remote villages; and</p>
<p>Whereas students stayed with local families during their trip and saw a world quite apart from their own, giving them the experience of a lifetime;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating members of the Human Rights Interact Club and teachers Heather Hughes and Heather Kent on their conscientious efforts, and wish them well in all their future humanitarian endeavours.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>The honourable Minister of Education.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#9083e65a-2973-487c-826c-5dbe3168699c"><num title="1080">RESOLUTION NO. 1080</num><from>HON. KAREN CASEY</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Cobequid Veterans Memorial Park in Bass River, Colchester North, was named the top Garden of Remembrance in Canada by the national Communities in Bloom program at a ceremony in Ottawa; and</p>
<p>Whereas the park, a vision of Dr. Karen Ewing, was established in 2008 by a committee with financial support of government and community-raised funds to remember and honour Canadian military who gave their lives, who have served or are serving, and their families; and</p>
<p>Whereas the park features eight themed granite stones bearing the names of military personnel, three themed gardens, benches to honour family members who support those who serve, a monument to animals who have served, and red maples, one planted for each Nova Scotian solider who was killed in Afghanistan;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Cobequid Veterans Memorial Park for being named the top Garden of Remembrance in Canada, for receiving the $1,500 which accompanies the award, for keeping us aware of the selfless contributions that our military have made, and for providing a beautiful spot to relax and reflect.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT BUSINESS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#bca364ea-bc08-403f-b7ec-38e16094c7f4">
          <from>MR. TERRY FARRELL</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Government Motions.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT MOTIONS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#bca364ea-bc08-403f-b7ec-38e16094c7f4">
          <from>MR. TERRY FARRELL</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, I move that you do now leave the Chair and the House resolve itself into a Committee of the Whole on Supply unto Her Majesty.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The motion carried.</p>
<p>We'll now recess the House for one minute while we set up for Committee of the Whole House on Supply.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>4:40 p.m. The House resolved itself into a CWH on Supply with Deputy Speaker Ms. Margaret Miller in the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <narrative>
          <p>8:45 p.m. CWH on Supply rose and the House reconvened with Deputy Speaker Ms. Margaret Miller in the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The Chairman of the Committee of the Whole House on Supply reports:</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined">
          <from>THE CLERK</from>
          <p>That the committee has met and made progress and begs leave to sit again.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>The honourable Deputy Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#bca364ea-bc08-403f-b7ec-38e16094c7f4"><from>MR. TERRY FARRELL</from><p>Madam Speaker, I move that the hours for tomorrow would be from 2:00 p.m. to 10:00 p.m. The order of business will be Government Motions and Committee of the Whole House on Supply unto Her Majesty. If time permits we will call second reading of Bill Nos. 35, 40, 43, 44, 45, and 49.</p>
<p>I move that the House do now rise to meet again from 2:00 p.m. to 10:00 p.m. tomorrow.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is that the House now rise to meet again tomorrow at the hour of 2:00 p.m.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>We stand adjourned until 2:00 p.m. tomorrow.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>The House rose at 8:46 p.m.</p>
        </narrative>
      </debateSection>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION UNDER RULE 32(3)</heading>
        <speech by="#abb112ca-5557-436b-b603-9754cce09178"><num title="1081">RESOLUTION NO. 1081</num><from>Ms. Karla MacFarlane</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas concerned parents of students at River John Consolidated and Highland Middle School lobbied Chignecto Regional School Board to keep their respective schools open; and</p>
<p>Whereas the parents have the support of community members and many local politicians; and</p>
<p>Whereas the parents and community members have many valid points for keeping their local schools open, including classroom size, the benefits for children to remain in their home communities, and the cost to retrofit a school to accommodate the displaced students;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly acknowledge the efforts of the parents and community members in trying to keep their schools open and the students in their home communities.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#a6511e6d-7220-4ede-a4f2-3fe849660042"><num title="1082">RESOLUTION NO. 1082</num><from>Mr. Tim Houston</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Douglas Lloy, a lawyer with Nova Scotia Legal Aid, recently received word from the province's Auditor General that he will be awarded the prestigious appointment to Queen's Council; and</p>
<p>Whereas this appointment will be made at the Lieutenant Governor's home later this Spring; and</p>
<p>Whereas this designation is a reflection of his 23-year long career;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Douglas Lloy on receiving his QC and wish him continued success in his career.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#a6511e6d-7220-4ede-a4f2-3fe849660042"><num title="1083">RESOLUTION NO. 1083</num><from>Mr. Tim Houston</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Pictou County Crime Prevention and Pictou County Crime Stoppers came together to show how these two volunteer groups combine in a common cause; and</p>
<p>Whereas both of these groups offer programs that are designed to meet the needs of seniors in their homes and community to keep them safe; and</p>
<p>Whereas this meeting informed seniors about the use of the tipster number so they can report a crime while remaining anonymous;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly thank the Pictou County Crime Prevention and Pictou County Crime Stoppers for making our seniors safer and more comfortable in their homes.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#d40ad9c0-f916-4a57-89ac-afb555ab1b1b"><num title="1084">RESOLUTION NO. 1084</num><from>Hon. David Wilson</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Ian Greedy from Lower Sackville is in his fourth year of Business Administration studies at Cape Breton University; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ian plays soccer for the Cape Breton University Capers and was presented with the Atlantic University Sport 2013 Most Valuable Player award; and</p>
<p>Whereas Ian was one of two soccer players from Cape Breton University who have been named Canadian Interuniversity Sport first-team all-stars for 2013;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that this Nova Scotia Legislature congratulate Lower Sackville's Ian Greedy on being recognized for his accomplishments in soccer by both Atlantic University Sport and Canadian Interuniversity Sport and wish him future success.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#6c29e100-c183-4cae-a6e0-92692d6dc9ee"><num title="1085">RESOLUTION NO. 1085</num><from>Hon. Randy Delorey</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas the Antigonish Mental Health and Awareness Support Group celebrated their first anniversary on March 7, 2014; and</p>
<p>Whereas the group was started to increase awareness and acceptance of the many ways mental health can affect individuals and their families; and</p>
<p>Whereas the group meets once a month, gathering to provide support, assistance, and encouragement to those who are affected by this illness;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Antigonish Mental Health and Awareness Support Group for celebrating their first year of coming together.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#e6d39654-bcf3-4494-b7df-bbb286f0eeef"><num title="1086">RESOLUTION NO. 1086</num><from>Hon. Kelly Regan</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Project ARC, a troupe of talented young students aged 12 - 18, has created an inspiring musical by youth and for youth about human rights and responsibilities; and</p>
<p>Whereas Project ABC uses music, drama, and dance to educate its audiences about the Universal Declaration of Human Rights and has presented its show in numerous schools in Nova Scotia, asking only that the schools donate directly to partner charities chosen by Project ARC; and</p>
<p>Whereas Project ARC stands for Action, Responsibility and Choice, illuminating the need for responsible, empathetic choice in an increasingly insecure world;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the members of Project ARC on their innovative project.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#8d336b40-1bad-4176-b6cc-e7e3d25ec01d"><num title="1087">RESOLUTION NO. 1087</num><from>Mr. Stephen Gough</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past four years Sackville Heights Elementary School in Middle Sackville has been offering the Breakfast Program, and the greatest challenge has been to secure dedicated volunteers to give 45 minutes of their time; and</p>
<p>Whereas Middle Sackville resident Marg Salter, one of five ladies from Sackville United Baptist Church, has risen early on Wednesdays to prepare and serve breakfast to any child who wants to attend the Breakfast Program where each morning an average of 50 students are served varying combinations of toast, bagels, juice, fresh fruit, cheese and yogurt; and</p>
<p>Whereas a nutritious breakfast is key to a successful day academically and socially, and without the dedication of volunteers like Ms. Salter, the Breakfast Program at Sackville Heights Elementary could not be offered;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly recognize Marg Salter for her dedication and support to the Sackville Heights Elementary Breakfast Program.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#8d336b40-1bad-4176-b6cc-e7e3d25ec01d"><num title="1088">RESOLUTION NO. 1088</num><from>Mr. Stephen Gough</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past four years Sackville Heights Elementary School in Middle Sackville has been offering the Breakfast Program, and the greatest challenge has been to secure dedicated volunteers to give 45 minutes of their time; and</p>
<p>Whereas Avila Cox, a parent of three boys attending SHES, has risen early on Monday to prepare and serve breakfast to any child who wants to attend to prepare and serve breakfast to any child who wants to attend the Breakfast Program where each morning an average of 50 students are served varying combinations of toast, bagels, juice, fresh fruit, cheese and yogurt; and</p>
<p>Whereas a nutritious breakfast is key to a successful day academically and socially, and without the dedication of volunteers like Ms. Cox, the Breakfast Program at Sackville Heights Elementary could not be offered;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly recognize Avila Cox for her dedication and support to the Sackville Heights Elementary Breakfast Program.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#8d336b40-1bad-4176-b6cc-e7e3d25ec01d"><num title="1089">RESOLUTION NO. 1089</num><from>Mr. Stephen Gough</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past four years Sackville Heights Elementary School in Middle Sackville has been offering the Breakfast Program, and the greatest challenge has been to secure dedicated volunteers to give 45 minutes of their time; and</p>
<p>Whereas Middle Sackville resident Wendy Spears, one of five ladies from Sackville United Baptist Church, has risen early on Fridays to prepare and serve breakfast to any child who wants to attend the Breakfast Program where each morning an average of 50 students are served varying combinations of toast, bagels, juice, fresh fruit, cheese and yogurt; and</p>
<p>Whereas a nutritious breakfast is key to a successful day academically and socially, and without the dedication of volunteers like Ms. Spears, the Breakfast Program at Sackville Heights Elementary could not be offered;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly recognize Wendy Spears for her dedication and support to the Sackville Heights Elementary Breakfast Program.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#8d336b40-1bad-4176-b6cc-e7e3d25ec01d"><num title="1090">RESOLUTION NO. 1090</num><from>Mr. Stephen Gough</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past four years Sackville Heights Elementary School in Middle Sackville has been offering the Breakfast Program, and the greatest challenge has been to secure dedicated volunteers to give 45 minutes of their time; and</p>
<p>Whereas Tom Miller, a parent of children attending Sackville Heights Elementary School, has risen early on Mondays to prepare and serve breakfast to any child who wants to attend the Breakfast Program where each morning an average of 50 students are served varying combinations of toast, bagels, juice, fresh fruit, cheese and yogurt; and</p>
<p>Whereas a nutritious breakfast is key to a successful day academically and socially, and without the dedication of volunteers like Mr. Miller, the Breakfast Program at Sackville Heights Elementary could not be offered;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that members of this House of Assembly recognize Tom Miller for his dedication and support to the Sackville Heights Elementary Breakfast Program.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#8d336b40-1bad-4176-b6cc-e7e3d25ec01d"><num title="1091">RESOLUTION NO. 1091</num><from>Mr. Stephen Gough</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past four years Sackville Heights Elementary School in Middle Sackville has been offering the Breakfast Program, and the greatest challenge has been to secure dedicated volunteers to give 45 minutes of their time; and</p>
<p>Whereas Pat Monahan has risen early on Fridays to prepare and serve breakfast to any child who wants to attend the Breakfast Program where each morning an average of 50 students are served varying combinations of toast, bagels, juice, fresh fruit, cheese and yogurt; and</p>
<p>Whereas a nutritious breakfast is key to a successful day academically and socially, and without the dedication of volunteers like Mr. Monahan, the Breakfast Program at Sackville Heights Elementary could not be offered;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly recognize Pat Monahan for his dedication and support to the Sackville Heights Elementary Breakfast Program.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#8d336b40-1bad-4176-b6cc-e7e3d25ec01d"><num title="1092">RESOLUTION NO. 1092</num><from>Mr. Stephen Gough</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past four years Sackville Heights Elementary School in Middle Sackville has been offering the Breakfast Program, and the greatest challenge has been to secure dedicated volunteers to give 45 minutes of their time; and</p>
<p>Whereas Krista Beaver, Cafeteria Manager at Sackville Heights Elementary School, gives of her time to make sure the breakfast food items are available for Mondays, Wednesdays and Fridays; and with an average of 50 students served each day of the program, purchasing the bread, bagels, juice, fresh fruit, cheese and yogurt, to ensure there is enough but not too much on hand requires careful planning;</p>
<p>Whereas a nutritious breakfast is key to a successful day academically and socially, and without the dedication of volunteers like Ms. Beaver, the Breakfast Program at Sackville Heights Elementary could not be offered;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly recognize Krista Beaver for her dedication and support to the Sackville Heights Elementary Breakfast Program.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#8d336b40-1bad-4176-b6cc-e7e3d25ec01d"><num title="1093">RESOLUTION NO. 1093</num><from>Mr. Stephen Gough</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past four years Sackville Heights Elementary School in Middle Sackville has been offering the Breakfast Program, and the greatest challenge has been to secure dedicated volunteers to give 45 minutes of their time; and</p>
<p>Whereas Sackville resident Mary Banks, one of five ladies from Sackville United Baptist Church, has risen early on Mondays to prepare and serve breakfast to any child who wants to attend the Breakfast Program, where each morning an average of 50 students are served varying combinations of toast, bagels, juice, fresh fruit, cheese and yogurt; and</p>
<p>Whereas a nutritious breakfast is key to a successful day academically and socially, and without the dedication of volunteers like Ms. Banks, the Breakfast Program at Sackville Heights Elementary could not be offered;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly recognize Mary Banks for her dedication and support to the Sackville Heights Elementary Breakfast Program.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#8d336b40-1bad-4176-b6cc-e7e3d25ec01d"><num title="1094">RESOLUTION NO. 1094</num><from>Mr. Stephen Gough</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past four years Sackville Heights Elementary School in Middle Sackville has been offering the Breakfast Program, and the greatest challenge has been to secure dedicated volunteers to give 45 minutes of their time; and</p>
<p>Whereas Sackville resident Valerie Gillis, one of five ladies from Sackville United Baptist Church, has risen early on Wednesdays to prepare and serve breakfast to any child who wants to attend the Breakfast Program, where each morning an average of 50 students are served varying combinations of toast, bagels, juice, fresh fruit, cheese and yogurt; and</p>
<p>Whereas a nutritious breakfast is key to a successful day academically and socially, and without the dedication of volunteers like Ms. Gillis, the Breakfast Program at Sackville Heights Elementary could not be offered;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly recognize Valerie Gillis for her dedication and support to the Sackville Heights Elementary Breakfast Program.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#8d336b40-1bad-4176-b6cc-e7e3d25ec01d"><num title="1095">RESOLUTION NO. 1095</num><from>Mr. Stephen Gough</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past four years Sackville Heights Elementary School in Middle Sackville has been offering the Breakfast Program, and the greatest challenge has been to secure dedicated volunteers to give 45 minutes of their time; and</p>
<p>Whereas Cindy Hunter, Custodian at Sackville Heights Elementary School, gives of her time on Mondays, Wednesdays and Fridays to make sure the table and chairs are set up for the Breakfast Program and everything is neat and tidy when breakfast is over; with an average of 50 students served each day of the program, cleanup is no small task; and</p>
<p>Whereas a nutritious breakfast is key to a successful day academically and socially, and without the dedication of volunteers like Ms. Hunter, the Breakfast Program at Sackville Heights Elementary could not be offered;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly recognize Cindy Hunter for her dedication and support to the Sackville Heights Elementary Breakfast Program.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#8d336b40-1bad-4176-b6cc-e7e3d25ec01d"><num title="1096">RESOLUTION NO. 1096</num><from>Mr. Stephen Gough</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas for the past four years Sackville Heights Elementary School in Middle Sackville has been offering the Breakfast Program, and the greatest challenge has been to secure dedicated volunteers to give 45 minutes of their time; and</p>
<p>Whereas Jason Arnold, a parent with children attending Sackville Heights Elementary School, has risen early on Monday to prepare and serve breakfast to any child who wants to attend the Breakfast Program, where each morning an average of 50 students are served varying combinations of toast, bagels, juice, fresh fruit, cheese and yogurt;</p>
<p>Whereas a nutritious breakfast is key to a successful day academically and socially, and without the dedication of volunteers like Mr. Arnold, the Breakfast Program at Sackville Heights Elementary could not be offered;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that the members of this House of Assembly recognize Jason Arnold for his dedication and support to the Sackville Heights Elementary Breakfast Program.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#64079cb8-9198-4f19-818a-597f1468ed7d"><num title="1097">RESOLUTION NO. 1097</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers are the cornerstone of Nova Scotia's communities who generously give their time and talents while expecting nothing in return; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Wednesday April 16<sup>th</sup>, the Royal Canadian Legion in Clark's Harbour will host the annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Barrington and Town of Clark's Harbour; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the volunteers to be honoured is Amelie Daykin, nominated by the Balmoral Rebekah Lodge #39 for her devotion of time and her many contributions to her community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Amelie Daykin on being honoured by the Municipality of Barrington and thank her for her dedication to her community.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#64079cb8-9198-4f19-818a-597f1468ed7d"><num title="1098">RESOLUTION NO. 1098</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers are the cornerstone of Nova Scotia's communities who generously give their time and talents while expecting nothing in return; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Wednesday April 16<sup>th</sup>, the Royal Canadian Legion in Clark's Harbour will host the annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Barrington and Town of Clark's Harbour; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the volunteers to be honoured is Betty Stewart, nominated by the Barrington and Area Lions Club for her devotion of time and her many contributions to her community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Betty Stewart on being honoured by the Municipality of Barrington and thank her for her dedication to her community.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#64079cb8-9198-4f19-818a-597f1468ed7d"><num title="1099">RESOLUTION NO. 1099</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers are the cornerstone of Nova Scotia's communities who generously give their time and talents while expecting nothing in return; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Wednesday April 16<sup>th</sup>, the Royal Canadian Legion in Clark's Harbour will host the annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Barrington and Town of Clark's Harbour; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the volunteers to be honoured is Cindy Ross, nominated by the Town of Clark's Harbour for her devotion of time and contributions to her community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Cindy Ross on being honoured by the Town of Clark's Harbour and thank her for her dedication to her community.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#64079cb8-9198-4f19-818a-597f1468ed7d"><num title="1100">RESOLUTION NO. 1100</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers are the cornerstone of Nova Scotia's communities who generously give their time and talents while expecting nothing in return; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Wednesday April 16<sup>th</sup>, the Royal Canadian Legion in Clark's Harbour will host the annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Barrington and Town of Clark's Harbour; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the volunteers to be honoured is Dawn Mitchell, nominated by the Canadian Legion #148 for her devotion of time and her many contributions to her community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Dawn Mitchell on being honoured by the Town of Clark's Harbour and thank her for her dedication to her community.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#64079cb8-9198-4f19-818a-597f1468ed7d"><num title="1101">RESOLUTION NO. 1101</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers are the cornerstone of Nova Scotia's communities who generously give their time and talents while expecting nothing in return; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Wednesday April 16<sup>th</sup>, the Royal Canadian Legion in Clark's Harbour will host the annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Barrington and Town of Clark's Harbour; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the volunteers to be honoured is Janice Smith, nominated by the Cape Sable Island New Horizons for her devotion of time and her many contributions to her community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Janice Smith on being honoured by the Town of Clark's Harbour and thank her for her dedication to her community.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#64079cb8-9198-4f19-818a-597f1468ed7d"><num title="1102">RESOLUTION NO. 1102</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers are the cornerstone of Nova Scotia's communities who generously give their time and talents while expecting nothing in return; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Wednesday April 16<sup>th</sup>, the Royal Canadian Legion in Clark's Harbour will host the annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Barrington and Town of Clark's Harbour; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the volunteers to be honoured is Jim Morton, nominated by the Town of Clark's Harbour for his devotion of time and his many contributions to his community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Jim Morton on being honoured by the Town of Clark's Harbour and thank him for his dedication to his community.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#64079cb8-9198-4f19-818a-597f1468ed7d"><num title="1103">RESOLUTION NO. 1103</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers are the cornerstone of Nova Scotia's communities who generously give their time and talents while expecting nothing in return; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Wednesday April 16<sup>th</sup>, the Royal Canadian Legion in Clark's Harbour will host the annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Barrington and Town of Clark's Harbour; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the volunteers to be honoured is Meredith Ross, nominated by the Town of Clark's Harbour for her devotion of time and her many contributions to her community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Meredith Ross on being honoured by the Town of Clark's Harbour and thank her for her dedication to her community.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#64079cb8-9198-4f19-818a-597f1468ed7d"><num title="1104">RESOLUTION NO. 1104</num><from>Hon. Christopher d'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers are the cornerstone of Nova Scotia's communities who generously give their time and talents while expecting nothing in return; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Wednesday April 16<sup>th</sup>, the Royal Canadian Legion in Clark's Harbour will host the annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Barrington and Town of Clark's Harbour; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the volunteers to be honoured are Ruby and Wes May, nominated by the New Horizons for devoting their time and for their many contributions to their community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ruby and Wes May on being honoured by the Town of Clark's Harbour and thank them and all the volunteers for their dedication to their community.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#64079cb8-9198-4f19-818a-597f1468ed7d"><num title="1105">RESOLUTION NO. 1105</num><from>Hon. Christopher D'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers are the cornerstone of Nova Scotia's communities who generously give their time and talents while expecting nothing in return; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Wednesday, April 16th, the Royal Canadian Legion in Clark's Harbour will host the annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Barrington and Town of Clark's Harbour; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the volunteers to be honoured are the Friends of the Cape Lighthouse, nominated by the Town of Clark's Harbour for their devotion of time and many contributions to their community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate the Friends of Cape Lighthouse on being honoured by the Town of Clark's Harbour and thank them and all the volunteers for their dedication to their community.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#64079cb8-9198-4f19-818a-597f1468ed7d"><num title="1106">RESOLUTION NO. 1106</num><from>Hon. Christopher D'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers are the cornerstone of Nova Scotia's communities who generously give their time and talents while expecting nothing in return; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Wednesday, April 16th, the Royal Canadian Legion in Clark's Harbour will host the annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Barrington and Town of Clark's Harbour; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the volunteers to be honoured is William Reashore, nominated by the Barrington Ground Search and Rescue for devoting his time and his many contributions to his community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate William Reashore on being honoured by the Municipality of Barrington and thank him for his dedication to his community.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#64079cb8-9198-4f19-818a-597f1468ed7d"><num title="1107">RESOLUTION NO. 1107</num><from>Hon. Christopher D'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers are the cornerstone of Nova Scotia's communities who generously give their time and talents while expecting nothing in return; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Wednesday, April 16th, the Royal Canadian Legion in Clark's Harbour will host the annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Barrington and Town of Clark's Harbour; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the volunteers to be honoured is Debbie Nickerson, nominated by the Town of Clark's harbour for her devotion of time and tireless efforts of contribution to her community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Debbie Nickerson on being honoured by the Town of Clark's Harbour and thank her for her dedication to her community.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#64079cb8-9198-4f19-818a-597f1468ed7d"><num title="1108">RESOLUTION NO. 1108</num><from>Hon. Christopher D'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers are the cornerstone of Nova Scotia's communities who generously give their time and talents while expecting nothing in return; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Wednesday, April 16th, the Royal Canadian Legion in Clark's Harbour will host the annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Barrington and Town of Clark's Harbour; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the volunteers to be honoured is Ruth Thomas, nominated by both the Clark's Harbour and Cape Sable Island Elementary schools for her devotion of time and tireless efforts of contribution to her community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Ruth Thomas on being honoured by the Municipality of Barrington and thank her for her dedication to her community.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#64079cb8-9198-4f19-818a-597f1468ed7d"><num title="1109">RESOLUTION NO. 1109</num><from>Hon. Christopher D'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers are the cornerstone of Nova Scotia's communities who generously give their time and talents while expecting nothing in return; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Wednesday, April 16th, the Royal Canadian Legion in Clark's Harbour will host the annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Barrington and Town of Clark's Harbour; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the volunteers to be honoured is Quent Wickens, nominated by the Barrington Recreation Department for his devotion of time and tireless efforts of contribution to his community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Quent Wickens on being honoured by the Municipality of Barrington and thank him and all the volunteers for their dedication to their community.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#64079cb8-9198-4f19-818a-597f1468ed7d"><num title="1110">RESOLUTION NO. 1110</num><from>Hon. Christopher D'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers are the cornerstone of Nova Scotia's communities who generously give their time and talents while expecting nothing in return; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Wednesday, April 16th, the Royal Canadian Legion in Clark's Harbour will host the annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Barrington and Town of Clark's Harbour; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the volunteers to be honoured is Drew McCarthy, nominated by the Barrington Municipal High School for his devotion of time and tireless efforts of contribution to his community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Drew McCarthy on being honoured by the Municipality of Barrington and thank him for his dedication to his community.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#64079cb8-9198-4f19-818a-597f1468ed7d"><num title="1111">RESOLUTION NO. 1111</num><from>Hon. Christopher D'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers are the cornerstone of Nova Scotia's communities who generously give their time and talents while expecting nothing in return; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Wednesday, April 16th, the Royal Canadian Legion in Clark's Harbour will host the annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Barrington and Town of Clark's Harbour; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the volunteers to be honoured is Joyce Swim, nominated by the Barrington-Clark's Harbour Terry Fox Run Committee for her devotion of time and may contributions to her community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Joyce Swim on being honoured by the Municipality of Barrington and thank her for her dedication to her community.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#64079cb8-9198-4f19-818a-597f1468ed7d"><num title="1112">RESOLUTION NO. 1112</num><from>Hon. Christopher D'Entremont</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas volunteers are the cornerstone of Nova Scotia's communities who generously give their time and talents while expecting nothing in return; and</p>
<p>Whereas on Wednesday, April 16th, the Royal Canadian Legion in Clark's Harbour will host the annual Volunteer Banquet for the Municipality of Barrington and Town of Clark's Harbour; and</p>
<p>Whereas among the volunteers to be honoured is Jack Fry, nominated by the Barrington-Clark's Harbour Terry Fox Run Committee for his devotion of time and tireless efforts of contribution to his community;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in congratulating Jack Fry on being honoured by the Municipality of Barrington and thank him for his dedication to his community.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91"><num title="1113">RESOLUTION NO. 1113</num><from>Hon. Lena Diab</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Sunday, March 23, 2014, the Halifax Hawks hockey team won first place in the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Halifax Hawks hosted the Provincial Tournament this year at the Centennial Arena and put together a wonderful opening ceremony welcoming all of the players and families of participating teams; and</p>
<p>Whereas Alex Needler, jersey number 3, has dedicated so much time with the help of coaches, parents and loved ones to be part of this exciting team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate Alex Needler and the Halifax Hawks on their outstanding performance and victory of the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Championship.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91"><num title="1114">RESOLUTION NO. 1114</num><from>Hon. Lena Diab</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Sunday, March 23, 2014, the Halifax Hawks hockey team won first place in the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Halifax Hawks hosted the Provincial Tournament this year at the Centennial Arena and put together a wonderful opening ceremony welcoming all of the players and families of participating teams; and</p>
<p>Whereas Benjamin Mercer, jersey number 9, has dedicated so much time with the help of coaches, parents and loved ones to be part of this exciting team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate Benjamin Mercer and the Halifax Hawks on their outstanding performance and victory of the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Championship.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91"><num title="1115">RESOLUTION NO. 1115</num><from>Hon. Lena Diab</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Sunday, March 23, 2014, the Halifax Hawks hockey team won first place in the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Halifax Hawks hosted the Provincial Tournament this year at the Centennial Arena and put together a wonderful opening ceremony welcoming all of the players and families of participating teams; and</p>
<p>Whereas Gabrielle Laaouan, jersey number 2, has dedicated so much time with the help of coaches, parents and loved ones to be part of this exciting team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate Gabrielle Laaouan and the Halifax Hawks on their outstanding performance and victory of the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Championship.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91"><num title="1116">RESOLUTION NO. 1116</num><from>Hon. Lena Diab</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Sunday, March 23, 2014, the Halifax Hawks hockey team won first place in the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Halifax Hawks hosted the Provincial Tournament this year at the Centennial Arena and put together a wonderful opening ceremony welcoming all of the players and families of participating teams; and</p>
<p>Whereas Gregory Goss, jersey number 5, has dedicated so much time with the help of coaches, parents and loved ones to be part of this exciting team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate Gregory Goss and the Halifax Hawks on their outstanding performance and victory of the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Championship.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91"><num title="1117">RESOLUTION NO. 1117</num><from>Hon. Lena Diab</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Sunday, March 23, 2014, the Halifax Hawks hockey team won first place in the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Halifax Hawks hosted the Provincial Tournament this year at the Centennial Arena and put together a wonderful opening ceremony welcoming all of the players and families of participating teams; and</p>
<p>Whereas Jacob Clothier, jersey number 8, has dedicated so much time with the help of coaches, parents and loved ones to be part of this exciting team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate Jacob Clothier and the Halifax Hawks on their outstanding performance and victory of the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Championship.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91"><num title="1118">RESOLUTION NO. 1118</num><from>Hon. Lena Diab</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Sunday, March 23, 2014, the Halifax Hawks hockey team won first place in the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Halifax Hawks hosted the Provincial Tournament this year at the Centennial Arena and put together a wonderful opening ceremony welcoming all of the players and families of participating teams; and</p>
<p>Whereas Joseph Henneberry, jersey number 15, has dedicated so much time with the help of coaches, parents and loved ones to be part of this exciting team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate Joseph Henneberry and the Halifax Hawks on their outstanding performance and victory of the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Championship.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91"><num title="1119">RESOLUTION NO. 1119</num><from>Hon. Lena Diab</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Sunday, March 23, 2014, the Halifax Hawks hockey team won first place in the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Halifax Hawks hosted the Provincial Tournament this year at the Centennial Arena and put together a wonderful opening ceremony welcoming all of the players and families of participating teams; and</p>
<p>Whereas Joshua O'Connor, jersey number 11, has dedicated so much time with the help of coaches, parents and loved ones to be part of this exciting team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate Joshua O'Connor and the Halifax Hawks on their outstanding performance and victory of the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Championship.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91"><num title="1120">RESOLUTION NO. 1120</num><from>Hon. Lena Diab</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Sunday, March 23, 2014, the Halifax Hawks hockey team won first place in the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Halifax Hawks hosted the Provincial Tournament this year at the Centennial Arena and put together a wonderful opening ceremony welcoming all of the players and families of participating teams; and</p>
<p>Whereas Kaden Keith, jersey number 1, has dedicated so much time with the help of coaches, parents and loved ones to be part of this exciting team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate Kaden Keith and the Halifax Hawks on their outstanding performance and victory of the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Championship.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91"><num title="1121">RESOLUTION NO. 1121</num><from>Hon. Lena Diab</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Sunday, March 23, 2014, the Halifax Hawks hockey team won first place in the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Halifax Hawks hosted the Provincial Tournament this year at the Centennial Arena and put together a wonderful opening ceremony welcoming all of the players and families of participating teams; and</p>
<p>Whereas Liam Apold, jersey number 4, has dedicated so much time with the help of coaches, parents and loved ones to be part of this exciting team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of the House of Assembly congratulate Liam Apold and the Halifax Hawks on their outstanding performance and victory of the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Championship.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91"><num title="1122">RESOLUTION NO. 1122</num><from>Hon. Lena Diab</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Sunday, March 23, 2014, the Halifax Hawks hockey team won first place in the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Halifax Hawks hosted the Provincial Tournament this year at the Centennial Arena and put together a wonderful opening ceremony welcoming all of the players and families of participating teams; and</p>
<p>Whereas Peter MacGregor, jersey number 10, has dedicated so much time with the help of coaches, parents and loved ones to be part of this exciting team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Peter MacGregor and the Halifax Hawks on their outstanding performance and victory of the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Championship.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91"><num title="1123">RESOLUTION NO. 1123</num><from>Hon. Lena Diab</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Sunday, March 23, 2014, the Halifax Hawks hockey team won first place in the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Halifax Hawks hosted the Provincial Tournament this year at the Centennial Arena and put together a wonderful opening ceremony welcoming all of the players and families of participating teams; and</p>
<p>Whereas Theo Iatrou, jersey number 7, has dedicated so much time with the help of coaches, parents and loved ones to be part of this exciting team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Theo Iatrou and the Halifax Hawks on their outstanding performance and victory of the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Championship.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91"><num title="1124">RESOLUTION NO. 1124</num><from>Hon. Lena Diab</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Sunday, March 23, 2014, the Halifax Hawks hockey team won first place in the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Halifax Hawks hosted the Provincial Tournament this year at the Centennial Arena and put together a wonderful opening ceremony welcoming all of the players and families of participating teams; and</p>
<p>Whereas William MacDonald, jersey number 6, has dedicated so much time with the help of coaches, parents and loved ones to be part of this exciting team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate William MacDonald and the Halifax Hawks on their outstanding performance and victory of the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Championship.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91"><num title="1125">RESOLUTION NO. 1125</num><from>Hon. Lena Diab</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Sunday, March 23, 2014, the Halifax Hawks hockey team won first place in the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Halifax Hawks hosted the Provincial Tournament this year at the Centennial Arena and put together a wonderful opening ceremony welcoming all of the players and families of participating teams; and</p>
<p>Whereas Zachary Welsh, jersey number 12, has dedicated so much time with the help of coaches, parents and loved ones to be part of this exciting team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Zachary Welsh and the Halifax Hawks on their outstanding performance and victory of the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Championship.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91"><num title="1126">RESOLUTION NO. 1126</num><from>Hon. Lena Diab</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Sunday, March 23, 2014, the Halifax Hawks hockey team won first place in the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Halifax Hawks hosted the Provincial Tournament this year at the Centennial Arena and put together a wonderful opening ceremony welcoming all of the players and families of participating teams; and</p>
<p>Whereas Giovacchino Dimattia, jersey number 31, has dedicated so much time with the help of coaches, parents and loved ones to be part of this exciting team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Giovacchino Dimattia and the Halifax Hawks on their outstanding performance and victory of the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Championship.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91"><num title="1127">RESOLUTION NO. 1127</num><from>Hon. Lena Diab</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Sunday, March 23, 2014, the Halifax Hawks hockey team won first place in the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Halifax Hawks hosted the Provincial Tournament this year at the Centennial Arena and put together a wonderful opening ceremony welcoming all of the players and families of participating teams; and</p>
<p>Whereas Peter Gillham, jersey number 16, has dedicated so much time with the help of coaches, parents and loved ones to be part of this exciting team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Peter Gillham and the Halifax Hawks on their outstanding performance and victory of the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Championship.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91"><num title="1128">RESOLUTION NO. 1128</num><from>Hon. Lena Diab</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Sunday, March 23, 2014, the Halifax Hawks hockey team won first place in the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Halifax Hawks hosted the Provincial Tournament this year at the Centennial Arena and put together a wonderful opening ceremony welcoming all of the players and families of participating teams; and</p>
<p>Whereas Robert Kraitzek, jersey number 18, has dedicated so much time with the help of coaches, parents and loved ones to be part of this exciting team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Robert Kraitzek and the Halifax Hawks on their outstanding performance and victory of the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Championship.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#7468ce01-c499-4768-9a8c-19e92ed26c91"><num title="1129">RESOLUTION NO. 1129</num><from>Hon. Lena Diab</from><p>I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas on Sunday, March 23, 2014, the Halifax Hawks hockey team won first place in the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Tournament; and</p>
<p>Whereas the Halifax Hawks hosted the Provincial Tournament this year at the Centennial Arena and put together a wonderful opening ceremony welcoming all of the players and families of participating teams; and</p>
<p>Whereas Zachary Lorette, jersey number 17, has dedicated so much time with the help of coaches, parents and loved ones to be part of this exciting team;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly congratulate Zachary Lorette and the Halifax Hawks on their outstanding performance and victory of the 2014 Atom AA Provincial Championship.</p></speech>
      </noticesOfMotion>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
