<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="joanne.bernard" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.joanne.bernard" showAs="HON. JOANNE BERNARD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="karla.macfarlane" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.karla.macfarlane" showAs="MS. KARLA MACFARLANE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="gordie.gosse" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.gordie.gosse" showAs="MR. GORDIE GOSSE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="kelly.regan" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.kelly.regan" showAs="HON. KELLY REGAN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="eddie.orrell" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.eddie.orrell" showAs="MR. EDDIE ORRELL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="jamie.baillie" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.jamie.baillie" showAs="HON. JAMIE BAILLIE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="maureen.macdonald" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.maureen.macdonald" showAs="HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="alfie.macleod" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.alfie.macleod" showAs="MR. ALFIE MACLEOD"/>
        <TLCPerson id="leo.glavine" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.leo.glavine" showAs="HON. LEO GLAVINE"/>
        <TLCPerson id="christopher.a.dentremont" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.christopher.a.dentremont" showAs="HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="frank.corbett" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.frank.corbett" showAs="HON. FRANK CORBETT"/>
        <TLCPerson id="lena.m.diab" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.lena.m.diab" showAs="HON. LENA DIAB"/>
        <TLCPerson id="david.allan.wilson" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.david.allan.wilson" showAs="HON. DAVID WILSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="patrick.dunn" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.patrick.dunn" showAs="HON. PAT DUNN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="zach.churchill" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.zach.churchill" showAs="HON. ZACH CHURCHILL"/>
        <TLCPerson id="larry.harrison" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.larry.harrison" showAs="MR. LARRY HARRISON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="geoff.maclellan" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.geoff.maclellan" showAs="HON. GEOFF MACLELLAN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="michel.p.samson" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.michel.p.samson" showAs="HON. MICHEL SAMSON"/>
        <TLCPerson id="diana.whalen" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.diana.whalen" showAs="HON. DIANA WHALEN"/>
        <TLCPerson id="tim.houston" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.tim.houston" showAs="MR. TIM HOUSTON"/>
        <TLCRole id="speaker" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.speaker" showAs="MR. SPEAKER"/>
        <TLCRole id="premier" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.premier" showAs="THE PREMIER"/>
        <TLCRole id="member" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.member" showAs="AN HON. MEMBER"/>
        <TLCRole id="clerk" href="/ontology/role/nslegislature.ca-ns.clerk" showAs="THE CLERK"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, 3 April 2014</docTitle>
      <docNumber>14-20</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2014-04-03">Thursday, April 3, 2014</docDate>
      <docAuthority>Nova Scotia House of Assembly</docAuthority>
      <legislature value="62">62nd General Assembly</legislature>
      <session value="1">1st Session</session>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://nslegislature.ca/index.php/proceedings/hansard/C94/house_14apr03/"/>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
        <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
        <p>Order, please. We'll now begin the daily routine.</p>
      </speech>
      <ministerialStatements>
        <heading>STATEMENTS BY MINISTERS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Community Services.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#joanne.bernard"><from>HON. JOANNE BERNARD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, Sexual Assault Awareness Month began two days ago with a strong commitment to do more to prevent sexual assault and sexual violence in Nova Scotia. While April is appropriately recognized as Sexual Assault Awareness Month, our efforts are needed 365 days a year.</p>
<p>We need to ensure that victims and survivors have greater access to appropriate services that will help them in their healing process. They deserve our compassion, our belief and our resolve to support them. Survivors, advocates, service providers, front-line workers, law enforcement and government are coming together to raise awareness about sexual assault and sexual violence in our communities.</p>
<p>Sexual assault is an affront to human dignity no matter where or when it occurs. While sexual assault can happen to anyone regardless of their sex, age, socio-economic status, sexual orientation, or where they live, we do know that those at greatest risk are women and girls.</p>
<p>Today, I am pleased to reaffirm our government's commitment to improving supports and services to victims, families, and communities. One of the earliest announcements made by this government was our intention to develop the first sexual violence strategy for Nova Scotia. My vision includes working across the provincial government with our partners, stakeholders, and advocates to create an action-oriented approach that supports the resiliency and courage of those impacted.</p>
<p>As we work to support the resiliency of victims of sexual assault, we also need to support the efforts of those who do their part to address these crimes and to work to prevent future occurrences. Today I want to commend and thank the many community service providers, advocates, front-line workers, and law enforcement for your essential and critical efforts.</p>
<p>In closing, I want to urge all Nova Scotians to support survivors of sexual assault, to work together to prevent these crimes in their communities, and to attend the many events that will take place throughout the province. I want to challenge every Nova Scotian to help raise awareness about sexualized violence and sexual assault and to not be a bystander. When sexual assault does take place, it cannot be tolerated. Victims must have access to support and offenders must be held to account for their actions. All Nova Scotians must play a role in changing a culture that enables sexual assault and sexual violence. Each of us can and must take action. Thank you, Mr. Speaker.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Pictou West.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#karla.macfarlane"><from>MS. KARLA MACFARLANE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I would like to thank the minister for providing a copy of her statement to me in advance. April is set aside to raise awareness about sexual assault and sexual violence. I agree with the minister that this is an issue that needs to be addressed 365 days a year.</p>
<p>I am pleased to hear the minister commit to improving supports and services to victims of sexual assault, their families, and their communities. As a caring society we must provide the support the courageous victims of sexual violence need to help them heal. We must also ensure that offenders are made to account for their criminal actions.</p>
<p>This morning I am pleased to have the opportunity to salute the many people across our province whose life's work is to provide the programs and supports to help victims - the activists, the advocates, the educators, the health advisors, law enforcement, and justice workers. Their jobs are not easy ones by any means, but it is an important job and an essential job. We all owe them a debt of gratitude - not just during Sexual Assault Awareness Month, but every day of the year.</p>
<p>We know that sexual abuse and sexualized violence in our communities is far more common than people think. According to a 2006 Statistics Canada report, one in three women will experience some form of sexual assault in their lifetime. Statistics provided by the Avalon Sexual Assault Centre indicate that in 2007 the rate of reported sexual assaults in Nova Scotia was 75 per 100,000 people, compared to the national rate of 65 per 100,000 people. As I said, we must provide those victims with the help they need, but we must also take action to prevent sexual violence in the first place. We must curb violence before it begins. We need to take the blinders off.</p>
<p>As caring citizens we need to create a better environment to ensure that victims of sexual assault and sexual violence feel they will be believed when they tell their stories. That starts with meaningful education and awareness. We must send the message that sexual violence is always wrong and not tolerated in our province.</p>
<p>Government and all Nova Scotians must double their efforts to change our culture, reduce the sad and alarming statistics of sexual violence in our province, and support the brave victims who come forward. I urge government to act quickly and decisively to make meaningful progress toward preventing and addressing sexual assault and sexual violence in Nova Scotia. Thank you.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Sydney-Whitney Pier.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#gordie.gosse"><from>MR. GORDIE GOSSE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, first I would like to thank the minister for providing a copy of her statement in advance this evening. Encouraging awareness of sexual violence is a very important initiative and it's an issue I take very seriously. Every year I attend events in my community held at Cape Breton University for Sexual Assault Awareness Week.</p>
<p>I applaud the work of organizations around the province that support victims of violence and sexual assault. In Cape Breton we are very lucky to have the Cape Breton Transition House, the Every Woman's Centre, and the Silent Witness program, with silhouettes there to honour women in Cape Breton Regional Municipality who have been killed in incidents of domestic violence since 1990.</p>
<p>Also in Cape Breton I'm very proud that we are home to the first Domestic Violence Court in Canada. The court officially opened in June 2012 at the Sydney Justice Centre. This was an initiative of the NDP Government which I'm very proud to have been a part of. I know that across the province so many survivors, advocates, service providers, front-line workers, and law enforcement have been working to raise awareness of sexual assault and sexual violence in our communities. I commend their efforts and I'm pleased that the government is prepared to work with them to develop a strategy addressing sexual violence.</p>
<p>I agree with the minister that we need to ensure victims and survivors of sexual violence have greater access to services that can help them to overcome their traumas. These victims absolutely deserve our compassion, our focus, and most importantly support from all Nova Scotians, including government. I'm anxious to see what tomorrow's budget will offer in this respect and I look forward to continuing to be an advocate for victims of violence and sexual assault as the Critic for Community Services and as the MLA for Sydney-Whitney Pier. Thank you, Mr. Speaker.</p></speech>
      </ministerialStatements>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Minister of Labour and Advanced Education.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#kelly.regan"><num title="831">RESOLUTION NO. 831</num><from>HON. KELLY REGAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas Nova Scotians marked International Adult Learners' Week from March 29<sup>th</sup> to April 6<sup>th</sup>, celebrating the achievements of adult learners and the organizations that support them; and</p>
<p>Whereas learning is the foundation for growth in all aspects of our lives, and Adult Learners' Week raises awareness of the value of lifelong learning and the supports and services available to Nova Scotians who wish to enhance their knowledge and skills; and</p>
<p>Whereas lifelong learning has a significant impact on individuals, their families and communities, by helping better prepare the province's workforce to seize the economic opportunities of today and tomorrow;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House celebrate the week of March 29 to April 6, 2014, as International Adult Learners' Week in the Province of Nova Scotia, and urge all citizens to observe this week and to be more fully aware of the importance of a lifetime full of learning in all aspects of their lives.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <noticesOfMotion>
        <heading>NOTICES OF MOTION</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable member for Northside-Westmount.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#eddie.orrell"><num title="832">RESOLUTION NO. 832</num><from>MR. EDDIE ORRELL</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I hereby give notice that on a future day I shall move the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>Whereas each Sunday morning the Royal Canadian Legion Branch 83 hosts a large fundraising breakfast to support Legion activities, and the proceeds from their March 30<sup>th</sup> meal was donated to the Florence Volunteer Fire Department; and</p>
<p>Whereas Legion President Lloyd Harris stated this is just one service group trying to help another for recognition of their service to the community; and</p>
<p>Whereas the fire department helped serve and do other breakfast-related activities, and the Legion members did the cooking;</p>
<p>Therefore be it resolved that all members of this House of Assembly join me in saluting Branch 83 for its community-minded spirit and generosity.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I request waiver of notice and passage without debate.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>There has been a request for waiver.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p></speech>
      </noticesOfMotion>
      <questions>
        <heading>ORAL QUESTIONS PUT BY MEMBERS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>The time is now 12:16 a.m. and we'll conclude Question Period at 1:16 a.m.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition.</p></speech>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>PREM.: PATIENT CARE - COMPROMISED</heading>
          <speech by="#jamie.baillie">
            <from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from>
            <p>My question is to the Premier. Mr. Speaker, we now know that as of this moment 293 surgeries have been cancelled at Capital Health. The strike hasn't even started yet, although we are hours away, and that is how much patient care has already been compromised, proving the point that even the threat of a strike affects patients care. That is why you don't wait to act. I will ask the Premier, will he now admit to those 293 families that patient care has, in fact, been compromised already under his watch?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, the Leader of the Official Opposition makes the very case for why this bill should be passed, and I would encourage both Opposition Parties to pass the bill.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#jamie.baillie"><from>MR. BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I believe the 293 families make the case that waiting seven months to take action does not protect patient care, that doing nothing with all the warnings that this government has had, and all the deadlines that they have missed has actually affected 293 surgeries. Whether they were essential or not under the Premier's bill is not the point; in fact, they probably aren't. But they are essential to those 293 families and that's why we should not have allowed a strike to get this far or a crisis to develop, and this has happened so many times before in this province's history.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, the Premier had seven months to get his act together and only now on the eve of a strike, when families - these 293 in particular - are already losing their health care, that is the problem. So I'll ask the Premier, how can he tell those 293 families that their care has been protected under his watch?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined"><from>THE PREMIER</from><p>What I can tell those 293 families is finally - finally, Mr. Speaker - a government is standing up to ensure that essential health services will be in place. (Applause)</p>
<p>Also the workers in this province - unlike the Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party, this Party believes in collective bargaining and the right to strike, and we'll do so, Mr. Speaker.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#jamie.baillie"><from>MR. BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, the one thing that we are constant in on this side of the House is that patients have to come first, and they have to be protected before a strike so that there isn't a strike and for all time. The Premier has failed to these 293 cases, his bill won't solve their problem in the future, it may not be essential to the union or to the government, but their surgeries are essential to them. That's why there shouldn't be a strike and that's why the government should have acted months ago.</p>
<p>As the Premier once said, Mr. Speaker, that we should not be legislating on the eve of a crisis, he has gone back on what he said and done just that, and 293 families are now paying the price. I'll ask the Premier, on behalf of those families, why did he wait until another crisis developed and 293 surgeries are cancelled, to finally act?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined"><from>THE PREMIER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, one of the great ironies of the Leader of the Official Opposition, if we had acted before we allowed the collective bargaining process to proceed he would have complained about the fact that we interfered in the collective bargaining process, which I think if you check Hansard, he already complained about that.</p>
<p>The fact of the matter is on Monday there was a 48-hour strike notice put in place. Our government responded - not only to deal with the issue of labour disruption in the health care system today, but for all time. We put in place a bill that will effectively put out essential services legislation that will ensure health care is there for Nova Scotians but, at the same time, respecting the right of health care workers to strike.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Leader of the New Democratic Party.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>PREM. - CAP. DHA: INDUSTRIAL INQUIRY - REQUEST</heading>
          <speech by="#maureen.macdonald"><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question through you is to the Premier. Last evening, I sent the Premier a letter requesting that his Minister of Labour and Advanced Education appoint an industrial inquiry commission. The commission would examine the dispute between the Capital District Health Authority and the Nova Scotia Government and General Employees Union regarding nurse staffing levels and patient safety - and I will table a copy of the letter.</p>
<p>As part of the request, the NDP are asking all sides to immediately accept a 90-day cooling-off period during which time the government would suspend passage of Bill No. 37 and the Nova Scotia Government and General Employees Union and the Capital District Health Authority would agree to no strike or no walkout, but the Premier has declined the offer. Instead of agreeing to a solution that would protect both the collective bargaining process and patient safety, the Premier has put both in danger.</p>
<p>My question for the Premier is, why did he refuse to advise his Minister of Labour and Advanced Education to appoint an industrial inquiry commission into patient safety and nurse staffing levels in the Capital District Health Authority?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>I would encourage the member opposite to pass Bill No. 37, which protects essential services legislation as well as the right to bargain. Furthermore, I want to inform the member opposite that the Minister of Health and Wellness is already dealing with health authorities across this province to deal with the critical issue of staffing, not only in the Capital District, but across the province - something that government failed to do for four years.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#maureen.macdonald"><from>MS. MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, a three-person commission would be chaired by a neutral labour relations expert, along with a representative of the employer and of the union. Research and expert opinion during a cooling-off period would bring light into an issue currently where there is not a great deal of light.</p>
<p>Will the Premier reconsider and agree to an industrial inquiry commission on patient safety and staffing levels? If not, perhaps the Premier can offer a more constructive solution than that of stripping health care workers of the fair collective bargaining process.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined"><from>THE PREMIER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, Bill No. 37 has struck a balance to ensure that essential health care services would be available to Nova Scotians. They'll know well in advance of any labour issues that may come up in the health care sector. At the same time, it protects the right to strike for health care workers.</p>
<p>It wasn't all that long ago when every major union leader in this province marched across into the Red Room and supported a bill by that government, by the NDP, to strip the right to strike from paramedics - to strip the right to strike from paramedics, Mr. Speaker. We struck a balance, which ensures that health and essential services be in place and ensuring that health care workers are protected to use the right to strike.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#maureen.macdonald"><from>MS. MACDONALD</from><p>It's very sad that the Premier is not interested in a common sense solution that would bring some sanity to a situation that is now spinning toward a situation that none of us want.</p>
<p>A 90-day cooling-off period before a legal strike would also allow the Liberal Cabinet members, and the members of the Liberal Government more generally, to hear from health care workers about the adverse effects of essential services legislation - if they haven't already heard about this.</p>
<p>Will the Premier again reconsider and allow his MLAs more time to study the negative effects this type of legislation will have on labour peace in this province because of the negative effect this type of legislation has had in other provinces, and if not, why not?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I want to tell you that every province other than Nova Scotia has a form of essential services in their individual provinces. If the Leader of the New Democratic Party (Interruptions)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Order, please. The honourable Premier has the floor.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, if the Leader of the New Democratic Party really wants to do something for patients in this province, I would encourage her to stop filibustering this bill and pass it tonight.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Leader of the Official Opposition.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>HEALTH &amp; WELLNESS - CAP. HEALTH MENTAL HEALTH UNIT: STAFF - LACK EXPLAIN</heading>
          <speech by="#jamie.baillie">
            <from>HON. JAMIE BAILLIE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, yesterday we learned from the Minister of Health and Wellness that there is a mental health unit with five patients, here at Capital Health, that will go unstaffed when the strike happens, unstaffed despite the fact that there is an existing essential services plan in place. These are vulnerable Nova Scotians in need of constant help who will be left alone when the strike starts, even with essential services plans in place already. I ask the Premier, how can he say to those five Nova Scotians that their health care is protected?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I want to inform the Leader of the Official Opposition that there is no essential services plan in place. What we have is an emergency service plan, quite frankly, which has no parameters around it. No one has to provide service; that's the very issue we're dealing with here in this House.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#jamie.baillie">
            <from>MR. BAILLIE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, the Premier should read his own bill because that's exactly the kind of plan that his bill will require, yet today it leaves these five mental health patients at risk of being without care. It's why you don't wait until there is a crisis to act. There was a time in Opposition when the Premier said that this is the worst time to be making up bills as you go along because it should be done when there is labour peace. He had seven months to do that and he didn't act. Now they bring in a bill, risking that it won't be passed, and leaving in time to protect people like these five individuals, these five Nova Scotians who are in need of mental health services. I'll ask the Premier, why did he wait and put their health care at risk?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I believe the Leader of the Progressive Conservative Party just said to this House that our bill would solve that problem. It is the very reason why we encourage the Opposition Parties to pass this bill.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#jamie.baillie"><from>MR. BAILLIE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I actually said that their bill would not solve that problem; that is, in fact, the point. Now we are hours away (Interruptions) That's right, it's actually not funny - a couple of hours from now, real Nova Scotians at mental health units, waiting for surgery, they're going to go without health care because once again, like so many times in the history of this province, a government waited until there was a crisis to actually act and that is wrong.</p>
<p>The Premier once agreed with that statement and said it's the worst time to be bringing in a bill, that it would be much better to put in place a plan for all time when there's labour peace, when neither nurses nor any other health care worker would feel that they are targeted. Instead, it's the same old way. They wait until there is a crisis and then they bring in a bill. In fact, by doing all we can, including giving up our own day today, to the government, to try to move this bill through, I actually think we're trying to clean up a crisis that the government, itself, contributed to by doing nothing until it was too late, but here we are.</p>
<p>Now we have people in hospital beds in Capital Health being sent to their home district, being sent home, being released from the hospital because no one is going to be there to care for them. I'll ask the Premier this question, how is sending people out of the hospital and back home protecting their care?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, the last time the Progressive Conservative Party was in power they did nothing, quite frankly, to protect the essential services of the people of this province. For the last four years Nova Scotians have felt neglected by the NDP. We have a bill in front of this House, which will protect essential services and allow health care workers to keep the right to strike.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Sydney River-Mira-Louisbourg.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>HEALTH &amp; WELLNESS - VETERANS SERVICES: STRIKE - IMPACT</heading>
          <speech by="#alfie.macleod"><from>MR. ALFIE MACLEOD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question through you will be to the Minister of Health and Wellness. All members of this House appreciate the great sacrifices that have been made by our veterans, sacrifices that allow us the many freedoms that we enjoy today. Those brave men and women gave all so that we could have 100 per cent freedom. Not 75 per cent freedom, not 50 per cent freedom.</p>
<p>So my question to the minister is, is he satisfied that, starting in six hours, veteran services will not be staffed at 100 per cent? How can he justify that our veterans will not be receiving 100 per cent of the services that they need and richly deserve?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#leo.glavine">
            <from>HON. LEO GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, to the member opposite, this was a question asked earlier in the week in terms of what emergency services would actually be covered in the event of a wildcat strike or a legal strike, which can start tomorrow at 7:00 a.m., and we were informed that veterans and their needs would be looked after.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#alfie.macleod"><from>MR. MACLEOD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, most Nova Scotians would be saddened and shocked to learn that veterans will suffer during the impending nurses' strike. The information that we have is that the services will not be 100 per cent staffed. In February, the MLA for Fairview-Clayton Park, who was critical of other Parties' support for our veterans said, "Doing nothing is not an option." I will table that quote.</p>
<p>My question for the minister is, will the minister detail for the House the actions that members of his Liberal caucus have taken to ensure that our veterans get 100 per cent of the health services that they deserve? Have they followed their own advice that doing nothing is not an option?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#leo.glavine">
            <from>MR. GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, to the member opposite, it is our understanding that there will be provisions to look after the needs of our veterans at Camp Hill who could be impacted. We've been assured that the necessary contingencies are in place, and if that is not the case, due to call-ins or people who don't show up for work, then that is certainly contrary to what we have been informed of at this stage.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#alfie.macleod">
            <from>MR. MACLEOD</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I consider all the freedoms we enjoy, and I am 100 per cent grateful for every one of them. I know that all Nova Scotians feel the same way. Will the minister please tell the House what contingencies have been made available to our veterans once this strike begins?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#leo.glavine">
            <from>MR. GLAVINE</from>
            <p>The member opposite is actually raising a very, very good point here in the Legislature, that we know that this would be one of the requirements, that under essential services legislation it would not be any concern or worry that our veterans wouldn't get the full services that they require. That is our understanding, that tomorrow, when there is a legal strike, that our veterans are looked after. I can let the member opposite know that that will be one of my calls tomorrow, to make sure that our veterans indeed are being looked after at Camp Hill. You know, as we linger into the wee hours of the morning here, I'd be willing also to join the member opposite and head to Ottawa and get some real concern for our veterans. (Applause)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Order, please. The honourable Leader of the New Democratic Party.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>PREM.: STRIKE RESTRICTING LEGISLATION - LEADERS' STANCE (2007)</heading>
          <speech by="#maureen.macdonald">
            <from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, my question through you is to the Premier. On the eve of a potential strike in 33 hospitals across the province back in 2010, The Chronicle Herald published an article, which I'll table, in which it says that none of the Party Leaders at the time thought that laws restricting strikes in the health care sector were necessary. Let me read what the article says was said by the Premier : "Liberal Leader Stephen McNeil said Nova Scotia effectively has &#x2026;"</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Order, please. Please make your reference to the Premier as the Premier.</p>
<p>The honourable Leader of the New Democratic Party has the floor.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#maureen.macdonald"><from>MS. MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I do know this.</p>
<p>In the article, the member for Annapolis is quoted as having said that "Nova Scotia effectively has essential services legislation already because collective agreements require emergency services staffing plans."</p>
<p>My question for the Premier is, why is he suddenly determined to impose on nurses legislation he said just a few short years ago was not needed?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>As the Leader of the New Democratic Party would know, in the last seven months we've had potential labour disruptions in the health care system. Unfortunately, the provision that you're referring to has not always been implemented, and she would know full well that when negotiations between an employer and a union begin to break down, they do not end up always agreeing on what is an emergency service. She would know that well - she took away the right to strike from paramedics because she wasn't sure they were going to provide emergency services. She's making the very case on why this should be put in legislation to ensure we never face this again.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#maureen.macdonald"><from>MS. MACDONALD</from><p>It never ceases to amaze me how the member for Annapolis can take a set of facts and twist them so that they are completely unrelated to what really happened. Nevertheless, Nova Scotians will find this out soon enough.</p>
<p>In 2007, in this House, the current Premier said of the Progressive Conservative essential services legislation, "I believe government wants to hold this over the heads of the nurses who are in negotiations now. Is that the kind of Nova Scotia that we want?" he asked. "Is that the new Nova Scotia?"</p>
<p>My question for the Premier is, is the new Nova Scotia one where the government can hold essential services over the heads of nurses?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, the new Nova Scotia that Nova Scotians voted for on October 8<sup>th</sup> was a government that respected the right to strike from all Nova Scotians, unlike the New Democratic Party that stripped that right from paramedics. Let me be clear: this is putting in place essential services legislation that would ensure that we protect services for patients. The New Democratic Party has a decision to make - they're either going to support patients or they're going to support their union bosses.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#maureen.macdonald"><from>MS. MACDONALD</from><p>The Premier had even more to say about essential services legislation in 2007. Once again, in this House, he said, "It has been proven from one end of this country to the other - this legislation will not work." Those are his words, Mr. Speaker, not mine.</p>
<p>So my question for the Premier is, why does he now want to impose bad legislation on thousands of Nova Scotians that he himself has said will not work?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined">
            <from>THE PREMIER</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I know the honourable member has been here longer than I have, but she seems to be forgetting a key fact to that piece of legislation she's referring to - it actually stripped the right to strike away from health care workers. I would encourage her to look at the bill that's in front of this House today which actually puts in place an essential services plan to provide health care services to Nova Scotians well in advance of a strike, and it also protects the health care workers' right to strike. That Party is going to have to determine whether or not they are going to support the patients or their union bosses.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>I just want to remind all members on both side of the House that if you have something to say, get yourself on the paper with your House Leader and take your turn.</p>
<p>The honourable member for Argyle-Barrington.</p></speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>JUSTICE - EAST COAST FORENSIC HOSP.: STAFFING - SAFETY</heading>
          <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><from>HON. CHRISTOPHER D'ENTREMONT</from><p>Thank you very much, Mr. Speaker, I assure you I'm on the list.</p>
<p>My question through you is to the Minister of Justice. Capital Health is warning that there is no emergency staffing level agreement &#x2026;</p></speech>
          <speech by="#frank.corbett">
            <from>HON. FRANK CORBETT</from>
            <p>Geoff, at least you're a good ballplayer, not like that one.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont">
            <from>MR. D'ENTREMONT</from>
            <p>Are you done, Frankie?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#frank.corbett">
            <from>MR. CORBETT</from>
            <p>Sorry. Yeah, I'm done.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont">
            <from>MR. D'ENTREMONT</from>
            <p>You're not on my list.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Start over again.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont">
            <from>MR. D'ENTREMONT</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, thank you. Capital Health is warning that there is no emergency staffing level agreement and that the current staffing plan creates an unsafe environment for patients and staff - and I'll table that document. There are approximately 11 nurses at the East Coast Forensic Hospital during normal staffing levels, and I'll table that one as well. So my question is, can the Minister of Justice update the House on what the staff levels could look like later today in the event of a strike?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#lena.m.diab">
            <from>HON. LENA DIAB</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, to the member opposite, I have been in contact with the East Coast Forensic Hospital and I've been informed from the leader of the Forensic Services and Offender Health, he has confirmed that we have an upgrade in staffing of one extra RN at night and security will not be affected by the strike.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><from>MR. D'ENTREMONT</from><p>According to the staffing level document on April 2, 2014, the staffing level for Rehab A could drop to one. So I guess what you're saying here is maybe one plus one - I know you'll probably have an opportunity next to update that. According to the same staffing level document, staffing level for Rehab B could also drop to one. In these two rehabilitation units there are 30 beds each, Mr. Speaker, so that would mean two or three nurses for the 30-bed units.</p>
<p>So my question to the Minister of Justice is, do you accept that these two rehabilitation units with patients referred there by the courts will maintain adequate oversight with only one or two nurses on that site?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#lena.m.diab">
            <from>MS. DIAB</from>
            <p>A very important question. Again I will repeat that the leader of the Forensic Services and Offender Health has assured us that security will not be affected by the strike and, in terms of the exact numbers, I will have to either get those to you or request that you refer that question to my colleague, the Minister of Health and Wellness.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont">
            <from>MR. D'ENTREMONT</from>
            <p>Well how about this, Mr. Speaker, that a (Interruptions)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Order, please. The honourable member for Argyle-Barrington on his final supplementary.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#christopher.a.dentremont"><from>MR. D'ENTREMONT</from><p>Thank you very much, Mr. Speaker, and I do hope that she does have the opportunity to update herself with the minister who is just sitting a few seats down from her.</p>
<p>The East Coast Forensic Hospital also houses a 24-bed mentally ill offender unit where court-ordered assessments are performed and treatment is provided to offenders diagnosed with mental illness. According to the staffing level document, the staffing level could drop to zero in the offender health services. Does the minister accept that the mentally ill patients who were court ordered to undergo assessment will receive adequate oversight with the zero nurses on strike? You may just refer it.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#lena.m.diab">
            <from>MS. DIAB</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I won't refer this one, no. These are patients and these are our most vulnerable, and yes, we do have to protect them. Again, as I said earlier, security will not be affected by the strike, as we've been assured by the leader of the Forensic Services and Offender Health just a few hours ago. Any more information, I'd be happy to gather that information and share it with the member opposite later.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Sackville-Cobequid.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>HEALTH &amp; WELLNESS - CAP. HEALTH: PATIENT SAFETY - ADDRESS</heading>
          <speech by="#david.allan.wilson"><from>HON. DAVID WILSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I'm on the list, so I'm glad to be able to stand and ask a question through you to the Minister of Health and Wellness. Yesterday, the Minister of Health and Wellness admitted for the first time that there is a staffing problem in health care in the Capital Region that affects patient safety. He says that he will deal with it.</p>
<p>My question to the Minister of Health and Wellness is, when will he tell Capital Health to address the patient safety, and will he direct Capital Health administration to leave their offices, tour the floors and see for themselves exactly what is going on within the health care sector in Capital Health?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#leo.glavine">
            <from>HON. LEO GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, to the member for Sackville-Cobequid, I do want to assure him and all members of the House that, in fact, the Capital District is the one remaining on my list to do - not just really a tour, but a great deal of discussion, and also to review what is taking place in many of the units and floors of the QEII, Dickson Centre and other facilities in Capital Health. We certainly want to get a full sense of what the staffing issues are. We got some glimpses and insights yesterday, as well as leading up to the wildcat strike. These will be investigated, reviewed and addressed in the coming weeks.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#david.allan.wilson"><from>MR. DAVID WILSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I know I've asked the minister yesterday if he was able to get a full sense by the many presenters who were witnesses at the Law Amendments Committee, and I hope he takes the time to talk to his colleagues who sat at the Law Amendments Committee. I know the Minister of Natural Resources and the Minister of Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal spent some time there early yesterday morning. I hope he takes that opportunity to hear from them about what they heard, what the sense was around staffing levels within Capital Health.</p>
<p>Last night we suggested a solution to the current labour dispute and that is what we are offering to the government. The Liberals would have saved face by withdrawing legislation that harms collective bargaining - no matter what the Premier says, it does harm the collective bargaining process - and there would have been a 90-day cooling off period with no work stoppages, and a commission would review nurse staffing levels and patient safety, something the minister just said he wants to look into.</p>
<p>I would like to ask the Minister of Health and Wellness, what was his response to the letter sent to him, and could he update us on what he advised either his staff or the Premier on what his response was to our offer for the commission?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#leo.glavine">
            <from>MR. GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, it is unfortunate that we've arrived at this point in a labour dispute where health care services are not at the 100 per cent level that Nova Scotians have come to expect and certainly deserve as we all work and want to see the highest quality of health care delivered daily throughout our province. What today's legislation, Bill No. 37, does is prepare a path for the future. I'm sure there will be other occasions when there will be labour disputes and negotiations will be challenging, but from this point forward, Nova Scotians will know exactly what services will be in place.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#david.allan.wilson"><from>MR. DAVID WILSON</from><p>Mr. Speaker, I can tell you, and through you to the Minister of Health and Wellness, the path forward is not going to be that good for the government. During any collective bargaining - and I don't know what kind of experience the Minister of Health and Wellness has had with it - no matter what decision you make, you can't back yourself into a corner. You have to be able to look at where you can go out. What we have done is offer a way for this government to have a cooling off period. We know the tensions are high on all sides and it would have been a way for them to find out if this is a direction that the government truly wants to go. Is this the path forward for them over the next four years?</p>
<p>The Minister of Labour and Advanced Education could immediately appoint an industrial inquiry commission under Section 73 of the Trade Union Act. I ask again, to the Minister of Health and Wellness, will he urge his colleagues to do so, to save both workers' rights and, most importantly, address patient safety?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#leo.glavine">
            <from>MR. GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I may not have all the nuances of collective bargaining; I have been a union rep and have the greatest respect for the negotiating process. There are times when we do reach an impasse and when that happens in health, we should not jeopardize not knowing what tomorrow will bring. One of the requests that is in the letter is to drop Bill No. 37 and that would not be being a responsible government to the citizens of this province.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Pictou Centre.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>HEALTH &amp; WELLNESS - ER BACKUPS: PREVENTION - PLANS</heading>
          <speech by="#patrick.dunn"><from>HON. PAT DUNN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question through you is for the Minister of Health and Wellness. Yesterday the minister said that there would be patients sent out of Capital Health for service. In the New Glasgow news Dr. Nicole Boutilier, vice-president of Medical Affairs for the Pictou County Health Authority, said the Pictou County Health Authority plans to retrieve as many of its patients as possible from Capital Health, to lessen the burden on the staff and services in the Halifax area.</p>
<p>Dr. Boutilier said we are going to have to make do with what we have, which is going to back us up in the emergency department. I have had the opportunity to visit the emergency department, perhaps about 20 times over the last two and a half weeks, and they can do without this strain. My question to the minister is, what preventive measures has the Liberal Government taken to prevent emergency room backups?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#leo.glavine">
            <from>MR. GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, we know that as we get into tomorrow, based on what we have seen in the last couple of days, many of our hospitals across the province will be challenged. However, they have all agreed to be supportive, to make sure that they co-operate with Capital Health and get as many patients looked after as they can, with their resources. Having met Dr. Boutilier and many of her clinicians at Aberdeen, I know that they will certainly be doing all they can to support patients first.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#patrick.dunn">
            <from>MR. DUNN</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, the Capital Health Authority plays a major role in the health care of the whole province and some procedures are only done in Halifax. The trickle-down effect can already be seen. In order to free up as many beds and staff as possible, the Pictou County Health Authority has cancelled all in-patient elective surgery, 11 to date. During the strike and botched labour negotiations the one clear loser is the patient. Will the minister accept responsibility for the province-wide chaos he and his government have created?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#leo.glavine">
            <from>MR. GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, it is unfortunate that we have arrived at this impasse and the possibility of legal strike action will take us into tomorrow. But you know there is always a point in time, both through negotiations and through the legislative process, to make a choice that does work in favour of patients not just here in the Capital District Health Authority, but all those who are impacted when services are disrupted. I think we have taken a very balanced approach to the future and we hope that we can get the co-operation of the House to move Bill No. 37 through and end this disruption and uncertainty for patients across the province.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#patrick.dunn"><from>MR. DUNN</from><p>The cancellations and emergency room backups don't stop in New Glasgow. Several other hospitals are also facing similar struggles. Cape Breton is experiencing more strain on the system when patients are recalled, emergency rooms are backed up, and certain procedures and surgeries are cancelled. These patients require varying levels of care, and the authorities do not have the ability to hire more nurses or add new beds, so they must use the resources that are available.</p>
<p>My question to the minister is, how much more of this government mismanagement will Nova Scotia patients have to endure?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#leo.glavine">
            <from>MR. GLAVINE</from>
            <p>Yesterday was a very, very challenging day here in the province, and not just with the wildcat strike and the interruption of services. We had Cape Breton Regional Hospital go on emergency power. We had Canso shut down, and will not have power restored for perhaps a couple of days more. We had an MRI machine in Cape Breton go out of service. I can assure the member opposite, all of us here and the people of Nova Scotia, that was one of the days - yesterday - when I saw the strength of the Department of Health and Wellness, and the duty officers man the emergency centre and carry things on almost as normal as any day in our province.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Sydney-Whitney Pier.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>IMMIGRATION - NURSES OUT-MIGRATION: IMMIGRATION STRATEGY - EFFECT</heading>
          <speech by="#gordie.gosse"><from>MR. GORDIE GOSSE</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question is to the Minister of Immigration. At the Law Amendments Committee we heard from Jessica Lemesurier. When she left her nursing job in Ontario to come to Nova Scotia, she told her partner she couldn't work in a province that didn't respect her job. When she left Ontario, she told her parents that she couldn't imagine things getting worse. Well, Mr. Speaker, things have gotten worse - a whole lot worse for our health care workers in this province.</p>
<p>My question to the Minister of Immigration is, how would the outward migration of nurses to other provinces affect Nova Scotia's Immigration Strategy?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#lena.m.diab">
            <from>HON. LENA DIAB</from>
            <p>To the member for Sydney-Whitney Pier, as he knows, I love Sydney and there are many immigrants who live in Sydney-Whitney Pier. This particular legislation, as the member has heard us talking about it for the last two days, is throughout Canada, and we are the only province in Canada that does not have it.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#gordie.gosse">
            <from>MR. GOSSE</from>
            <p>When Jessica testified before the Law Amendments Committee, she told the committee that younger nurses she has spoken to will now consider finding work in other provinces, due to both working conditions and the Liberal essential services legislation. My second question to the minister is, is the Minister of Immigration looking at nurses as skilled worker targets in the immigration strategy?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#lena.m.diab">
            <from>MS. DIAB</from>
            <p>I, in fact, was present when the individual spoke yesterday and I also heard her say that she was in various other provinces as well. We have many nurses in this province and I'm very confident in the levels that we do have. Immigration is one that we wish to attract - through the Department of Labour and Advanced Education, our priority is to bring all our youth back that have left Nova Scotia, whether it's nurses or everyone else, and through immigration we do intend to concentrate on the skilled workers, yes.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#gordie.gosse"><from>MR. GOSSE</from><p>At Law Amendments Committee we heard from many health care professionals who wanted to know why the Liberal Government seems to want to drive them into quitting their profession, or taking their training and expertise elsewhere. Members from both my caucus and the Progressive Conservative caucus asked many questions to try to gain a full appreciation of what the nurses have been going through.</p>
<p>My question to the Minister of Immigration is, given the importance of immigration to Nova Scotia, why did the minister not ask one single question at the Law Amendments Committee to the nurses thinking of emigrating to other provinces?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#lena.m.diab">
            <from>MS. DIAB</from>
            <p>I would love to have a discussion with the member opposite at any point he wishes with respect to the duties of a chairman, whether it's the Law Amendments Committee or any other day. (Applause) I can assure the member opposite and everyone in the Legislature that I've been chairing meetings for about three decades and very much understand what it takes. I also do recall at the Law Amendments Committee that I was able to attend and did in fact ask &#x2026;</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Order, please. I'd just like to remind the minister to direct her comments to the Chair and not across the floor.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#lena.m.diab">
            <from>MS. DIAB</from>
            <p>My apologies for that. I couldn't help but look at the member opposite there. (Laughter)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#member" status="undefined">
            <from>AN HON. MEMBER</from>
            <p>Get over yourself, Gordie. (Laughter)</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#lena.m.diab">
            <from>MS. DIAB</from>
            <p>Anyway, I think my point has been made. Thank you very much.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Sydney River-Mira-Louisbourg.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>NAT. RES.: FOREST ROADS - CLOSURES</heading>
          <speech by="#alfie.macleod"><from>MR. ALFIE MACLEOD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question through you will be to the Minister of Natural Resources.</p>
<p>Yesterday the minister announced the April 3<sup>rd</sup> closure of the forest roads on western Crown land formerly owned by Bowater. These road closures come just two days after the government hit the six-month countdown clock for fibre access. My question to the minister is, why did he put up yet another roadblock for our forestry industry, and will they stop the six-month countdown clock while the roads are closed?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#zach.churchill">
            <from>HON. ZACH CHURCHILL</from>
            <p>Just for clarification in this House - the reason why there are some roads that are closed that are access points for our woodlands is because of safety reasons. As the Minister of Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal would know the Spring thaw creates a lot of challenging conditions, especially on our dirt roads, and the equipment required to go into those woodlands to take the fibre out wouldn't be possible, so that's why those roads are closed.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#alfie.macleod"><from>MR. MACLEOD</from><p>That was a great explanation, Mr. Speaker, on why the roads are closed. The question was whether or not the countdown will stop on the clock - will the six months be there for the forestry? The forestry industry adds about $579 million to our provincial economy and the members on this side of the House believe that our traditional industries must be protected. The Ivany Report states that in future, as in the past, the traditional rural industries - tourism, manufacturing, mining, fisheries, forestry, and agriculture - will provide the essential foundations for Nova Scotia's rural economies.</p>
<p>My question to the minister is, does he think that locking the gates to Crown land access is providing a good foundation for Nova Scotia's rural economy, and will he stop the clock until those roads are opened?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#zach.churchill">
            <from>MR. CHURCHILL</from>
            <p>Just to explain to the member - not every access road is closed for woodcutters to go in and cut fibre and take it out. The roads that are closed are closed because of safety issues, and the equipment that is required to go in there wouldn't be able to pass the roads anyway. The member opposite refers to a six-month countdown. There is no six-month countdown. I believe what he's referring to is the six-month, short-term allocations that were given out to woodcutters across the province. There is not a countdown to the end of those six months that will prevent them from cutting wood. In fact, during this particular time right now, our department is negotiating long-term fibre allocations that will go beyond those six months.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#alfie.macleod">
            <from>MR. MACLEOD</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, the forestry industry needs a real plan for the future, not short-term fixes. All we've seen from this government is band-aids and gate closures. When will the minister release the long-term plan for Nova Scotia's forestry industry?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#zach.churchill">
            <from>MR. CHURCHILL</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, in fact, it is this government that is keeping our eye toward the future when it comes to this critical industry to rural Nova Scotia. That is why our government invested over $1 million into innovation to help move this industry forward on how to improve our harvesting methods, our processing methods, as this critical industry goes through a transformation phase. We're the government that is also tackling the issue around our fibre challenge for the long term, including private wood suppliers across this province, so that this industry is not only important to today's generation, but for future generations.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable member for Colchester-Musquodoboit Valley.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>TIR: BRIDGE CLOSURES - LIST INFO</heading>
          <speech by="#larry.harrison">
            <from>MR. LARRY HARRISON</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, my question is for the Minister of Transportation and Infrastructure Renewal. A recent report indicated there are 391 bridges in Nova Scotia that have serious damage. I think I get phone calls on 300 of them. The province's chief highway engineer says the condition of some of the bridges have really reached a critical point. The suggestion is that some of the smaller bridges might have to be closed. Is there a list for bridges that might need to be closed in the near future?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#geoff.maclellan"><from>HON. GEOFF MACLELLAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, that report that was produced a few weeks ago, I think, was a very important one for Nova Scotians to get a sense of what the infrastructure deficit looks like for the government and obviously for the people of Nova Scotia. We've got over 4,300 bridges, and as the member suggested, there is a level of critical concern for about 300 of those.</p>
<p>I want to assure the House and again the importance of the question is this, we don't take the lead as politicians. For sure, we rely on our department for things of this critical nature. Our engineers are top-notch, they're world-class, and they tell us what the issues are, they tell us what the timelines look like, they tell us what the repair requirements would be, and we take our lead thoroughly and first and foremost from them; our chief engineer, Bruce Fitzner, does a great job at that.</p>
<p>I can tell the member that there is no list, per se. What we are going to do though, given the fact that this is now a public conversation, we can go out into the communities. If there are very low-volume bridges on that list, which many of the 300 are, then we can start to look at maybe what some of the alternatives are. Again, we're not going to force-feed that on the communities. It will be a community decision that we include all stakeholders in, and if the decision is to move on a bridge, we will do that. Again, there is no list and no urgency to close bridges at this point. Thank you.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#larry.harrison">
            <from>MR. HARRISON</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, bridges classified as poor condition have pieces of concrete falling off, there is structural erosion because of sediment, and so on. Those considered in serious shape had various forms of erosion and crumbling that affected primary structural components. Does the minister plan to follow the advice of the engineer to make these significant repairs that need to be made?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#geoff.maclellan"><from>MR. MACLELLAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, absolutely, without question. One of the things that we run into and some of the challenges, I guess, with the perceptions on this particular issue is that Nova Scotians see a bridge and it may look like it's in a state of disrepair, and it may be aesthetics, or it may be some of the structural concerns. But at the end of the day, again to the member's question directly, we would not put any Nova Scotian on a road that was deemed to be unsafe.</p>
<p>We take the lead entirely from our engineers. When they tell us to take action, we do so. Any time there's a critical point where we can't keep a bridge operating, we close it immediately. Short of that, we give any indication of slowing down or any challenges that might exist there, we let the public know, and communication is part of that process as well. Without question, our engineers take the lead, and we follow their advice.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#larry.harrison"><from>MR. HARRISON</from><p>It's indicated that just half of the province's 4,310 bridges are more than 50 years old, and again, I think my constituency has about 4,000 of them. An engineer in the department has said that the budget is tight - there's no question about that - and I think a lot of people appreciate that.</p>
<p>How many of those bridges listed as poor or worse will have to wait for repairs before the salt really takes its toll on the roads and bridges?</p></speech>
          <speech by="#geoff.maclellan"><from>MR. MACLELLAN</from><p>Mr. Speaker, the member is absolutely correct. A lot of our inventory of bridges is post-Second World War era. Some of them are even at the turn of the century - the 20<sup>th</sup> Century, so very old bridges. A lot that are in existence now were built for rail, so there was no intention to ever have motor vehicles on those, and of course we're using those. They're an important part of our stock and inventory on our Nova Scotia roadways.</p>
<p>Again, we take full lead from the department on this one. Of those 300, we have a very detailed breakdown of each and every bridge. The engineers typically do their inspections on an annual basis, but any sign that there may be decay or issues - we're always better off to take a look, as opposed to just taking our chances. The engineers are out there, and I know that the member has 98 per cent of our bridges in the province, by the sounds of things, so any time the member has a specific question, he's more than welcome to bring it to us, and we'll check right away.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>The honourable Leader of the New Democratic Party.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection>
          <heading>PREM. - NURSING CARE: INVESTMENT - INFO</heading>
          <speech by="#maureen.macdonald"><from>HON. MAUREEN MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, my question through you is to the Premier. Prior to the election, the Premier told nurses, "We need to change how we're delivering health care to protect front-line nursing care." He added, "Let's make sure that the dollars are spent on front-line care." Yet today, the Premier seems to be singing a much different tune. Now it appears that the Premier believes the current level of front-line nursing care in Nova Scotia is more than adequate. In fact, just this week he told nurses, "What more do you want? How much above the national average does Nova Scotia have to become?"</p>
<p>My question to the Premier is, what happened to the investment in front-line nursing care that was promised before the election? Where has your government decided to spend health care dollars instead?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined"><from>THE PREMIER</from><p>I think that when tomorrow's budget is introduced the member opposite will recognize that we have a major investment in health care. She would also recognize that when we were going into this campaign we assured Nova Scotians that we would put patients first. That's why the Minister of Health and Wellness is going around this province, to take from an administrative-focused health care system to one that is focused on patients.</p>
<p>It's the very reason why we've introduced Bill No. 37 - so that we can put a focus back on patients to ensure that essential services are in place. At the same time, we're protecting the right to strike for health care workers. I want to add that, unlike the New Democratic Party, we have not stripped the right to strike away from health care workers.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#maureen.macdonald"><from>MS. MACDONALD</from><p>Mr. Speaker, one of the few election promises the Liberals intend to keep is to amalgamate the district health authorities into a single super health board. While the Premier and his Minister of Health and Wellness are out trumpeting the benefits of this unproven plan, they're neglecting to tell Nova Scotians just how much that will cost. In Alberta, the amalgamation of health authorities cost $100 million, and $46 million of that alone went for severance packages and pension payouts to the executives who lost their jobs.</p>
<p>My question for the Premier is, how much money does his Liberal Government have earmarked for pension payouts and severance packages - money that could be invested in front-line nursing care?</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#premier" status="undefined"><from>THE PREMIER</from><p>Mr. Speaker, as I said earlier, I want to encourage the Leader of the New Democratic Party to pay attention to the budget tomorrow and recognize the investment that will be made in health care. As well, I want to, again, remind the honourable member that there is a bill before this House that would protect patients in this province. It is unbelievable that the Leader of the New Democratic Party is putting the interest of the union leader ahead of patients in this province.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I guess she got the word after the last one.</p></speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Order, please. The time allotted for the Oral Question Period has expired.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#alfie.macleod">
            <from>MR. ALFIE MACLEOD</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, on a point of order. During Question Period, in a response by the Minister of Health and Wellness, regarding our concerns about the veterans of this province, the minister made reference that he would be glad to go to Ottawa to bring forward the interests and the concerns of the veterans of this province. For the record, my colleague, the member for Northside-Westmount and I have already been to Ottawa, but I would be glad to go with him to show him where the minister's office is so that he can really do something well, because doing nothing is not an option.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Point taken. We'll move on.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
          <speech by="#michel.p.samson">
            <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, just before that, on the point of order from the member for Sydney River-Mira-Louisbourg &#x2026;</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
            <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
            <p>Order, please. Technically it wasn't a point of order, so we are not going to entertain any responses to the point of order.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </questions>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT BUSINESS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson"><from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from><p>We'll save that one for another day, Mr. Speaker, but I assure you there will be another day on that one.</p>
<p>Mr. Speaker, I move that you do now leave the Chair and the House resolve itself into a Committee of the Whole House on Bills.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>The motion is carried.</p>
<p>We will now recess for five minutes while we get set up.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>1:25 a.m. The House resolved into a CWH on Bills with Deputy Speaker Ms. Margaret Miller in the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <narrative>
          <p>4:13 a.m. CWH on Bills rose and the House reconvened with Deputy Speaker Ms. Margaret Miller in the Chair.</p>
        </narrative>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MADAM SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The Chairman of the Committee of the Whole House on Bills reports:</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#clerk" status="undefined"><from>THE CLERK</from><p>That the Committee of the Whole House on Bills has met and considered the following bill:</p>
<p><b>Bill No. 37 - Essential Health and Community Services Act.</b></p>
<p>and the chairman has been instructed to recommend this bill to the favourable consideration of the House, without amendment.</p></speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>Ordered that this bill be read a third time on a future day.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson">
          <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
          <p>Madam Speaker, in light of the fact that there is a labour disruption that is going to be taking place in less than three hours, I would ask that you request unanimous consent of the House to have Bill No. 37 now considered for third reading.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is for third reading of Bill No. 37. Would all those in favour of the motion please say Aye. Contrary minded, Nay.</p>
<p>I hear several Noes.</p>
<p>The motion is defeated.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson">
          <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
          <p>Madam Speaker, in light of the decision by the NDP caucus not to allow this bill to be read a third time, I move that the House do now recess and meet again at 2:15 p.m., when the Budget Speech will be delivered. The replies from both the Official Opposition and the NDP caucus will be delivered following the speech, and we will look to call Government Business following that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MADAM SPEAKER</from><p>The motion is to recess until 2:15 p.m. today.</p>
<p>Is it agreed?</p>
<p>It is agreed.</p>
<p>The House stands recessed.</p></speech>
        <narrative>
          <p>4:16 a.m. The House recessed.</p>
        </narrative>
        <narrative>
          <p>2:15 p.m. The House reconvened.</p>
        </narrative>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined"><from>MR. SPEAKER</from><p>Order, please.</p>
<p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p></speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson">
          <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call the order of business, Government Motions.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection>
        <heading>GOVERNMENT MOTIONS</heading>
        <speech by="" as="#speaker" status="undefined">
          <from>MR. SPEAKER</from>
          <p>The honourable Government House Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#michel.p.samson">
          <from>HON. MICHEL SAMSON</from>
          <p>Mr. Speaker, would you please call Resolution No. 800.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
